<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tipula (Vestiplex) uncinella Yang &amp; Pan &amp; Liu &amp; Yang 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514483</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7226456BFA6D527C1C1A9AA7A1E59D6C</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Tipula (Vestiplex) Bezzi (Diptera, Tipulidae) from Tibet</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1477</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
uncinella
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
635FCCE1-5615-49F6-B272-82142261A897
</p>
      <p>
Figs 10–20
, 
86
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Scape and pedicel yellow, flagellum grayish yellow. Prescutum with four grayish yellow stripes, all stripes with brown margins. Scutellum yellow with dark brown mid-longitudinal stripe. Mediotergite yellow with brown mid-longitudinal stripe. Tergite 9 separated medially, pair of angular arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9, arms with granulated margins. Base of posterior margin of inner gonostylus without a small protrusion; upper beak slightly twisted, lower beak curved, middle concave.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named after the uncinatus of the adminiculum, the Latin adjective ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
uncinella
</tp:taxon-name>
’ means ‘bearing hooks, barbed’.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Bomi
, 
Yigong
; 
30°16′19″ N
, 
94°48′28″ E
; 

2270 m
a.s.l.

; 

5–7 May 2017

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
sweeping net
; 
CAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
12 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
CAU
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
9 ♂♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Bomi
, 
106K
; 
29°50′04″ N
, 
94°44′36″ E
; 

2290 m
a.s.l.

; 

17 May 2017

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
light trap
; 
CAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Figs 10–12.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
uncinella
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratypes, ♂♂ (CAU). 
10
. Habitus, lateral view. 
11
. Wing. 
12
. Habitus, dorsal view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Body length 14.0 mm, wing length 18.0–20.0 mm, antenna length 3.0–3.5 mm (n = 22).</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 10, 12
). Mainly yellow. Occipital stripe dark gray. Rostrum and nasus yellow. Setae on head brown. Scape and pedicel yellow, flagellum grayish yellow. Proboscis and palpus brownish yellow.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Figs 10, 12
). Mainly yellow, heavily pruinose. Pronotum brownish yellow with yellow setae. Prescutum with four grayish yellow stripes, all stripes with brown margins, median stripe broadened apically and gradually narrowing to base, lateral stripes long-oval. Scutum yellow with four grayish yellow spots, anterior margins of anterior two spots brown. Scutellum yellow with dark brown midlongitudinal stripe. Mediotergite yellow with brown mid-longitudinal stripe. Thoracic pleuron yellow. Parascutellum yellow. Meron yellow. Setae on thorax yellow. Legs with coxae and femora yellow, femora with dark brown apices, tibiae and tarsi dark brown. Setae on legs dark brown. Wing variegated light brown; pterostigma brown; petiole of cell m1 distinctly shorter than discal cell (
Fig. 11
). Halter with stem yellow, knob pale black with pale yellow apex.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Figs 10, 12
). Mainly yellow. Abdominal tergites each with three brown stripes. Abdominal segments 5–9 dark brown to black. Setae on abdomen brownish yellow.
</p>
      <p>
HYPOPYGIUM (
Figs 13–17, 20
). Gonocoxite elongated, separated from sternite 9, posterior margin with an unusually strong and slender black spine, directed chiefly dorsally, slightly twisted. Tergite 9 separated medially, middle of posterior margin of lobe slightly protrude; a pair of angular black arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9, surface of arms not smooth, with granulated margin. Sternite 9 with a median prominence. Adminiculum narrow spade-like, apex slightly furcal, ventral caudal part with a small uncinate projection. Outer gonostylus anteriorly bent, posterior margin of basal half truncated (
Fig. 16
). Inner gonostylus with concavity at middle, posterior margin with big semicircular bulge; base of posterior margin of inner gonostylus without a small protrusion; upper beak slightly twisted, lower beak curved, middle concave (
Fig. 14
). Semen pump (
Figs 18–19
) as shown in figures. Aedeagus wide, basal width about 0.5 mm, gradually narrowing towards apex, and apex not bifurcated.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown or unrecognized.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Tibet
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new species is similar to 
T
. (
V
.) 
schizophallus
(Alexander, 1973), but the latter differs in the following characters: arms of tergite 9 with only inner margin roughened; gonocoxite with an additional small spine (the one near posterior margin of basistylar suture); outer gonostylus with very abundant black setae from conspicuous punctures; apex of adminiculum profoundly divided into two long parallel spines, ventral caudal part without uncinatus. It is also similar 
T
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
(
V
.) 
deserrata
Alexander, 1934
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
T
. (
V
.) 
factiosa
Alexander, 1940, but the posterior margin of inner gonostylus in the latter has no protrusion. The posterior margin of tergite 9 of 
T
. (
V
.) 
factiosa
is smooth, its arms are large and strong.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
