<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tipula (Vestiplex) bucera Yang &amp; Pan &amp; Liu &amp; Yang 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514499</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/038487C8FFBDFF97FDEBFA07FBC0FDB1</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Tipula (Vestiplex) Bezzi (Diptera, Tipulidae) from Tibet</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1477</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
bucera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
4AB06AB7-6108-40AF-A8C8-CAEDF0226964
</p>
      <p>
Figs 39–50
, 
84, 86
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Scape and pedicel yellow, first flagellar segment dark yellow, other flagellar segments bicolor, yellowish with dark brown base. Scutellum and mediotergite dark yellow. Gonocoxite elongated, separated from sternite 9, posterior margin with an unusually strong black spine, bent inward and horn-like.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named after the shape of gonocoxite, the Latin adjective ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
bucera
</tp:taxon-name>
’ means ‘ox-horned’.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Bomi
, 
Yigong
; 
30°16′19″ N
, 
94°48′28″ E
; 

2240 m
a.s.l.

; 

7 Jun. 2017

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
light trap
; 
CAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Figs 39–41.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
bucera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (CAU). 
39
. Habitus, lateral view. 
40
. Wing. 
41
. Habitus, dorsal view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 42–43.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
bucera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, allotype, ♀ (CAU). 
42
. Habitus, lateral view. 
43
. Ovipositor, lateral view. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 44–50.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
bucera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (CAU). 
44
. Hypopygium, lateral view. 
45
. Inner gonostylus, lateral external view. 
46–47
. Semen pump, lateral view and dorsal view. 
48
. Outer and inner gonostylus, lateral external view. 
49
. Tergite nine, dorsal view. 
50
. Hypopygium, ventral view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars: 44, 49–50 = 0.5 mm; 45–48 = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Allotype
CHINA
• 
♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
CAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
9 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
CAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Body length 13.0 mm, wing length 15.0 mm, antenna length 4.5 mm (n = 10).</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 39, 41
). Mainly yellow. Occipital stripe dark brown, with brown setae. Rostrum and nasus yellow, rostrum with brown setae and nasus with dark yellow setae. Scape and pedicel yellow, first flagellar segment dark yellow, other flagellar segments bicolor yellowish with dark brown base. Proboscis and palpus grayish yellow.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Figs 39, 41
). Mainly yellow, heavily pruinose. Pronotum yellow with yellow setae. Prescutum with four yellowish gray stripes, median stripe broadened apically and gradually narrowing to base, lateral stripes long-oval. Scutum yellow with four yellowish gray spots. Scutellum and mediotergite dark yellow. Thoracic pleuron yellow. Parascutellum pale yellow. Meron yellow. Setae on thorax yellow. Legs with coxae and femora yellow, femora with dark brown apices and brown middle parts; tibiae and tarsi dark brown. Setae on legs dark brown. Wing light brown; pterostigma brown; petiole of cell m 
1
and discal cell almost equilong (
Fig. 40
). Halter with stem brown, knob dark brown with pale tip.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Figs 39, 41
). Mainly yellow. Abdominal tergites each with three stripes, middle stripe pale gray, lateral stripes brown. Abdominal segments 5–9 black. Setae on abdomen brownish yellow.
</p>
      <p>
HYPOPYGIUM (
Figs 44–45, 48–50
). Gonocoxite elongated, separated from sternite 9, gonocoxite ends with an unusually strong black spine, bent inward and horn-like, ventral of spine with long setae, basal setae longest and decreases to tip, curl inward. Tergite 9 longitudinally divided into two parts, slightly connected. Sternite 9 with a median prominence, adminiculum with a pair of sharp projections on both sides. Outer gonostylus black with yellow bristles, bent, willow leaf shaped (
Figs 44, 48
). Inner gonostylus with a slanted bar like raise; upper beak sharp, curled inward (
Figs 45, 48
). Semen pump (
Figs 46–47
) as shown in figures. Aedeagus with a sclerotized suborbicular appendage at base.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 17.5 mm, wing length 
17 mm
, antenna length 
3 mm
(n = 1).
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Body color slightly darker than male. Antenna relatively shorter than male. Scape and pedicel yellow, flagellar segments 1–4 bicolor yellow with pale brown base, other segments pale brown. Brown and black part of legs paler than male. Wing same as male except knob of halter without pale tip. Abdominal tergites each with three stripes, middle stripe brown, lateral stripes black, abdominal segments 5–7 yellowish brown, and brown gradually deepened, 8 
th
segment dark brown. Other characteristics as in male (
Fig. 42
).
</p>
      <p>
OVIPOSITOR. Tergite 9 dark brown, tergite 10 shining reddish brown. Cercus brown, tip slightly upturned, outer margin with rough serration (
Fig. 43
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Tibet
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new species is similar to 
T
. (
V
.) 
coxitalis
Alexander, 1935
from Anhui and 
Taiwan
, 
China
, but the latter differs in the following characters: gonocoxite ends with a slightly twisted spine; outer gonostylus narrow, filiform; inner gonostylus without slanted bar-like raise; sternite 9 near caudal end on either side of midline with a conspicuous hair pencil of reddish bristles, these pencils not arising from basal tubercles (
Men 2015
). This species is similar to 
T
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
(
V
.) 
bicalcarata
Savchenko, 1965
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
T
. (
V
.) 
maoershanensis
Men &amp; Young, 2017
, but the outer gonostylus of the latter is not willow leaf shaped. The posterior margin of inner gonostylus with a finger-like protrusion (

Men 
et al.
2017

).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
