<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tipula (Vestiplex) motuoensis Yang &amp; Pan &amp; Liu &amp; Yang 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514513</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E8C44B30A8917CD14470F26474B8E35B</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Tipula (Vestiplex) Bezzi (Diptera, Tipulidae) from Tibet</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1477</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula (Vestiplex) motuoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
6536F0F9-0D40-490C-BEF5-06A3A1153033
</p>
      <p>
Figs 75–83
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Proboscis relatively short. Pronotum brownish yellow with dark yellow setae. Prescutum mainly reddish yellow with four olive-brown striped pruinescence, velvety, two middle stripes virtually fused. Gonocoxite ends hook-like, not separated from sternite 9; tergite 9 with two pairs of lobes, longitudinally divided into two parts, slightly connected, pair of emarginate arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9. Inner gonostylus with posterior crest produced backward, base of inner gonostylus and outer basal lobe of inner gonostylus rolled inward, produced depression with row of short setulae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named after the 
type
locality Motuo.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Motuo
, 
80K
; 
29°39′29″ N
, 
95°29′24″ E
; 

2020 m
a.s.l.

; 

13 Jun. 2017

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
light trap
; 
CAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Allotype
CHINA
• 
♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
CAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Figs 74–76.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
motuoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (CAU). 
74
. Habitus, lateral view. 
75
. Male habitus, dorsal view. 
76
. Wing. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 77–78.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
motuoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, allotype, ♀ (CAU). 
77
. Habitus, lateral view. 
78
. Ovipositor, lateral view. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 79–83.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
motuoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (CAU). 
79
. Hypopygium, lateral view. 
80–81
. Outer and inner gonostylus, lateral external view and lateral dorsal view. 
82
. Tergite nine, dorsal view. 
83
. Hypopygium, ventral view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars: 79, 82–83 = 0.5 mm; 80–81 = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
CHINA
• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
CAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Body length 12.0 mm, wing length 15.0 mm, antenna length 4.0 mm (n = 2).</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 74–75
). Mainly dark yellow. Vertex with dark brown stripe. Frontal tubercle relatively high. Proboscis relatively short, rostrum and nasus dark yellow. Setae on head dark brown. Scape yellow, pedicel pale yellow, flagellum dark brown. Proboscis and palpus brownish yellow.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Figs 74–75
). Mainly dark yellow, heavily pruinescence. Pronotum brownish yellow with dark yellow setae. Prescutum mainly reddish yellow with four olive-brown striped pruinescence, velvety, two middle stripes virtually fused. Scutum with four reddish brown spots, with olive-brown striped pruinescence. Scutellum and mediotergite yellow with pale brown mid-longitudinal stripes. Thorax yellow in lateral view. Pleura below anterior thoracic spiracle to middle with an irregular brownish black spot; anepisternum and katepisternum pale brownish yellow. Setae on thorax yellow. Legs with coxae and bases of femora pale yellow, apices of femora brown; tibiae and tarsi dark brown. Setae on legs brownish black. Wing light brown; pterostigma brown; petiole of cell m1 shorter than discal cell (
Fig. 76
). Halter with stem dark yellow, knob brownish yellow.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Figs 74–75
). Mainly yellow. Abdominal dorsum with three brown longitudinal stripes, abdominal segment 6 brownish yellow, segments 7–9 brown. Setae on abdomen dark brown and yellow.
</p>
      <p>
HYPOPYGIUM (
Figs 79–83
). Gonocoxite ends hook-like, not separated from sternite 9, tergite 9 bearing two pairs of lobes, longitudinally divided into two parts, slightly connected, inner margin with dense setae; a pair of emarginate arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9, inner margin black, other areas yellow. Sternite 9 with a median prominence, middle of sternite 9 slightly raised. Sternite 8 with abundant setae. Outer gonostylus slender and small, apex curly (
Figs 79–81
). Inner gonostylus, dorsal crest produced into fishtail, base of inner gonostylus and outer basal lobe of inner gonostylus inward-rolled, produced depression with a row of short setulae, outer basal lobe of inner gonostylus large triangular (
Figs 80–81
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
13 mm
, wing length 
15 mm
, antenna length 2.4 mm (n = 1).
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Body color slightly paler than male. Antenna shorter than male, dark yellow. Legs paler than male, tibiae and tarsi dark yellow. Abdominal tergites each with three stripes, middle stripe brown, lateral stripes brownish black, abdominal 7–8 segments yellowish brown, 8th segment dark brown. Junction of each 3–9 segments brownish black (
Fig. 77
).
</p>
      <p>
OVIPOSITOR. Tergite 9 yellowish brown, tergite 10 yellow. Cercus dark yellow, slightly up-turned, outer margin without rough serration (
Fig. 78
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Tibet
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new species is similar to 
T
. (
V
.) 
theowaldana
Alexander, 1964 from 
Assam
, 
India
, but the latter differs in the following characters: basal abdominal tergites yellow; gonocoxite ends sharp and not hooked; tergite 9 with a pair of larger and elongate lobes. The species may form a new species group, perhaps together with 
T
. (
V
.) 
theowaldana
. However, we have not examined the specimens of the latter species and can therefore not say with certainty if these two species share characteristics that would separate them from existing species groups.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
