<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tipula (Vestiplex) nayogabuensis Yang &amp; Pan &amp; Liu &amp; Yang 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514487</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6D9517658B8D043A4401B5A3D7987FD0</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Tipula (Vestiplex) Bezzi (Diptera, Tipulidae) from Tibet</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1477</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
nayogabuensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D91DF543-8018-4FD5-8E99-DCB2AAF3E8FF
</p>
      <p>
Figs 21–29
, 
86
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Vertex brownish black, relatively protruded. Prescutum virtually brownish black, black stripes distinct, all stripes with dark black margins. Scutum virtually brownish black. Scutellum dark yellow with brownish black mid-longitudinal stripe. Mediotergite reddish dark brown, dried with pale gray pruinescence and black mid-longitudinally. Thoracic pleuron dark brown with pale gray pruinescence. Posterior margin of tergite 9 with long setae, pair of weak arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9, slender hidden bridge between them.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named after the 
type
locality Nayogabu Snow Mountain.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Bomi
, 
Yigong
; 
30°16′19″ N
, 
94°48′28″ E
; 

2290 m
a.s.l.

; 

7 May 2017

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
light trap
; 
CAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
8 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
CAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Body length 16.5–18.5 mm, wing length 20–22.0 mm, antenna length 4.5 mm (n = 9).</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 21, 23
). Mainly brownish yellow. Occipital mark dark brown, vertex brownish black, relatively protruded. Rostrum and nasus dark yellow, nasus relatively long. Setae on head dark brown. Scape dark yellow, pedicel pale yellow, flagellum brownish black except first flagellar segment yellowish brown. Proboscis and palpus yellowish gray.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Figs 21–23
). Mainly dark brown, heavily pale gray pruinescence. Pronotum brown with yellow setae. Prescutum virtually brownish black, black stripes distinct, all stripes with dark black margin. Scutum virtually brownish black. Scutellum dark yellow with brownish black mid-longitudinal stripe. Mediotergite reddish dark brown, dried with pale gray pruinescence and black mid-longitudinally. Thoracic pleuron dark brown with pale gray pruinescence. Parascutellum dark brown. Meron brown. Setae on thorax pale yellow. Legs with coxae and femora yellow, femora with brownish black apexes; tibiae and tarsi dark brown. Setae on legs dark brown. Wing variegated brown; pterostigma brown; petiole of cell m distinctly shorter than discal cell (
Fig. 24
). Halter with stem yellow, knob dark brown.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Figs 21, 23
). Mainly yellow. Abdominal tergites each with three stripes, middle stripe of tergites 1–2 brownish black, wide, others brown; bilateral stripes black. Abdominal segments 6–9 dark black. Setae on abdomen yellow.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 21–24.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
nayogabuensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (CAU). 
21
. Habitus, lateral view. 
22
. Parasitic mites. 
23
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
24
. Wing. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 25–29.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
nayogabuensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (CAU). 
25
. Hypopygium, lateral view. 
26
. Outer gonostylus, lateral external view. 
27
. Inner gonostylus, lateral external view. 
28
. Tergite nine, dorsal view. 
29
. Hypopygium, ventral view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars: 25, 28–29 = 0.5 mm; 26–27 = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
HYPOPYGIUM (
Figs 25–29
). Gonocoxite hardly elongated, unseparated from sternite 9. Tergite 9 longitudinally divided into two parts, posterior margin with long setae, a pair of weak arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9, a slender hidden bridge between them (
Fig. 28
). Appendages of sternite 9 slender (
Fig. 29
). Apex and middle of outer gonostylus slightly wide (
Fig. 26
). Inner gonostylus with concavity at middle, posterior part with many bristles, lower margin with bristled raise; base of lower beak inward-rolled, enwrapped black lower beak; upper beak yellow, lower margin black, base with a slight raise (
Fig. 27
). Apex of adminiculum hooked.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown or unrecognized.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
: 
Tibet
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
T
. (
V
.) 
zayulensis
</tp:taxon-name>
from Chayu (= Zayu) of 
Tibet
, but the latter differs in the following characters: prescutum and scutum yellowish brown; thoracic pleuron brownish yellow; all sterno-pleurite with dark brown margin. The outer gonostylus is different from that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T
. (
V
.) 
nayogabuensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
