<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tipula (Vestiplex) nigroapicalis Brunetti 1911</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514507</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CAE617B97E2177F28056E0D91A126EC8</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Tipula (Vestiplex) Bezzi (Diptera, Tipulidae) from Tibet</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1477</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
nigroapicalis
Brunetti, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 58–65
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula nigroapicalis
Brunetti, 1911: 257
</tp:taxon-name>

. 
Type
locality: 
India
: Darjiling.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula lepcha
Alexander, 1958: 151
</tp:taxon-name>

. 
Type
locality: 
Nepal
: Simbhanjang Pass.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula nigroapicalis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Edwards 1928: 692

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
nigroapicalis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Alexander 1953: 342

; 

1968: 91

. — 


Pilipenko 
et al
. 2019: 10


.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Tipula lepcha</tp:taxon-name>
–

Alexander 1960: 144

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Occipital stripe dark brown. Rostrum brownish yellow, nasus brown with yellow setae. Scape brownish yellow and pedicel pale yellow, first flagellar segment brownish yellow, other flagellar segments black. Scutum yellow with four brownish black spots, which are virtually confluent on each side, anterior two spots small; all spots with olive-gray pruinescence. Upper part of fore coxa brownish black. Inner gonostylus with upper beak sharp bearing, a semicircular striped raise at base; posterior crest produced backward. Adminiculum with a pair of long projections on both sides, longer than apex of phallic guide.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
3 ♂♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Yadong
; 
27°29′52″ N
, 
88°55′51″ E
; 

3200 m
a.s.l.

; 

12 Jul. 2018

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
light trap
; 
CAU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Figs 58–60.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
nigroapicalis
Brunetti, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CAU). 
58
. Habitus, lateral view. 
59
. Wing. 
60
. Habitus, dorsal view. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
   <p>
Figs 61–65.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
nigroapicalis
Brunetti, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CAU). 
61
. Hypopygium, lateral view. 
62
. Outer gonostylus, lateral external view. 
63
. Inner gonostylus, lateral external view. 
64
. Tergite nine, dorsal view. 
65
. Hypopygium, ventral view. Scale bars: 61, 64–65 = 0.5 mm; 62–63 = 0.1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Body length 12.0–13.0 mm, wing length 15.0 mm, antenna length 3.0 mm (n = 3).</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 58, 60
). Mainly brownish yellow. Occipital stripe dark brown. Rostrum brownish yellow, nasus brown with yellow setae. Setae on head brownish black. Scape brownish yellow, pedicel pale yellow, first flagellar segment brownish yellow, other flagellar segments black. Proboscis and palpus black.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Figs 58, 60
). Mainly brownish yellow, heavily yellow and gray pruinescence. Pronotum brownish gray. Prescutum with four dark brownish black stripes, median stripes virtually confluent, broadened apically and gradually narrowing to base, lateral stripes long-oval; all stripes with olive-gray pruinescence. Scutum yellow with four dark brownish black spots, which are virtually confluent on each side, anterior two spots small, all spots with olive-gray pruinescence. Scutellum yellow with dark brown mid-longitudinal stripe. Mediotergite yellow, middlly pale gray with dark brown mid-longitudinal stripe. Scutellum and mediotergite with golden pruinescence. Thoracic pleuron with yellow pruinescence. Anepisternum and katepisternum yellow, each with a brownish black anterior lower spot. Anepimeron yellow with a small brownish black upper spot; katepimeron yellow. Meron yellow with brownish black lower part. Parascutellum yellow. Anatergite and katatergite yellow. Setae on thorax dark yellow. Legs with coxae and femora yellow, except upper part of fore coxa brownish black, femora with black apices; tibiae brownish yellow with black apices; tarsi dark black. Setae on legs black. Wing yellowish brown; pterostigma brown; petiole of cell m 
1
slightly shorter than discal cell (
Fig. 59
). Halter with stem brown, knob grayish black with pale gray apex.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Figs 58, 60
). Mainly yellow.Abdominal tergites each with three brown stripes, middle stripe pale. Abdominal segments 7–9 brownish black. Setae on abdomen yellow except black setae on middle stripe.
</p>
      <p>
HYPOPYGIUM (
Figs 61–65
). Gonocoxite elongated into dagger-shaped extension, separated from sternite 9. Posterior margin of tergite 9 depressed medially, connected by a short bridge. Sternite 9, adminiculum trident-shaped, with a pair of long projections on both sides, longer than apex of phallic guide, ventral part of adminiculum with a large projection. Outer gonostylus black, with a central bulge posterior margin bearing subtriangular protrusion (
Fig. 62
). Inner gonostylus with upper beak sharp, base of beak with a semicircular striped raise; posterior crest produced backward (
Fig. 63
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
See 
Brunetti (1911)
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Tibet
); 
India
(
Uttarakhand
, W Bengal); 
Nepal
(Simbhanjang Pass).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
