<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Campoplex corsicator Aubert 1960,
                        stat. rev.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4638111</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0384433845102F7FFD93F9DAFADAFA96</uri>
                  <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the Campoplex difformis group (Ichneumonidae,
                        Campopleginae), with particular reference to species of economic
                        importance</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.740.1277</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex corsicator Aubert, 1960 </tp:taxon-name> stat. rev. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 2E , 3 , 7F , 9F , 10F , 14F </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex mutabilis corsicator Aubert, 1960: 64 </tp:taxon-name> .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Lectotype designated here </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> FRANCE • 1 ♀ , last 6 flagellomeres of right antenna
                        missing; “TYPE // <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex </tp:taxon-name> ♀; (=
                              <tp:taxon-name> Omorgus </tp:taxon-name> ); <tp:taxon-name> mutabilis
                              Holm </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> corsicator Aub.
                        </tp:taxon-name> // Comparée au; lectotype (Hinz) // J. F. Aubert ;
                        13.8.1959 ; Ajaccio (Corse) // <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex ( Nemeritis )
                        </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> tibialis Szepl. </tp:taxon-name> ; (=
                              <tp:taxon-name> corsicator Aub. </tp:taxon-name> ) // Syntype 1/? (6);
                              <tp:taxon-name>Campoplex</tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name>mutabilis
                              corsicator</tp:taxon-name> ; Aubert, 1960g ; labelled by S. Klopfstein
                        2009”. </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description based on the lectotype </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 7.1 mm ; fore wing length 4.4 mm . </p>
            <p>HEAD. Face about 0.80–0.90 × as high as wide. Malar space 0.5–0.6 × width of
                  mandibular base. Gena about 0.4 × as long as eye (maximum width, seen laterally);
                  temple 0.3 × as long as eye (see dorsally), narrowed behind eye, imaginary lines
                  connecting outer side of eye and temple intersect not before the level of the
                  scutellar groove or just behind it. OOD 0.65 × distance between lateral ocelli.
                  Mandibular teeth subequal. Clypeus 0.4–0.5 × as high as wide, not produced in
                  profile medially, matt and coriaceous, its apical margin sharp and gently rounded.
                  Face and frons granulate and matt. Vertex and temples coriaceous and subpolished.
                  Flagellum in the examined specimen with 33 segments, flagellomeres in apical
                  quarter about 0.8–0.9 × as long as wide.</p>
            <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex corsicator Aubert, 1960 </tp:taxon-name> (MZL), ♀,
                  lectotype, designated on original syntype. A . Habitus and labels. B . Head,
                  lateral view. C . Mesopleuron and epicnemial carina, lateral view. </p>
            <p> Fig. 4. Epicnemial carinae, in lateral view, and shape of temples behind eye, dorsal
                  view. A . <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex melanostoma (Strobl, 1904) (ZSM)
                  </tp:taxon-name> . B . <tp:taxon-name> C. punctulatus (Szépligeti, 1916) (ZSM)
                  </tp:taxon-name> . C . Schematic drawing illustrating the epicnemial carina
                  subventrally turned towards the ventral hind corner of pronotum. D .
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. difformis ( Gmelin, 1790 ) (ZSM) </tp:taxon-name> . E .
                  Schematic drawing illustrating the epicnemial carina subventrally more or less
                  straight, not turned towards the ventral hind corner of pronotum. F .
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. restrictor Aubert, 1960 </tp:taxon-name> (ZSM), temples
                  strongly narrowed behind eyes (i.e., imaginary lines connecting outer side of eye
                  and temple intersect at the level of the scutellar groove). G . <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        tibialis (Szépligeti, 1916) (ZSM) </tp:taxon-name> , temples not strongly
                  narrowed behind eyes (i.e., imaginary lines connecting outer side of eye and gena
                  intersect at the level of the scutellum or behind it). Abbreviations: ep.c. =
                  epicnemial carina; m.g. = mesopleural groove; sp. = speculum. </p>
            <p> Fig. 5. Epicnemial carinae, in ventrolateral view and related schematic drawings, in
                  frontal view. A . <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex bilobus (Thomson, 1887) (ZSM)
                  </tp:taxon-name> , epicnemial carina ventrally raised and divided into two lobes.
                  B . <tp:taxon-name> C. hercynicus Horstmann, 1985 </tp:taxon-name> (ZSM),
                  epicnemial carina ventrally raised and slightly notched in the middle. C .
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. unicingulatus ( Schmiedeknecht, 1909 ) (ZSM)
                  </tp:taxon-name> , epicnemial carina evenly raised ventrally and not divided nor
                  notched in the middle. D . <tp:taxon-name> C. difformis ( Gmelin, 1790 ) (ZSM)
                  </tp:taxon-name> , epicnemial carina ventrally only very slightly raised.
                  Abbreviations: ep.c. = epicnemial carina; m.s. = medial sternal groove. </p>
            <p> Fig. 6. A. <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex tibialis (Szépligeti, 1916) </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  ♀ (ZSM), habitus and labels. B . <tp:taxon-name> C. unicingulatus (
                        Schmiedeknecht, 1909 ) </tp:taxon-name> , ♀ (ZSM), habitus and labels. </p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. Pronotum medio-ventrally with longitudinal striae, dorsally coriaceous.
                  Epomia indistinct. Mesoscutum and scutellum granulate and matt, scutellum without
                  lateral carinae. Mesopleuron coriaceous and matt, with shallow and scattered
                  punctures, especially on antero-ventral half; speculum smooth, anteriorly with
                  fine longitudinal striae. Epicnemial carina only slightly sinuate subventrally,
                  ventrally slightly raised, in middle without notch and not produced into lobes.
                  Metapleuron coriaceous and matt. Fore wing with areolet small and petiolate, 2m-cu
                  beyond its middle; 1cu-a opposite M&amp;RS. Hind wing with proximal abscissa of CU
                  4.5 × as long as cu-a, distal abscissa of CU unpigmented. Hind femur 4.5 × as long
                  as its maximum width, the longer inner tibial spur about 0.5–0.6 × as long as hind
                  basitarsus. Propodeum with area basalis triangular and connected by a small
                  longitudinal carina to anterior margin of area superomedia, at its anterior end
                  about 0.4 × as wide as area superomedia (width at level of costulae); area
                  superomedia large, about 1.4 × as wide as long, coriaceous and matt, not depressed
                  and open posteriorly, with few transverse striae at its lateral margins. Area
                  petiolaris very slightly depressed and with irregular transverse striae. Rim of
                  propodeal spiracle and carina connecting propodeal spiracle to pleural carina
                  normal.</p>
            <p>METASOMA. Postpetiole coriaceous. Metasomal tergite II 1.6 × as long as posteriorly
                  wide. Ovipositor ratio about 1.6.</p>
            <p>COLOUR. Black. Palps and tegulae yellowish-white. Mandibles (except black base and
                  reddish teeth) and pedicel apically yellow. Scape and flagellum yellowish-brown,
                  flagellum lighter distally. Pterostigma yellowish-brown. All coxae black, fore
                  coxa yellow marked distally, all tibial spurs yellowish-white; fore and mid
                  trochanters and trochantelli yellow, fore and mid femora, tibiae and tarsi
                  yellowish-red. Hind trochanter and trochantellus brownish, hind femur red, hind
                  tibia and tarsus yellowish-red, tibia with very small light spot at base, slightly
                  brownish subbasally. Metasoma and ovipositor sheath black.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Notes </p>
            <p> The examined specimen, which we designate as the lectotype , does not fit the
                  description of <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex tibialis </tp:taxon-name> , as the
                  ovipositor ratio is clearly greater than that of <tp:taxon-name> C. tibialis
                  </tp:taxon-name> . Also, the specimen is characterized by the temple, in lateral
                  view, at most 0.4–0.5 × as long as the transverse diameter of the eye and the
                  propodeum with the area basalis triangular (as in <tp:taxon-name> Campoplex
                        angustioranae (Bauer, 1937) </tp:taxon-name> ; Horstmann 1985 ). These
                  reasons led us to remove <tp:taxon-name> C. corsicator </tp:taxon-name> from
                  synonymy with <tp:taxon-name> C. tibialis ( Horstmann, 1985 ) </tp:taxon-name> .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
