<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Handaoia ruizcancinoi Bordera 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5056074</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FCAB303F3588A4E19CC92E2407EE055A</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Handaoia Seyrig, 1952 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Phygadeuontinae): the first to be described from the New World</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1415</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia ruizcancinoi
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
151C284F-8024-4A2A-97FD-D0BBDE6AF048
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1E
, 
7
, 
9A
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia ruizcancinoi
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be distinguished from all other New World species by the combination of the following characters: apophysis of propodeum conspicuously high, subtriangular with blunt tip (
Fig. 7H
, arrow); juxtacoxal carina weak but complete, joining submetapleural carina at its anterior part (
Fig. 7G
, arrow); inner side of area externa about 7.0× as long as inner side of area dentipara (
Fig. 1E
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named in honour of Dr Enrique Ruiz Cancino from Universidad Autónoma de 
Tamaulipas
(
Mexico
), in recognition of his contribution to the study of the 
<tp:taxon-name>Ichneumonidae</tp:taxon-name>
of 
Mexico
. A noun in the genitive case.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
holotype
female.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MEXICO
• 
♀
; 
Tamaulipas
, Ocampo, J. de Manantiales; 
T. Amarillas
; 

13 May 1995

; 
J. Coronado
, 
S. Nino
and 
C. Hernández
leg.; 
CEUA
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Body length (without ovipositor) 4.0 mm. Fore wing about 3.0 mm long.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
Morphology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia ruizcancinoi
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (CEUA). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head, front view. 
C
. Head and mososoma, lateral view. 
D
. Head and mososoma, dorsal view. 
E
. Tergite I, dorsal view. 
F
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
G
. Metapleuron (arrow: juxtacoxal carina). 
H
. Propodeum (arrow: propodeal apophysis). Scale bars: A = 0.5 mm; B–F = 0.2 mm; G–H = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Finely granulate, matt, strongly narrowed behind eyes, occiput very concave centrally in dorsal view (
Fig. 7B–D
); gena 0.14 × length of eye in dorsal view; posterior ocellus separated from eye by 1.55 × its maximum diameter; distance between posterior ocelli 1.27 × maximum ocellar diameter; occipital carina gently V-shaped medially (
Fig. 7D
); malar space 1.3× basal width of mandible; face conspicuously swollen medially (
Fig. 7B
); clypeus (
Fig. 7B
) quite convex, gently granulate with scattered coarse punctures, apex slightly rounded, about 1.8 × as wide as high; mandible quite tapered to apex, ventral tooth of mandible a little shorter than upper tooth; flagellum widened in middle, tapered towards apex, flagellomeres 8–18 flattened ventrally; flagellum with 20 segments, length-thickness ratios: 1 
st
segment = 4.1, 2 
nd
= 3.27 and 10 
th
= 0.72.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA. Finely granulate and matt (
Fig. 7A, C–D
); mesoscutum slightly convex, almost flat posteriorly; notauli moderately deep over 0.7× length of mesoscutum (
Fig. 7D
); scutellum moderately convex, without lateral carinae; sternaulus as a wide V-shaped depression anteriorly, reaching about 0.3× the length of mesopleuron (
Fig. 7C
); juxtacoxal carina weak but complete, joining submetapleural carina at its anterior part (
Fig. 7G
, arrow); propodeum (
Figs 1E
, 
7C, H
) with strong and conspicuous carinae; area superomedia confluent with area basalis and separated from area petiolaris; inner side of area externa about 7.0× as long as inner side of area dentipara; inner side of area dentipara about 0.3× length of outer side; area spiracularis confluent with area lateralis; posterior transverse carina strong, forming an elevated apophysis joining lateral longitudinal carina, apophysis subtriangular with blunt tip (
Fig. 7C, H
, arrow). Length of hind femur 3.9× its height. Hind wing with vein 
cu-a
0.77 × as long as abscissa of 
CU
between 
M
and 
cu-a
.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA. Tergite I (
Fig. 7E
) finely granulate, shiny, strigose laterally, about 2.4× as long as its maximum width; lateromedian longitudinal carina moderately strong, reaching posterior 0.8× length of tergite; lateral longitudinal carina present from spiracle to posterior margin of postpetiole; tergite II (
Fig. 7F
) shiny, smooth and almost glabrous; remaining tergites (
Fig. 7F
) smooth and shiny, with short and moderately dense setiferous punctures. Ovipositor sheath about 0.5× as long as hind tibia.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR. Head (
Fig. 7B–D
) brown, darker dorsally, lighter ventrally, mandibular teeth and labrum dark brown; antenna with scape, pedicel and first flagellomere light brown, remaining flagellomeres dark brown, flagellomeres 5–7 dorsally white (
Fig. 7A
). Mesosoma (
Fig. 7A, C
) brown, more infuscate ventrally. Metasoma (
Fig. 7E–F
) dark brown. Legs (
Fig. 7A
) mostly dark brown; fore and mid coxae and trochanters, and hind trochanter, white. Wings (
Fig. 7A
) evenly infuscate.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
