<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Handaoia Seyrig 1952</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5515757</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03858793FFD0FFA3DA58FA7D7D68F85B</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Handaoia Seyrig, 1952 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Phygadeuontinae): the first to be described from the New World</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1415</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus
<tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia
Seyrig, 1952
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia
Seyrig, 1952: 26
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
(type species: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia spinosa
Seyrig, 1952
</tp:taxon-name>
, by original designation).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia
</tp:taxon-name>
can be recognized and separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>Phygadeuontinae</tp:taxon-name>
genera by the combination of the distally expanded and ventrally flattened antennal flagellum, complete posterior transverse carina of the mesosternum, isolated ʻpit’ (episternal scrobe) in the mesopleuron, and a single bulla in fore wing vein 2 
m-cu
. The following more complete diagnosis is modified from 
Townes (1970)
, who included 
<tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia
</tp:taxon-name>
in a key to the genera of ‘Chiroticina’. Townes’ definition applies equally well to the Afrotropical species originally included as well as to the Neotropical and Palaearctic species: flagellum of female antenna fusiform (expanded beyond the middle and flattened ventrally) with a median white ring; genal carina reaching base of mandible; mandibular teeth subequal; maxillary palp long, reaching beyond centre of mesosternum; pronotum with two dorsal pits separated by weak longitudinal carina, usually flanked laterally by 3–4 longitudinal carinae; epomia absent; median lobe of mesoscutum without median longitudinal groove; scutellum without lateral carinae; mesopleural impression (episternal scrobe) ventral to speculum as an isolated pit, some distance from mesopleural furrow; posterior transverse carina of mesosternum complete; fore wing with areolet pentagonal, its outer side open (vein 3 
rs-m
missing), vein 2 
m-cu
with one wide bulla; area superomedia always separated from area petiolaris and usually confluent with area basalis; laterotergites of metasomal tergites 2 and 3 not separated or only weakly separated from tergite. Small species, body length 
2–5 mm
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key to the New World species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Apophysis of propodeum high, parallel sided or subtriangular, with blunt tip (
Figs 2F
, 
4G
, 
7H
, arrows) .............................................................................................................................................. 2

</p>
      <p>

– Apophysis of propodeum as a low transverse rounded crest, or slightly pointed (
Figs 3G
, 
5I
, 
8I
, arrows) .............................................................................................................................................. 4

</p>
      <p>

2. Area externa of propodeum confluent with area dentipara (
Fig. 1A
). Juxtacoxal carina absent (
Fig. 2C
). First and second flagellomeres about 5.6 and 6.5 × as long as wide respectively. Hind coxa tinged with white (
Fig. 2A
) .............................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. cuscoensis
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Area externa of propodeum separated from area dentipara by strong carina (
Fig. 1C, E
). Juxtacoxal carina present, usually strong (
Figs 4F
, 
7G
). First and second flagellomeres about 4–5 and 3.2–5.4 × as long as wide, respectively. Hind coxa entirely dark brown (
Figs 4A
, 
7A
) .................................. 3

</p>
      <p>

3. Fore wing with well-defined transverse dark brown band (
Fig. 4A
). Inner side of area externa 4.7 × as long as inner side of area dentipara (
Fig. 1C
). Juxtacoxal carina strong, irregular, joining submetapleural carina at its mid-length (
Fig. 4F
). Tergite I about 1.8× as long as its maximum width. First and second flagellomeres about 5 and 5.4× as long as wide respectively. Flagellum dark brown (except white band), with first and second flagellomeres light brown (
Fig. 4A– B
) .................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. mercedensis
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Fore wing evenly infuscate (
Fig. 7A
). Inner side of area externa 7.0× as long as inner side of area dentipara (
Fig. 1E
). Juxtacoxal carina weak but complete, joining anterior part of submetapleural carina (
Fig. 7G
). Tergite I about 2.4× as long as its maximum width. First and second flagellomeres 4.1 and 3.3× as long as wide respectively. Flagellum dark brown (except white band), with only first flagellomere light brown (
Fig. 7A
) ................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. ruizcancinoi
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

4. Area externa of propodeum confluent with area dentipara (
Fig. 1D
). Juxtacoxal carina absent (
Fig. 5H
). Sternaulus very short and weak, reaching at most 0.3× the length of the mesopleuron (
Fig. 5E
). Head coarsely granulate (
Fig. 5B–C
) ............................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. plaumanni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Area externa of propodeum separated from area dentipara by a strong carina (
Fig. 1B, F
). Juxtacoxal carina present (
Figs 3F
, 
8H
, arrows). Sternaulus deep, reaching at least 0.5 × the length of the mesopleuron (
Figs 3D
, 
8G
). Head finely granulate .......................................................................... 5

</p>
      <p>

5. Inner side of area externa 3.0–3.4 × as long as inner side of area dentipara (
Fig. 1B
); inner side of area dentipara (section of the lateromedian longitudinal carina) 0.4–0.5 × the length of the outer side (section of the lateral longitudinal carina) (
Fig. 1B
). Lateromedian longitudinal carina of first metasomal tergite weak, reaching at most 0.6× the length of the tergite, or sometimes inconspicuous (
Fig. 1B
). Malar space 1.15–1.25× as long as basal mandibular width (
Fig. 3E
). Tergite II smooth and shiny (
Fig. 3B
). Clypeus 2.1–2.2 × as wide as high (
Fig. 3E
) ..................................................... ................................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. fritzi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Inner side of area externa about 8.0× as long as inner side of area dentipara (
Fig. 1F
); inner side of area dentipara 0.25 × the length of the outer side (
Fig. 1F
). Lateromedian longitudinal carina of tergite I strong, reaching 0.8 × the length of the tergite (
Fig. 1F
). Malar space 1.4 × as long as mandible base (
Fig. 8B
). Tergite II finely granulate (
Fig. 8D
). Clypeus 1.6× as wide as high (
Fig. 8B
) ................................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. urceus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
