<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) triquetrus</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4545863</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/358BB15341FFB678E9E45934F7FE2A6E</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic review of the Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) agenor species group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus triquetrus
Luederwaldt, 1923:11
</tp:taxon-name>
(original description).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pintous triquetrus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Blackwelder 1944: 208

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius triquetrus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 
Schoolmeesters 2018
(
Catalogue of Life
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius triquetrus
</tp:taxon-name>
is separated from other species in the group by the following combination of characters: dorsal and ventral surface reddish to dark brown. Anterior clypeal margin with deep emargination separating two obtuse teeth. Head interocular space displaying flat punctures, resembling rough; distinct ocellate punctuation near eyes. Pronotum medial disc with fine punctures, anterolateral edges with well-impressed punctures, ocellate punctuation along margins. Elytra striae strongly marked, interstriae microsculpture shagreened
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO
• 
♀
; “Caparo Trinidad Heyne, Berlin-Wilm.” [white, p]/ “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus triquetrus
</tp:taxon-name>
n. sp.
L̹d.det.23” [white, hw]/ “18188” [white, p] /[blue rounded label]; 
MZSP
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; 
St. George Co.
, 
Range
, 
Simla Research Station
, 
Arima Valley
, 
N. Range
; 

800 ft
a.s.l.

; 
10º41′34″ N
, 
61º17′22″ W
; FIT [
flight interception trap
]; premontane tropical rainforest; 

3 Jun. 2000

; 
S. Alistair
and 
Ramsdale
leg.; 
CEMT
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Trinidad
; 1904; 
F. Birch
leg.; 
BMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Antilles Trinidad
; 
Fry
leg.; 
BMNH 1905-100
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Porto Spain
, 

Dec 1912

– 

May 1913

; 
R. Thaiter
leg.; 
MZSP
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
VENEZUELA
• 
1 ♂
; 
BMNH
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
COUNTRY UNKNOWN • 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Nevinson
leg.; 
BMNH 1918-14
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
17.89 mm
. Dorsal and ventral surfaces reddish to dark brown.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Anterior edge surface horizontally rugose, interocular space displaying flat punctures, resembling rough; distinct ocellate punctuation near eyes. Clypeus with central deep emargination separating two acute clypeal teeth (
Fig. 16
B–C). Cephalic carina bituberculate, wider than high, tubercles obtuse apically (
Fig. 16C
). Ventral clypeal process truncate (see 
Fig. 2B
).
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM. Gibbous, wider than long. Pronotal anterior disc shiny and smooth with fine, dense and wellimpressed punctures near antero-lateral sides. Uninterrupted ocellate punctures along pronotal margins (
Fig. 16B, D
). Hypomeral disc punctate; external margin bearing single row of organized long setae, approximately of same length (see 
Fig. 2F
).
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Prosternum surface with fine microsculptured, glabrous. Mesosternum and metepisternum surface microsculpture shagreened with ocellate setigerous punctures. Metasternum setigerous punctures restricted mainly to anterior and lateral edges of mestasternal lobe, puncture diameter variable. Punctuation of antero-median edge connecting with lateral ones through margin of mesocoxa (see 
Fig. 2G
). Lateral edges of metasternum with ocellate, setigerous punctures separated by width of a puncture, pilosity sparse, setae short, not reaching metepisternum suture. Longitudinal sulcus clearly visible. Ocellate punctures along anterior margins of sternites. Pygidium ocellate punctation on basal edge and through lateral margins.
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA. Interstriae microsculpture shagreened (see 
Fig. 2J
), fine punctures randomly distributed. Striae strongly marked, ocellate punctures separated by diameter of a puncture on elytral disc (
Fig. 16D
).
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Metacoxa posterior edge bearing single row of organized ocellate punctures, separated by diameter of a puncture. Posterior margin of meta-trochanter with long setae.</p>
      <p>
Morphological variation
</p>
      <p>
Males
(
Fig. 16A
) are distinguished from females as follows:
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Cephalic carina higher than wide, conical in shape. Median tubercle twice as high as lateral tubercles, rounded, weakly bifurcate apically and curved posteriorly. Apex of lateral tubercles acute.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Surface covered by fine punctures, denser at antero-lateral areas; anterior disc with weak declivity.</p>
      <p>
PARAMERES AND LAMELLA COPULATRIX. As in 
Fig. 16
E–G.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This is an endemic species from 
Trinidad
.The redescription was based on the well-developed female of the MZSP and the underdeveloped female at the CEMT. The male redescription was based on the specimen in the MZSP wrongly determined by Pereira as “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus belus
</tp:taxon-name>
” and an underdeveloped male from the CEMT. Male genitalia were extracted from the underdeveloped male at CEMT. 
Luederwaldt (1923)
also mentioned a male specimen in the 
type
series that could not be traced.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
