<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) sagittarius Montoya-Molina &amp; Vaz-De 2021, stat. rev.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4545857</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/508C73EC019D6D12FEB6FE4FAE552E06</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic review of the Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) agenor species group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus sagittarius
Harold, 1869
</tp:taxon-name>
(original description).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus sagittarius
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Luederwaldt 1929: 99

. — 

Blackwelder 1944: 208

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius amplicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

López-Guerrero 2005: 196

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius sagittarius
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. rev.
is separated from other species in the group by the following combination of characters: head cephalic carina median tubercle approximately twice as high as lateral ones, conical in shape, weakly curved posterially and never bifurcated at apex. Anterior disc of the pronotum displaying moderate declivity, not abrupt and truncated as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. agenor
</tp:taxon-name>
and 

<tp:taxon-name>D. amplicollis</tp:taxon-name>
.

External margin of hypomeron bearing multiple rows of disorganized long setae. Metacoxa posterior edge with single row of ocellate punctures, punctation never merges. Elytral interstriae shagreened.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated) 
MEXICO
• 
♂
; “Toxpam 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. sagittarius
Harold.
</tp:taxon-name>
” [white with red margins, hw]/ “ 
Ex-Musaeo E. Harold
” [white with black margins, p]; 
MNHN
.

</p>
      <p>
Paralectotypes

(2 ♂♂, 
1 ♀
)
</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
• 
♀
; “Mexique 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus sagittarius
Chevrol.
</tp:taxon-name>
” [white, hw]/ “Ex-Museaeo E. Harold / PARALECTOTYPE ♀ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus sagittarius
Harold
</tp:taxon-name>
des. 
F.Z. Vaz-de-Mello
, 2014” [yellow with black margin, phw]; 
MNHN

• 

♂
;“Type” [white,rounded with red margins]/“Cordova”[white,p] / “Mexico Sallé Coll.” [white, p]/ “B.C.A. p. 52 sp.4” [white, phw]/ “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus sagittarius
</tp:taxon-name>
Type Harold apud Sallé” [white, hw]/ “NHMUK 010847040 [white, p]; 
BMNH

• 

♂
; “Type” [white, rounded with red margins]/ “Cordova” [white, p]/ “Mexico Sallé Coll.” [white, p] / B.C.A. p. 52 sp.4 [white, phw]/ 720 [green, p]/ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus sagittarius
</tp:taxon-name>
Type Harold apud Sallé [white, hw]/ 
<tp:taxon-name>P. Sagittarius Harold.</tp:taxon-name>
[white, hw] /TYPE 
<tp:taxon-name>
SAGITTARIUS
HAROLD
</tp:taxon-name>
det. F. Génier, 2008 [white with black margins, phw] / PARALECTOTYPE [yellow with black margins, p]/ “NHMUK 010847041” [white, p]; 
BMNH

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
BELIZE
• 
1 ♂
; 
Cayo
, 
Las Cuevas Research station
; 

550 m
a.s.l.

; 
16º43.99 N
, 
88º59.20 W
; 

22 May 2000

; 
M. Caterino
; 
BMNH

• 

4 ♂♂
, 
3 ♀♀
; 
Chiquibul Forest Res
, 
Las Cuevas field station
; 

500–700 m
a.s.l.

; 
88º59′ W
; 
16º44′ N
; 
May–Jun.
1997; 
D. Inward
leg.; 
BMNH 2005-78

.
</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
• 
1 ♂
; 
Fry
leg.; 
BMNH 1905-100

• 

1 ♀
; 
Fry
leg.; 
BMNH 1905-100

• 

1 ♀
; 
Curtis
leg.; 
BMNH
. – 

Chiapas

• 

12 ♂♂
, 
17 ♀♀
; 
Marqués de Comillas
, 
Chajul
; 
16º05′32″ N
, 
90º12′13″ W
; 
Frag. Rafa
; 

Aug. 2005

; 

G. Ponce
leg.; 
CEMT
.


– 

Oaxaca

• 
2 ♂♂
; 
Santa María Chimalapa
; 

187 m
a.s.l.

; 
16º55′27.2″ N
, 
94º42′20″ W
; 

12 Jul. 2015

; 

Victor Moctezuma
leg.; 
CEMT
.


– 

Veracruz

• 
6 ♂♂
, 
7 ♀♀
; 
La Bocana
; 
human faeces
; 

26 Jul. 1996

; 
CEMT

• 

1 ♀
; 
Fortín
; 

1–4 Oct. 1967

; 
E. Greenwood
leg.; 
CEMT
.


– 

San Luis

• 
1 ♂
; 

3 mi.
W of El Naranjo

; 

1100 m
a.s.l.

; 

10–18 Jun. 1971

; 
A. Newton
leg.; 
CEMT

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
20.43 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Anterior surface rugose, not extending posteriorly to base of cephalic carina. Cephalic carina wider than high. Median tubercle twice as high as lateral tubercles. Median tubercle conical in shape, weakly curved, apically obtuse and never bifurcate (
Fig. 13C
). Inter-ocular space shiny, smooth and surrounded by small shallow punctures. Ventral clypeal process truncate and expanded distally (see 
Fig. 2B
).
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM. Wider than long and wider than elytra. Anterior disk with moderate declivity, anterolateral surface next to fossae with fine punctures. Row of interrupted ocellate punctures along Pronotal margins, denser on anterior and posterior margins (
Fig. 13A
). Pronotal medial disc shiny, covered by fine punctures. Hypomeron disc smooth, lacking punctures. External margin bearing multiple rows of disorganized long setae, all approximately of same length (see 
Fig. 2E
).
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Mesosternum and metepisternum covered by dense ocellate setigerous punctures. Metasternum setigerous punctures restricted mainly to lateral and anterior areas of mestasternal lobe. Pilosity of antero-median portion connecting with lateral through margin of mesocoxa (see 
Fig. 2G
). Metasternum lateral surface, with ocellate setigerous punctures separated by three times width of a puncture. Ocellate punctures along anterior margins of each sternite, denser in lateral sides, medial portion smooth. Pygidium basal margin bearing some ocellate punctures.
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA. Interstriae shagreened with fine, randomly separated punctures. Striae clearly marked, with ocellate punctures separated by diameter of a puncture on elytral disc (
Fig. 13A
).
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Metacoxa posterior edge bearing single row of organized setigerous punctures, separated between them by one time diameter of a puncture, punctures never merge together (
Fig. 13D
).
</p>
      <p>
PARAMERES AND LAMELLA COPULATRIX. As in 
Fig. 13
E–G.
</p>
      <p>
Morphological variation
</p>
      <p>
Females
(
Fig. 13B
)
</p>
      <p>As males except for the following characters:</p>
      <p>HEAD. Surface completely transversely rugose, denser on anterior portion. Cephalic carina quadridentate, feebly elevated.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Weak medial knob discernible on lateral view, punctures denser and deeply impressed laterally.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Striae, thinner with small punctures separated by twice diameter of a puncture on elytral disc.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius sagittarius
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. rev.
was synonymized with 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. amplicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
by 
López-Guerrero (2005)
. A detailed examination of the 
lectotype
led us to conclude that 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. sagittarius
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. rev.
should be revalidated, as there are clear differences between the types and recently collected specimens of both species. The distribution of this species follows areas of dry forests of the Gulf of 
Mexico
and the 
Yucatán
peninsula across the Mexican east coast (
Morrone 2001
). According to 
Morrone (2001)
, these two areas are ecologically similar and comparable with areas in the province of 
Chiapas
and the east and south of the Sierra Madre, suggesting that it is highly probable that 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. sagittarius
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. rev.
will be found in those areas.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
