<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia)
                        simplicicornis</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4545859</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03850669FFB9FFE5FE2A274D39D4CFB0</uri>
                  <article-title>Taxonomic review of the Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) agenor
                        species group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature/>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Pinotus simplicicornis Luederwaldt, 1935: 340 </tp:taxon-name>
                  (original description). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Pinotus simplicicornis </tp:taxon-name> – Blackwelder 1944: 208 . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Dichotomius simplicicornis </tp:taxon-name> – Ratcliffe et al .
                  2015: 197 . — Chamorro et al. 2018: 95 ; 2019: 132 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Dichotomius simplicicornis </tp:taxon-name> is separated from
                  other species in the group by the following combination of characters: cephalic
                  carina median tubercle higher than lateral ones, apically rounded and emarginate.
                  Lateral tubercles short with acute on apex. Ventral clypeal process conical
                  apically acute. Pronotum medial edge of the anterior disc declivity deeper than
                  lateral sides, resembling two underdeveloped lobes. Elytral striae well marked,
                  punctuation same width of striae; interstriae smooth. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Lectotype (head and pronotum, here designated) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> PERU • ♂ ; “Peru” [white, hw]/ “ <tp:taxon-name> Pinotus
                              simplicicornis </tp:taxon-name> n. sp. Lueder. Det. 1934” [white, hw]/
                        “Fry Coll. 1905-100” [white, p]/ “34600” [white, hw]/ “ HOLOTYPE ” [red with
                        black margins, p]; BMNH . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Additional material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> PERU • 8 ♂♂ , 4 ♀♀ ; Junín , Pichinaqui , Yaroni ; 2 Apr.
                        2006 ; A. Santibáñez leg.; CEMT </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Redescription </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Length: 20.17 mm . </p>
            <p> HEAD. Anterior third surface transversely rugose, extending posteriorly not reaching
                  base of cephalic carina. Interocular space smooth, with scattered deep punctures (
                  Fig. 14 C–D). Clypeal margin with large medial emargination separating two rounded
                  clypeal teeth feebly angled upwards. Cephalic carina, wider than high and conical
                  in shape ( Fig. 14D ). Median tubercle three times as high as lateral tubercles,
                  apically rounded and emarginate. Lateral tubercles short and acute on apex ( Fig.
                  14C ). Ventral clypeal process conical in shape and apically acute. </p>
            <p> PRONOTUM. Twice as wide as it is long, wider than elytra. Pronotal disc shiny and
                  with well-impressed simple punctures, larger punctures on anterolateral edges and
                  near posterior basal central margin.Anterior disc with sharp declivity, medial
                  portion deeper than lateral sides, resembling two underdeveloped lobes ( Fig. 14A,
                  D ). Hypomeron medial disc smooth and shiny, external margin bearing rows of
                  disorganized setigerous punctures, setae all approximately of same length (see
                  Fig. 2E ). </p>
            <p> ABDOMEN. Prosternum surface shagreened, with scattered ocellate setigerous
                  punctures. Mesosternum and metepisternum surface shagreened, with large ocellate
                  setigerous punctures, separated by less than twice diameter of a puncture.
                  Metasternum anterior surface and margins of mesocoxa microsculpture shagreened,
                  covered by dense long setae that surrounds the margins of mesocoxa, joining the
                  anteromedial with lateral portions of metasternum (see Fig. 2G ). Longitudinal
                  sulcus distinctly sculpted, ending as shallow mid-fossa. Sternites with ocellate
                  punctures along anterior margins. Pygidium delimited by incomplete margin, faded
                  apically, large punctures restricted to basal margin, medial and apical surfaces
                  finely punctate. </p>
            <p> Fig. 14. <tp:taxon-name> Dichotomius simplicicornis ( Luederwaldt, 1935 )
                  </tp:taxon-name> . A–B . Dorsal habitus. A . ♂. B . ♀. C . Lateral view of the
                  aedeagus. D . Frontal view of the male head, cephalic carina apically rounded,
                  emarginate, lateral tubercles short and acute on the apex. E . Ventral view of the
                  aedeagus. F–G . Lamella copulatrix. H . Pronotum arcuate viewed from above,
                  anterior edge declivity resembling two under-developed lobes at the sides. </p>
            <p>ELYTRA. Shiny, wider than long. Striae distinctly punctate separated by two times
                  diameter of a puncture on elytral disc; punctures same width of striae.
                  Interstriae smooth with conspicuous randomly arranged punctures.</p>
            <p>LEGS. Metacoxa microsculpture shagreened, posterior edge covered by row of dense
                  setigerous punctures separated by less than diameter of a puncture, setae dense.
                  In ventral view, profemora surface with scattered well-imprinted punctation,
                  setigerous punctation restricted to medial edge.</p>
            <p> PARAMERES AND LAMELLA COPULATRIX. See Fig. 14 E–G. </p>
            <p> Morphological variation </p>
            <p> Females ( Fig. 14B ) </p>
            <p>As males except for the following characters:</p>
            <p>HEAD. Surface completely rugose. Space between clypeal teeth less separated than in
                  males. Genae border protruding clypeal margin. Fronto-clypeal carina
                  bituberculate.</p>
            <p>PRONOTUM. Narrower than elytra, gibbous.</p>
            <p>ELYTRA. Twice as long as pronotum with shagreened microsculpture.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> The holotype has the first half of the body (head and pronotum) of a male and the
                  second half (abdomen) of a female. As the ICZN states in Article 73.1.5 “ If a
                  subsequent author finds that a holotype which consists of a set of components
                  (e.g. disarticulated body parts) is not derived from an individual animal, the
                  extraneous components may, by appropriate citation, be excluded from the holotype
                  (material may be excluded from a hapantotype if it is found to contain components
                  representing more than one taxon ”; therefore, we here designate the head and the
                  pronotum as lectotype . Endemic species from Peru and individuals cited by
                  Chamorro et al. (2018: 95 , 2019: 132 ) from Ecuador were the rare species
                        <tp:taxon-name> Dichotomius foveicollis (Kirsch, 1871) </tp:taxon-name> .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
