<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Handaoia urceus Bordera &amp; Broad 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5056076</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F9DE6527DD79621EED715B0835E28958</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Handaoia Seyrig, 1952 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Phygadeuontinae): the first to be described from the New World</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1415</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia urceus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
5413C7C8-D785-4583-803F-0C1E75B7EA9E
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1F
, 
8
, 
9B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia urceus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be distinguished from all other New World species by the combination of the following characters: apophysis of propodeum as a low transverse rounded crest (
Fig. 8I
, arrow); tergite II finely granulate (
Fig. 8D
); juxtacoxal carina strong anteriorly, weak posteriorly, joining submetapleural carina at its half length (
Fig. 8H
, arrow); area externa of propodeum separated from area dentipara by strong carina (
Fig. 1F
); inner side of area externa about 8.0× as long as inner side of area dentipara (
Fig. 1F
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>From the Latin for ‘pitcher’, named after the flask- or pitcher-shaped combined area basalis + superomedia. A noun in apposition.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
holotype
female.
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Nova Teutonia
; 
27º11′ S
, 
52º23′ W
; 

8 Feb. 1939

; 
F. Plaumann
leg.; B.M. 1939-181; 
B.M. Type Hym
3b.2873; 
NHMUK010636380
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length (without ovipositor) 
4.3 mm
. Fore wing 
3.7 mm
long.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Finely granulate, matt, distinctly narrowed behind eyes, occiput very concave centrally in dorsal view (
Fig. 8B–C
); gena 0.22 × length of eye in dorsal view; posterior ocellus separated from eye by 1.0 × its maximum diameter; distance between posterior ocelli 1.0× maximum ocellar diameter (
Fig. 8C
); occipital carina gently V-shaped medially (
Fig. 8E
); malar space 1.44 × basal width of mandible; face moderately swollen medially (
Fig. 8B
); clypeus (
Fig. 8B
) weakly convex, gently granulate with scattered punctures, apex slightly rounded, about 1.6× as wide as high; mandible slightly tapered to apex, ventral tooth approximately same length as upper tooth; maxillary palp long, almost reaching middle coxa; flagellum widened in middle, tapered towards apex (
Fig. 8A
), flagellomeres 8–18 flattened ventrally; flagellum with 22 segments, length-thickness ratios: 1 
st
segment = 4.9, 2 
nd
= 6.1 and 10 
th
= 1.13.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA. Finely granulate and matt (
Fig. 8E, G
); mesoscutum (
Fig. 8E, G
) convex, notauli moderately deep anteriorly, reaching about 0.3 × distance to scuto-scutellar groove; scutellum moderately convex, without lateral carinae; sternaulus moderately deep, reaching about mid-point of mesopleuron (
Fig. 8G
); juxtacoxal carina strong anteriorly, weak posteriorly, joining submetapleural carina at mid length (
Fig. 8H
, arrow); propodeum (
Figs 1F
, 
8I
) with strong and conspicuous carinae; area superomedia confluent with area basalis and separated from area petiolaris; inner side of area externa about 8.0 × as long as inner side of area dentipara; inner side of area dentipara 0.25 × length of outer side; area spiracularis confluent with area lateralis; posterior transverse carina strongly elevated, forming a low transverse crest joining lateral longitudinal carina (
Fig. 8I
, arrow). Length of hind femur 4.2 × its height. Hind wing with vein 
cu-a
about 1.0 × as long as abscissa of 
CU
between 
M
and 
cu-a
.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA. Tergite I (
Figs 1F
, 
8D
) finely granulate, matt, about 1.70 × as long as its maximum width; postpetiole laterally and posteriorly tending to fine strigosity; lateromedian and lateral longitudinal carinae strong, reaching at least 0.8× length of tergite; tergite II (
Fig. 8D, F
) finely granulate, shiny; remaining tergites (
Fig. 8D, F
) smooth and shiny with inconspicuous setiferous punctures. Ovipositor sheath about 0.54× as long as hind tibia.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR. Head (
Fig. 8B–C
) dark brown tending to be more reddish on clypeus and mandibles; palpi light brown; antenna with scape, pedicel and flagellomeres I–II (III) light brown, remaining flagellomeres dark brown, distal part of flagellomere 4 to flagellomere 7 dorsally white (
Fig. 8A
). Mesosoma (
Fig. 8E– G
) entirely orange. Metasoma (
Fig. 8D–F
) with a gradient from orange at anterior of tergite I to dark brown on posterior tergites, posterior rim of tergites I–III yellowish. Legs (
Fig. 8A
) light brown, distal tarsomeres dark brown, fore and mid coxae, part of hind coxa and all trochanters and trochantelli lighter. Wings (
Fig. 8A
) slightly infuscate.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
Morphology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia urceus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (NMHUK). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head, front view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
E
. Head and mesosoma, dorsal view. 
F
. Metasoma, lateral view. 
G
. Head and mesosoma, dorsolateral view. 
H
. Metapleuron (arrow: juxtacoxal carina). 
I
. Propodeum (arrow: propodeal apophysis). Scale bars: A, D–G = 0.5 mm; B–C, H–I = 0.2 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
