<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Xim Ibarra-Núñez &amp; Chamé-Vázquez &amp; Maya-Morales 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4452289</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0386965E2C30FFE971B9FCFE0F53D000</uri>
         <article-title>A new spider genus (Araneae: Linyphiidae: Erigoninae) from a tropical montane cloud forest of Mexico</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Xim
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E6CE6724-C10E-47E9-BC3A-9FC415514958
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Xim trenzado
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
by monotypy and present designation.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Xim
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
is sister to a clade including 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratinopsis
Emerton, 1882
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tutaibo
Chamberlin, 1916
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphecozone
O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1871
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xim
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
shares with each of these three genera a subtegulum ectal to the tegulum (
Figs 2C, F
, 
3A
), a membranous connection between radix and embolus (
Fig. 2B
), embolus originated from radix at a distinct angle (
Figs 2B, E
, H–I, 3B), a short, entire epigynum (
Fig. 5
A–B, G), fertilization duct separated from copulatory duct (
Fig. 5H
), and copulatory openings at the dorsal plate-ventral plate junction (
Fig. 5
A–B). Additionally, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xim
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
shares with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratinopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tutaibo
</tp:taxon-name>
an intersegmental, straight-hook paracymbium (
Fig. 2C, F
), a tegulum with papillae (
Fig. 2
B–C, E–F, H), a spiral radical tailpiece (
Figs 2
A–B, D–E, 3B) and a radical ridge (
Figs 2E
, H–I, 3B). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xim
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
differs from each of those three genera by having a high cymbium (
Figs 1B
, 
2A
, C–D, F), a large paracymbium (
Figs 2
A–F, 3A), a very short straight embolus (
Figs 2B, E
, H–I, 3B), male cheliceral stridulatory striae scaly, widely and evenly spaced, both sexes with a post-ocular lobe (
Fig. 1B, E
), male with two series of prolateral macrosetae on femur I (
Figs 1
A–B, 4A–G), and the female by having strongly oblong, u-shaped spermathecae (
Fig. 5
C–H). Furthermore, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xim
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratinopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking trichobothria on the prolateral side of palpal tibia, by having a retrolateral tibial apophysis (
Fig. 2C, F
) and the dorsal plate of epigynum with an anterior lobe flush with the ventral plate (
Fig. 5
A–B, G); from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tutaibo
</tp:taxon-name>
by lacking a cymbial basal excavation and a tegular sclerite on the anterior part of the tegulum, by having a cymbium retrolateral groove (
Fig. 2C
, F–H), an embolic membrane (
Figs 2E
, H–I, 3B), copulatory ducts not encapsulated (
Fig. 5
C–F, H) and male lacking a proximal dorsal macroseta on the tibiae I and II; from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphecozone
</tp:taxon-name>
by having a paracymbium (
Figs 2
A–F, 3A), a cymbial retrolateral groove (
Fig. 2C
, F–H), by lacking a cymbial basal excavation, and by lacking an epigynal atrium.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The genus is named after the word spider in the Mam language, whose native speakers inhabit the border area between 
Mexico
and 
Guatemala
. The gender is masculine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>BODY. Small (1.49–1.91), light brown; post-ocular lobe conical, lower in females; AER and PER slightly recurved; male with prolateral macrosetae on femur I; leg formula 1423.</p>
      <p>MALE PALP. Tibia with conspicuous prolateral apophysis, small retrolateral apophysis and one retrolateral trichobothrium; cymbium with prolateral and dorsal processes; paracymbium large; tegulum elliptical; radix with spiral tailpiece and serrated ridge; embolus very short and straight.</p>
      <p>EPIGYNUM. Ventral plate large, ovoid with anterior semicircular concavity; dorsal plate small rectangular and transverse with large anterior lobe; copulatory openings as narrow slits between ventral plate and anterior lobe of dorsal plate; copulatory ducts short and wide; spermathecae oblong, u-shaped with one mesal and one ectal branch; fertilization ducts small.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Phylogenetic relationships and justification of monotypy
</p>
      <p>
Our phylogenetic analysis yielded eight equally most parsimonious trees (L 1096, CI 0.19, RI 0.58; excluding uninformative characters 104 and 155: L 1094). The topology of the strict consensus of these trees (L 1099, CI 0.19, RI 0.58) is identical to the consensus tree of 

Frick 
et al.
(2010)

, except that here (and in each of the eight most parsimonious trees) 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xim trenzado
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
is sister to a clade that includes 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratinopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tutaibo
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphecozone
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Figs 6–7
), corresponding to clades 76 of 
Miller &amp; Hormiga (2004)
and 62 of 

Frick 
et al.
(2010)

. Circumscribing 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xim trenzado
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
within a polytypic genus would require synonymization of these three genera. Nevertheless, 
Miller &amp; Hormiga (2004: 402)
stated that the monophyly of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphecozone
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tutaibo
</tp:taxon-name>
are not in doubt and are clearly diagnosable. The phylogenetic analysis supports, with nine unambiguous characters, the hypothesis that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xim trenzado
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
is not congeneric with the genera included in clade 76 of 
Miller &amp; Hormiga (2004)
, making necessary a new genus for this species. The nine unambiguous characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xim trenzado
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
are: cymbium as tall as long (9-1); sperm duct path in distal part of tegulum with thigh kink (23-1), embolus short (43-1), initial orientation of PTA perpendicular (68-0), RTA present (70-1), male with a post-ocular, conical lobe (103-1), cheliceral stridulatory striae scaly (117-1), female palpal tarsus without proximal dorsomesal macrosetae (127-0), female palpal tarsus with one ventroectal macrosetae (132-1).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
