<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Docleiana Delicado &amp; Pesic 2021, gen.
            nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5493136</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/038A87BDFF82677BFDCA82B0FC7DFDE1</uri>
         <article-title>Arganiella Giusti &amp; Pezzoli, 1980 (Caenogastropoda: Truncatelloidea:
            Hydrobiidae): a widespread genus or several narrow-range endemic genera?</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1369</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Docleiana Delicado &amp; Pešić </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 04639DB3-91D2-46B7-BFAB-FFC1EA3C27BD </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Arganiella tabanensis Boeters, Glöer &amp; Pešić, 2014 </tp:taxon-name> .
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Revised diagnosis </p>
      <p>Shell valvatiform; whorls ca 3; aperture complete, from rounded to ellipsoidal; outer lip
         narrow, straight in lateral profile; umbilicus wide. Operculum corneous, yellowish, thin,
         pliable, rounded, paucispiral with a central nucleus, without peg. Two pairs of basal cusps
         on each central radular tooth. Ctenidium well developed, with 10–11 gill filaments. Animal
         unpigmented. Osphradium positioned opposite approximately to the middle of the ctenidium.
         Stomach without gastric caecum; rectum forms a gentle V-shape in the mantle cavity. Bursa
         copulatrix small, globular, pedunculated and positioned beyond the posterior edge of the
         albumen gland; bursal duct longer than bursal length; unpigmented renal oviduct; one
         pyriform seminal receptacle arising at the insertion point with the bursal duct loop. Penis
         small and simple, gradually tapering.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p>The new genus is named after Doclea, the name of the Roman city located on the site of
         modern Podgorica on whose municipal territory a new genus was found; gender feminine.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Docleiana Delicado &amp; Pešić </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. can be
         distinguished from <tp:taxon-name> Arganiella </tp:taxon-name> as the former has a more
         ellipsoidal shell aperture, a narrower base of the penis, a smaller bursa copulatrix that
         is positioned beyond the posterior edge of the albumen gland, a larger seminal receptacle
         and more cusps on the lateral radular teeth ( Fig. 2 ; for comparison, see Giusti &amp;
         Pezzoli 1980 ; Boeters et al. 2014 ). The new genus differs from the closely related genus
            <tp:taxon-name> Kerkia </tp:taxon-name> by its smaller shell, absence of lobes on the
         inner edge of the penis, a smaller bursa copulatrix, a more globular seminal receptacle and
         V-shaped rectum (see Radoman 1978 ; Bodon et al. 2001 ). Mean COI sequence divergence for
            <tp:taxon-name> Docleiana Delicado &amp; Pešić </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. was 14.5% with
            <tp:taxon-name> Arganiella </tp:taxon-name> and 12.3% with <tp:taxon-name> Kerkia
         </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
