<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aretiana
Delicado &amp; Ramos
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
7B207B6D-47E8-4211-8139-0CF98DA353D7
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Boetersiella wolfi
Boeters &amp; Glöer, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 1.
Maximum likelihood tree based on the combined (COI, 18S) dataset. Statistical support of the nodes is indicated when Bayesian posterior probabilities ≥ 0.95 and bootstrap supports ≥ 75% (black dots). On the right, the morphology of shell, penis and distal female genitalia is presented for: a) 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arganiella wolfi
Boeters &amp; Glöer
</tp:taxon-name>
, b) 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. pescei
Giusti &amp; Pezzoli, 1980
</tp:taxon-name>
and c) 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tabanensis
Boeters, Glöer &amp; Pešić, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
. Reproductive organs were re-drawn from 
Arconada &amp; Ramos (2007a)
, 

Bodon 
et al.
(2001)

and 

Boeters 
et al.
(2014)

for the three species, respectively. Scale bar below topology: substitutions per site.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Revised diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Shell trochiform; whorls 3.5–4.0; aperture complete, rounded; outer lip narrow, straight in lateral profile; umbilicus wide. Operculum corneous, yellowish, thin, pliable, oval to rounded, paucispiral with a central nucleus, without peg. Two pairs of basal cusps on each central radular tooth. Ctenidium well developed, with approximately 14 gill filaments. Osphradium positioned opposite to approximately the middle of the ctenidium. Stomach without gastric caecum; rectum forms a gentle U-shape in the mantle cavity. Bursa copulatrix medium-sized, pyriform, pedunculated and protruding beyond the posterior edge of the albumen gland; bursal duct shorter than bursal length; unpigmented renal oviduct that makes a complete loop over the pallial gland; one elongated or pyriform seminal receptacle arising from the renal oviduct, just above the insertion point with the bursal duct. Prostate gland bean-shaped, about twice as long as wide. Penis small and simple, gradually tapering. Nervous system unpigmented.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The genus is named after Villa 
<tp:taxon-name>Aretiana</tp:taxon-name>
, the Roman name of the town Aracena, which gives its name to the mountain range where the genus was found (i.e., Sierra de Aracena); gender feminine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aretiana
Delicado &amp; Ramos
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arganiella
</tp:taxon-name>
as the former has a taller shell, a more oval operculum, pigmentation on the body and eyespots, fewer gill filaments, a narrower penis, a larger and pyriform bursa copulatrix located beyond the posterior edge of the albumen gland and fewer cusps on the lateral radular teeth (for comparison, see 
Giusti &amp; Pezzoli 1980
; 
Boeters &amp; Glöer 2007
; 
Arconada &amp; Ramos 2007a
). The new genus differs from the closely related genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Iberhoratia
</tp:taxon-name>
by its taller shell with a narrower umbilicus, the absence of lobes on the inner edge of the penis and of a proximal seminal receptacle (SR2) and presence of two pairs of basal cusps on each central radular tooth (see Arconada 
et al.
2007). Mean COI divergence for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aretiana
Delicado &amp; Ramos
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
was 15.9% with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arganiella
</tp:taxon-name>
and 11.2% with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Iberhoratia
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
