<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Eusarcus xambioa Júnior &amp; Ázara
                        &amp; Ferreira 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4633424</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/038B87ED0507FF97FDF7F9CC989D42DB</uri>
                  <article-title>Three new species of Eusarcus Perty, 1833 (Opiliones, Gonyleptidae)
                        from Brazilian caves</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://zoobank.org/bcc18dc2-7b6b-4f20-bf87-d94c4214a824</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus xambioa </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 96736EDB-2D6D-48A0-9FA8-9D41BCBAEA9F </p>
            <p> Figs 7–11 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus xambioa </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. resembles
                        <tp:taxon-name> E. aduncus </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> E. armatus
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> E. cavernicola </tp:taxon-name> ,
                        <tp:taxon-name> E. dandara </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> E. fulvus
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> E. mirabilis </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> E. oxyacanthus </tp:taxon-name> by having coxa IV with one
                  transversal, proapical, acute and conical apophysis but can be distinguished by
                  the following characters: short (shorter than trochanter IV width) probasal
                  apophysis on trochanter IV, high ocularium with spine, and femur IV with
                  proventral and retroventral rows of acuminate tubercles increasing in size
                  apically. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The specific epithet ʻ <tp:taxon-name> xambioa </tp:taxon-name> ʼ means ʻfast birdʼ
                  in the TUpi langUage and refers to a groUp of natives of the Araguaia River. It
                  also refers to the municipality where the type was found. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 7. <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus xambioa </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂, holotype (ISLA
            60386), habitUs. A . Dorsal view. B . Ventral view. C . Lateral view. Scale bars: A–B =
            1 mm; C = 0.5 mm. </p>
      <p> Fig. 8. <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus xambioa </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂, holotype (ISLA
            60386). A–B . Femur IV, dorsal and ventral view, respectively. C–D . Femur III, dorsal
            and ventral view, respectively. E–F . Patella and tibia IV, dorsal and ventral view,
            respectively. G–H . Patella and tibia III, dorsal and ventral view, respectively. I– J .
            Detail of trochanter IV, dorsal and ventral view, respectively. Scale bars: A–H = 0.5
            mm; I–J = 0.2 mm. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype BRAZIL • ♂ ; Tocantins State , Xambioá
                        MUnicipality, Caverna da Explosão ; 6°25′36.8″ S , 48°22′30.0″ W ; 21 Feb.
                        2018 ; R.L. Ferreira et al. leg; ISLA 60386 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male ( holotype , ISLA 60386) </p>
            <p>MEASUREMENTS. DSL 3.77, DSW 3.19, femur I 2.38, II 4.80, III 3.25, IV 4.49.</p>
            <p> DORSUM ( Fig. 7A, C ). Blunt PAM; acuminate median paracheliceral projection similar
                  in size to PAM. High ocularium with median spine (about twice times ocularium
                  height). Carapace with scattered granules. Scutal areas I–IV with scattered
                  granules with some tubercles among them. Posterior margin of dorsal scutum with
                  scattered granules. Lateral margins with blunt tubercles about the same size as
                  those on the scUtUm. Free tergites I–III with a defined row of granUles. Anal
                  opercUlUm with scattered granules. </p>
            <p> VENTER ( Fig. 7B ). Coxa I with irregular row of setiferous tubercles, coxae II–IV
                  densely and irregularly granulate. </p>
            <p>CHELICERAE. Segment I with two ectal-basal tubercles and one mesal-basal
                  tubercle.</p>
            <p>PEDIPALPS. Trochanter with sparse tubercles dorsally. Femur with one mesal apical
                  setiferous tubercle. Tibia setation: ectal IiIi, mesal IiIi; tarsus setation:
                  ectal IIIi, mesal IIi.</p>
            <p> LEGS ( Fig. 8 ). Coxae I–III with scattered granules; coxa IV with one transversal,
                  prolateral and apical apophysis, which is conical and short. Trochanters I–IV with
                  scattered tubercles; trochanter IV with one probasal apophysis, which is conical,
                  short and dorsally oriented. Femur III with proventral and retroventral rows of
                  acute tubercles increasing in size apically; tibia III with proventral and
                  retroventral </p>
            <p> Fig. 9. <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus xambioa </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂, holotype
                  (ISLA 60386), distal part of penis. A . Dorsal view. B . Ventral view. C . Right
                  lateral view. Scale bars = 50 μm. </p>
            <p>rows of acuminate tubercles. Femur IV slightly sinuous, with small PDS and RDS,
                  proventral row of acuminate tubercles increasing in size apically and retroventral
                  row with reduced tubercles; tibia IV with proventral and retroventral rows of
                  acuminate tubercles increasing in size subapically.</p>
            <p> PENIS ( Fig. 9 ). Ventral plate with substraight lateral margins; distal margin
                  slightly concave; ventral surface entirely covered with type T1 microsetae; with
                  three pairs of lateral-distal MS C1–C3, three pairs of A1, one pair of B1, one
                  pair of minute D1 and E1 absent. Stylus with ventrally-tilted medianventral
                  trichomes. Ventral process tUbUlar, cUrved, with apex with flabelliform
                  projection. </p>
            <p> COLOURATION (in alcohol) ( Figs 7–8 ). Body and appendages background colour Deep
                  Orange Yellow (69), appendages Strong Orange Yellow (68). </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Geographical distribution </p>
            <p> Known only from the type locality ( Fig. 11 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 10. A . External landscape of Vargem Alta Municipality, with many quarries for marble
            extraction. B . Living specimen of <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus marmoreus </tp:taxon-name>
            sp. nov. , ♂, holotype (ISLA 12968) from Caverna Archimides Panssini Cave, Vargem Alta
            Municipality, Espírito Santo State, Brazil. C . Living specimen of <tp:taxon-name>
                  Eusarcus xambioa </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂, holotype (ISLA 60386) from Caverna
            da Explosão Cave, Xambioá Municipality, Tocantins State, Brazil. Photos by R.L.
            Ferreira. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Ecological remarks </p>
            <p> Caverna da Explosão is a limestone cave with 1203 meters of horizontal projection.
                  The main entrance of the cave collapsed in the past, so that the access to the
                  cave interior is currently made through a small entrance located at the base of
                  the outcrop, leading to a very narrow passage. Most of the cave floor is covered
                  with terrigenoUs sediments, althoUgh a few fallen blocks are also present. Most of
                  the organic resources occurring in the cave are vegetal debris transported by
                  water during strong rains and especially bat guano, produced by a variety of bat
                  species, although droppings of hematophagous bats are the most common ones.
                  Despite the lack of any regUlar water flow, several areas of the cave can be
                  partially submerged during the rainy period. The single collected specimen was
                  observed freely walking on the cave floor ( Fig. 10C ), close to a gUano pile
                  prodUced by hematophagoUs bats. Since the cave was not completely surveyed during
                  our sampling, there is no indication of the size of the species’ population and
                  its density inside the cave. The region presents an Aw5 climate according to the
                  Köppen classification system, with an average annUal precipitation of aroUnd 1558
                  mm and an average annual temperature of 26.3ºC. The external area is quite
                  altered, especially due the replacement of natural vegetation by <tp:taxon-name>
                        Eucalyptus L’Hér. </tp:taxon-name> plantations. However, the outcrop where
                  the cave is located is surrounded by secondary forest. As with the other species
                  described herein, the area outside the cave was not sampled, so it is impossible
                  to determine the habitat preference for this species. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
