<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Platygaster karimpouri Asadi-Farfar &amp; Karimpour &amp; Lotfalizadeh &amp; Buhl 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773578</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/90CFC6F931C31730E3959ADD38BFC345</uri>
         <article-title>Four new species and new records of Platygastrinae (Hymenoptera: Platygastridae) from Iran</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1359</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Platygaster karimpouri
Asadi &amp; Buhl
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
0E67BA6B-93EC-4D7C-9278-04428A9D5DBB
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
(female)
</p>
      <p>A9 about 1.7 times as long as wide; head 1.7 times as wide as long, finely and densely striated behind; notauli indicated in about posterior half; female metasoma 1.1 times as long as rest of body, more than half of T2 striated at base, shorter medially.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Named after Dr Younes Karimpour at the Department of Plant Protection, Urmia University, 
Iran
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
♀
; 
East Azarbaijan Province
, 
Tasuj
; 
38°19′ N
, 
45°21′ E
; 

1500 m
a.s.l.

; 

23–30 May 2015

; 
H. Lotfalizadeh
leg.; 
Malaise trap
; 
HMIM
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
IRAN
• 
1 ♀
; 
East Azarbaijan Province
, 
Khosroshah
; 
37°58′ N
, 
46°02′ E
; 

1357 m
a.s.l.

; 

Aug. 2008

; 
H. Lotfalizadeh
leg.; 
Malaise trap
; 
HMIM
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(female)
</p>
      <p>
BODY LENGTH
. 
1.2 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
COLOR
. Black; metasoma towards apex with brownish tint; antennae, mandibles, tegulae, coxae and legs dark brown; A2–A5, trochanters, most of fore femora, entire fore tibiae, base of mid and hind tibiae, and all tarsi light brown.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD
. From above 1.7 times as wide as long, 1.15 times as wide as mesosoma; occiput rounded, finely but distinctly half-circularly striated all over; vertex smooth; frons with fine oblique striation on each side of a smooth midline. OOL:POL:LOL = 3.3:5.5:2.0. Eyes bare. Malar space about equal to half of eye height. Head in frontal view 1.2 times as wide as high. Antenna with A1 hardly noticeable, shorter than height of head (about 15.0:15.5), longer than distance between inner orbits (15:13). Length:width of A1–A10 = 15.0:2.3; 4.0:1.7; 1.4:1.0; 3.0:1.3; 2.8:1.3; 3.0:1.8; 3.2:2.0; 3.2:2.0; 3.2:1.9; 5.0:1.8. Flagellar pubescence hardly noticeable.
</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. 1.5 times as long as wide, hardly 1.1 times as high as wide. Sides of pronotum smooth except for sparse hair sockets in upper half and very weak rugosity in upper anterior corner. Mesoscutum with scattered hairs towards sides, bare on mid 0.4 of width, smooth, only slightly rugose at anterior ends of notauli, these weakly indicated in slightly more than posterior half; mid lobe broad, at hind margin slightly but distinctly prolonged, covering extreme base of scutellum; numerous greyish hairs cover rather narrow scuto-scutellar grooves. Mesopleuron smooth. Scutellum weakly and evenly convex, almost bare along the middle, towards sides moderately densely hairy, smooth except for hair sockets. Metapleuron with pilosity all over, though in anterior half very sparse, smooth. Propodeal carinae short, parallel; area between them smooth, much transverse.</p>
      <p>
WINGS
. Fore wing 0.75 as long as entire body, 2.4 times as long as wide, surpassing tip of metasoma by a distance equal to length of 
T
6, clear, with fine and dense microtrichia; marginal cilia about 0.05 width of wing. Hind wing 5.0 times as long as wide, with two hamuli; marginal cilia very slightly more than 0.2 width of wing.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA. Around 1.1 times as long as rest of body, 2.1 times as long as wide, slightly wider than mesosoma (about 18:17). Length:width of 
T
1– 
T
6 = 5.0:8.5; 19.0:18.0; 3.5:17.0; 3.0:14.5; 3.0:11.0; 5.0:7.5. 
T
1 with about six somewhat uneven, rather weak longitudinal carinae and a few even weaker additional ones, bare dorsally, along sides with a few inconspicuous hairs. 
T
2 weakly striated from basal foveae to 0.65 of length of tergite, medially with four short striae to 0.15 of length, rest of tergite as well as following tergites smooth. 
T
3– 
T
6 with moderately strong punctures with inconspicuous hairs: about four on 
T
3, 12 in a transverse row on each of 
T
4– 
T
5, slightly fewer and more scattered on 
T
6.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Very similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. papei
Buhl, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
(from the 
United Arab Emirates
) but with more slender antennae, more striate occiput and T2 (vs occiput finely and irregularly transversely striate in posterior half, rest of occiput and vertex almost smooth except for fine and weak reticulation around ocelli in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. papei
</tp:taxon-name>
), and more distinct notauli (vs absent in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. papei
</tp:taxon-name>
). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platygaster karimpouri
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
has slightly more slender antennae than 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. pedasus
Walker, 1835
</tp:taxon-name>
which also has the occiput and T2 less striate, and mid lobe between notauli not quite reaching scutellum. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platygaster karimpouri
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
has antennae slightly less slender than 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. ennius
Walker, 1835
</tp:taxon-name>
which also has head 2.2 times as wide as long, nearly complete notauli, and T2 striate only in the basal third.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
