<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Eusarcus marmoreus Júnior &amp;
                        Ázara &amp; Ferreira 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4633420</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/038B87ED050BFF8DFDE8FEBC9E44456E</uri>
                  <article-title>Three new species of Eusarcus Perty, 1833 (Opiliones, Gonyleptidae)
                        from Brazilian caves</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://zoobank.org/bcc18dc2-7b6b-4f20-bf87-d94c4214a824</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus marmoreus </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 39CE9706-C0D6-49A2-9832-FD777C5201CF </p>
            <p> Figs 4–6 , 10–11 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus marmoreus </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. can be distinguished
                  from all species of the genus by having coxa IV with one transversal, proapical,
                  trifurcated and truncated apophysis, with one dorsal apex higher than the other
                  two ventrally-disposed apices. <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus marmoreus </tp:taxon-name>
                  sp. nov. resembles <tp:taxon-name> E. berlae (Mello-Leitão, 1932) </tp:taxon-name>
                  , <tp:taxon-name> E. sergipanus Hara </tp:taxon-name> &amp; Pinto-da-Rocha, 2010,
                        <tp:taxon-name> E. signatus (Roewer, 1949) </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> E. sooretamae (Soares &amp; Soares, 1946) </tp:taxon-name>
                  by the presence of a proapical truncated apophysis at coxa IV but can be
                  distinguished by the following characters: unarmed scutal area III, low ocularium
                  with a median spine, femur IV with proventral and retroventral rows of acuminate
                  tubercles increasing in size apically and trochanter IV with only one high (taller
                  than trochanter width) promedian apophysis. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The specific epithet ʻ <tp:taxon-name> marmoreus </tp:taxon-name> ʼ means ʻof
                  marbleʼ in Latin and refers to the lithology of the cave where the type specimen
                  was found. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype BRAZIL • ♂ ; Espírito Santo State , Vargem Alta
                        MUnicipality, Caverna Archimides Panssini cave ; 20°41′15.3″ S , 41°03′45.0″
                        W ; 4 Apr. 2014 ; R.L. Ferreira et al. leg.; ISLA 12968 (destroyed).
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes BRAZIL • 3 ♀♀ ; same collection data as for
                        holotype; ISLA 66190 to 66192 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for holotype; ISLA 1472
                        (destroyed) </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male ( holotype , ISLA 12968) </p>
            <p>MEASUREMENTS. DSL 4.79, DSW 3.41, femur I 2.72, II 6.27, III 4.08, IV 5.03.</p>
            <p> DORSUM ( Fig. 4A, E ). Blunt PAM; acuminate median paracheliceral projection lower
                  than PAM. Low ocularium with median spine (about two times ocularium height).
                  Carapace with scattered granules. Scutal areas I–IV with scattered granules with
                  higher density on scutal areas III–IV. Posterior margin of dorsal scUtUm with
                  scattered granUles. Free tergites I–III with a defined row of granUles. Anal
                  opercUlUm with scattered granules. </p>
            <p> VENTER ( Fig. 4B ). Coxa I with irregular row of setiferous tubercles, coxae II–IV
                  densely and irregularly granulate. </p>
            <p>CHELICERAE. Segment I with two ectal-basal tubercles fused at the base and one
                  irregular mesal-basal tubercle.</p>
            <p>PEDIPALPS. Trochanter with sparse tubercles dorsally. Femur with one mesal apical
                  setiferous tubercle.</p>
            <p> LEGS ( Fig. 5 ). Coxae I–III with scattered granules; coxa IV with one transversal,
                  proapical, trifurcated and truncated apophysis, with one dorsal apex higher than
                  the other two ventrally-disposed apices. Trochanters I–IV with scattered
                  tubercles; trochanter IV with one high (taller than trochanter width) promedian
                  apophysis, which is conical, with rounded and anteriorly-curved apex. Femur III
                  with proventral and retroventral rows of acute tubercles increasing in size
                  apically; femur IV slightly sinuous, with small PDS and RDS, with proventral and
                  retroventral rows of acuminate tubercles increasing in size apically. Patellae,
                  tibiae and metatarsi I–IV granUlated withoUt defined armatUre. </p>
            <p> Fig. 4. <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus marmoreus </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , habitus. A–B
                  , E . ♂, holotype (ISLA 12968). C–D , F . ♀, paratype (ISLA 66190). A . Dorsal
                  view. B . Ventral view. C . Dorsal view. D . Ventral view. E–F . Right lateral
                  view. Scale bars: A–E = 1 mm; F = 0.5 mm. </p>
            <p> Fig. 5. <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus marmoreus </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂, holotype
                  (ISLA 12968). A–B . Femur IV, dorsal and ventral view, respectively. C–D . Patella
                  and tibia IV, dorsal and ventral view, respectively. E–F . Femur III, dorsal and
                  ventral view, respectively. G–H . Trochanter IV dorsal and ventral view,
                  respectively. Scale bars: A–F = 0.5 mm; G–H = 0.2 mm. </p>
            <p> Fig. 6. <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus marmoreus </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂, holotype
                  (ISLA 12968), distal part of penis. A . Dorsal view. B . Ventral view. C . Right
                  lateral view. D . Left lateral view. Macrosetae highlighted in different coloUrs:
                  light blUe = MS A; pUrple = MS B; pink = MS C; yellow = MS D. Scale bars 50 μm. </p>
            <p> COLOURATION (in alcohol) ( Figs 4–5 ). Body and appendages background colour Strong
                  Brown (55), appendages Strong Orange (50). </p>
            <p> PENIS ( Fig. 6 ). Ventral plate dorsally concave with substraight lateral margins;
                  distal margin straight; ventral surface entirely covered with type T1 microsetae;
                  with three pairs of lateral-distal MS C1–C3, three wide pairs of A1, one pair of
                  B1, one pair of minute D1, and E1 absent. Stylus smooth, wider at apex, ventrally
                  tilted. Ventral process spatula-shaped, dorsally tilted. </p>
            <p> Female ( paratype , ISLA 66190) </p>
            <p>MEASUREMENTS. DSL 4.73, DSW 2.93, femur I 2.40, II 5.18, III 3.57, IV 4.53.</p>
            <p>Similar to male, except for leg IV unarmed with only coxa IV having one short
                  proapical tubercle.</p>
            <p> Intraspecific variation </p>
            <p>Males (n = 2): DSL 4.79–4.17; DSW 3.41–3.02, femur I 2.72–2.44, II 6.27–6.11, III
                  4.08–4.20, IV 5.03– 5.12.</p>
            <p> Geographical distribution </p>
            <p> Known only from the type locality ( Fig. 11 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Ecological remarks </p>
            <p> Archimides Panssini is a marble cave located in Vargem Alta Municipality ( Espírito
                  Santo State , southreastern Brazil ). It possesses around 150 meters of horizontal
                  projection, with an irregular topography. The inner cave chamber harboUrs a small
                  amoUnt of water flow. ThUs, organic resoUrces observed in the cave were vegetal
                  debris broUght in by water flow and piles of bat gUano, especially those produced
                  by hematophagous bats. Roots from the external vegetation were also observed in a
                  few areas. Specimens of <tp:taxon-name> Eusarcus marmoreus </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. were found freely walking in the inner cave chambers, usually associated with
                  moistened substrates ( Fig. 10B ). The Archimides Panssini Cave is also the type
                  locality of the troglobitic palpigrade <tp:taxon-name> Eukoenenia spelunca Souza
                        &amp; Ferreira, 2011 </tp:taxon-name> ( Souza &amp; Ferreira 2011 ), which
                  reinforces its relevance. The cave is located in the Atlantic Forest domain, and
                  the external landscape is topographically heterogeneous. The region presents a Cwa
                  climate according to the Köppen classification system, with an average annUal
                  precipitation ranging from 1000 to 1300 mm and an average annual temperature of
                  20.9ºC. The external landscape is quite altered, especially due to the removal of
                  native vegetation for crops. Furthermore, many quarries for the extraction of
                  marble were observed in the area during the last visit (in 2014) ( Fig. 10A ),
                  which represents a serious threat for species associated with caves. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
