<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratouphapleura
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
883121EC-5626-40EA-BC42-CC2A7FE7B166
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
and only species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pa. aaroni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The generic name ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratouphapleura
</tp:taxon-name>
’ is a combination of the Greek παρά [pará], meaning ‘besides’, ‘beyond’, and the genus name 
<tp:taxon-name>
Touphapleura
</tp:taxon-name>
, pointing to the general morphological resemblance of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Touphapleura
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratouphapleura
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
Gender: feminine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Membor of 
<tp:taxon-name>Cletodidae T. Scott, 1904</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Cletodinae T. Scott</tp:taxon-name>
, 1904, and the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratonotus
</tp:taxon-name>
group 
sensu
Conroy-Dalton (2001)
. Body more or less cylindrical, tapering slightly posteriorly, without clear demarcation between pro- and urosoma. In female fusion of last thoracic (P6-bearing) and first abdominal (= genital) somite to form GDS. Cephalothorax with weakly developed cephalothoracic anterior lateroventral processes (CLVPa); cephalothoracic posterior lateroventral processes (CLVPp) well-developed, jet-wing-like, with 1 sensillum each on the anterior margin and the tip; cephalothoracic anterodorsal processes (CADP) and cephalothoracic laterodorsal processes (CLDPp) not developed; anterior cephalothoracic setulose tufts (ACST) present, posterior cephalothoracic setulose tufts (PCST) absent. Rostrum small, broader than long, fused to cephalothorax; with paired sensilla, 1 tube pore, paired membranous projections, and rostral setulose tuft (RST). Pedigerous somites dorsally with long tube pore, those bearing P2–P4 additionally with pairs of small and unarmed dorsal cuticular processes (DP1–DP3), each carrying a sensillum at its tip, and laterally with setulose tufts (TST1–TST3); P6-bearing somite laterally with setulose tufts (GST). Urosomal somites laterally with tube pores accompanied by abdominal lateral spinulose tufts (AST1–AST3); first abdominal somite (= posterior part of female GDS) and following 2 abdominal somites with dorsal row of spinules on posterior margin, the former and the second somite additionally with pair of tube pores dorsally. Telson half as long as penultimate somite, with spinulose anal operculum flanked by 2 sensilla and spinulose tufts (AST4) running lateroventrally at the bases of the furcal rami. The latter about three times as long as broad, with 7 setae (I–VII). Antennule 4-segmented in the female, 7-segmented and subchirocer in the male; first segment elongated and equipped with long spinules along anterior margin. Antenna with allobasis and 1-segmented endopod, without exopod; allobasis with 2 abexopodal setae; endopod with 2 spines, apically with 5 setae, 4 of which geniculate. Swimming legs with bow-like intercoxal sclerites, small coxae, and transversely elongated bases; P1 with 2-segmented lobes, non-prehensile; basis with inner and outer seta; exp-1 with 1 outer bipinnate spine, exp-2 with all elements located apically: 1 bipinnate outer spine and 4 bare or unipinnate geniculated setae. P2–P4 bases carrying 1 outer seta, with 3-segmented exopods; P2, P4, and female P3 with 2-segmented endopods, male P3 endopod 3-segmented, enp-2 with apophysis on inner apical edge. P5 with endopodal lobe reduced to a minute pedestal with 1 seta. Female GDS with P6 strongly reduced, not forming a genital operculum.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
