<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Poropsyllus menzelae George 2021</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5589671</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/038E87BCA64E540D5422FEA3FD2CFBC8</uri>
         <article-title>Four new genera of the Ceratonotus group (Copepoda, Harpacticoida), including the description of two new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.774.1525</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Poropsyllus menzelae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D3681697-E1C8-40A4-8CC4-7DEB1705903E
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–7
; 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The epitheton 
<tp:taxon-name>
menzelae
</tp:taxon-name>
is given in friendly dedication to Dr Lena Menzel (Bremerhaven, 
Germany
), who obtained the material from Prof. Por and placed it at the author’s disposal for further study.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
Map of Antarctica showing sampling station #133, the type locality of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratouphapleura aaroni
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, on the eastern continental slope off the Antarctic Peninsula.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Poropsyllus menzelae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, female holotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP808). 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view; on the upper left: cphth in lateral view; arrowheads point to the CLVPa. 
B
. Left FR, dorsal view. Scales bars: A = 100 µm; B = 50 µm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CYPRUS
• 
♀
; 
Akrotiri Bay
(locus typicus), 
E of Cape Gata
(S Cyprus); 
geographic transect
: 
34°33'54" N
/ 
33°02'45" E
–34°34'20" N/33°04'06" E; depth 115 fathoms (= 

210.5 m

); 

26 Oct. 1968

; 
F.D. Por
leg.; 
Ockelmann detritus sledge
(

Por 
et al.
1972

); 
HUJ INVCRUCOP808
, on 1 slide.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
(
allotype
)

CYPRUS
• 
♂
; 
Coral Bay
(
SW Cyprus
); 
geographic transect
: 
34°48'24" N
/ 
32°22'57" E
– 34°48'06" N/32°21'24" E; depth 100 fathoms (= 183.0 m); 

31 Oct. 1968
F.D. Por
leg.; 
Ockelmann
detritus sledge
(

Por 
et al.
1972

); 
HUJ INVCRUCOP809
, on 1 slide
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Both specimens show several instances of damage, mainly loss of setae, segments of appendages, and both antennular segments and cuticular processes (male 
allotype
). Dissection, which would have caused further destruction of the individuals, was not conducted, but all parts except the maxillula were drawn and described.
</p>
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
HABITUS (
Fig. 3A
). Elongate, cylindrical (body length including FR 550 µm), podoplean boundary between pro- and urosoma inconspicuous. Cphth about ¼ of total body length, with some sensilla and long tube pores laterally and dorsally; moreover, with small frontolateral horns (FLH), ventrally directed cephalothoracic anterior lateroventral processes (CLVPa) (arrowheads in 
Fig. 3A
), and bifurcate cephalothoracic posterior lateroventral processes (CLVPp). Cephalic front produced into a massive diverging peak, from which the A1 arises. Rostrum (
Figs 3A
, 
4A
) absent, original central position indicated by small paired membranous projections accompanied by a pair of sensilla and 1 tube pore. P2–P4-bearing pedigerous somites with small dorsal cuticular processes (DP1–DP3); each process carrying a sensillum at its tip (most of them broken in 
Fig. 3A
). Body somites except last thoracic somite (= anterior half of female GDS) and telson laterally with 1 long tube pore. Thoracic body somites with additional dorsal long tube pore. First abdominal somite fused with last thoracic body somite to form a GDS. Thoracic part of GDS dorsally with pair of diagonal cuticular ridges; abdominal part of GDS and abdominal somites except telson with abdominal lateral setulose tufts (AST1–AST3). Telson broader than long, trapezoidal in dorsal view, anal operculum flanked by 2 sensilla, posterior margin with row of fine spinules.
</p>
      <p>
FR (
Fig. 3A–B
). Diverging, rami slender, about 11 times as long as broad and longer than abdomen and GDS together, bearing 7 bare setae (
Fig. 3B
). Setae I and II inserting laterally, standing close together, I minute, II twice as long as I; III inserting subapically on outer margin; setae IV and V located apically, IV slightly smaller than III, and V as long as fifth pedigerous somite, abdomen, and FR combined (
Fig. 3A
); VI as long as IV, inserting apically on inner margin; VII tri-articulate, arising dorsally from small knob.
</p>
      <p>
A1 (
Fig. 4B
). 4-segmented, long and slender. First segment longest, second to fourth segments of almost the same size. First 3 segments with long spinules (several spinules broken in 
Fig. 4B
). Several setae broken in 
Fig. 4B
; first segment distally with 1 seta (broken); second segment with 7 setae (6 broken, 1 biplumose); third segment with at least 6 setae (all but 1 bare seta broken); pedestal for acrothek discernible close to apical margin (elements broken); fourth segment with 11 bare setae (1 apical seta broken), two of which fused with 1 small aes.
</p>
      <p>Armature formula: I–1; II–7; III–6(7?) + aes, IV–11 + aes.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Poropsyllus menzelae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, female holotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP808). 
A
. Cephalothoracic peak. 
B
. A1. 
C
. Md. 
D
. Mx. 
E
. Mxp. Scales: 50 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Poropsyllus menzelae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A
. Male allotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP809), A2. 
B
. Female holotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP808), P1. 
C
. Female holotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP808), P5. Scale bar: 50 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Poropsyllus menzelae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A–C
. Female holotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP808). 
A
. P2. 
B
. P3 exp-2 and exp-3. 
C
. P4 exp-2 and exp-3. 
D
. Male allotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP809), P3 endopod. Scale bar: 50 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Table 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Poropsyllus menzelae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, setation of swimming legs P2–P4; Roman numerals indicate outer, Arabic numerals inner elements.
</p>
      <p>
Leg
Exopod
Endopod
P2
I–0; I–I; II–2–1
—
P3 male
I–0; I–1; II–2–2
0; 0 (apophysis); 0–1–0
P3 female
I–0; I–1; II–2–2
—
P4 female
I–0; I–I; II–2–1
—
</p>
      <p>
A2. See description of 
allotype
.
</p>
      <p>
MD (
Fig. 4C
). Gnathobase small in comparison with palp, apically with 3 multicuspidate teeth; palp unilobed, subapically with some fine, long spinules, and with 2 lateral (basal) and 3 apical (endopodal) setae, all biplumose.
</p>
      <p>
MXL. Because dissection, which would have caused destruction of the individuals, was not conducted, no 
in situ
description could be made, and the mxl was not drawn.
</p>
      <p>
MX
(
Fig. 4D
). Syncoxa and allobasis separate, syncoxa with 2 endites. Proximal endite with 1 strong unipinnate spine fused to the segment, and with 1 bare and 1 biplumose seta. Distal endite with 1 strong bare spine fused to the segment, and with 1 unipinnate seta. Allobasis with 1 claw-like element fused to the segment; additionally with 1 strong and 2 slender bare setae. Endopod distinct, small, 1-segmented, with 2 bare setae.
</p>
      <p>
MXP (
Fig. 4E
). Prehensile, syncoxa with few long spinules and 1 strong multipinnate seta. Basis with 3 rows of long spinules. Endopod produced into long biplumose claw, basally accompanied by 1 tiny seta.
</p>
      <p>
P1–P4 (
Figs 5B
, 
6A–C
). With slender, bow-like intercoxal sclerites (
Figs 5B
, 
6A
); bases extraordinarily elongated transversely (
Figs 3A
, 
5B
, 
6A
), without any spinulose ornamentation, except the presence of 1 tube pore at mid-length on the anterior margin (
Figs 5B
, 
6A
). P1 (
Fig. 5B
) basis with 1 inner bare and 1 outer biplumose seta; with tube pore on anterior margin; endopod represented by 1 bare seta; exopod 2-segmented, exp-2 about 3 times as long as exp-1; exp-1 with 1 outer bipinnate seta; exp-2 with 1 outer bipinnate seta; apically with 4 geniculate setae (2 broken in 
Fig. 5B
), one of which unipinnate. P2–P4 (
Fig. 6A–C
) without endopods; bases with 1 short bare outer seta (
Fig. 6A
) and with tube pore on anterior margin; exopods 3-segmented, segments with few or without spinules as depicted; exp-1 with outer bipinnate seta (
Fig. 6A
); exp-2 with 1 outer and 1 inner seta; exp-3 with 2 outer bipinnate setae, the posterior one shifted to an apical (P2, P3; 
Fig. 6A–B
) or subapical position (P4; 
Fig. 6C
); exp- 3 additionally with 2 apical setae. P2 exp-3 (
Fig. 6A
) in addition subapically with long tube pore. P2 and P4 exp-3 with 1, P3 exp-3 with 2 inner setae. Inner setae and innermost apical seta biplumose, but outermost apical seta bare. Setation of P2–P4 as in 
Table 1.
</p>
      <p>
P5 (
Fig. 5C
). Baseoendopod and exopod fused. Baseoendopod with outer bipinnate seta arising from minute setophore and accompanied by 1 long tube pore. Endopodal lobe completely reduced, represented
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Poropsyllus menzelae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A
. Female holotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP808), genital double somite with genital field and P6. 
B
. Male allotype (HUJ INVCRUCOP809), A1, showing the first 3 segments. 
C
. Male allotype, P5. Scale bar: 50 µm.
</p>
      <p>by 1 long and 1 small bare seta. Exopodal lobe with 1 bipinnate outer seta and 3 apical setae, two of which bipinnate, the remaining one bare; subapically with long tube pore.</p>
      <p>
GF (
Fig. 7A
). With fused gonopores covered by slender genital operculum derived from the medially fused P6, whose minute lobes each end in a bare seta.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>The male resembles the female in most characters. Sexual dimorphism is expressed in a slightly smaller body size (480 µm incl. FR), in the A1, the P3 endopod, the P5, and the absence of a P6.</p>
      <p>
A1 (
Fig. 7B
). Damaged, but sexual dimorphism still discernible. First segment as in female; second segment half as long as first, with 7 setae and long spinules on anterior margin; third segment about ⅓ the length of previous segment, with 1 bare seta. Following segments broken, not illustrated.
</p>
      <p>
A2 (
Fig. 5A
). Without exp. Allobasis with 2 abexopodal bare setae. Endopod laterally on distal half with 2 well-developed setae, one of which bipinnate, and with 1 small bare seta; additionally, with frill-like row of long fine spinules. Apically with 3 long geniculate setae (one broken); moreover with 1 bipinnate and 1 bare slender seta. Subapically with spinulose frill.
</p>
      <p>
P3 ENDOPOD (
Fig. 6D
). 3-segmented, first segment small and unarmed, second segment about 6 times as long as first, ending in an acute apophysis; third segment slightly longer than first, apically with 1 small bare seta.
</p>
      <p>
P5 (
Fig. 7C
). With exopod separated from baseoendopod, carrying 2 outer bipinnate and 3 bare apical setae; subapically with tube pore. Outer baseoendopodal seta bare, accompanied by small tube pore; endopodal lobe represented by 1 bare seta.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
