<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Paratouphapleura aaroni George 2021,
                        gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5589673</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/038E87BCA64754165439FCB3FA81FD22</uri>
                  <article-title>Four new genera of the Ceratonotus group (Copepoda, Harpacticoida),
                        including the description of two new species</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.774.1525</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 6F7C1F0C-7A6F-473A-B5B4-78859FE44D59 </p>
            <p> Figs 8–14 ; Table 2 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The epitheton <tp:taxon-name> aaroni </tp:taxon-name> is given in fond dedication to
                  my brother, Mr Aaron Martin George (Münster/ Selters, Germany ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p> 3 ♀♀ , 3 ♂♂ , collected during research cruise ANT-XIX/4 ( ANDEEP II ) of RV
                  POLARSTERN in 2002. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype ANTARCTICA • ♀ ; Weddell Sea , E of Antarctic
                        Peninsula ; station #133; 65°20.30' S / 54°14.67' W ; depth 1109.6 m (locus
                        typicus); multiple corer; SMF 37270/1 , on 1 slide. </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes ANTARCTICA • 2♀♀ , 3 ♂♂ ; same collection data as
                        for holotype; SMF 37271/1 (♂ paratype 1/allotype, on 1 slide), SMF 37272/1
                        (♀ paratype 2, on 1 slide), SMF 37273/1–9 (♀ paratype 3, on 9 slides), SMF
                        37274/1–8 (♂ paratype 4, on 8 slides), SMF 37275/1 (♂ paratype 5, on 1
                        slide) </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> HABITUS ( Fig. 8A ). Elongate, cylindrical; body length including FR: 493 µm (
                  holotype ), 562 µm ( paratype 2), 515 µm ( paratype 3). Podoplean boundary between
                  pro- and urosoma inconspicuous. Cphth about ⅓ of total body length, with some
                  sensilla and long tube pores laterally and dorsally, and with anterior
                  cephalothoracic setulose tufts (ACST). Cephalic front produced into a moderate
                  peak, from which the A1 arises. Without frontolateral horns (FLH), but
                  cephalothoracic anterior lateroventral processes (CLVPa) weakly developed, ending
                  in long tube pore; sensilla not discernible. Cphth additionally with 3 pairs of
                  tube pores, two of which located dorsally, the third laterally. Cephalothoracic
                  posterior lateroventral processes (CLVPp) ( Fig. 9B ) long and jet-wing-like, with
                  1 sensillum halfway on anterior margin and 1 sensillum on its tip. Rostrum ( Fig.
                  9A ) small, broader than long, fused to cephalothorax; with pair of sensilla, 1
                  tube pore, paired membranous projections, and rostral setulose tuft (RST).
                  P2–P4-bearing thoracic somites ( Fig. 8A ) dorsally with 1 tube pore and paired
                  unarmoured small cuticular processes (DP1–DP3), each carrying a sensillum at its
                  tip; laterally with thoracic setulose tufts TST1–TST3. Following body somites
                  without cuticular processes. P5-bearing somite dorsally with tube pore and 2
                  sensilla. GDS dorsally with fine suture indicating former separation; anterior
                  part of GDS dorsally with 1 tube pore, laterally with setulose tufts (GST)
                  accompanied by 1 tube pore; posterior part of GDS as well as subsequent abdominal
                  somite dorsally with 2 tube pores and 2 sensilla on posterior margin, which in
                  addition presents a row of spinules; laterally with abdominal lateral setulose
                  tufts AST1 and AST2, each accompanied by 1 tube pore. Penultimate abdominal somite
                  dorsally with spinulose posterior margin and with AST3 (only discernible on the
                  right side in Fig. 8A ) but without sensilla and tube pores. Telson half as long
                  as previous somite, slightly trapezoidal, with AST4 and spinulose anal operculum
                  flanked by 2 sensilla. </p>
            <p> Fig. 8. <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. A
                  . Female holotype (SMF 37270/1), habitus, dorsal view. B . Male allotype (SMF
                  37271/1), habitus, dorsal view. Scale bar: 100 µm. </p>
            <p> Fig. 9. <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov.
                  A–C . Female holotype (SMF 37270/1). A . Rostrum, dorsal view. B . Left
                  cephalothoracic posterior lateroventral process (CLVPp), dorsal view. C . Telson
                  and right FR, dorsal view. D . Female paratype 3 (SMF 37273), genital field with
                  P6. Scale bar: 50 µm. </p>
            <p> Fig. 10. <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. A
                  . Female holotype (SMF 37270/1), A1. B . Female paratype 3 (SMF 37273), P1. Scale
                  bar: 50 µm. </p>
            <p> Fig. 11. <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. A
                  . Male paratype 4 (SMF 37274), A2. B–E . Female paratype 3 (SMF 37273). B . Md. C
                  . Mxl. D . Mx. E . Mxp. Scale bars: 50 µm. </p>
            <p> FR ( Figs 8A , 9C ). Diverging, rami slender, about 3.5 times as long as broad and
                  as long as telson and preceding somite together, with 1 small tube pore proximally
                  on outer margin and bearing 7 bare setae ( Fig. 9C ): setae I and II of almost the
                  same length, inserting halfway on outer margin and set close together, I
                  bipinnate, II bare; III bipinnate, inserting subapically on outer margin; setae IV
                  and V located apically, IV bare, visibly smaller than III, V longest element,
                  bipinnate; VI bare, even smaller than IV, inserting apically on inner margin; VII
                  bare, tri-articulate, arising dorsally from small knob. </p>
            <p> A1 ( Fig. 10A ). Partly or completely broken in all three females . Most complete
                  condition present in holotype : slender, 4-segmented, first and third segments of
                  almost the same size, about twice as long as second and fourth segment. First and
                  second segments with several long spinules, following segments without spinulose
                  ornamentation. First segment with biplumose seta subapically; second segment with
                  8 setae (5 broken); third segment with 8 setae (2 broken), 2 of which forming
                  acrothek together with aes; fourth segment with 3 lateral setae; apically with at
                  least 5 setae; acrothek that might consist of 2 additional setae and aes broken,
                  not discernible. </p>
            <p>Armature formula: I–1; II–8; III–6(+ 2 + aes), IV–8(+2? + aes?).</p>
            <p> A2 ( Fig. 11A ). Without exp. Allobasis with row of spinules and 2 abexopodal
                  bipinnate setae. Endopod laterally with few spinules, on distal half with 2
                  well-developed bipinnate setae, third small bare seta absent. Apically with 4 long
                  geniculate setae and 1 smaller seta, all bare, and with spinulose frill. </p>
            <p> MD ( Fig. 11B ). Gnathobase apically with 2 multicuspidate teeth; palp unilobed,
                  with some fine, long spinules, and with 2 lateral (basal), 3 apical (endopodal),
                  and 1 outer (exopodal) setae, all biplumose. </p>
            <p> MXL ( Fig. 11C ). Praecoxal arthrite with set of spinules, apically with 6 spines
                  and on each edge with 1 seta; additionally, with 2 surface setae; all elements
                  bare. Coxal endite apically with 1 bare seta. Basis, endopod and exopod fused to
                  single lobe, carrying 4 lateral setae, the proximal one bipinnate, the remaining
                  three bare; apically with 3 bare setae and 2 unipinnate spines. </p>
            <p> MX ( Fig. 11D ). Syncoxa and allobasis separated; syncoxa apically with cluster of
                  spinules, and with 2 endites; proximal endite with 1 strong bipinnate spine, fused
                  to segment, and with 2 bare setae; distal endite with bare spine fused to the
                  segment, and with 2 bare setae. Allobasis with 1 claw-like element fused to the
                  segment; additionally, with 2 bare setae. Endopod 1-segmented, small, with 2 bare
                  setae. </p>
            <p> MXP ( Fig. 11E ). Prehensile, syncoxa without spinules but with 1 biplumose seta on
                  apical edge; basis with 2 rows of long spinules; endopod produced into long bare
                  claw, basally accompanied by 1 tiny seta. </p>
            <p> P1 ( Fig. 10B ). With transversely elongated basis and 2-segmented exo- and endopod.
                  Praecoxa small, triangular; coxa small, more or less rectangular. Basis with
                  several long spinules on anterior margin, and with 1 inner and 1 outer element
                  (broken in Fig. 10B ). Exopodal segments of nearly the same size, exp- 1 with row
                  of spinules on outer distal margin, and with 1 outer bipinnate seta; exp-2 without
                  spinules, with 1 bipinnate outer seta, and (sub)apically with 4 geniculate
                  elements, all with row of pinnules previous to geniculation. </p>
            <p> Fig. 12. <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. ,
                  female paratype 3 (SMF 37273). A . P2. B . P3 exopod. C . P3 endopod. D . P4
                  exopod. E . P4 endopod. F . P3 intercoxal sclerite. G . P4 intercoxal sclerite.
                  Scale: 50 µm. </p>
            <p> Table 2. <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. ,
                  setation of swimming legs P2–P4; Roman numerals indicate outer, Arabic numerals
                  inner elements. </p>
            <p> Leg Exopod Endopod P2 I–0; I–I; II–2–1 0; 0–2–0 P3 male I–0; I–1; II–2–2 0; 0
                  (apophysis); 0–2–0 P3 female I–0; I–1; II–2–2 0; I–2–0 P4 female I–0; I–I; II–2–1
                  0; I–2–0 </p>
            <p> P2–P4 ( Fig. 12A–G ). With slender, bow-like intercoxal sclerites (P3: Fig. 12F; P 4
                  : Fig. 12G ) and transversely elongated bases that carry long spinules and 1 tube
                  pore on their anterior margins, as shown for P2 ( Fig. 12A ). Exp-1 with few
                  spinules on inner and/or outer margin, posteriorly with 1 bipinnate spine; exp-2
                  also with few spinules as depicted, and with 1 inner biplumose seta and 1
                  bipinnate outer spine; exp-3 with 2 outer bipinnate elements, short and spine-like
                  in P2 but long and seta-like in P3 and P4; additionally, with 2 apical biplumose
                  setae; inner margin of exp-3 with 1 biplumose seta in P2 and P4, but with 2
                  biplumose setae in P3. Endopods small and 2-segmented, enp-1 shorter than enp-2,
                  without ornamentation; P2 enp-2 with few spinules and 2 apical setae, outermost
                  pinnate on the outer but plumose on the inner margin, innermost seta biplumose and
                  not reaching half the length of the outer one; enp-2 of P3 and P4 each with 2
                  biplumose apical setae, and with 1 outer bipinnate seta reaching at most ⅓ (P3) or
                  half (P4) the length of the apical elements. Setation of P2–P4 as in Table 2. </p>
            <p> P5 ( Fig. 13A ). Baseoendopod and exopod distinct. Baseoendopod with outer bipinnate
                  seta arising from long slender setophore (broken in Fig. 13A ) and accompanied by
                  1 long tube pore and long spinules. Endopodal lobe minute, with 1 long bipinnate
                  seta on its distal part, and with 1 tube pore. Exopodal lobe slightly longer than
                  baseoendopod, with 2 outer, 1 subapical, and 2 apical bipinnate setae; subapically
                  with long tube pore. </p>
            <p> GF ( Fig. 9D ). With single gonopore; P6 not forming genital operculum; lobes
                  strongly reduced, each ending in a small bare seta (1 seta broken in Fig. 9D ). </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> The male ( Fig. 8B ) resembles the female in most characters. Sexual dimorphism
                  consists of a slightly smaller body size ( allotype : 410 µm, paratype 4: 417 µm,
                  paratype 5: 459 µm), smaller dorsal cuticular processes DP1–DP3, the A1, the P3
                  endopod, the P5, and the absence of a P6. </p>
            <p> A1 ( Fig. 14A ). 7-segmented, subchirocer. First segment with long spinules on
                  surface and anterior margin, and with 1 seta apically (broken in Fig. 14A );
                  second segment as long as first, with 8 bare setae (two of which broken in Fig.
                  14A ); third segment small, almost triangular, with 4 bare setae; fifth segment
                  minute, with 2 small bare setae; sixth segment swollen, setation not discernible
                  because of position on the slide and the risk of breaking the A1 if it is turned
                  (its description is therefore postponed until additional material is found) sixth
                  segment small and squarish, without ornamentation; seventh segment twice as long
                  as sixth, tapering posteriorly, with 9 bare setae, 2 of which form an apical
                  acrothek together with 1 aes. </p>
            <p> Fig. 13. <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. A
                  . Female paratype 3 (SMF 37273), P5. B . Male paratype 4 (SMF 37274), P5. Scale
                  bar: 50 µm. </p>
            <p> Fig. 14. <tp:taxon-name> Paratouphapleura aaroni </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. ,
                  male paratype 4 (SMF 37274). A . A1. B . P3 endopod. Scale bar: 50 µm. </p>
            <p> P3 ENDOPOD ( Fig. 14B ). 3-segmented, first segment small and unarmed, second
                  segment about three times as long as first, ending in acute apophysis; third
                  segment slightly shorter and narrower than first, not reaching end of apophysis,
                  with 2 long biplumose setae apically. </p>
            <p> P5 ( Fig. 13B ). Exopod separated from baseoendopod, with several long spinules and
                  2 outer and 2 apical bipinnate setae; additionally, with 1 subapical bare seta but
                  without tube pore; baseoendopod as in female but endopodal lobe smaller, likewise
                  the single endopodal seta, which is small and bare. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
