<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Poropsyllus George 2021, gen.
            nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5552808</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/038E87BCA6495405546CFC58FC79FEF8</uri>
         <article-title>Four new genera of the Ceratonotus group (Copepoda, Harpacticoida),
            including the description of two new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.774.1525</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Poropsyllus </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: FF3B0077-C40A-464C-9D52-B0F43FA82497 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> The generic name is given in respectful remembrance of the collector of the species, Prof.
         Dr Francis Dov Por ( Israel ) and is a compound of the collector’s name and the Greek
         ψύλλος [psillos] (‘flea’), a term often used in the naming of taxa of the <tp:taxon-name>
            Ceratonotus </tp:taxon-name> group (e.g., <tp:taxon-name> Dendropsyllus </tp:taxon-name>
         , <tp:taxon-name> Echinopsyllus </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Pseudechinopsyllus
         </tp:taxon-name> ). Gender: masculine. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type and only species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Poropsyllus menzelae </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> Member of <tp:taxon-name>Cletodidae T. Scott, 1905</tp:taxon-name> ,
            <tp:taxon-name>Cletodinae T. Scott, 1905</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Ceratonotus
         </tp:taxon-name> group sensu Conroy-Dalton (2001) . Body elongate, cylindrical, podoplean
         boundary between pro- and urosoma inconspicuous. Sexual dimorphism in A1, P3, P5, and P6;
         female with GDS due to fusion of last (P6- bearing) thoracic and first abdominal (genital)
         somites. Cphth about ¼ of total body length, with some sensilla and long tube pores
         laterally and dorsally; moreover, with small, sensilla-bearing frontolateral horns (FLH),
         ventrally directed cephalothoracic anterior lateroventral processes (CLVPa), and bifurcate
         cephalothoracic posterior lateroventral processes (CLVPp). Cephalic front produced into a
         massive diverging peak. P2–P4-bearing pedigerous somites with dorsal cuticular processes.
         Rostrum absent, original central position indicated by small paired membranous projections
         accompanied by a pair of sensilla and 1 tube pore. Body somites except last thoracic somite
         (= anterior half of female GDS) and telson laterally with 1 long tube pore. Thoracic body
         somites dorsally also with 1 long tube pore. Telson broader than long, trapezoid in dorsal
         view, anal operculum flanked by 2 sensilla, posterior margin with row of fine spinules. FR
         long and slender, diverging, with 7 setae. Female A1 slender, 4-segmented, male A1 sexually
         dimorphic, number of segments unknown. A2 without exopod, allobasis with 2 abexopodal
         setae; endopod 1-segmented, with 2 spines and 1 slender additional seta; apically with 5
         setae, 3 of which geniculate. Intercoxal sclerites of P1–P4 slender, bow-like; P1 with
         transversely elongated basis and 2-segmented exopod, endopod absent, represented by 1 long
         bare seta; bases of P2–P4 showing extreme transverse elongation, without endopods, except
         male P3, which bears a 3-segmented endopod with an apophysis on enp-2. P5 also considerably
         elongated, reaching anterior margin of telson; in the female with exopod fused to
         baseoendopod, in male exopod distinct. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
