<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:pub: 
54D43422-15B7-4EC9-ACC9-E764D3A7BF6D
Figs 2–8
; 
Tables 2–3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Elongated body with head separated from the trunk by slight neck constrictions. Total body length of 
215–408 µm
; furcal rami 
93 µm
long with 19–21 segments per side. Three-lobed, rounded head with a well-developed cephalion showing two lateral projections; one rugous pair of lateral pleurae and a ventral hypostomium present. Body mostly covered by pentagonal or hexagonal spined scales (

Type
1

scales) of various sizes (
3.5–11 µm
) increasing in length progressively from anterior (
3.5–8.5 µm
) to posterior body (
4.5–11 µm
) ends and from ventral (
3.5–7 µm
) to dorsal surface (
3.5–11 µm
). Overall, the shape of the 

Type
1

scales is very distinct, with 5–6 corners and an anterior elevation that forms the spine base and opens towards a middle groove and a posterior cleavage.A triangular dorsal scale is found immediately anterior to the furca base, highly lifted and spineless (

Type
2

scale). Dorsally on the furca base there is a spineless zone composed by a patch lacking cuticular ornamentation and flat, rounded or polygonal scales without spines measuring 
2.5–5 µm
(

Type
4

scales). The posterior end of the ventral field is covered by a pair of keeled oval scales (

Type
6

scales) and two pairs of small, elongated (

Type
7

scales) or rounded scales (

Type
8

scales), both bearing straight and long spines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From the Latin 
<tp:taxon-name>
insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
meaning ‘belonging to an islandʼ, in reference to the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material estudied
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
adult
(photographs, the specimen was destroyed); State of 
Pernambuco
, 
Fernando de Noronha archipelago
, 
Xaréu Reservoir
; 
ZUEC
GCH 55
.

</p>
      <p>
Specimen was examined while still alive under a compound microscope however, due to the fragility of the body, it was destroyed and is no longer available (

Garraffoni 
et al
. 2019b

). Photographs of the specimen are available at the Museum of Zoology of the University of Campinas under the access number 
ZUEC
GCH
55 (
ICZN 2017
: Article 73, Recommendation 73G, Statement 45). The 
holotype
is shown in 
Figs 2A–C
, 
3A–I
and 
4B, D
.
</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
3 adults
specs (micrographs, the specimens were destroyed); same collection data as for holotype; 
ZUEC
GCH 56 to GCH 58

• 

2 specs
(prepared for SEM); same collection datas as for holotype; 
ZUEC
GCH 59
, 
GCH 60

.
</p>
      <p>
Specimens were examined while still alive under a compound microscope, however, due to the fragility of their bodies, they were destroyed and are no longer available (

Garraffoni 
et al.
2019b

). Photographs of the specimens are available at the Museum of Zoology of the University of Campinas, under the
</p>
      <p>
access numbers 
ZUEC
GCH
56 to 58 (
ICZN 2017
: Article 73, Recommendation 73G, Statement 45). An example of 
paratypes
are shown in 
Fig. 4A, C
.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
BRAZIL
• 
8 specs
(examined while still alive under a compound microscope and, among those, three were prepared for DNA sequencing (no longer available)); same collection datas as for holotype.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
The description is based on both the 
holotype
and 
5 paratypes
(
Figs 2–8
; 
Table 2
).
</p>
      <p>
HABITUS. Specimens have a slender body with total length ranging from 
215 µm
to 
408 µm
, showing a slight neck constriction, represented by a small variation in width between the head and the neck. The cylindrical trunk is 
31–55 µm
wide at middle body length, showing little variation in width throughout its length, except for the set apart furcal rami, which are preceded by a pronounced constriction (
Fig. 2
). Body widths at head, medium length and furca base are, respectively, 
24–42 µm
, 
31–55 µm
and 
23– 25 µm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. The three-lobed head is 
24–42 µm
wide and has three sets of distinct plates. The cephalion (U1–U6) is 
19–25 µm
long and 
20–36 µm
wide, with a free (detached from the cuticle) posterior portion and short paired lateral projections (lappets), each 
10–18 µm
long, posteriorly detached from the head and slightly lifted (
Figs 3A
, 
7A–C
). There is a pair of pleurae (U2–U6), each 
12–15 µm
long and presenting a rough texture with small parallel grooves, contrasting with the smooth surface of the cephalion (
Figs 3B
, 
7C
). The ventral hypostomion is a well-marked transversal bar, at U4, 13– 
17 µm
long and shaped like an arch (i.e., decreasing in thickness towards the lateral extremities) with a middle concavity (
Fig. 3C
). Two tufts of cilia (cephalic sensory bristles) are present on each side of the head. The first tuft is shorter, approximately 
10.5 µm
long and located below the cephalion projections (U1), while the second is situated between the cephalion and the pleurae (U2), bearing longer cilia with an average length of 
14 µm
(
Fig. 3B
). No dorsal sensory bristles were observed. Mouth is subterminal, with 
8–13 µm
of diameter and surrounded by a ring that is segmented with longitudinal ridges (
Fig. 3A–C
). The pharynx is relatively long, reaching up to one-quarter body length (adhesive tubes excluded) and situated between U2 and U20. It is 
74 µm
long, 
25 µm
wide at mid-length and divided in 2 regions, without any distinct constrictions. Pharynx becomes wider towards its inferior portion at the pharyngeal intestinal junction (from 
19 µm
to 
27 µm
) while at its superior end a distinct, although small, furrow is formed at the junction of the internal regions (
Fig. 3B
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
Light microscopy – DIC. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (ZUEC GCH 55). Full body view. 
A
. Dorsal view. 
B
. Internal view. 
C
. Ventral view. Scale bars = 30 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
Light microscopy – DIC. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (ZUEC GCH 55). 
A–C
. Correspond to the most anterior third of the specimen. 
A
. Anterior dorsal region. 
B
. Anterior internal region. 
C
. anterior ventral region. 
D–F
. Correspond to the trunk. 
D
. Dorsal trunk. 
E
. Internal trunk. 
F
. Ventral trunk. 
G–I
. Correspond to the posterior third of the specimen. 
G
. Dorsal posterior third. 
H
. Internal posterior third. 
I
. Ventral posterior third. Abbreviations: ce = cephalion; ct = cephalic bristles; eg = egg; hy = hypostomium; i = intestine; is = interciliary spines; lc = locomotory cilia; lce = lateral cephalic expansions; mo = mouth; ne = nephridia; pl = pleurae; ph = pharynx; PhIJ = pharyngealintestinal junction; sc-1 = 
Type 1
scales; sc-2 = 
Type 2
scale; sc-3 = 
Type 3
scales; sc-4 = 
Type 4
scales; vs = 
Type 1
ventral scale. Scale bars = 20 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Table 2
(continued on next page). Morphometric features of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
All scale lengths for which the scale 
type
is 
<tp:taxon-name>not</tp:taxon-name>
specified are from 

Type
1

scales. Abbrevation: N = total number of measured adult specimens.
</p>
      <p>
Features
Range (µm)
Mean (µm)
N
Total body length
215–408
322
5
Body length (furcal rami excluded)
139–308
222
5
Furcal rami length
91.5–94.5
93
2
Furcal rami + adhesive tubes length
109–117
113
2
Adhesive tubes length
16–23
19.5
2
Furca base width
26.5–27.5
27
1
Number of furcal rami segments per side
19–21
20
1
Length of ornamentation bristles on the furcal rami segments
4–8
6
3
Body width at head
24–42
32
4
Body width at medium length
31–55
40
4
Body width at furca base
23–25
24
4
Diameter of mouth ring
8–13
10
3
Number of cephalic lobes
3
3
1
Number of head cilia tufts
4
4
3
Length of first cilia tuft
9–12
10.5
1
Length of second cilia tuft
11–19.5
14
1
Cephalion length
19–25
23
3
Cephalion width
20–36
28
2
Lateral projections (lappets) length
10–18
14
3
Pleurae length
12–15
14
3
Hypostomium length
13–17
15
2
Pharynx length
74
74
1
Pharynx width at upper length
19
19
1
Pharynx width at medium length
25
25
1
Pharynx width at pharingeointestinal junction
27
27
1
Egg width
30
30
1
Protonephridia length
105
105
1
Length of locomotory cilia
5–8.5
7
1
Total number of longitudinal columns of scales
42
42
1
Number of scales in a single longitudinal column
55
55
1
Total number of horizontal rows of scales
64
64
1
</p>
      <p>
Table 2

(continued).
</p>
      <p>
Features
Range (µm)
Mean (µm)
N
Number of scales in a single horizontal row
10
10
1
Length of neck dorsolateral scales
3.5–8.5
6
4
Length of middle trunk dorsal scales
5.5–9
8.5
2
Length of middle trunk lateral scales
6.5–11
8.5
2
Length of rear dorsolateral scales
7.5–9
6
2

Length of rear triangular scale (
Type 2
)

5–7
6
3

Length of small rounded scales with posterior spines (
Type 3
)

4.5
4.5
1

Length of rear dorsal small scales (
Type 4
)

2.5–5
3
1

Length of rear indented scales (
Type 5
)

7–8
7.5
1
Length of neck ventral scales
3.5–5
4
2
Length of middle trunk ventral scales
4.5
4.5
1
Length of rear trunk ventral scales
4–7
5
1

Length of keeled ventral scales (
Type 6
)

9.5–10
10
1

Length of small ventral elongated scales (
Type 7
)

3.5–4
3.5
1

Length of small ventral round scales (
Type 8
)

4.5–7
6
1
Length of head and neck dorsolateral spines
2–13
7.5
2
Length of upper trunk dorsolateral spines
8–15
11.5
2
Length of middle trunk dorsolateral spines
8.5–22.5
15.5
5
Length of rear trunk and furca base dorsolateral spines
18–33
25.5
5
Length of neck ventral spines
5.5–7.5
6.5
1
Length of trunk ventral spines
5.8–9.8
8
2
Length of rear ventral spines
5.7–15
10
1

Length of keels on 
Type 6
scales

6–7
6.5
1
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
Light microscopy – DIC. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Posterior region of the body. 
A
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 56). 
B, D
. Holotype (ZUEC GCH 55). 
C
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 57). 
A–B
. Posterior dorsal view. 
C
. Posterior dorsolateral view. 
D
. Posterior ventral view. Abbreviations: fr = furcal rami; sc-1 = 
Type 1
scales; sc-2 = 
Type 2
scale; sc-3 = 
Type 3
scales; sc-4 = 
Type 4
scales. Scale bars = 40 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
Close-up of the different types of scales described for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–C
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 59). 
D, F
. Holotype (ZUEC GCH 55). 
E
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 56). 
A–C
. Scanning electron microscopy. 
D–F
. Light microscopy – DIC. 
A
. Detail of a section of the dorsal middle trunk, showing the most common type of scale, 
Type 1
, with emphasis on its characteristic shape. 
B
. Detail of a section of the dorsal posterior trunk, showing 
Type 2
and 
Type 3
scales. 
C–E
. Detail of the transition between the dorsal posterior trunk and the dorsal furca base, showing the particular scale covering of this region. 
F
. Detail of the transition between the ventral posterior trunk and the ventral furca base, showing the particular scale covering this region. Abbreviations: sc-1 = 
Type 1
scales; sc-2 = 
Type 2
scale; sc-3 = 
Type 3
scales; sc-4 = 
Type 4
scales; sc-5 = 
Type 5
scales; sc-6 = 
Type 6
scales; sc-7 = 
Type 7
scales; sc-8 = 
Type 8
scales; svs = small ventral pair of spines. Scale bars: A–C = 5 µm; D = 10 µm; E = 15 µm; F = 10 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
Schematic illustration of dorsal and ventral posterior regions and type scales of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–B
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 56). 
A
. Dorsal view of the posterior end. Some 
Type 1
scales are faded for a better visualization of 
Types 2
, 
3
and 
5
scales. 
B
. Ventral view of the posterior end. 
C
. Each type of scale, individually depicted (
<tp:taxon-name>not</tp:taxon-name>
to scale). Abbreviations: ff = furcal furrow; fr = furcal rami; lc = locomotory cilia; is = interciliary spines; sc-1 = 
Type 1
scales; sc-2 = 
Type 2
scale; sc-3 = 
Type 3
scales; sc-4 = 
Type 4
scales; sc-5 = 
Type 5
scales; sc-6 = 
Type 6
scales; sc-7 = 
Type 7
scales; sc-8 = 
Type 8
scales. Scale bars = 40 µm.
</p>
      <p>
INTERNAL ANATOMY. Internally, a pair of protonephridia (
105 µm
long) are present, lateral to the intestine and posterior to the pharyngeointestinal junction (U29 – U75) (
Fig. 3E
).
</p>
      <p>
FURCA. Is 
109–117 µm
long (¼ of the body) and furca base is 
27 µm
wide, showing a V-shaped gap with a large and distinct U-shaped middle furrow (“helmet like” shape, as described by 
Roszczak 1969
). Presence of a single pair of very small ventral spines, one per side of the furrow (
Fig. 5C
). Furcal rami are 
93 µm
long (around 
1/5
of body length) and appear to be composed of 19–21 segments (
Figs 4A
, 
6B
, 
7A
, 
8C
). Segments of the furcal rami show well marked ornamentations in both DIC and SEM images, with well defined edges and covered at both sides – sometimes almost entirely – with short, straight or slightly bent up spines (bristles) measuring around 
4–8 µm
(
Figs 4A–C
, 
8D–E
). These ornamentations decrease in thickness and length towards the posterior end of the furca, which seems to be partially due to the decrease in the number and length of the spines (bristles). In fact, thickness, number and length of the spines on the ornamentation are variable among the specimens (
Figs 2A
, 
4A–C
, 
8D–E
). The inner portion of the first 10 
th
of the furca length, which precedes segmentation, is smooth, while the outer portion is covered by the aforementioned bristles.
</p>
      <p>
VENTRAL CILIATURE. Composed of two longitudinal bands of locomotory cilia with approximately 
5–8.5 µm
of length, starting at U1, immediately below the mouth line, and ending at U71, right before the location of the 

Type
6

scales (
Figs 3C, I
, 
6B
, 
7C
). Ventral ciliary bands are separated by the ventral interciliary field covered by small spined scales (
Figs 3I
, 
6B
). Although cilia are 
<tp:taxon-name>not</tp:taxon-name>
well visible in the pictures and were 
<tp:taxon-name>not</tp:taxon-name>
very well oriented for measurements, due to the position and preservation state of the individuals, they are depicted in the illustrated schematics (
Fig. 6B
).
</p>
      <p>
DORSAL SCALES. Most of the cuticular armature of the body is composed of simple spined scales arranged in approximately 42 longitudinal columns, each column bearing 55 scales, and approximately 64 horizontal, alternate rows, with around 10 scales per row (
Fig. 2A
). Dorsolateral scales covering anterior, middle and most of the posterior body surface are roughly polygonal in shape (most presenting pentagonal or hexagonal form), with an elevated anterior portion, a distal incision and bearing a single spine (
Type 1
scales – 
Figs 3D
, 
4D
, 
5A
, 
6A–C
, 
7D–E
). These polygonal scales are the most common type found on the specimens, covering the majority of the body, both dorsolaterally and ventrally. They are outlined by five to six corners, with two distinctive elements (
Figs 5A
, 
6A–C
, 
7D–E
): (a) an elevated anterior portion formed by the spine’s curvature – as it arises from the scale’s surface at middle range, from semi triangular keels – and (b) a longitudinal concavity delimited by two sloping edges that extend from the spine’s insertion to the posterior end of the scale, often ending in a gap, where the two most distal corners meet forming a wide angle. SEM images (
Figs 7A, D–E
, 
8A–B
) reveal that these scales are considerably overlapped (overlapping usually hides their anterior half). Dorsal scales arranged in the first five transversal rows are rounded, very small and rather close to each other, measuring 
3.5–5.5 µm
(scale type unidentified) (
Fig. 3A
). From the fifth transversal row, dorsal scales become predominantly polygonal (
Type 1
scales), reaching 
8.5 µm
at the pharygeointestinal junction (U20 – 
Fig. 3A–B, D
). At the middle trunk (from the pharingeointestinal junction to the proximities of furca base, at U73– U75) they range from 
5.5 to 9 µm
, while at the lateral sides they become slightly larger, measuring 
6.5–11 µm
(
Figs 3D, I
, 
4D
). All dorsal scales are mostly parallel to the transverse axis of the body, with the exception of one distinct elevated spineless scale immediately anterior to the furca base (U71), which is 
5–7 µm
long and shaped as a triangle with well-marked edges (
Type 2
scale – 
Figs 3G
, 
4A–C
, 
5B, D–E
, 
6A, C
). Laterally and below the 
Type 2
scale, at U72, there is a pair of small (
4.5 µm
) rounded scales, one at each side of the caudal field, bearing long spines (
16–21 µm
) which arise directly from the scale’s most posterior end, instead of from the middle, as it normally occurs (
Type 3
scales – 
Figs 3G
, 
4B
, 
5B–D
, 
6A, C
). Immediately following this region (at U 
62 in
the 
paratype
photographed with SEM and between U 
71–75 in
the 
holotype
), there is a rather noticeable spineless field covered by: (a) a patch lacking cuticular ornamentation (situated medially from the surroundings of the furca base until the uppermost portion of the adhesive tubes), and (b) a complex of small, flat, rounded or polygonal and spineless scales (U73–U75), 
2.5–5 µm
long, covering the initial portion of each furcal rami (
Type 4
scales) (
Figs 3G
, 
4A
, 
5D–E
, 
6A
, 
8A
). Below 
Type 2
scales there is a pair of spineless, wide and rounded scales, 
7.5 µm
long, presenting small indentations at their posterior ends (
Type 5
scales – 
Figs 5C
, 
6A, C
, 
8B
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
Scanning electron microscopy. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–B, D–E
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 59). 
C
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 60). 
A
. Dorsal view of the body. 
B
. Dorsolateral view of the head, showing the cephalion and its lateral projections. 
C
. Lateral view of the head, highlighting the lateral pleurae. 
D–E
. Dorsal trunk view, highlighting scale 
Type 1
. Abbreviations: ce = cephalion; fr = furcal rami; lc = locomotory cilia; lce = lateral cephalic expansions; pl = pleurae; sc-1 = 
Type 1
scales. Scale bars: A = 40 µm; B–C = 5 µm; D = 20 µm; E = 10 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
Scanning electron microscopy. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–B, D
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 59). 
C, E
. Paratype (ZUEC GCH 60). 
A–B
. Posterior dorsal view. 
C
. Detail of the furca base in posterior dorsolateral view. 
D–E
. Details of the furcal rami. Abbreviations: fb = furca base; fr = furcal rami; sc-4 = 
Type 4
scales; sc-5 = 
Type 5
scales. Scale bars = 10 µm.
</p>
      <p>
DORSAL SPINES. Dorsolateral spines covering the head and neck (U1–U20) are rather short, ranging from 
2–13 µm
. The first two rows of spines, disposed immediately around and below the cephalic plates are much shorter (
2–7 µm
) and slightly curved, while the remaining rows along the neck contain longer and straighter spines. Through the upper and middle trunk (U21–U44), the dorsal spines increase progressively in length, with an average length of 
11.5 µm
and 
15.5 µm
, respectively, reaching their largest dimensions at the rear trunk (U45–U51), with an average range of 
25.5µm
. At rear trunk, towards the furca base (U75), dorsolateral spines become much longer (
18–33 µm
) and straighter, grouping into two pairs pair of small, tight clusters at the lateral edges of the body surrounding the anterior-most portion of the furca base (
Figs 2A
, 
3G
, 
4A–B
). Most spines arise at a medial point on a scale’s surface, under a small ridge-shaped elevation that is formed by the junction of: (a) the spine’s anterior end, as it rises from the scale, and (b) the superposition between the scale’s anterior portion and the posterior ends of the two scales in the former row (
Figs 6A–C
, 
7E
).
</p>
      <p>
VENTRAL INTERCILIARY SCALES. Are small in the head and neck region (
3.5–5 µm
) and increase in size towards the middle trunk (
4.5 µm
) and rear trunk (
4–7 µm
), similarly to the dorsal and lateral scales. At the posterior end of the ventral surface, the scales are rounded or polygonal and flat (unidentified type). Among these scales is situated a particular and very distinct pair of oval scales at the middle of the posterior interciliary ventral field (U71); each scale bears a keel that emerges from the anterior portion of the scale and extends across its length (
Type 6
scales – 
Figs 5F
, 
6B–C
). In the 
holotype
, the largest scale of the pair is 
10 µm
long, with a keel 
6 µm
long, while the smaller scale is 
9.5 µm
long, showing a 
7 µm
long keel. However, such asymmetrical pattern might 
<tp:taxon-name>not</tp:taxon-name>
be ubiquitous; it was only reported for the 
holotype
because it was 
<tp:taxon-name>not</tp:taxon-name>
possible to visualize and measure these structures in the 
paratypes
. The most distal extremity of the ventral furca base (U75) is covered by two columns of small (
3.5–7 µm
long) scales (
Types 7
and 
8
scales) bearing spines that are very long and straight, measuring from 11 up to 
20 µm
. These scales are elongated antero-posteriorly and laterally narrowed, showing a middle furrow and lateral projections (
Type 7
scales), or rounded and antero-posteriorly narrowed (
Type 8
scales) (
Figs 5F
, 
6B–C
).
</p>
      <p>
VENTRAL INTERCILIARY SPINES. Are shorter than the dorsal spines. They range in size from 
5.5–15 µm
, and become longer and thicker from anterior to posterior region and from ventral to ventrolateral sides.
</p>
      <p>
EGG. A single egg was present in the 
holotype
(
Fig. 3E
); it was 
30 µm
wide and situated between the cuticle and the intestine, extending from the upper to rear trunk (U21–U51). No sperm and reproductive organs were observed.
</p>
      <p>
Taxonomic remarks
</p>
      <p>
Specimens of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus
</tp:taxon-name>
, when compared with the remaining members of 
<tp:taxon-name>Chaetonotida</tp:taxon-name>
, are easily recognized due to their large size (some species are the longest known chaetonotidans), the presence of ring-like ornamentations – usually called segmentations – on the furcal rami, and a cephalion with prominent lateral expansions. Although all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus
</tp:taxon-name>
share these characteristics, it is possible to recognize among them very distinct morphotypes, generally based on their cuticular ornamentation and body outline. Regarding the latest, it is possible to distinguish completely straight outlines with absent body constrictions, as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. serraticaudus
(
Voigt, 1901
)
</tp:taxon-name>
from more tenpin-like shapes as occurs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rhomboides
</tp:taxon-name>
. Furthermore, the caudal portion varies in length, thickness and segmentation 
type
(partial or complete). In what accounts for cuticular coverage, species may present spined scales that lack a peduncle (column-like base) or pedunculated scales (stalked scales). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
bears spined scales that lack a peduncle, and in terms of cuticular coverage resembles six other species: 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. nodicaudus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. serraticaudus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. entzii
(Daday, 1882)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. nodifurca
(Marcolongo, 1910)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. paraelongatus
(
Grosso &amp; Drahg, 1986
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. ringueleti
(Grosso, 1975)
</tp:taxon-name>
. However, the new species has a specific set of characteristics that distinguishes it from these congeners: (1) a cuticular armature composed of simple spined scales with polygonal shape (

Type
1

scales), (2) a single, spineless dorsal scale with a triangular shape located terminally next to the furca base (

Type
2

scale), (3) a spineless zone composed by a patch lacking cuticular ornamentation and flat, rounded or polygonal scales without spines (

Type
4

scales) (4) particular sets of terminal spined or keeled scales located both dorsally and ventrally around the furca base (

Types
3

, 
5
, 
6
, 
7
and 
8
scales). In addition to these characteristics, the new species can be differentiated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. nodicaudus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P
. 
paraelongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
by the presence of a U-shaped furca instead of a V-shaped furca, and from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. entzii
</tp:taxon-name>
by the absence of long spines in each of the ring-like ornamentations (segments) of the furca rami. Additionally, the new species contrasts with 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. nodifurca
</tp:taxon-name>
by long and straight spines instead of short, curved spines, as found in the aforementioned species. Finally, spined-scales are present along the dorsolateral, lateral and ventrolateral regions in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, which distinguishes it from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P
. 
ringueleti
</tp:taxon-name>
; while the long, narrow and segmented furcal rami of the new species are very different from the short, thick and unornamented furca present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. serraticaudus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Table 3
(continued on next page). Comparison of several morphological structures among different species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus
Remane, 1927
</tp:taxon-name>
belonging to the ‘spined scales’ morphotype.
</p>
      <p>
Characteristics
<tp:taxon-name>
P. 
insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
P. nodicaudus
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
P. entzii
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
P. nodifurca
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
P. paraelongatum
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
P. ringueleti
</tp:taxon-name>
Body shape
Elongated
Elongated
Elongated
Elongated
Elongated
Elongated
Total length
215–408 µm
330–544 µm
350–420 µm
395 µm
504 µm
290 µm
Pharynx constriction
Slightly evident
Slightly evident
Slightly evident
Slightly evident
Slightly evident
Slightly evident
Furca base constriction
Accentuated
Accentuated
Accentuated
Accentuated
Slightly accentuated
Accentuated
Pharynx
Cylindrical shape, gradative enlargement towards the rear end
Cylindrical
No description
Cylindrical
No description
Slightly evident posterior enlargement
General structure of scales
Spined, no peduncle Spined, no peduncle
Spined, no peduncle
Spined, no peduncle
Spined, no peduncle
Spined, no peduncle
General shape of scales
Pentagonal, anteriorly curved Anteriorly rounded, as a dome and distally posterior end shaped incised, or all-rounded and as an U smaller
Anterior and lateral extremities with concave shape
No description
Anteriorly rounded, posterior extremity V-shaped
No description
Spines
Present
Present
Present
Present
Present
Present
Shape of dorsal spines
Straight, usually long, shorter Short and simple, near the head larger posteriorly
No description
Short, simple
Simple
No description
</p>
      <p>
Table 3
(continued).
</p>
      <p>
Characteristics
<tp:taxon-name>
P. 
insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
P. nodicaudus
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
P. entzii
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
P. nodifurca
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
P. paraelongatum
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
P. ringueleti
</tp:taxon-name>
Furca
Shaped as a U, middle furrow V-shaped, no furrow V-shaped
Shaped as a wider U, middle furrow present
No description
V-shaped
U-shaped
Ventral scales at furca base
Polygonal or rounded, no peduncle nor superposition
No description
No description
No description
No description
No description
Dorsal scales at furca base
Spineless, mostly pentagonal, a few visibly by SEM oval or rounded, larger and flat
<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

Internal pair of small spines at ventral furca base
Present
<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

Absent
<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

<tp:taxon-name>Not</tp:taxon-name>
described

</p>
      <p>
Phylogenetic relationships
</p>
      <p>
The final alignments of 18S rDNA and 28S rDNA yielded 1761 and 4141 positions, respectively, while the concatenated alignment had 5902 positions. The phylogenetic reconstruction based on a multigene approach supported the currently recognized monophyly of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus
</tp:taxon-name>
with a very high bayesian (1–0.98) and bootstrap (99–98) support for the phylogenetic signal on both internal and external nodes of the Maximum Likelihood (
Fig. 9
) and Consensus trees (Supp. file 2). Accordingly, the 
two specimens
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
were grouped together and nested within 
<tp:taxon-name>
Polymerurus
</tp:taxon-name>
, with branch supports of 1 and 99. As expected, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. nodicaudus
</tp:taxon-name>
was recovered as sister clade to 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, reflecting the morphological similarities between the two species, such as spined scales with no peduncles, in contrast with the pedunculated scales of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rhomboides
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
