<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Catapyrgus jami
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
98955097-7D04-4822-8408-30E37B79766B
</p>
      <p>
Figs 4
A–B, 
5A
, 
6
A, 
7
, 
8
A, 
9
; Tables 
1
– 
2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Catapyrgus jami
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. matapango
</tp:taxon-name>
, however but is, genetically distinct at 59 alignment positions. Furthermore, it differs from its congeners in the shape of the bursa copulatrix, which is globular rather than kidney-shaped.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Catapyrgus jami
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is named after Jochen A. Modess, musician and composer who until his retirement from the university in 2019 has significantly shaped the cultural life of the city of Greifswald for over 25 years. The name is based on the initials of the dedicatee.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 3.
Shell morphology. Principal component analysis based on five shell measurements of Table 1.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype

(
Fig. 4A
) 
NEW ZEALAND
• 
Kahurangi National Park
, 
SW of Collingwood, Kaituna Track
; 
40°42ʹ36.3ʺ S
, 
172°33ʹ36.3ʺ E
; 

28 Feb. 2016

; 
G. Verhaegen
and 
M. Haase
leg.; 
on leaves, stones, woody debris in small spring
; 
NMNZ.M.330187
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes

(
Fig. 4B
)
</p>
      <p>
NEW ZEALAND
• 
9
specs; same collection data as for holotype; 
NMNZ.M.330188

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
SHELL (
Figs 4
A–B, 5A). Short turriform, about 1.7 times as high as than wide, white-translucent with light brown periostracum; protoconch with fine pits comprising 0.75 whorls (
Fig. 6A
); entire shell with 3.875 to 4.25 whorls without structure apart from growth lines; umbilicus narrow; aperture orthocline, almost circular, only slightly higher than wide.
</p>
      <p>
OPERCULUM (
Fig. 7
). Yellowish to light orange, paucispiral; with non-calcareous white peg in submarginal nucleus.
</p>
      <p>EXTERNAL FEATURES. Epidermis without pigment; eyes small with bean-shaped pigment spot; tentacles without particular ciliation.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
Types. 
A–B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Catapyrgus jami
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
C–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Opacuincola lisannea
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(D from northern locality). 
E–F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Op. gretathunbergae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
G–H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Op. mete kahurangi
</tp:taxon-name>
subsp. nov. 
I–J
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Obtusopyrgus farri
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A, C, E, G, I, holotypes, rest paratypes.
</p>
      <p>MANTLE CAVITY. No ctenidial filaments; osphradium ovate-elongate.</p>
      <p>
DIGESTIVE SYSTEM. Radula has formula R 5-6 1 5-6/2 2, L 4-5 1 7, M1 25-29, M2 22-24 (
Fig. 8A
); stomach without caecum; intestine makes narrow, long coil in roof of mantle cavity.
</p>
      <p>
FEMALE GENITALIA (n = 3; 
Fig 9A
). Ovary short, simple sac not reaching stomach; renal oviduct first coiling 180° clockwise, then 270° counter-clockwise; one small, distal receptaculum seminis; bursa copulatrix globular, behind albumen gland, bursal duct entering ventrally; ovoviviparous, brooding at least one embryo in pallial oviduct, pallial oviduct as brood pouch with albumen gland as well as capsule gland with a larger posterior and short anterior section.
</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA (n = 1; 
Fig. 9B
). Testis sac with short lobes, starting more than one whorl below apex, comprises ca 0.5 whorl, anteriorly just reaching stomach; vesicula seminalis coils along anterior half of testis; proximal and distal vasa deferentia insert closely in about middle of flat pear-shaped prostate; penis slender, unclear from CT-scans whether it has a lobe or not.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 5.
Shells. SEM photographs of paratypes. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Catapyrgus jami
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
B–C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Opacuincola lisannea
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(B, topotype; C, northern locality). 
D–E
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Op. gretathunbergae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
F–G
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Op. mete kahurangi
</tp:taxon-name>
subsp. nov. 
H–I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Obtusopyrgus farri
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Catapyrgus jami
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. matapango
</tp:taxon-name>
in terms of shell size and shape (
Fig. 3
). The latter is the only other species of the genus for which sequence data exist. The divergence of the species was fairly large (
Fig. 2
) with a COI p-distance of 0.07, and 45 and 14 diagnostic characters in COI and 16S, respectively (
Table 2
). The reduced eyes suggest that this species dwells in the transition zone of epigean and ground waters. The new species occurred sympatrically with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Op. lisannea
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
