<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Opacuincola gretathunbergae
                        Verhaegen &amp; Haase 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4448202</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03903223FD69FFDAFDBED0DF895AFEF1</uri>
                  <article-title>All-inclusive descriptions of new freshwater snail taxa of the
                        hyperdiverse family Tateidae (Gastropoda, Caenogastropoda) from the South
                        Island of New Zealand</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Opacuincola gretathunbergae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: FCAB414F-A55A-4819-AFE1-CE2AF78D6B2F </p>
            <p> Figs 4 E–F, 5 D–E, 6 D, 8 C, 11 B, 12 ; Tables 1–2 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> The new species is most similar to <tp:taxon-name> Op. ngatapuna </tp:taxon-name> in
                  terms of shape and epidermal pigmentation. It differs from the latter in 11
                  diagnostic DNA positions, in being much larger and in penial morphology. The penis
                  and penial lobe of <tp:taxon-name> Op. gretathunbergae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  are considerably more delicate. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>The dedicatee of this new species is the Swedish teenage climate activist Greta
                  Thunberg. Starting with a single-person school strike and demonstration to save
                  our climate she has sparked the global movement “Fridays for Future” supported
                  primarily by young people and managed to finally get momentum in global politics
                  toward action against climate change after warnings of scientists have been
                  largely ignored for more than 30 years. We wish her and the movement the endurance
                  necessary to keep the pressure up!</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype ( Fig. 4E ) NEW ZEALAND • Kahurangi National Park
                        , W of Motueka, Cobb Dam Road ; 41°04ʹ25.0ʺ S , 172°45ʹ18.5ʺ E ; 1 Mar. 2016
                        ; G. Verhaegen and M. Haase leg.; on leaves, stones, woody debris in trickle
                        along road ; NMNZ.M.330191 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes ( Figs. 4F ; 5 D–E) NEW ZEALAND • 21 specs; same
                        collection data as for holotype; NMNZ.M.330192 </tp:material-citation> .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> SHELL ( Figs 4 E–F, 5D–E). Blunt-conical to pupiform, about 1.65 times as high as
                  than wide, whitetranslucent with brown periostracum; protoconch almost smooth with
                  fine pits comprising ca 0.75 whorl ( Fig. 6D ); entire shell with 3.5 to 4.25
                  whorls, teleoconch initially with fine longitudinal ridges, then without structure
                  apart from growth lines; umbilicus narrow; aperture orthocline, slightly higher
                  than wide. </p>
            <p>OPERCULUM. Orange, paucispiral; nucleus submarginal, without peg.</p>
            <p> EXTERNAL FEATURES ( Figs 4 E–F). Epidermis with irregular, large pigment blotches;
                  eyes well developed and entirely pigmented; tentacles without particular
                  ciliation. </p>
            <p>MANTLE CAVITY (n = 3). 10–12 ctenidial filaments; osphradium ovate-elongate, behind
                  middle of gill.</p>
            <p> DIGESTIVE SYSTEM. Radula has formula R 5-6 1 5–6/3–4 3–4, L 5–6 1 6, M1 22–26, M2
                  31–32 ( Fig. 8C ); stomach without caecum; rectal loop pointing left in roof of
                  mantle cavity, in males more distinct than in females. </p>
            <p> FEMALE GENITALIA (n = 2; Fig. 12 ). Ovary small, simple sac starting&gt; 1.5 whorls
                  below apex, comprising 0.25 whorl and not reaching stomach; renal oviduct first
                  coiling 180° clockwise, then 270° counterclockwise; one distal, large receptaculum
                  seminis lying against anterior area of bursa copulatrix; bursa copulatrix large,
                  globular, extending behind much smaller albumen gland, bursal duct entering
                  anteriorly; ovoviviparous, brooding at least three embryos in pallial oviduct,
                  pallial oviduct as brood pouch with very short albumen gland and large capsule
                  gland, the latter histologically uniform in CT scans. </p>
            <p> MALE GENITALIA (n = 4). Testis lobate sac, starting ca 0.75 whorl below apex,
                  comprising up to 1 whorl, may reach stomach; vesicula seminalis coils along
                  anterior half of testis; proximal vas deferens inserts close to middle of
                  kidney-shaped prostate, distal vas deferens leaving anteriorly; penis long,
                  slender, continuously tapering, pointed; distinct lobe on right side pointing
                  forward ( Fig. 11B ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> The sister relationship of <tp:taxon-name> Op. gretathunbergae </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. to <tp:taxon-name> Op. ngatapuna </tp:taxon-name> was fairly well supported (
                  Fig. 2 ). The average COI p-distance was 0.014 and there were eight type 1
                  characters in COI and three in 16S ( Table 2 ). Morphologically, the new species
                  is larger. Univariate tests comparing shell dimensions could not be conducted,
                  though, because of the small sample size available for <tp:taxon-name> Op.
                        ngatapuna </tp:taxon-name> . But the PCA ( Fig. 3 ) and the data in Haase
                  (2008) are clear regarding the size difference. Anatomically, only the male
                  genitalia could be compared because this information is lacking for
                        <tp:taxon-name> Op. ngatapuna ( Haase 2008 ) </tp:taxon-name> . The
                  well-developed eyes indicate that the new species is a true crenobiont. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
