<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus danum
Robillard &amp; Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
0DEB5BDB-6E85-4691-B5D1-E6258239370A
</p>
      <p>
Figs 5
, 
8D
, 
10C
, 
11C
, 
12C
, 
14C
, 
17E
, 19; 
Tables 2
, 
5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species differs from all known congeners by face part of fastigium with a black band across eyes and antennal cavity, frons otherwise yellow (reddish on preserved specimens); pronotal lateral lobe black dorsally and yellow ventrally; longitudinal white stripe only between M and R and lateral field matted black; Sc projections black. This new species is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. hughtani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
from 
Sumatra
, but differs by the following characters: smaller in size, vertex black with yellow margin around eyes (instead of cream-coloured), frons with a black band across eyes and antennal cavity (yellow in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. hughtani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
); frons yellow (instead of black with a cream-coloured band ventral to eyes); mouthparts yellowish with some black spots; lateral part of head with a black band posterior of eye (instead of black with a cream-coloured ring around eye). This species is also similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. musicus
</tp:taxon-name>
from Kinabalu range, but differs by mouthparts yellow (instead of black), FIIIs not black dorsally, female papilla, and distribution: 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. musicus
</tp:taxon-name>
is restricted to the highlands in the Kinabalu range, while 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. danum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
occurs in the Danum Valley and Tawau Hill areas at the east of 
Sabah
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific name is a noun in apposition taken from the 
type
locality, Danum Valley, 
Malaysia
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MALAYSIA
– 

Sabah

• 
♀
; 
Danum Valley Field Centre
; 
4°57′52.95″ N
, 
117°48′18.25″ E
; ca 

150 m
a.s.l.

; 

26 May–20 Jun. 1987

; 
C. v. Achterberg
and 
Kennedy
leg.; PII: N54; 
RMNH
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
MALAYSIA
– 

Sabah

• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
RMNH

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF10945

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional specimens
</p>
      <p>
MALAYSIA
– 

Sabah

• 
1 ♀
; 
Tawau Hill Park
; 
4°24′0.0″ N
, 
117°53′24.0″ E
; 

7 Mar. 2018

; 
C. Elder
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/19511712

• 

1 ♀
; 
Danum Valley
; 
4°57′42.6″ N
, 
117°41′22.2″ E
; 

2 Oct. 2020

; 
L. Day
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/21010925

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Slender and relatively large habitus (
Figs 8D
, 
19
). Vertex black with yellow margin around eyes (
Fig. 11C
). Fastigium velvety black with yellow margins. Scapes dark red brown to black (particularly on the dorsoinner margins). Antennae black with wide whitish rings. Face part of fastigium with a black band across eyes and antennal cavity, otherwise yellow (reddish in preserved specimens); frons almost entirely yellow, including mouthparts, with some black spots (
Fig. 10C
). Maxillary palpi cream-coloured; apical segment black apically (
Fig. 10C
). Lateral part of head with a black band posterior to eye (
Fig. 12C
). Pronotum covered with white setae; dorsal disk dark brown to black (
Fig. 11C
). Lateral lobes of pronotum dorsal third black, vivid yellow ventrally (cream-coloured in preserved specimens) (
Fig. 12C
). Legs generally red brown, sometimes dorsally darker. FIIIs brown, knees dark brown to black; TIIIs brown with black spines and spurs, dark brown to black near distal end; tarsomeres dark brown to black. Tergites red brown, with a pale band laterally; sternites pale, with red brown median area. Cerci red brown, short and conical.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 19.
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus danum
Robillard &amp; Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, adult ♀♀ in their natural environment. Photograph source and credits: iNaturalist; Arthur Anker (A), Charlie Elder (B).
</p>
      <p>
Table 5.
Measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus danum
Robillard &amp; Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(in mm, means in brackets).
</p>
      <p>
PronL
PronW
FWL
FWW
HWT
FIIIL FIIIW
TIIIL
Female holotype
2.0
3.2
10.8
3.5
6.4
15.3
2.7
15.5
Females (n = 3)
2.0–2.3
3.2–3.5
10.8–11.7
3.5–4.2
6.4–7.7
15.3
2.7
15.5
(2.2)
(3.4)
(11.4)
(4.0)
(7.2)
(15.3) (2.7)
(15.5)
Dorsal spines of TIII
Ias
Ibs
Oas
Obs
TaIIIs
OL
Female holotype
13
2–3
24
2–3
2
17.2
Females (n = 3)
NA
NA
NA
NA
NA
17.2–18.5 (17.9)
</p>
      <p>
Female
FOREWINGS. FW colouration (
Fig. 14C
): veins generally yellow; cells infumated black. Longitudinal
</p>
      <p>infumated white stripe only in M and R. Lateral field matted black, Sc projections black. FW venation: 6–7 strong longitudinal veins on dorsal field, cross-veins irregular and often sinuous; lateral field with 6 projections of Sc.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Ovipositor: distinctly longer than FIII; apex thin with both dorsal and ventral edges smooth. Copulatory papilla conical, smaller and stout; apex strongly folded (could be due to the preservation of specimen) ventrally, short, pointed; dorsal face with a sclerotized area (
Fig. 17E
).
</p>
      <p>
Juvenile
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 5
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Borneo (
Sabah
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type locality
</p>
      <p>
Malaysia
: 
Sabah
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Calling song
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
