<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Nisitrus hughtani Robillard &amp; Tan 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5170007</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/039487A4FFCCFFD8FDFAF5B4FEECF9E2</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the cricket genus Nisitrus Saussure (Orthoptera: Gryllidae: Eneopterinae) and descriptions of five new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.761.1449</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus hughtani
Robillard &amp; Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
8E5BC124-4F3C-432E-BB94-A19C32128B06
</p>
      <p>
Figs 5
, 
7C
, 
8E
, 
10D
, 
11D
, 
12D
, 
13C
, 
14D
, 
15A
, 
16C
, 
17F–G
, 20; 
Tables 1–2
, 
6
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Large and slender species. Head mostly black, but with cream-coloured margin around eyes in both dorsal and lateral views; frons mostly black, but yellow ventral to eyes and antennal cavity; maxillary palpi white. Pronotum dorsal lobe black, lateral lobe mostly white or yellow, its dorsal margin black. Female FWs with dorsal field infumated black; lateral field ventrally black; M/R area forming a clearly defined white/yellow stripe. This species is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. danum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
from Borneo, but differs by the following characters: larger in size, vertex black with cream-coloured margin around eyes (instead of yellow); frons and mouthparts dark red brown to black; frons black with a cream-coloured band ventral to eyes (instead of completely yellow). This species also differs from the sympatric 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. insignis
</tp:taxon-name>
by frons mostly black (instead of yellow); lateral field M/R area forming a clearly defined white stripe (instead of dark); female FW dorsal field with veins black (instead of yellow) and juvenile colouration.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The new species is named after Prof. Hugh Tiang Wah Tan, a renowned botanist and conservation biologist from 
Singapore
and the PhD supervisor of M.K. Tan.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
INDONESIA
– 

Sumatra

• 
♀
; “Nambaru, Kec. Bundar Pasir Mandage, Kab. Asahan”; 
2°44′24.17″ N
, 
99°15′02.52″ E
; 

980 m
a.s.l.

; 

5 Aug. 1983

; 
Yusup
leg.; 
MZB.ORTH.12193
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
INDONESIA
– 

Sumatra

• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; (MZB.ORTH.12192); 
MNHN- EO-ENSIF10946
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
Sarapai
”; “ 

8 July

” 1916; 
Edward Jacobson
leg.; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 

20 km
east of Sasak

, environment of 
Harau Valley National Park
; 
0°04′51.79″ S
, 
100°39′08.13″ E
; 

24–26 Nov. 1999

; 
A.V. Gorochov
leg.; PIII: N34 Nmb1; 
ZIN
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Deli
; 
3°19′ N
, 
98°35′ E
; 

12 Oct. 1895

; 
W. Burchard
leg.; 
ZMH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 juvenile
; 
Batu-Seri
(Medan.); 
3°35′10″ N
, 
98°40′19″ E
; 

10 Mar. 1900

; 
B. Jachan
leg.; 
ZMH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 juvenile
; 

20 km
east of Sasak

, environment of 
Harau Valley National Park
; 
0°04′51.79″ S
, 
100°39′08.13″ E
; 

24–26 Nov. 1999

; 
A.V. Gorochov
leg.; 
ZIN
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 1877–1878; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Additional specimens
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
INDONESIA
– 

Sumatra

• 
1 juvenile
; 
Panti
, 
Pasaman Regency
, 
West Sumatra
; 
0°20′45.7″ N
, 
100°3′56.4″ E
; 

25 Jan. 2019

; 
S.B. Shakya
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/20129372
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Sungai Penuh City
, 
Jambi
; 
2°05′58.5″ S
, 
101°15′57.8″ E
; 

18 Jun. 2019

; 
S. Wollney
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/27481224
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Lempur Tengah
, 
Gunung Raya
, 
Kerinci Regency
, 
Jambi
; 
2°19′24.2″ S
, 
101°32′11.1″ E
; 

12 Nov. 2019

; 
T. Sanders
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/36674976
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 juvenile
; 
Kerinci
, 
Jambi
; 
2°15′12.6″ S
, 
101°34′17.0″ E
; 

12 Aug. 2019

; 
pmaaskant
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/37984028
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 juvenile
; 
Aceh
; 
3°36′47.6″ N
, 
97°26′23.8″ E
; 

14 Apr. 2009

; 
G. Bohne
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/27198231
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 juvenile
; 
Aceh
; 
3°36′55.2″ N
, 
97°34′33.3″ E
; 

14 Apr. 2009

; 
G. Bohne
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/27198588
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 juvenile
; 
Aceh
; 
3°46′11.5″ N
, 
97°31′57.7″ E
; 

14 Apr. 2009

; 
G. Bohne
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/27198509
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Aceh
, 
Gunung Leuser National Park
, 
Gurah
; 
3°46′15″ N
, 
97°14′25.9″ E
; 

16 Feb. 2014

; 
Michael Kesl
leg.; https://www.biolib.cz/en/image/id334434
</tp:material-citation>
/ • 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Aceh
, 
Gunung Leuser National Park
, 
Gurah
; 
3°46′15″ N
, 
97°14′25.9″ E
; 

16 Feb. 2014

; 
Michael Kesl
leg.; https://www.biolib.cz/en/image/id334435
</tp:material-citation>
/ • 
<tp:material-citation>
1 juvenile
; 
Aceh
, 
Gunung Leuser National Park
, 
Gurah
; 
3°46′15″ N
, 
97°14′25.9″ E
; 

16 Feb. 2014

; 
M. Kesl
leg.; https://www.biolib.cz/en/image/id334438
</tp:material-citation>
/ • 
<tp:material-citation>
2 juveniles
; 
Aceh
, 
Gunung Leuser National Park
, 
Gurah
; 
3°46′15″ N
, 
97°14′25.9″ E
; 

16 Feb. 2014

; 
M. Kesl
leg.; https://www.biolib.cz/en/image/id334439
</tp:material-citation>
/ • 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
West Sumatra
, 
Gunung Talakmau
camp 1; 
0°05′50.1″ N
, 
99°56′50.8″ E
; 

15 Mar. 2018

; 
O. Johnson
leg.; https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/11085385
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Habitus large and slender, colouration very contrasting with black, white and vivid yellow when alive (
Figs 7C
, 
20A–B
). Vertex black with cream-coloured margin around eyes (
Fig. 11D
). Fastigium velvety black with cream-coloured margins. Scapes dark red brown to black (particularly on the dorso-inner margins). Antennae black with wide white rings. Frons and mouthparts dark red brown to black, frons cream-coloured (whitish when alive) ventral to eyes (
Fig. 10D
). Maxillary palpi cream-coloured; apical segment black apically (
Fig. 10D
). Head lateral side dark coloured, with broad cream-coloured band around eyes extending to area behind eyes (
Fig. 12D
). Pronotum covered with white setae; dorsal disk velvety black (
Fig. 11D
). Lateral lobes of pronotum with dorsal-third black, cream-coloured ventrally, vivid yellow when alive (
Fig. 12D
). Legs dark brown. FIII brown, knees dark brown to black; TIIIs brown with black spines and spurs, dark brown to black near distal end; tarsomeres dark brown to black. Hindwings hyaline brown apically, longer than FWs, the dark brown tail exceeding FW more than twice as long as pronotum. Tergites red brown, with a pale band laterally; sternites pale, with a red brown median area. Cerci red brown.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 20.
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus hughtani
Robillard &amp; Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in its natural environment in West Sumatra. 
A–B
. Adult ♀♀. 
C–E
. Juveniles. Photograph source and credits: iNaturalist; Oscar Johnson (A), Michael Kesl (B–E).
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
FOREWINGS. FW colouration (
Fig. 13C
): dorsal field cells mostly transparent, veins mostly dark brown to black, cream-coloured in apical field. Basal area brown, basally cream-coloured, brown towards distal part. R cream-coloured, Sc projections cream-coloured basally, black apically. Lateral field brown. FW venation (
Fig. 13C
): 1A curved, slightly angulated. Harp slightly longer than wide, with 3 oblique veins, basal one bifurcate distally, distal one bifurcate basally. c1 long and wide, c2 diamond-shaped; mirror (d1) longer than wide, not rounded, generally separated into two parts by a distinct transverse vein, the posterior part hexagonal, shorter than anterior part. Cell d2 narrower than d1, more or less rectangular. Apical field short and rounded, with 3 wide cell alignments posterior to mirror and a narrow apical alignment. Lateral field with 6 projections of Sc. Epiproct black. Subgenital plate pale cream-coloured with median area, anterior and posterior margins black.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
Fig. 16C
). Pseudepiphallus sclerotized, large and slender, anterior margin narrow and straight, posterior margin also straight, lateral margins distinctly converging posteriorly. Posterior apex with paired lophi longer than wide (at base), subacute at apex, sclerotized laterally only and covered with short strong setae, narrowly spaced apart from each other. Rami swollen preapically, somewhat sinuous. Pseudepiphallic parameres narrow, divergent posteriorly sclerotized arm base to parameres distinctly curved laterally. Ectophallic arc transverse, complete, with anterior and posterior margins straight. Ectophallic fold strong rounded lateral sclerites appearing bean-shaped. Ectophallic apodemes long, straight and slightly divergent. Endophallic sclerite large and sclerotized, its posterior apex with divergent lateral arms and with a short median expansion curved dorsally. Endophallic apodeme with lateral lamellae and dorsal crest only slightly longer than wide.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
FOREWINGS. FW colouration (
Fig. 14D
): cells black, veins generally black. Longitudinal white stripe around region of CuA, M and R with a distinct margin against black colouration on dorsal field; Sc projections cream-coloured basally, black apically. Lateral field dark. FW venation: 6–7 strong longitudinal veins on dorsal field; lateral field with 6 projections of Sc.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Ovipositor: distinctly longer than FIII. Copulatory papilla conical, large (similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. brunnerianus
</tp:taxon-name>
but less slender—possibly due to preservation of specimen); apex folded ventrally, elongated like in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. brunnerianus
</tp:taxon-name>
, pointed; dorsal face with a sclerotized area, but less sclerotized than in congeners; ventro-anterior end forming a somewhat triangular rim (
Fig. 17F–G
).
</p>
      <p>
Juvenile
(
Fig. 20C–E
)
</p>
      <p>Early instars with a pale colouration with numerous dark stripes all around body. Head generally reddish. Eyes with numerous dark stripes. Pronotum with three thick, dark longitudinal stripes on dorsal disk, one very thick and velvety black stripe between dorsal disk and lateral lobe; another curved stripe on lateral lobe ventral of the thick stripe; stripes never reaching the margins. Fore and middle legs with longitudinal dark stripes. FIII also with longitudinal dark stripes, two dorsally, one on each side; and two ventrally, one on each side. Thoracic (excluding pronotum) and abdominal tergites typically dark or greyish, anterior margin darkest, posterior margin whitish. Cerci whitish with a black stripe.</p>
      <p>
Table 6.
Measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus hughtani
Robillard &amp; Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(in mm, means in brackets).
</p>
      <p>
PronL
PronW
FWL
FWW
HWT
FIIIL FIIIW
TIIIL
Female holotype
2.5
4.0
14.8
4.9
8.4
16.5 2.7
16.2
Females (n = 5)
2.2–2.6 (2.4)
3.7–4.0 (3.8)
12.5–14.8 (13.6)
4.4–4.9 (4.7)
8.3–8.7 (8.4)
16.5–17.2 2.7–3.2 (16.8) (2.9)
16.2–18.0 (17.1)
Male (n = 1)
2.2
3.4
10.6
?
8.0
13.9 2.3
14.6
Dorsal spines of TIII
Ias
Ibs
Oas
Obs
TaIIIs
OL
Female holotype
15
2–3
22
2–3
3
19.5
Females (n = 3)
15–16 (15)
2–3
21–24 (22)
2–3
2–3
18.6–21.4 (19.5)
Male (n = 1)
14
2–3
20
2–3
2
–
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 6
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Northern 
Sumatra
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type locality
</p>
      <p>
Indonesia
, northern 
Sumatra
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Calling song
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
