<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Nisitrus crucius Robillard &amp; Tan 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5169999</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/039487A4FFF7FFE2FDC5F533FEECFE3A</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the cricket genus Nisitrus Saussure (Orthoptera: Gryllidae: Eneopterinae) and descriptions of five new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.761.1449</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus crucius
Robillard &amp; Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3140F3A4-21FB-4BB4-ACC6-57BD749A6C3B
</p>
      <p>
Figs 5
, 
7B
, 
8C
, 
10B
, 
11B
, 
12B
, 
13B
, 
14B
, 
16B
, 
17C–D
; 
Tables 2
, 
4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species differs from all known congeners by the following combination of characters: frons yellow, with a cross-shaped black pattern above mouthparts; face part of fastigium between eyes black. Male FWs with a basal area generally paler; female ovipositor only about as long as FIII. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus crucius
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. brunnerianus
</tp:taxon-name>
, from which it differs by smaller size and shorter ovipositor. It is also similar in size to 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. vittatus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. malaya
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
but differs by female FW with cells on dorsal field mostly infumated black, gradually becoming yellow near CuA, M and R veins.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name refers to the dark cross marking on the frons (ʻ 
crucis
ʼ = ʻcrossʼ, in Latin).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
INDONESIA
– 

Kalimantan

• 
♂
; “ 
Biv. Long Hoet
”; 
1°21′7.2″ N
, 
116°31′4.1″ E
; 

16–20 Aug. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF11261
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
INDONESIA
– 

Kalimantan

• 
1 ♀
; “ 
Long Navang
” [
Long Nawang
]; 
Mjöberg
leg.; 
MNHN-EO- ENSIF11262
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
Midden O. Borneo
, 
Marah
”; 
0°58′31″ N
, 
116°33′14.8″ E
; 

10–28 Nov. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF11263
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
Biv. Long Hoet
”; 
1°21′7.2″ N
, 
116°31′4.1″ E
; 

16– 20 Aug. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF11264
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
Melawi
W 
Borneo
”; 
0°34′28″ S
, 
111°45′5″ E
; 

Nov.–Dec. 1924

; 
Blanchemanche
leg.; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF1732
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF11265
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
Samarinda
”; 
0°29′47″ S
, 
117°8′23″ E
; 
M.-E. Walsh
leg.; 
ZMLU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MALAYSIA
– 

Sarawak

• 
1 ♂
; “ 
Kapit
”; 
1°46′0″ N
, 
113°32′12″ E
; 

9 Jul. 1970

; 
Baebe
leg.; 
Ind. Mus.
; PII: N56; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF1750
</tp:material-citation>
. – 
<tp:material-citation>
Sabah

• 
1 ♂
; “nr. 
Long Pa Sia
(
West
)”; 
4°24′21″ N
, 
115°43′47″ E
; “c. 

1200m

”; 

2–13 Apr. 1987

; 
C. v. Achterberg
leg.; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
NO COUNTRY • 
1 ♀
; “ 
Borneo
”; 1891; 
Chaper
leg.; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF11266
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Average size (
Fig. 7B
). Colour pattern somewhat intermediate between 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. brunnerianus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. vittatus
</tp:taxon-name>
. Vertex black with cream-coloured margin around eyes (
Fig. 11B
). Fastigium velvety black with creamcoloured margins. Scapes black dorsally, sometimes reddish ventrally or along dorso-inner margins. Antennae black. Frons yellow, face part of fastigium black between eyes, with a cross-shaped black pattern above mouthparts; clypeus sometimes darkened, mouthparts dark red brown to black (
Fig. 10B
). Maxillary palpi cream-coloured. Head lateral side generally black. Pronotal disk black with white setae (
Fig. 11B
). Lateral lobes of pronotum with dorsal third black, cream-coloured ventrally (
Fig. 12B
). Legs red brown, sometimes internal-basal area black. FIIIs dark red brown, knees dark brown to black; TIIIs brown with black spines and spurs, dark brown to black near distal end; tarsomeres dark brown to black. Hindwings dark hyaline, with a rounded transparent window near internal-basal area; longer than FWs, the dark brown tail exceeding the FWs about twice as long as pronotum. Tergites black, with a pale band laterally of variable thickness; sternites pale, with a black median area.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
FOREWINGS. FW colouration (
Fig. 13B
): dorsal field cells mostly transparent; veins mostly creamcoloured, sometimes black. Basal area brown, basally cream-coloured, brown towards distal part. R and Sc projections cream-coloured. Lateral field hyaline, with dorsal parts infumated cream-coloured. FW venation (
Fig. 13B
): 1A somewhat straight. Harp slightly longer than wide, with 2 oblique veins, distal one bifurcate basally. Cell c1 long and wide, c2 diamond-shaped; mirror (d1) longer than wide, not rounded, generally separated into two parts by a distinct straight transverse vein, the posterior part somewhat rectangular, much shorter than anterior part. Cell d2 narrower than d1, usually subdivided by accessory veins. Apical field short and rounded, with 3 wide cell alignments posterior to mirror and a narrow apical alignment; veins cream-coloured. Lateral field with 5 projections of Sc. Epiproct black. Subgenital plate pale cream-coloured with median area and anterior and posterior margins black.
</p>
      <p>
Table 4.
Measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus crucius
Robillard &amp; Tan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(in mm, means in brackets).
</p>
      <p>
PronL
PronW
FWL
FWW
HWT
FIIIL
FIIIW
TIIIL
Male holotype
2.1
2.9
10.8
3.7
6.9
13.0
2.3
12.0
Males (n = 3)
1.7–2.1 (1.9)
2.9–3.4 (3.1)
9.9–10.8 (10.3)
3.7–4.2 (4.0)
5.3–7.0 (6.4)
12.5–13.0 2.3–2.8 (12.7) (2.5)
12.0–13.0 (12.5)
Females (n = 5)
1.9–2.1 (2.0)
2.8–3.5 (3.3)
10.5–11.7 (11.3)
3.0–3.3 (3.2)
6.5–8.0 (7.1)
13.1–14.5 2.6–2.9 (13.9) (2.7)
13.0–15.0 (14.1)
Dorsal spines of TIII
Ias
Ibs
Oas
Obs
TaIIIs
OL
Male holotype
16
3-5
23
3–5
4
–
Males (n = 3)
13–16 (15)
3–5
17–23 (20)
3–7
4
–
Females (n = 5)
11–12 (12)
3–4
19–20 (20)
3–8
3–4
13.8–15.0 (14.3)
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
Fig. 16B
). Pseudepiphallus sclerotized, stout (small but broad) compared to congeners, anterior margin somewhat broad and straight, posterior margin also straight, lateral margins faintly converging posteriorly. Posterior apex with paired lophi slightly longer than wide (at base), obtuse at apex, sclerotized laterally only and covered with short strong setae; narrowly spaced apart from one another. Rami swollen preapically, anterior apex somewhat truncated. Pseudepiphallic parameres narrow, divergent posteriorly, their basis membranous, with a sclerotized lobe on anterior apex. Ectophallic arc transverse, complete, with anterior and posterior margins straight. Ectophallic fold strong rounded lateral sclerites appearing bean-shaped. Ectophallic apodemes long, straight and slightly divergent basally. Endophallic sclerite large and sclerotized, its posterior apex with divergent lateral arms and with a short median expansion curved dorsally. Endophallic apodeme with lateral lamellae stout.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
FOREWINGS. FW with cells on dorsal field mostly infumated black, gradually becoming yellow near CuA, M and R veins; veins generally yellow (
Fig. 14B
). Sc projections cream-coloured. Lateral field transparent, sometimes infumated black apically.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Ovipositor: only slightly longer than FIII. Copulatory papilla conical, smaller and stout; apex folded ventrally, short, pointed; dorsal face with a sclerotized area; ventro-anterior end forming an oval to pyriform rim (
Fig. 17C–D
).
</p>
      <p>
Juvenile
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Borneo (Kalimantan, 
Sabah
, 
Sarawak
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type locality
</p>
      <p>
Indonesia
, 
Kalimantan
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Calling song
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
