<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Nisitrus rindu Robillard &amp; Tan
                        2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5170037</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/039487A4FFD0FFC2FDD0F7BCFEECFB7A</uri>
                  <article-title>Revision of the cricket genus Nisitrus Saussure (Orthoptera:
                        Gryllidae: Eneopterinae) and descriptions of five new
                        species</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.761.1449</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Nisitrus rindu Robillard &amp; Tan </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: A3AE87F7-8196-4C9B-BDEF-8E9D21B92BE5 </p>
            <p> Figs 5 , 9C–D , 10H , 11H , 12H , 14H , 17N–O ; Tables 2 , 10 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Nisitrus brunnerianus </tp:taxon-name> – Robillard &amp;
                  Desutter-Grandcolas 2004a: 276 (morphological phylogeny). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> This species differs from all known congeners by the combination of these
                  characters: dorsum of head cream-coloured with a black band or T-shaped marking;
                  frons completely black; pronotal lateral lobes yellow, their anterior ventral
                  corner black. Female FW dorsal field with cells almost completely black; veins
                  yellow; longitudinal veins on dorsal field with many more cross-veins, creating a
                  net-like mosaic; lateral field with M, R cream-coloured. This species is similar
                  to <tp:taxon-name> N. insignis </tp:taxon-name> by pattern on head dorsum, but
                  differs by frons completely black (instead of yellow), unique pronotum colouration
                  and female FW lateral field with M and R cream-coloured (instead of dark
                  coloured). This species is also similar to <tp:taxon-name> N. brunnerianus
                  </tp:taxon-name> , which probably occurs in sympatry, and <tp:taxon-name> N.
                        hughtani </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. by dark frons, but differs by the
                  characteristic pattern on dorsum of head and pronotal lateral lobe, and by female
                  FW lateral field hyaline in ventral half. It also differs from the sympatric
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. vittatus </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> N. crucius
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. by the black frons, pronotum lateral lobe and FW
                  colouration. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>This species name refers to the word ʻrinduʼ, which means ʻloveʼ [verb] in Iban [a
                  group of indigenous people from Borneo] language and ʻhome-sicknessʼ = ʻmissʼ
                  [verb] in Bahasa Melayu (Malay language) and Indonesian. This new species is
                  dedicated to the front-liners fighting against the COVID-19 pandemic who were far
                  from their homes and loved ones during the early phase of the global pandemic
                  (when the speciesʼ name was chosen).</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Holotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> MALAYSIA – Sarawak • ♀ ; Mount Murud ; 6500 ft a.s.l. ;
                        3°54′28.44″ N , 115°29′12.68″ E ; 15 Apr. 1979 ; identified as
                              <tp:taxon-name> Nisitra brunneriana </tp:taxon-name> by L. Chopard ;
                        MNHN-EO-ENSIF10939 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> INDONESIA – Kalimantan • 3 ♀ ; “ West Borneo , Midden” [
                        borders of Apokajan, Boeloengan and Beraoe ]; 1°58′43″ N , 116°6′43″ E ;
                        15–20 Oct. 1925 ; H.C. Siebers leg.; identified as <tp:taxon-name> Nisitrus
                              brunnerianus </tp:taxon-name> by T. Robillard 2004; MNHN-EO-ENSIF10940
                        to ENSIF10942 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; Long
                        Petak ; 1°42′6″ N , 116°12′25″ E ; 450 m a.s.l. ; Sep. 1925 ; Brugs leg.;
                        identified as <tp:taxon-name> Nisitrus brunnerianus </tp:taxon-name> by T.
                        Robillard 2004; MNHN-EO-ENSIF10943 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> MALAYSIA – Sabah • 1 ♀ ; near Long Pasia “Long Pa Sia” ;
                        4°24′22.05″ N , 115°43′40.97″ E ; 1020 m a.s.l. ; 1–14 Apr. 1987 ; C. v.
                        Achterberg leg.; RMNH </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ;
                        same collection data as for preceding; PII: N57; RMNH
                  </tp:material-citation> . – <tp:material-citation> Sarawak • 1 ♀ ; Mount Tibang ;
                        1°39′ N , 114°34′ E ; 1700 m a.s.l. ; E.G. Mjöberg leg.; MNHN-EO-ENSIF10944
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Relatively large for the genus, colouration contrasted ( Fig. 9C–D ). Vertex
                  cream-coloured with a variable longitudinal black band and one or two faint
                  transverse black bands forming a T- or ʻ+ʼ-shaped black pattern ( Fig. 11H ).
                  Scapes black, posterior end red brown. Antennae red brown with some segments
                  black. Frons and face part of fastigium completely black, without yellow spots or
                  bands ( Fig. 10H ). Mouthparts dark red brown to black. Maxillary palpi
                  cream-coloured ( Fig. 10H ). Head lateral side black, sometimes with a small
                  yellow spot at the ventro-posterior margin of eye ( Fig. 12H ). Pronotal disk
                  generally black with lateral and posterior margins yellow ( Fig. 11H ); pronotal
                  lateral lobe yellow, its ventro-anterior corner black ( Fig. 12H ). Legs red
                  brown. FIIIs dark red brown, their inner basal area black; knees dark brown to
                  black; TIIIs brown with black spines and spurs, dark brown to black near distal
                  end; tarsomeres dark brown to black. Hindwings hyaline brown, with a longitudinal
                  transparent window near external-basal area; longer than FWs, forming a dark brown
                  tail exceeding FWs more than twice as long as pronotum. Abdomen generally black. </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> FOREWINGS. FW dorsal field with cells almost completely black; veins almost always
                  yellow ( Fig. 14H ). Lateral field with M and R cream-coloured, sometimes with a
                  cream-coloured patch at base; otherwise transparent or dark. FW venation:
                  longitudinal veins on dorsal field with many cross-veins, creating a thin net-like
                  mosaic. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA. Ovipositor distinctly longer than FIII; apex thin. Copulatory papilla
                  conical, smaller and stout; apex folded ventrally, elongated, pointed; dorsal face
                  with a sclerotized area; ventro-anterior end an oblong rim ( Fig. 17N–O ). </p>
            <p> Measurements </p>
            <p> See Table 10 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Table 10. Measurements of <tp:taxon-name> Nisitrus rindu Robillard &amp; Tan
            </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. (in mm, means in brackets). </p>
      <p> PronL PronW FWL FWW HWT FIIIL FIIIW TIIIL Female holotype 1.8 2.8 11.3 3.4 6.0 13.0 2.3
            13.3 Females (n = 5) 1.8–2.2 (2.0) 2.8–3.7 (3.1) 11.3–13.5 (12.5) 3.4–4.3 (3.8) 5.8–7.5
            (6.7) 13.0–16.4 2.3–3.1 (15.2) (2.8) 13.3–17.5 (15.5) Dorsal spines of TIII Ias Ibs Oas
            Obs TaIIIs OL Female holotype 17 3–5 21 3–6 3 17.3 Females (n = 5) 13–17 (15) 3–5 21–24
            (23) 3–6 3 17.1–21.2 (18.9) </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Ecology </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Borneo: Sabah , Sarawak and Kalimantan. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type locality </p>
            <p> Malaysia : Sabah . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Calling song </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
