<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microplitis
Förster, 1862
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Microplitis
Förster, 1862: 245
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_reference">
      <p>
(type species: 

<tp:taxon-name>
Microgaster sordipes
Nees, 1834: 167
</tp:taxon-name>

(by original designation, 
holotype
♀
, Klugiano Museum)).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Members of this genus are distinguished by having anteromesoscutum densely sculptured, seldom shining, often with notauli which sometimes are strongly defined; propodeum evenly curved in profile, completely rugose and often with a median longitudinal carina but never with any indication of areola; fore wing always with a closed areolet; vannal lobe of the hind wing convex and setose; metacoxa small, not reaching past the posterior margin of T1; metatibial spurs shorter than one-half of metabasitarsus; mesotibial spurs shorter than mesobasitarsus; T1 of variable shape, from widening to narrowing posteriorly and usually sculptured; T2+ smooth, rarely weakly sculptured and often with a weakly delimited trapezoidal median area; T3 always longer than T2, the transverse groove separating them frequently not, or only poorly, defined; hypopygium usually rather small but sometimes elongated medially, rarely conspicuously so, occasionally truncate or medially emarginated; ovipositor and its sheath usually short (
Mason 1981
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Identification key to the Iranian species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microplitis
Förster, 1862
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
The following identification key is mostly based on 
Papp (1984)
, 
Tobias (1986)
and 
Kotenko (2007)
but modified for Iranian species and including one species newly described in this paper.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. T1 distinctly broadening posteriorly, T1 length almost equal to its posterior width (
Figs 8F
, 
9F
); T2 distinctly rugoluse ............................................................................................................................. 2

</p>
      <p>

– T1 parallel- to sub-parallel-sided or weakly broadening posteriorly (
Figs 2F
, 
3F
, 
4F
, 
5F
, 
6F
, 
7F
, 
10F
, 
11F
, 
12F
, 
13F
, 
14F
), T1 much longer than posterior width; T2 with variable sculptures ................. 4

</p>
      <p>

2. Body mostly reddish yellow, except for black head (
Fig. 8A–F
); vein R1 more than 0.5 × pterostigma length; pterostigma length 2.00 × its width (
Fig. 8D
) ....................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. ochraceus
Szepligeti, 1896
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Body black; other characters variable ............................................................................................... 3
</p>
      <p>

3. Antenna shorter than body; F15 length 1.50 × its width; hypopygium in lateral view strongly developed, with characteristically pointed apex; tegula black ................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. xanthopus
Ruthe, 1860
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Antenna as long as body; F15 length 2.00 × its width; hypopygium normal; tegula yellow or reddish yellow ................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. pallidipennis
Tobias, 1964
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

4. T1 length more than 1.70 × (1.70–3.00) its maximum width, T1 usually parallel-sided or narrowing posteriorly (
Figs 2F
, 
3F
, 
7F
, 
10F
, 
13F
) .............................................................................................. 5

</p>
      <p>

– T1 length 1.60 × or less (1.40–1.60) its maximum width, T1 more or less broadening posteriorly (
Figs 4F
, 
5F
, 
6F
, 
11F
, 
12F
, 
14F
) ...................................................................................................... 14

</p>
      <p>
5. Antenna clearly shorter than body .................................................................................................... 6
</p>
      <p>
– Antenna as long as or longer than body ............................................................................................ 7
</p>
      <p>

6. In dorsal view, head width (between temples) slightly broader than head width (between eyes); tegula yellow to brown; vein R1 0.5 × pterostigma length; vein 1CUb 2.50 × as long as vein 1CUa; vein 1CUb and vein r–m slightly curved; vein r shorter than vein 2RS; T1 weakly broadening posteriorly ................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. aduncus
(
Ruthe, 1860
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– In dorsal view, head width (between temples) similar to head width (between eyes) (
Fig. 2B
); tegula black; vein R1 more than 0.5 × pterostigma length; vein 1CUb 2.00 × as long as vein 1CUa; vein 1CUb and vein r–m straight; vein r slightly longer than vein 2RS (
Fig. 2D
); T1 parallel-sided or weakly barrel-shaped (
Fig. 2F
) .......................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. alborziensis
Abdoli &amp; Talebi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
7. Tegula and metafemur dark brown to black ..................................................................................... 8
</p>
      <p>
– Tegula and metafemur yellow to reddish yellow .............................................................................. 9
</p>
      <p>

8. Pterostigma with large anterior pale spot; T1 medially smooth to uneven, shiny, laterally rugorugulose .......................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. sofron
Nixon, 1970
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Pterostigma without or with a small anterior yellow spot; T1 rugose to coriaceous, matte ............... .......................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. cebes
Nixon, 1970
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

9. Metasoma yellow or reddish yellow, at least last 2–3 segments more or less darkening ................... .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. rufiventris
Kokujev, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Metasoma black or dark brown, at least first 2–3 segments lightening .......................................... 10
</p>
      <p>

10. T1 length more than 2.20 × (2.50–3.50) its maximum width; antenna dark, brown to black; tergites black, sometimes T2 and T3 yellow to brown; metacoxa yellow to reddish yellow; in fore wing, vein 1CUb 2.00 × as long as vein 1CUa (
Fig. 13D
); in hind wing, vein 2r–m about 1.75–1.90 × as long as vein 1r–m (
Fig. 13E
) ................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. tuberculifer
(
Wesmael, 1837
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– T1 length 2.00 × (or less) its maximum width, other characters variable .......................................11
</p>
      <p>

11. 6 
th
sternite distinctly developed, produced beyond apex of metasoma; T1 reddish yellow (sometimes with blackish suffusion) and narrowed toward apex and base ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. fulvicornis
(
Wesmael, 1837
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
–
6 
th
sternite not produced beyond apex of metasoma; T1 black or dark brown and narrowed toward apex or base .................................................................................................................................... 12

</p>
      <p>

12. Antenna usually light coloured (yellow to brownish yellow), distally darkening; tergites and metacoxa black; in fore wing, vein 1CUb 3.00 × as long as vein 1CUa (
Fig. 7D
); in hind wing, vein 2r–m about 1.40–1.60 × as long as vein 1r–m (
Fig. 7D
) ............... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. mandibularis
Thomson, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Antenna always dark brown or black (scape reddish yellow or black); other characters variable ..... ......................................................................................................................................................... 13
</p>
      <p>

13. T 
1 in
posterior third sculptured, matte, in basal half smooth; pterostigma entirely dark brown, without anterior pale spot; basal one third of wing with light-coloured veins, the rest with darkened veins; scape reddish yellow, in contrasts with a dark-coloured flagellum; T2 and T3 black ............. .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. marshallii
Kokujev, 1898
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– T1 almost entirely sculptured; pterostigma with anterior pale spot; wing all smoky, with darkened veins; scape dark-coloured, does not contrast in colour with the flagellum; T2 and T3 often light coloured ................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. mediator
Haliday, 1834
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

14. Antenna shorter than body; F15 1.40–1.50 × as long as wide (
Fig. 11A
); pterostigma length 2.30– 2.40 × its width, with light yellow spot anteriorly (
Fig. 11D
); all coxae black to infuscate; metafemur reddish brown, brown to black; tegula dark brown to black .............. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. spectabilis
(
Haliday, 1834
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Antenna longer than body; other characters variable ..................................................................... 15
</p>
      <p>

15. T2 rugulose or sub-rugulose (
Fig. 12E
); frons polished (
Fig. 12D
) .......... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. spinolae
(
Nees, 1834
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– T2 smooth, frons not polished (if T2 uneven to shrivelled then frons sculptured) ......................... 16
</p>
      <p>
16. Tegula and metafemur yellow or reddish yellow ............................................................................ 17
</p>
      <p>
– Tegula black and metafemur variable coloured .............................................................................. 19
</p>
      <p>

17. Mesoscutellar disc weakly and dispersedly punctate to smooth, with medio-longitudinal keel anteriorly which is rather short and low; pterostigma without anterior pale spot; T2 rather smooth to polished, though frequently uneven to shrivelled, less frequently rugulose ....................................... ......................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. deprimator
(
Fabricius, 1798
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Mesoscutellar disc coriaceous to rugulose, without keel anteriorly, pterostigma with or without anterior yellow spot ........................................................................................................................ 18
</p>
      <p>

18. T2 and T3 yellow or reddish yellow (
Fig. 6F
); pterostigma with anterior yellow spot (
Fig. 6D
) ...... ......................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. kaszabi
Papp, 1980
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– T2 and T3 black or brown, sometimes with small yellow areas; pterostigma without anterior pale spot (
Fig. 5D
) ......................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. eremitus
Reinhard, 1880
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

19. Metafemur yellow; tergites black, sometimes T2 and T3 ferruginous to red ..................................... ...................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. scrophulariae
Szépligeti, 1898
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Metafemur black or dark brown (sometimes with yellowish patterns); tergites black ................... 20
</p>
      <p>

20. Mesoscutellar disc strongly rugose (
Fig. 4C
); scape yellow to reddish yellow, contrasting with dark brown flagellum; pterostigma without anterior pale spot (
Fig. 4D
) .............. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. docilis
Nixon, 1970
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Mesoscutellar disc with usual sculpture, finely to densely punctate, matte or shiny; scape black or brown, similar colour to flagellum; pterostigma with or without anterior pale spot ...................... 21
</p>
      <p>

21. Fore wing areolet relatively very large and almost pentagonal; lateral and median lobes of anteromesonotum densely shagreened, dull; pterostigma black, with a small pale spot anteriorly ... ...................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. decipiens
Prell, 1925
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Fore wing areolet relatively smaller and triangular; lateral and median lobes of anteromesonotum rugulose to rugose; pterostigma with or without pale spot anteriorly ............................................ 22
</p>
      <p>

22. Pterostigma with distinct pale spot anteriorly (
Fig. 14D
); F15 length 2.00 × its width; body relatively smaller, its length at most 
3.50 mm
, usually 
2.80–3.50 mm
...................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. varipes
(
Ruthe, 1860
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Pterostigma evenly brown or with diffusely pale spot anteriorly; F15 length 1.50 × its width; body relatively bigger, usually 4.00– 
4.20 mm
..................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. viduus
(
Ruthe, 1860
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
