<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Gehundra cristalinensis Domahovski
                        2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4716279</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03977924187BFFA2A226FE27FE593DC8</uri>
                  <article-title>Two new species of Hyalojassini (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae: Iassinae)
                        to the genera Comanopa Blocker and Gehundra Blocker, description of the male
                        of G. sordida (Baker) and key to species</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://zoobank.org/c82e9877-eab4-41b1-a73a-0687c94d9472</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Gehundra cristalinensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 25FBE065-ECF1-4D42-9AF4-A82F25D83058 </p>
            <p> Figs 13–31 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Male pygofer ( Figs 17–19 ) ventral margin with long thin setae on apical half.
                  Subgenital plate ( Figs 17– 20 ) with external margin rounded, almost circular;
                  apex deeply notched, pseudostyle acute, with few short setae. Style ( Fig. 21 )
                  approximately straight; apex slightly tapered and curved dorsally. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The new species name refers to the locality (Parque Estadual do Cristalino) where
                  the type series was collected. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype BRAZIL • ♂ ; “ Brasil , MT [ Mato Grosso ], Novo
                        Mundo , Pq. [Parque]\ Est. [Estadual] do Cristalino , 09.4517ºS , \
                        55.8396ºW , 240m , light trap , \ 21-25.vi.2017 , RR Cavichioli \ &amp; AC
                        Domahovski ”; DZUP 215443 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes BRAZIL • 5 ♂♂ , 4 ♀♀ ; same collection data as
                        for holotype; DZUP 215444 to 215452 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ , 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype;
                        DZRJ </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; “ Brasil , MT ,
                        Novo Mundo , \ Pq. Est. do Cristalino , \ 09.4517ºS 55.8396ºW ,\ 240m ,
                        luminárias - aloja \mento AC Domahovski”; DZUP 215453
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p>MEASUREMENTS (mm). Holotype (♂) total length 4.7. Paratypes (♂) 4.6–4.8; (♀)
                  4.8–5.0.</p>
            <p>BODY. Small and ovate leafhoppers, not depressed dorsoventrally.</p>
            <p> HEAD ( Figs 13–15 ). Dorsal view: very short, transocular width nine-tenths humeral
                  width of pronotum; crown not developed, vertical, surface whit transverse striae;
                  anterior and posterior margins parallel and broadly rounded; ocelli not visible
                  dorsally; lateral view: crown-face transition broadly rounded with transverse
                  striae; frons and clypeus slightly inflated; ventral view: face more than two
                  times wider than high; ocelli small, on anterior margin, mesad of antennal pits
                  and distant from eyes; frons with transverse striae, lateral margins strongly
                  convergent ventrally; frontogenal suture surpassing antennal ledge, extending to
                  anterior margin of crown; antennal ledge carinate and slightly oblique, not
                  concealing antennal base; antenna length ca ⅓ width of head; gena broad, with
                  small setae; ventrolateral margin broadly rounded, completely concealing
                  proepisternum; maxillary plate produced ventrally as far as clypeus apex; lorum
                  with few short setae, narrower than clypeus width, subgenal suture rounded,
                  extended nearly to midlength of lateral margin of frons; clypeus slightly shorter
                  than basal width, epistomal suture complete and rounded, lateral margins excavated
                  medially, apex slightly broadened, rounded and carinated. </p>
            <p> PRONOTUM ( Figs 13–14 ). Dorsal view: anterior margin broadly rounded, posterior
                  margin slightly excavated; surface without setae, with transverse striae, except
                  on anterior third; lateral margins convergent anterad, carinate, slightly shorter
                  than eye length; lateral view: convex and declivous anterad. </p>
            <p> MESONOTUM AND SCUTELLUM ( Fig. 13 ). Dorsal view: longer than pronotum length;
                  surface with transverse striae, except lateral angles with texture shagreen;
                  scutellum flat. </p>
            <p> FOREWING ( Figs 13–14 ). With many small erect setae, venation obscure; clavus
                  truncate apically; vein separating appendix and first apical cell complete (not
                  evanescent apically), appendix and first apical cell broad, more membranous than
                  adjacent cells, glabrous; 3 closed anteapical cells and 4 apical cells (2 nd , 3
                  rd and 4 th cells short; R1 vein absent). </p>
            <p>HIND WING. Veins R4+5 and M1+2 fused apically.</p>
            <p>LEGS. Profemur moderately elongated, 2.9 times longer than high; PD, AD and AM rows
                  formed by undifferentiated setae, PD1 and AD1 setae short and AM1 absent; IC row
                  formed by double row of fine setae, continuous with AV row; AV and PV rows formed
                  by several fine setae. Protibia, in cross-section, almost circular, without
                  defined longitudinal carina adjacent to PD row; AV row formed by short, thin setae
                  in the basal half and slightly more robust setae distally; AD row consisting of
                  only undifferentiated setae; PD row formed by with 3–4 long setae intercaled by
                  undifferentiated setae; PV row with 6–7 short setae. Hind leg with femoral setal
                  formula 2:2:1 or 2:2:1:1; PD2 seta reduced in size; metatibia PD, AD and AV rows
                  with 14–19, 9–11 and 10–12 macrosetae respectively; AD row without intercalary
                  setae between macrosetae; PV row with setae of apical half intercalating 1 longer
                  and thicker seta and 3–4 shorter and thinner setae, ending with 3 thin setae;
                  first tarsomere without enlarged dorsoapical seta; ventral surface with two
                  longitudinal rows of simple (non-cucullate) thin setae; pecten with 4 platellae
                  flanked by tapered lateral setae; second tarsomere pecten with 2 platellae flanked
                  by tapered lateral setae.</p>
            <p> COLORATION. Head and thorax ( Figs 13–15 ) brownish-yellow. Face ( Fig. 15 ) with
                  muscle impressions of frons brown; lorum with ventral half brown. Pronotum ( Fig.
                  13 ) with irregular brown markings near anterior margin. Mesonotum ( Fig. 13 )
                  with lateral angles dark brown. Forewing ( Figs 13–14 ) with brown setae and
                  groups of black setae at midlength of anal margin, apex of clavus and apex of
                  inner discal cell (variable in intensity between the specimens). </p>
            <p> TERMINALIA. Sternite VIII ( Fig. 16 ) convex, strongly produced posterad, two times
                  longer than wide, longer than sternites VII and VI combined; ventral surface with
                  many small setae, except basal portion and along median line; lateral margins
                  tapered toward apex, with small rounded lobe at basal third; apex subacute. Valve
                  ( Figs 17–18 ) longer than wide, broadly fused laterally to pygofer; lateral
                  margins convergent toward ventral margin, with strong integument thickening;
                  ventral margin rounded. In lateral view, pygofer ( Figs 17–18 ) without processes,
                  higher near base; dorsal margin deeply notched after half its length;
                  dorsoposterior margin fused to pygofer lobes, straight and oblique; ventral margin
                  approximately straight, with short setae near base and long thin setae on apical
                  half; lateral surface with longitudinal carina near ventral margin of basal ⅔;
                  apex very wide and truncated; without macrosetae, but with few short setae near
                  apex. In ventral view, pygofer ( Fig. 19 ) with ventral margin folded inward, from
                  base to apex, with short setae on inner surface. Anal tube ( Fig. 17 ) membranous,
                  without processes. Subgenital plate ( Figs 17–20 ) short, with well developed
                  pseudostyle; inner margin nearly straight; external margin rounded, almost
                  circular, overlapping pygofer laterally; apex deeply notched, pseudostyle acute,
                  with few short setae. Connective amorphous. Style ( Figs 17, 21 ) long,
                  approximately straight, apodeme and apophysis long, subequal in length; apex
                  slightly tapered and curved dorsally. Aedeagus ( Figs 22–23 ), with preatrium not
                  developed; dorsal apodeme developed, with lateral margins extended laterad and
                  posterior margin extending to almost apex of shaft; shaft slightly curved
                  dorsally; dorsal margin rounded near base and straight distally; ventral margin
                  broadly rounded. In ventral view, aedeagus ( Fig. 23 ) with shaft apex bifid;
                  gonopore subapical. </p>
            <p> Figs 13–23. <tp:taxon-name> Gehundra cristalinensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ,
                  holotype, ♂ (DZUP 215443). 13 . Habitus, dorsal view. 14 . Habitus, lateral view.
                  15 . Head, ventral view. 16 . Sternite VIII, ventral view. 17 . Genital capsule,
                  lateral view. 18 . Pygofer, valve and subgenital plate, lateral view. 19 .
                  Pygofer, valve and subgenital plate, ventral view. 20 . Subgenital plate, ventral
                  view. 21 . Style, lateral view. 22 . Aedeagus, lateral view. 23 . Aedeagus,
                  ventral view. Scale bars in mm. </p>
            <p> Female TERMINALIA. Sternite VII ( Figs 24–25 ) ca two times wider than long; ventral
                  surface with short setae; posterior margin deeply excavated, V-shaped. Internal
                  sternite VIII membranous. Pygofer ( Figs 24, 26 ) with many thin setae; ventral
                  margin broadly rounded with group of thick setae at base; apex obliquely
                  truncated. Ovipositor slender, evenly curved dorsad, not surpassing pygofer apex.
                  First valvifer ( Fig. 27 ) trapezoid, approximately as long as wide; anterior
                  margins of both valvifers connected by sclerotized membrane. First valvula ( Fig.
                  27 ) with dorsal and ventral margins almost parallel, slightly convergent
                  apically, ca 7 times longer than high at base; ventral interlocking device long,
                  extending over basal ⅔; dorsal sculptured area areolate starting before the
                  midlength; apical portion ( Fig. 28 ) with ventral sculpture present only near
                  apex, continuous with the dorsal sculpture, apex moderately tapered and acute.
                  Second valvifer ( Fig. 31 ) ca three times higher than long. Second valvula ( Fig.
                  29 ) ca 10 times longer than high; dorsal and ventral margins parallel; dorsal
                  margin with three distinct subapical teeth widely spaced; apical portion ( Fig. 30
                  ) of dorsal margin with two rounded subapical notches forming one rounded tooth
                  between apex and first subapical tooth; ventral margin without denticles and with
                  one subapical tooth. Gonoplac ( Fig. 31 ) four times longer than high; dorsoapical
                  margin long, half length of gonoplac; external surface without dentiform cuticular
                  projections; ventral margin broadly rounded, with few spaced macrosetae near
                  ventral margin; apex rounded. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Figs 24–31. <tp:taxon-name> Gehundra cristalinensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , paratype,
            ♀ (DZUP 215451). 24 . Apical portion of abdomen, ventral view. 25 . Apical portion of
            abdomen, lateral view. 26 . Enlarged view of basal portion of pygofer. 27 . First
            valvifer and first valvula, lateral view. 28 . Apical portion of first valvula. 29 .
            Second valvula, lateral view. 30 . Apical portion of second valvula. 31 . Second
            valvifer and gonoplac, lateral view. Scale bars in mm. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Gehundra cristalinensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is most similar
                  to <tp:taxon-name> G. avulsa </tp:taxon-name> in having the male pygofer with
                  ventral margin bearing long setae on apical half and the subgenital plate deeply
                  notched apically. However, the new species can easily by separated by the
                  subgenital plate ( Fig. 20 ) with external margin rounded, almost circular (less
                  expanded laterally and not circular in <tp:taxon-name> G. avulsa </tp:taxon-name>
                  ) and the style ( Fig. 21 ) approximately straight, with apex slightly tapered
                  (style with apophysis more curved, with apex footshaped in <tp:taxon-name> G.
                        avulsa </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
