<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Comanopa mananciensis Domahovski 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4716201</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03977924187FFFADA221FB52FB5D3A9F</uri>
         <article-title>Two new species of Hyalojassini (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae: Iassinae) to the genera Comanopa Blocker and Gehundra Blocker, description of the male of G. sordida (Baker) and key to species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/c82e9877-eab4-41b1-a73a-0687c94d9472</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Comanopa mananciensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
1496BF6F-94E4-4E89-92EB-1E7457C88C06
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–12
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Head and thorax (
Figs 1–3
) brownish-yellow. Face (
Fig. 3
) with crown-face transition black. Male pygofer (
Figs 5–7
) with pair of processes arising near base of plates, short and rounded apically; ventral margin of pygofer strongly produced ventrad. Aedeagus (
Figs 11–12
) with shaft deeply split apically, whit pair of subapical processes directed laterally.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The new species name refers to the locality (Mananciais da Serra) where the 
holotype
was collected.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; “ 
Brasil
, 
Paraná
, 
Piraquara
, Ma-\ nanciais da Serra, 
25º29’47”S
\ 
48º58’54”W
1021m

, Sweep, \ 

21-28.XI.2018

, 
A.P. Pinto
, 
B.R. \Araujo
&amp; 
A.C. Domahovski
”; 
DZUP 215440
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♂
; “ 
Brasil
, 
PR
[
Paraná
], 
S. [São] J. [José] dos Pinhais
\ 
Rep. [Represa] Guaricana
, 
Luz
\ 
25.7150ºS
48.9711ºW
\ 

750 a 
400m
12-14.XII.2017

\ 
Cavichioli
&amp; 
Domahovski
”; 
DZUP 215441
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS (mm). 
Holotype
(
♂
) total length 3.8. 
Paratype
(
♂
) 4.0.
</p>
      <p>BODY. Small and ovate leafhoppers, not depressed dorsoventrally.</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 1–3
). Dorsal view: very short, transocular width nine-tenths humeral width of pronotum; crown not developed, nearly vertical, median length 
1/10
of interocular width, surface with transverse striae; anterior and posterior margins parallel and broadly rounded; ocelli not visible dorsally; lateral view: crown-face transition broadly rounded with transverse striae; frons slightly inflated; clypeus almost flat; ventral view: face less than two times wider than high; ocelli small, on anterior margin, mesad of antennal pits and distant from eyes; frons with transverse striae, lateral margins strongly convergent ventrally; frontogenal suture extending to antennal ledges; antennal ledge carinate and slightly oblique, not concealing antennal base; antenna length ca ⅓ width of head; gena broad, with small setae; ventrolateral margin broadly rounded, completely concealing proepisternum; maxillary plate produced ventrally as far as clypeus apex; lorum broad, with short setae, maximum width approximately equal to that of clypeus, subgenal suture rounded, extended nearly to midlength of lateral margin of frons; clypeus slightly longer than wide, epistomal suture complete and straight, lateral margins parallel, apex carinated and straight.
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM (
Figs 1–2
). Dorsal view: anterior margin broadly rounded, posterior margin slightly excavated; surface without setae, with transverse striae, except on anterior third; lateral margins convergent anterad, carinate, slightly shorter than eye length; lateral view: convex and declivous anterad.
</p>
      <p>
MESONOTUM AND SCUTELLUM (
Fig. 1
). Dorsal view: as long as pronotum length; surface with transverse striae; scutellum flat.
</p>
      <p>
FOREWING (
Figs 1–2
). Many small erect setae, venation obscure; clavus truncate apically; appendix and first apical cell more membranous than adjacent cells, glabrous, vein separating appendix and first apical cell evanescent apically; 3 closed anteapical cells and 4 apical cells (2 
nd
, 3 
rd
and 4 
th
cells short; R1 vein absent).
</p>
      <p>HIND WING. Veins R4+5 and M1+2 fused apically.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Profemur moderately elongated, 2.7 times longer than high; PD, AD and AM rows formed by undifferentiated setae, PD1 and AD1 setae short and AM1 absent; IC row formed by double row of fine setae, continuous with AV row; AV and PV rows formed by several fine setae. Protibia, in crosssection, almost circular; AV row formed by short, thin setae in the basal half and slightly more robust setae distally; AD row consisting of only undifferentiated setae; PD row with 3 long setae intercaled by undifferentiated setae; PV row with 3–4 long setae intercaled by undifferentiated setae. Hind leg with femoral setal formula 2:2:1; PD2 seta reduced in size; metatibia PD, AD and AV rows with 15–16, 9–10 and 9–10 macrosetae respectively; AD row without intercalary setae between macrosetae; PV row with setae of apical half intercalating 1 longer and thicker seta and 3–4 shorter and thinner setae, ending with 2 very short, thin setae; first tarsomere without enlarged dorsoapical seta; ventral surface with two longitudinal rows of simple (non-cucullate) thin setae; pecten with 4 platellae flanked by tapered lateral setae; second tarsomere pecten with 2 platellae flanked by tapered lateral setae.</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Head and thorax (
Figs 1–3
) brownish-yellow. Face (
Fig. 3
) with crown-face transition black. Mesonotum (
Fig. 1
) dark brown; scutellum brownish-yellow with lateral margins light-yellow. Forewing (
Figs 1–2
) with black setae. Legs (
Figs 2–3
) hind tibia with cucullate bases of macrosetae black.
</p>
      <p>
TERMINALIA. Sternite VIII (
Fig. 4
) convex, moderately produced posterad, 1.2 times wider than long, shorter than sternites VII and VI combined; ventral surface with many small setae; lateral angles
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–12.
<tp:taxon-name>
Comanopa mananciensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (DZUP 215440). 
1
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
2
. Habitus, lateral view. 
3
. Head, ventral view. 
4
. Sternite VIII, ventral view. 
5
. Genital capsule, lateral view. 
6
. Pygofer, valve and subgenital plate, lateral view. 
7
. Pygofer, valve and subgenital plate (left subgenital plate removed), ventral view. 
8
. Subgenital plate, ventral view. 
9
. Connective and style, dorsal view. 
10
. Style, lateral view. 
11
. Aedeagus, lateral view. 
12
. Aedeagus, anterior view. Scale bars in mm.
</p>
      <p>
rounded; posterior margin straight. Valve (
Figs 5–7
) broadly fused laterally to pygofer; ventral margin excavated laterad of small median lobe. Pygofer (
Figs 5–7
) with pair of processes arising near base of plates, short and rounded apically, ventral surface with short setae. In lateral view, pygofer (
Fig. 6
) higher on apical half; dorsal margin widely notched on basal ⅔; dorsoposterior margin fused to pygofer lobes; ventral margin strongly produced ventrad, with short setae forming two longitudinal lines, internal process fused to pygofer lobe, arising near apex and bordering ventral margin, forming a small dentiform protrusion near apex of subgenital plate; lateral surface with longitudinal carina on basal ⅔; apex very wide and truncated; few macrosetae dispersed near apex. Anal tube (
Fig. 5
) membranous, without processes. Subgenital plate (
Figs 5–8
) short, not overlapping pygofer laterally, produced posteriorly as far as half length of pygofer; ventral surface without setae; anterior portion elongated and curved dorsally; apical portion expanded and ovate; apex rounded. Connective (
Fig. 9
), thin, slightly arched bar. Style (
Figs 9–10
), short, not surpassing apex of subgenital plates; apex curved ventrad in lateral view; apex subacute, slightly curved outward in dorsal view. In lateral view, aedeagus (
Fig. 11
) with preatrium moderately developed, produced anterad; dorsal apodeme developed, anterior margin forming pair of flattened divergent arms truncated apically, directed dorsally, posterior margin produced ventrally; shaft directed ventrally, slightly curved posterad and tapered apically. In anterior view, aedeagus (
Fig. 12
) with shaft deeply split apically, whit pair of subapical processes long, directed laterally; gonopore subapical.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
         <p>
Remarks
</p>
         <p>
The known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Comanopa
</tp:taxon-name>
have subgenital plates and styles very similar to each other, but can be separated by the shape of pygofer and aedeagus. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Comanopa mananciensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be easily recognized by the pygofer (
Fig. 6
) with ventral margin strongly produced ventrad and the aedeagus (
Fig. 12
) deeply split apically, with pair of long subapical processes, directed laterally.
</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Comanopa mananciensis Domahovski 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4716201</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/039779241878FFADA0CCFB3FFA9A38A1</uri>
               <article-title>Two new species of Hyalojassini (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae: Iassinae) to the genera Comanopa Blocker and Gehundra Blocker, description of the male of G. sordida (Baker) and key to species</article-title>
               <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/c82e9877-eab4-41b1-a73a-0687c94d9472</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:nomenclature/>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
1. In posterior view, aedeagus without subapical processes ................................................................. 2
</p>
            <p>

– In posterior view, aedeagus with subapical processes (
Fig. 12
) ....................................................... 3

</p>
            <p>

2. Pygofer with processes poorly developed, not exceeding the ventral margin (
Blocker 1982: 646
, fig. 28). In posterior view, aedeagus not split apically ........... 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. hamiltoni
Blocker, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Jamaica
)

</p>
            <p>

– Pygofer with processes developed, exceeding the ventral margin (
Blocker 1979: 37
, fig. 77). In posterior view, aedeagus split apically ................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. puertoricensis
(Caldwell, 1952)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Puerto Rico
)

</p>
            <p>

3. In posterior view, aedeagus with subapical processes very short, triangular-shaped (
Blocker 1979: 37
, fig. 79) .................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. adelpha
Blocker, 1979
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Panama
)

</p>
            <p>

– In posterior view, aedeagus with subapical processes long, directed laterally (
Fig. 12
) .................... ....................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. mananciensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(
Brazil
)

</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Comanopa mananciensis Domahovski 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4716201</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/039779241878FFADA0CCFB3FFA9A38A1</uri>
         <article-title>Two new species of Hyalojassini (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae: Iassinae) to the genera Comanopa Blocker and Gehundra Blocker, description of the male of G. sordida (Baker) and key to species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/c82e9877-eab4-41b1-a73a-0687c94d9472</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>
1. In posterior view, aedeagus without subapical processes ................................................................. 2
</p>
      <p>

– In posterior view, aedeagus with subapical processes (
Fig. 12
) ....................................................... 3

</p>
      <p>

2. Pygofer with processes poorly developed, not exceeding the ventral margin (
Blocker 1982: 646
, fig. 28). In posterior view, aedeagus not split apically ........... 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. hamiltoni
Blocker, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Jamaica
)

</p>
      <p>

– Pygofer with processes developed, exceeding the ventral margin (
Blocker 1979: 37
, fig. 77). In posterior view, aedeagus split apically ................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. puertoricensis
(Caldwell, 1952)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Puerto Rico
)

</p>
      <p>

3. In posterior view, aedeagus with subapical processes very short, triangular-shaped (
Blocker 1979: 37
, fig. 79) .................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. adelpha
Blocker, 1979
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Panama
)

</p>
      <p>

– In posterior view, aedeagus with subapical processes long, directed laterally (
Fig. 12
) .................... ....................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. mananciensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(
Brazil
)

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
