<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Gibbosaverruca weijiai Gan &amp; Zhang &amp; Wang 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4621387</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03A1291FC512FF891600FD8551938577</uri>
         <article-title>Gibbosaverruca weijiai, a new verrucid (Crustacea, Thoracica) species from the Weijia Guyot deep-sea seamount in the West Pacific</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1273</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Gibbosaverruca weijiai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
C0F9728C-1D03-4E52-BBE4-053C9586095D
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–4
; 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>All plates with prominent growth lines. External surface of rostrum with four ridges, uppermost largest, upper margin of rostrum sloping down to base of movable scutum, faint ridge between them. Movable tergum with three articular ridges, axial ridge strongly prominent, intermediate ridge widest. Movable scutum with three articular ridges, axial ridge thin, second ridge prominent, wider than axial ridge. Cirrus I and cirrus II with anterior rami no more than half length of posterior rami. Intermediate segments of cirrus VI with three pairs of setae on anterior margin. Caudal appendage very long, more than five times as long as protopodite.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Gibbosaverruca weijiai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, SRSIO17090313. 
A
. Opercular plates. 
B
. Fixed tergum and scutum. 
C
. From above. 
D
. Fixed tergum. 
E
. Fixed scutum. 
F
. Movable tergum. 
G
. Movable scutum.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The new species is named after its 
type
locality, Weijia Guyot, the West Pacific.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
WEST PACIFIC
• measurements BD = 
10.29 mm
; 
roof deck of Weijia Guyot
; 
156°41′15.72″ E
, 
12°47′22.20″ N
; depth 

1935 m

; 

21 Sep. 2017

; crews of ROV 

Haima

leg.; Stn MCROV06; Dayang 41B cruise; attached to sponge remains; GenBank: 
MW033972
(COI), 
MW033931
(16S rRNA); 
SRSIO17090313
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
WEST PACIFIC
• 
6 specimens
, measurements BD = 
7.82–10.36 mm
; same collection data as for holotype; 
attached to sponge remains
; 
SRSIO17090314
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 specimens
, measurements BD = 
8.05– 9.12 mm
; 
roof deck of Weijia Guyot
; 
156°17′13.56″ E
, 
12°22′37.92″ N
; depth 

1995 m

; 

22 Sep. 2017

; crews of ROV 

Haima

leg.; Stn MCROV02; Dayang 41B cruise; 
attached to sponge remains
; 
SRSIO17090314
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Gibbosaverruca weijiai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, SRSIO17090313. 
A
. Inner edge of labrum. 
B
. Palp. 
C
. Mandible. 
D
. Maxillule. 
E
. Maxilla.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Large-sized verrucid species. Shell white, growth lines prominent on all plates. Apices of rostrum and carina projecting well beyond margins of fixed tergum and fixed scutum (
Fig. 1A–C
). Rostrum and carina interlocking by four articular ridges (
Fig. 1A
), with narrow grooves between them on rostrocarinal articulation. Rostrum lower but longer than carina; anterior surface with four ridges, uppermost largest, as wide as following three ridges combined, lowest ridge faint; upper margin of rostrum sloping down to base of movable scutum, faint ridge between them terminating at end of axial ridge of carina. Carina with four articular ridges, first two similar in width, larger than following two; lowest ridge feebly developed.
</p>
      <p>
Fixed tergum (
Fig. 1B, D
) higher than fixed scutum, axial ridge prominent, narrow, both sides with welldeveloped alar-like projections; apex flexed towards fixed scutum. Axial ridge of fixed scutum (
Fig. 1B, E
) wide, about three times width of fixed tergum; alar-like process directed toward rostrum, wide, about two times width of radius-like process, directed toward fixed tergum; apex straight.
</p>
      <p>
Movable tergum (
Fig. 1A, F
) quadrangular, with three articular ridges; axial ridge prominent, narrow groove between it and intermediate ridge; intermediate ridge very wide, triangular, about three times width of axial ridge; broad groove between intermediate ridge and upper ridge; upper ridge thin, submarginal; internal surface smooth. Movable scutum (
Fig. 1A, G
) triangular, smaller than movable tergum; three articular ridges, axial ridge narrow, low, intermediate ridge largest, prominent, upper ridge short, sub-marginal; area between intermediate ridge and upper ridge smooth, without growth line; internal surface smooth.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Gibbosaverruca weijiai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, SRSIO17090313. 
A
. Soft body. 
B
. Cirrus I. 
C
. Cirrus II. 
D
. Cirrus III. 
E
. Cirrus IV. 
F
. Cirrus V. 
G
. Cirrus VI. 
H
. Penis. 
I
. Eggs.
</p>
      <p>
Labrum (
Fig. 2A
) with line of bifid or trifid teeth. Palp (
Fig. 2B
) narrow, with simple setae on terminal and inner margin. Mandible (
Fig. 2C
) with three teeth, first larger than following two; inferior angle acute, superior border armed with series of spinules. Cutting edge of maxillule (
Fig. 2D
) inflected; upper angle with large spine and some cuspidate setae; lower region projecting, furnished with cuspidate setae. Anterior margin of maxilla (
Fig. 2E
) with small notch, upper and anterior margins covered by long setae.
</p>
      <p>
Soft body (
Fig. 3
) without filamentary appendage. Cirrus I separated from, and shorter, sturdier than cirri II–VI (
Fig. 3B
), coxopodite inflated; anterior ramus slightly shorter than half length of posterior ramus; both rami with wide basal segments tapering distally. Cirrus II (
Fig. 3C
) with anterior ramus slightly shorter than half length of posterior ramus. Cirri III–VI (
Fig. 3D–G
) with rami subequal; intermediate segments of cirrus VI with two pairs of long setae and one pair of short setae on anterior margin. Caudal appendage (Fig. G) very long, more than five times length of protopodite, with more than 50 segments. Number of segments of cirri I–VI and caudal appendage are presented in 
Table 1
. Penis (
Fig. 3H
) robust, tapering, surface with annular wrinkles. Eggs (
Fig. 3I
) globular, encompassed by transparent film capsule.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
In situ figures of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gibbosaverruca weijiai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(red arrows).
</p>
      <p>
Table 1.
Number of segments on cirri I–VI and caudal appendage of the holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gibbosaverruca weijiai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
I
II
Cirri III IV
V
VI
Caudal appendage
left
18/29
12/32
27/31
36/40
41/45
48/49
51
right
18/30
13/31
29/32
35/38
43/45
47/50
50
</p>
      <p>
Habitat and distribution
</p>
      <p>
Roof deck of Weijia Guyot, depth 
1935–1995 m
, attached to sponge remains (
Fig. 4
). Currently only known from the 
type
locality, Weijia Guyot.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
