<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Helioandesia tarregai Vargas 2021,
                        gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4452611</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03A587BDBB265E61617763DB9EA060CD</uri>
                  <article-title>Systematics of Helioandesia tarregai gen. et sp. nov. (Lepidoptera:
                        Yponomeutoidea: Heliodinidae) from the Andes of Northern
                        Chile</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 935E51EF-4505-454E-98DA-1FA3156E7ED7 </p>
            <p> Figs 3–6 , Table 1 – 2 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>As for genus.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 7. Habitat and host plant of <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia tarregai </tp:taxon-name>
            gen. et sp. nov. A . The type locality near Zapahuira Village at about 3400 m elevation
            on the western slopes of the Andes of the Parinacota Province, northern Chile. B . The
            host plant <tp:taxon-name> Mirabilis acuta (Reiche) Heimerl </tp:taxon-name> (
                  <tp:taxon-name>Nyctaginaceae</tp:taxon-name> ). C . Detail of the damage pattern
            on a leaf of the host. D . Flower of <tp:taxon-name> M. acuta </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. is named
                  in memory of the eminent Spanish guitarist and composer Francisco Tárrega, for his
                  huge contribution to the repertory of the classical guitar, especially for the
                  wonderful ʻMarietaʼ. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Holotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> CHILE • ♂; Parinacota Province , Zapahuira ; 18°19′45″ S ,
                        69°34′56″ W ; 3400 m a.s.l. ; emerged Apr. 2019 ; H.A. Vargas leg.;
                        ex-larva, <tp:taxon-name> Mirabilis acuta (Reiche) Heimerl </tp:taxon-name>
                        ; coll. Mar. 2019 ; “ Holotype / <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia
                        </tp:taxon-name> / <tp:taxon-name> tarregai </tp:taxon-name> / Vargas” [red
                        handwritten label]; genitalia slide HAV-1379; IDEA-LEPI-2020-015 .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> CHILE • 3 ♂♂ , 2 ♀♀ ; same collection data as for holotype;
                        IDEA-LEPI-2020-016 to IDEA- LEPI-2020-020 ; genitalia slide HAV-1374 female
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 2 ♂♂ , 2 ♀♀ ; Parinacota Province
                        , Zapahuira ; 18°19′45″ S ; 69°34′56″ W ; 3400 m a.s.l. ; emerged May 2018 ;
                        H.A. Vargas leg.; ex-larva <tp:taxon-name> Mirabilis acuta (Reiche) Heimerl
                        </tp:taxon-name> ; coll. Apr. 2018 ; IDEA-LEPI-2020-021 to
                        IDEA-LEPI-2020-024 ; genitalia slides HAV-1371 male, HAV-1372 female,
                        HAV-1373 male; IDEA </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> Forewing length 5.5–6.1 mm . ( Fig. 3 A–E). </p>
            <p>HEAD. Vertex and frons silvery metallic. Pale orange yellow scales behind compound
                  eyes. Antenna with alternate rings of creamy white and brownish gray on basal two
                  third, distal third brownish gray. Labial palpus creamy white on two basal
                  segments; brownish gray scales with creamy white margin on third segment.</p>
            <p> Fig. 8. Geographic distribution of three Neotropical
                        <tp:taxon-name>Heliodinidae</tp:taxon-name> . Red rectangle on left
                  indicates the location in South America of the area enlarged on right. Circle =
                  type locality of <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et
                  sp. nov. in northern Chile. Triangles = distribution of <tp:taxon-name> Aetole
                        demarcha ( Meyrick, 1917 ) </tp:taxon-name> , the geographically nearest
                  heliodinid species to <tp:taxon-name> H. tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp.
                  nov. on the western slopes of the Andes, in Peru. Square = type locality of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Lithariapteryx loriculata (Meyrick, 1932) </tp:taxon-name>
                  on the eastern slopes of the Andes of Bolivia, the morphologically nearest species
                  to <tp:taxon-name> H. tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </p>
            <p>THORAX. Variable proportion of silvery metallic and brownish gray with creamy white
                  margin scales dorsally, brownish gray scales with wider creamy white margin
                  latero-ventrally. Legs mainly concolorous with latero-ventral side of thorax.
                  Forewing mostly covered by brownish gray with creamy white margin scales; five
                  metallic silvery bulging spots with black proximal margin, three near costal
                  margin, size progressively decreasing from base to apex, two near anal margin;
                  small metallic silvery spot near tegula, slightly differentiated metallic silvery
                  diagonal stripe from about middle of distal margin of discal cell to near costal
                  margin; a few brownish orange scattered scales mainly on distal half; fringe
                  brownish gray. Hindwing brownish gray; fringe concolorous.</p>
            <p>ABDOMEN. Mainly brownish gray dorsally, lighter near posterior margin of each
                  segment; scales brownish gray with creamy white margin ventrally.</p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Fig. 5 ). As described for genus. </p>
            <p> Female Similar to male. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Fig. 6 ). As described for genus. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Host plant </p>
            <p> The only known host plant is the native <tp:taxon-name> Mirabilis acuta
                  </tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>Nyctaginaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) ( Fig. 7 ), a
                  Chilean endemic ( Rodríguez et al. 2018 ). In the study zone <tp:taxon-name> M.
                        acuta </tp:taxon-name> sprout and flower after the summer rains. The larvae
                  of <tp:taxon-name> H. tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. feed externally
                  as leaf skeletonizers, remaining partially covered by a fine silk layer ( Fig. 7C
                  ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Known only from the type locality ( Fig. 8 ), near Zapahuira, Parinacota Province,
                  at about 3400 m elevation on the western slopes of the Andes of northern Chile .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
