<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Helioandesia Vargas 2021, gen.
                        nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4452221</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03A587BDBB2B5E6761DD61369F876559</uri>
                  <article-title>Systematics of Helioandesia tarregai gen. et sp. nov. (Lepidoptera:
                        Yponomeutoidea: Heliodinidae) from the Andes of Northern
                        Chile</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 2ACDF84E-8E2D-43C6-90D5-B271DC332483 </p>
            <p> Figs 3–6 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p> Type species </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. ,
                  designated here. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. can be recognized by the
                  following combination of morphological characters: (1) presence of CuP on forewing
                  of female and male; (2) two bristles of unequal length in the female frenulum; (3)
                  forewing mostly gray, ornamented with strongly bulging metallic spots, (4) two
                  triangular processes on anterior margin of tergum VIII in the male abdomen; (5)
                  sclerotization of the widened proximal part of the ductus bursae not reaching the
                  ostium; (6) signum with proximal portion coarser than distal portion; (7) presence
                  of an appendix bursae; (8) slightly swollen distal end of the saccus; and (9) a
                  well-developed cornutus on the vesica. The mostly gray forewing pattern of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. , ornamented with
                  strongly bulging metallic spots, resembles that of the mainly Nearctic
                        <tp:taxon-name> Lithariapteryx </tp:taxon-name> . However, the latter lacks
                  CuP in the forewing of female and male, has a single bristle in the female
                  frenulum, and lacks a well-developed cornutus on the vesica. The female genitalia
                  of <tp:taxon-name> H. tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. are very similar
                  to those of the Bolivian <tp:taxon-name> Lithariapteryx loriculata (Meyrick, 1932)
                  </tp:taxon-name> in the shape of the transverse bridge, signum and antrum.
                  However, <tp:taxon-name> H. tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. lacks a
                  V-shaped mark from costa on the forewing, has a sclerotization on the distal part
                  of the ductus bursae and has the signum on the left margin of the corpus bursae,
                  while <tp:taxon-name> L. loriculata </tp:taxon-name> has a V-shaped mark from the
                  costa on the forewing, lacks sclerotization on the distal part of the ductus
                  bursae and has the signum on the middle of the ventral part of the corpus bursae.
                  The male of <tp:taxon-name> L. loriculata </tp:taxon-name> remains unknown,
                  impeding comparison with <tp:taxon-name> H. tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp.
                  nov. Two bristles of unequal length in the female frenulum of <tp:taxon-name>
                        Helioandesia </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. resemble those of <tp:taxon-name>
                        Epicroesa Meyrick, 1907 </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Heliodines
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Lamprolophus Busck, 1900 </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> Philocoristis Meyrick, 1927 </tp:taxon-name> . However, all
                  these genera lack CuP in the forewing. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The genus name is derived from the Greek ʻ helios ʼ (sun), the root of the family
                  name <tp:taxon-name>Heliodinidae</tp:taxon-name> , and Andes, in reference to the
                  Andes Range, among whose amazing landscapes the type species of <tp:taxon-name>
                        Helioandesia </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. was discovered. The name is
                  considered feminine in gender. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> HEAD. Frons and vertex with appressed scales; narrow, elongated scales behind
                  compound eyes. Antenna filiform, about 0.7 times as long as forewing, basal five
                  segments of flagellum slightly broadened ( Fig. 3C ) due to narrow superimposed
                  scales on dorsal side. Labial palpus ( Fig. 3B ) porrect, with appressed scales. </p>
            <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name> Helioandesia tarregai </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. , ♂,
                  holotype (IDEA-LEPI-2020-015). A . Dorsal view. B . Head, lateral. C . Basal
                  flagellomeres of right antenna. D . Three bulging metallic spots on the basal half
                  of forewing. E . Hair pencil from base of subcosta, ventral. Scale bar: 1 mm. </p>
            <p> THORAX. Covered with appressed scales. Tibial spurs 0-2-4; metatibia with inner spur
                  of proximal pair about twice as long as outer one. Forewing lanceolate ( Fig. 4 ),
                  with strongly bulging metallic spots ( Fig. 3A, D ); hair pencil ( Fig. 3E ) from
                  base of subcosta ventrally; 12 veins; five R, all separate; M1 and M2 separate;
                  CuA1 and CuA2 separate, proximal part of latter lost; CuP present as tubular vein
                  near margin; 1A+2A present. Hindwing ( Fig. 4 ) lanceolate, six veins; Sc+R1 and
                  Rs separate; M1 and M2 stalked; CuA1 and CuA2 stalked; frenulum a single bristle. </p>
            <p> ABDOMEN. Tergum VIII ( Fig. 5C ) triangular; anterior margin slightly concave,
                  antero-lateral vertices as small processes slightly extending anteriorly beneath
                  tergum VII; lateral margin widely convex; posterior margin about ¼ of anterior
                  margin, with wide rounded notch in middle. Pleural lobe ( Fig. 5C ) triangular,
                  with slightly sclerotized stripe near posterior margin. Sternum VIII not
                  differentiated. Coremata ( Fig. 5G ) between pleural lobes and genitalia. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Fig. 5 ). Tegumen posteriorly expanded, somewhat conical, narrowing
                  posteriorly. Gnathos absent. Socius ( Fig. 5D ) narrow, conical, with hair-like
                  setae, apex coincides with that of tegumen. Saccus narrow, rod-shaped, about twice
                  as long as tegumen, slightly broadened near base, distal end slightly swollen.
                  Valva simple, with a few hair-like setae, costal margin broadly concave, ventral
                  margin broadly convex, apex rounded. Phallus cylindrical, elongated, slightly
                  longer than tegumen + saccus, slightly curved ventrally; vesica with prominent,
                  long spine-like cornutus ( Fig. 5B, F ) slightly smaller than half of phallus, and
                  group of small spine-like cornuti ( Fig. 5E ); insertion of ductus ejaculatorius
                  near basal third of phallus. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> Mainly similar to male, but hindwing with two asymmetrical bristles on frenulum (
                  Fig. 4 ), and abdominal segment VIII not modified as in male. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Fig. 6 ). Papillae anales ( Fig. 6B ) narrow, elongated, slightly
                  sclerotized, with hair-like setae. Posterior apophysis rod-like, about twice as
                  long as papillae anales. Anterior apophysis rod-like, slightly shorter than
                  posterior apophysis. Transverse bridge as rectangular transversal band, anterior
                  vertices fused with posterior end of anterior apophyses. Ostium bursae membranous.
                  Ductus bursae narrow, mainly membranous; proximal fourth widened, with distal half
                  sclerotized; slightly widened and sclerotized near corpus bursae. Ductus seminalis
                  arises on distal fourth of ductus bursae. Corpus bursae mainly membranous,
                  lenticular; signum on left side, narrow, elongated, minutely sculptured, proximal
                  ( Fig. 6C ) portion coarser than distal ( Fig. 6D ) portion, slightly invaginate
                  and broadened subapically, length about ¾ that of corpus bursae. Appendix bursae
                  spherical, membranous, on the middle of corpus bursae, on the opposite side of
                  signum. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
