<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Platevindex latus Goulding &amp; Bourke &amp; Comendador &amp; Khalil &amp; Quang &amp; Tan &amp; Tan &amp; Dayrat 2021</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4602485</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F0B202804EFF284D7AA1B5229DB8367C</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of Platevindex Baker, 1938 (Gastropoda: Euthyneura: Onchidiidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.737.1259</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
(
Plate, 1893
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 70–73
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
Plate, 1893: 191–192
</tp:taxon-name>

, pl. 7, fig. 2, pl. 11, fig. 59.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Stantschinsky 1907: 395

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Dayrat 2009: 5

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
PAPUA NEW GUINEA
• 
lectotype
(27/ 
27 mm
); 
Neu-Britannien
[New Britain, Papua New Guinea]; 
ZMB/Moll 45656a
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paralectotypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
PAPUA NEW GUINEA
• 
3 paralectotypes
(28/27, 27/24 and 23/ 
26 mm
); same collection data as for lectotype; 
ZMB/Moll 45656b
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Notes on 
type
material

</p>
      <p>
The 
lectotype
was dissected for the present study and all its internal organs were left inside except for the penial complex, which was extracted and retained in a small vial. The three 
paralectotypes
were previously dissected and are completely empty with no internal organs. All their male parts are missing. Pieces of dorsal notum, stomach, digestive gland, intestine and female gland mass remain in the jar, all mixed together, but they cannot be assigned to a particular 
paralectotype
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
PAPUA NEW GUINEA
• 
3 specs
(33/28 [#3], 32/31 [#1] and 30/25 [#2] mm); 
New Britain
?; 
ZMH 27511
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Color and morphology
(
Fig. 70
) The color of live slugs is unknown. The preserved dorsal surface is dark brown, occasionally with lighter brown, longitudinal stripes. The preserved hyponotum is blue-grey and the foot is light yellow. Dorsal papillae are large and thorny, and do not bear dorsal eyes.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 70.
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
(
Plate, 1893
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, preserved specimens. 
A
. Dorsal view, 24 mm, syntype, New Britain, Papua New Guinea (ZMB/Moll 45656). 
B
. Ventral view, same as A. 
C
. Close-up of papillae, same as A. 
D
. Dorsal view, 25 mm, Papua New Guinea (ZMH 27511). 
E.
Ventral view, same as D.
</p>
      <p>
Digestive system
(
Figs 3B
, 
71–72
)
</p>
      <p>
Radulae measure up to 
7.2 mm
in length. Examples of radular formulae are presented in 
Table 5
. The intestinal loops are of 
type
III, with a transitional loop oriented between 12 and 2 o’clock (
Figs 3B
, 
72
).
</p>
      <p>
Reproductive system
(
Fig. 73
)
</p>
      <p>In the posterior reproductive system, the oviduct is short and approximately as wide as the deferent duct. Its distal section (distal to the spermatheca) is approximately as long as its proximal section. The deferent duct is longer than the oviduct, not attached to it, and is tightly coiled with a few short U-shaped loops. There are no hooks inside the distal, flexible region of the penis. The posterior retractor muscle inserts in the anterior half of the visceral cavity. The retractor muscle of the penis varies from approximately half the length of the penial sheath to ¾ its length. The deferent duct is highly convoluted.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 71.
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
(
Plate, 1893
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, radula, Papua New Guinea [#1] (ZMB/Moll 45656). 
A–C
. Rachidian and lateral teeth. 
D
. Lateral teeth. 
E
. Outermost lateral teeth. Scale bars: A, D = 100 μm; B, E = 20 μm; C = 50 μm.
</p>
      <p>
Distinctive diagnostic features
(
Table 4
)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. amboinae
</tp:taxon-name>
are the only known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
with no dorsal eyes and no penial hooks. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
</tp:taxon-name>
can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. amboinae
</tp:taxon-name>
externally by its large and thorny dorsal papillae and internally by its anterior deferent duct, which is slightly less convoluted.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
(
Fig. 10C
)
</p>
      <p>
Papua New Guinea
: 
New Britain
(
type
locality and present study).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 72.
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
(
Plate, 1893
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, digestive system, dorsal view, intestinal loops of type III. 
A
. Transitional loop oriented at 2 o’clock, New Britain, Papua New Guinea, lectotype (ZMB/Moll 45656a). 
B
. Transitional loop oriented at 12 o’clock, Papua New Guinea [#1] (ZMH 27511). 
C
. Transitional loop oriented at 2 o’clock, Papua New Guinea [#2] (ZMH 27511). Abbreviations: ddg = dorsal digestive gland; i = intestine; pdg = posterior digestive gland; rg = rectal gland; st = stomach. Scale bars = 3 mm.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 73.
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
(
Plate, 1893
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, reproductive system. 
A
. Posterior reproductive system, Papua New Guinea [#2] (ZMH 27511). 
B
.Anterior, male copulatory apparatus, New Britain, Papua New Guinea, lectotype (ZMB/Moll 45656a). 
C
. Anterior, male copulatory apparatus, same as A. Abbreviations: dd = deferent duct; fgm = female gland mass; hd = hermaphroditic duct; hg = hermaphroditic gland; ov = oviduct; ps = penial sheath; rm = retractor muscle; rs = receptaculum seminis; sp = spermatheca; v = vestibule. Scale bars: A = 3 mm; B–C = 2 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Habitat
</p>
      <p>
No habitat was mentioned in the original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
or on the labels of the additional material. However, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
likely lives on dead logs in mangroves, like its close relative 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. amboinae
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The flattened body and narrow foot of the 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
</tp:taxon-name>
clearly indicate that it belongs to 

<tp:taxon-name>Platevindex</tp:taxon-name>
.

In the original description, 
Plate (1893)
did not mention whether a rectal gland is present or absent, but it is present in the 
lectotype
as well as in the non-type material (it is present in all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
). An accessory penial gland is also absent in both the 
lectotype
and the non-type material (it is absent in all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
      <p>
In the original description, 
Plate (1893: 191)
described dorsal “conical granules” and indicated that “the mantle appears through them as if spiked with small thorns.” Conical papillae are present in the 
lectotype
and all 
paralectotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
as well as in the additional material from 
Papua New Guinea
. 
Plate (1893: 192)
described the length of the penis but did not mention penial hooks, so it can be assumed that he did not see penial hooks in the types he dissected (now 
paralectotypes
). However, because the male parts are missing from the three 
paralectotypes
dissected by Plate, this could not be confirmed. At any rate, penial hooks are absent in the 
lectotype
dissected for the present study. The intestinal loops of the 
lectotype
are of type III and 
Plate’s (1893: 192)
description of a type II likely is a mistake, which would be consistent as he made the same error in the description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. amboinae
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Fresh material for DNA sequencing was not available. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
</tp:taxon-name>
was not collected during the recent MNHN expeditions in 
Madang
and 
New Ireland
, 
Papua New Guinea
. Some old material discovered at the Zoologisches Museum in Hamburg seems to be part of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
even though its locality is uncertain (the label in the jar states “ 
Papua New Guinea
. 
New Britain
? Museum Godeffroy”). This material is externally identical to the 
lectotype
(and 
paralectotypes
) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Plate (1893: 192)
described a penis measuring 
7 mm
long (the proximal chondroid tube being 
5 mm
long and the distal, flexible region being 
2 mm
long). In one specimen from the Zoologisches Museum in Hamburg, the chondroid tube also measured 
5 mm
, but the distal region without hooks was 
0.5 mm
long rather than 
2 mm
. However, individual variation in this character occurs within species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
, and more specimens are needed to evaluate the variation for this trait within 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Hoffmann (1928: 86)
suggested that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
</tp:taxon-name>
(as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
) was a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Onchidium granulosum
Lesson, 1831
</tp:taxon-name>
(
type
locality 
New Ireland
, 
Papua New Guinea
), based on the original descriptions. Although Hoffmann acknowledged that Lesson’s description was not very informative, he considered that Lesson’s description of a notum being much wider than the sole indicated that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Onchidium granulosum
</tp:taxon-name>
referred to a species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis
(
Platevindex
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Labbé (1934: 234)
agreed with Hoffmann. However, Lesson’s description is brief and leaves out many important details, such as whether dorsal eyes are present or not. The wide foot in Lesson’s illustration of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Onchidium granulosum
</tp:taxon-name>
(Lesson 1831: pl. 14, fig. 2) does not appear to represent a species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
. The description of the habitat as a rocky shore also strongly suggests that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Onchidium granulosum
</tp:taxon-name>
does not apply to a species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
, but, instead, possibly to a species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Peronia
</tp:taxon-name>
or 
<tp:taxon-name>
Wallaconchis
</tp:taxon-name>
. Adams &amp; Adams (1855: 234) transferred 
<tp:taxon-name>
Onchidium granulosum
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Onchidella
</tp:taxon-name>
with no justification. Because its 
type
material could not be located and its internal anatomy was not described by Lesson, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Onchidium granulosum
</tp:taxon-name>
is regarded here as a nomen dubium which applies to an onchidiid species of an unidentifiable genus.
</p>
      <p>
Von 
Martens (1897: 128)
indicated that M. Weber found 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
in “Celebs: M̹ndung des Flusses Djenemaedja in Luwu” [
Sulawesi
: mouth of the river Djenemaedja in Luwu]. Measurements were provided for the largest and smallest specimens, and the edge of the hyponotum was described as dirty yellow-gray. Von Martens indicated that the specimens are exactly the same as 
Plate’s (1893)
description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. lata
</tp:taxon-name>
, except for the color of edge of the hyponotum. However, when specimens from Luwu collected by M. Weber (identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
) were examined, they did not have the large thornlike papillae characteristic of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. lata
</tp:taxon-name>
. Thus, 
Sulawesi
is not considered part of the geographic range of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. lata
</tp:taxon-name>
, and those specimens are identified here as 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. amboinae
</tp:taxon-name>
(see that species).
</p>
      <p>
Bretnall’s (1919: 323)
description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
is merely a translation of Plate’s original description, except that 
Plate’s (1893: 191)
correct statement that “eyes are missing” was changed to “eyes are present on all of the papillae.” Bretnall likely assumed that Plate made a mistake because dorsal eyes are present in most other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
and because eyes can be difficult to see when dorsal papillae are retracted. However, it is confirmed here that dorsal eyes are not present in the 
type
material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Labbé (1934: 234)
identified two specimens (24/17 and 19/ 
14 mm
) from the Malabar coast (southwest 
India
) collected by M. Dussumier as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis granulosa
</tp:taxon-name>
, but also indicated that the exterior aspect of his specimens was similar to that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
New Britain
. However, Labbé also reported that the notum is granular with tubers that are not prominent, and that dorsal eyes are not very visible. The intestinal loops are also described as 
type
II by Labbé, while they are of 
type
III in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
. Due to the lack of dorsal papillae in the specimens Labbé examined, and the fact that Labbé’s description suggests that dorsal eyes may have simply been retracted, the specimens he examined are not considered to be 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
. It is also worth noting that the specimens Labbé examined from western 
India
are very distant from 
New Britain
, 
Papua New Guinea
, and that no observations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oncis lata
</tp:taxon-name>
have been confirmed west of 
New Britain
.
</p>
      <p>
Morphological evidence suggests that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex latus
</tp:taxon-name>
is closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. amboinae
</tp:taxon-name>
because both species lack penial hooks and dorsal eyes, which are present in all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
. They also are the only species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platevindex
</tp:taxon-name>
with intestinal loops of 
type
III.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
