<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Landouria trochomorphoides Nahok &amp; Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514735</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A63BE15E6B451DEA809A53AE84899737</uri>
         <article-title>Five new species of the land snail genus Landouria Godwin-Austen, 1918 (Gastropoda, Camaenidae) from northeastern Thailand, with note on genitalia and radula morphology of Landouria diplogramma (Möllendorff, 1902)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.767.1495</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Landouria trochomorphoides
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
B7DBFB2E-E7BF-46E5-AFB5-1B45CA4072DE
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3C
, 
4C
, 
5C
, 
6G–I
; 
Tables 1–4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Shell with rather low spire, sharply keeled, with radial scaly processes (
Fig. 4C
). Basal portion of flagellum thickened, tapering towards tip; penis narrow and cylindrical; base of gametolytic sac narrow. Radula, with lanceolate central and lateral teeth.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
trochomorphoides
</tp:taxon-name>
’ refers to the conchological similarity between the shell of the new species and that of the land snail genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trochomorpha
Albers, 1850
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Trochomorphidae Möllendorf, 1890</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
THAILAND
• 
shell
(SH = 10.0 mm, SW = 
21.3 mm
, AH = 
7.4 mm
, AW = 
9.1 mm
, UW = 
6.2 mm
); 
Loei Province
, 
Pha Khao District
, 
Pha Sawan Cave
; 
17°7′8.42″ N
, 
101°56′3.59″ E
; alt. 

359 m

; 

6 Oct. 2017

; 
B. Nahok
, 
S. Tumpeesuwan
and 
C. Tumpeesuwan
leg.; 
NHMSU-00027
. (
Fig. 3C
)
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
THAILAND
• 
17 shells
, 
9 living specs
; same collection data as for holotype; GenBank No. 
MN449403 and MZ435748
; 
NHMSU-00028
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
SHELL (
Fig. 3C
, 
Table 1
). Dextral, relatively large-sized. Whorls six, suture shallow, spire only slightly elevated. Protoconch with radially elongated scars. Body whorl sharply keeled, brownish-corneous with a brown zone at periphery, scaly processes all over shell surface (
Fig. 4C
). Umbilicus moderately deep and very wide. Aperture lip rhombic, peristome reflexed, and expanded.
</p>
      <p>
GENITAL SYSTEM (n = 3) (
Fig. 5C
, 
Table 4
). Penis slightly longer than vagina, slender cylindrical, internally with parallel, transverse robust folds; verge absent. Epiphallus slender cylindrical with thickened end. Flagellum as long as epiphallus, basal portion thick and progressively tapering towards tip, without nodes, inner surface smooth. Vas deferens is a thin cylindrical tube, entering epiphallus apically. Vagina thinner than penis, internally with parallel, transverse robust folds. Free oviduct very short. Gametolytic sac slightly narrower at base, with a long narrow cylindrical tube, and a small, oval sac at the distal end. Prostate gland and uterus very long.
</p>
      <p>
RADULA (n = 3). Comprises 107–111 transverse rows with 65–73 teeth per row; radular formula: (24– 26)-(8–10)-1-(8–10)-(24–26). Central tooth unicuspid triangular (
Fig. 6G
). Lateral teeth short and broad leaf-shaped, bicuspid, larger than central tooth, with small ectocone (
Fig. 6G–H
). Marginal teeth asymmetric, tricuspid with small endocone; mesocone large and long, with curved margins; ectocone triangular with two to four cusps (
Fig. 6H–I
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Landouria trochomorphoides
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
differs from other taxa by its very large, rather flat, sharply keeled shell with scaly surface (
Figs 3C
, 
4C
). Lateral teeth of radula are stout bicuspid (
Fig. 6G–I
), genital system is small and slim (
Fig. 5C
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Landouria trochomorphoides
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
