<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Orphnus medvedevi Frolov &amp;
                        Akhmetova 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514743</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03AEE5789D493E227730D02B714BFE3B</uri>
                  <article-title>Review of the Orphninae (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae) of Sri Lanka,
                        with description of a new species of genus Orphnus Macleay,
                        1819</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.767.1485</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Orphnus medvedevi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 3F99F2E5-0FD6-4CE9-A3AC-53A7FBA4241D </p>
            <p> Fig. 3 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Differential diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Orphnus medvedevi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is similar to
                        <tp:taxon-name> O. mysoriensis </tp:taxon-name> in having the pronotum with
                  more or less developed tubercle on base medially and endophallus with one group of
                  spinules. It differs from the latter in shorter body (4.6–6.0 mm, as opposed to
                  8.0–10.0 mm. in <tp:taxon-name> O. mysoriensis </tp:taxon-name> ), spinules of
                  endophallus as a compact cluster consisting of less than 10 spinules (as opposed
                  to a rather dispersed group of more than 10 spinules in <tp:taxon-name> O.
                        mysoriensis </tp:taxon-name> , Fig. 3G vs Fig. 1G ), and tubercle on the
                  base of pronotum always smooth (as opposed to having normally two punctures in
                        <tp:taxon-name> O. mysoriensis </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>The new species is named after Gleb Sergeevich Medvedev (1931–2009), a Russian
                  coleopterist.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype SRI LANKA • ♂ ; “ Shri Lanka Vilpattu [ Sri Lanka
                        , Wilpattu] 7.10.1982 G. Medvedev ”; ZIN . </tp:material-citation>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes SRI LANKA • 2 ♀♀ ; “ Shri Lanka Vilpattu [ Sri
                        Lanka , Wilpattu] 8.10.1982 G. Medvedev ”; ZIN </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ , 6 ♀♀ ; “ Sri Lanka . Nat. Park Wilpattu.
                        Talawila 9.X. 982. Medvedev”; ZIN </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 13 ♂♂ , 13 ♀♀ ; “ Sri Lanka , Wilpattu N.P. 17 km WNW
                        entrance Tala Wila , 8.X.1982 V.F. Zaitzev leg.”; ZIN
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male, holotype ( Fig. 3A, D–G ) </p>
            <p>BODY. Length 6.0 mm. Colour uniformly brown.</p>
            <p>CLYPEUS. Wide, with convex anterior margin, rounded laterally, finely crenulate.
                  Genae small, not protruding past eyes. Frontal suture indistinct. Clypeus with
                  long, slender horn directed upwards and slightly curved backwards apically. Dorsal
                  surface of head finely punctate. Labrum deeply sinuate in the middle, distinctly
                  protruding past clypeus.</p>
            <p>PRONOTUM. With rounded sides, about 1.5 times as wide as long, with deeply concave
                  disc, conical lateral processes aside excavation, and smooth, rounded tubercle
                  medially near base. Anterior angles acute; posterior angles rounded, indistinct in
                  dorsal view. Pronotum bordered on anterior margin and base. Lateral margins with
                  long, sparse, brown setae. Sides irregularly punctate with round punctures
                  separated by 3–5 puncture diameters.</p>
            <p> SCUTELLUM. Subtriangular, narrowly rounded apically, about 1/10 length of elytra. </p>
            <p>ELYTRA. About as long as wide, with distinct humeral humps, widest in middle, lateral
                  margins slightly rounded in basal half. First (sutural) stria distinct, as feebly
                  impressed groove with row of punctures. Other stria before humeral humps as rows
                  of round setiferous punctures, separated by more than 3 their diameters except for
                  base of elytra. Elytral intervals covered with minute punctures.</p>
            <p>WINGS. Macropterous.</p>
            <p>LEGS. Protibiae with 3 outer teeth. Lateral margin basad of outer teeth not
                  crenulate. Apical spur of protibia absent. Left protarsus absent. Middle and hind
                  legs similar in shape; metafemora and metatibiae about ⅛ as long as the mesofemora
                  and mesotibiae. Mesotibia and metatibiae somewhat triangular with 2 apical spurs,
                  inner margin almost straight, with 1 transverse keel. Upper spur of tibiae as long
                  as two basal tarsomeres. Claws ⅓ length of apical tarsomere. Femora almost
                  impunctate.</p>
            <p>ABDOMEN. Ventrally irregularly punctate, pubescent, with sparse, long setae.
                  Abdominal sternite 8 medially shorter than sternites 4–7 combined. Pygidium
                  invisible from above, with slightly truncate apex in caudal view. Plectrum
                  triangular with rounded apex, wider than long.</p>
            <p> AEDEAGUS. Parameres relatively short (0.5 length of phallobase), curved downwards,
                  tapering apically, spear-shaped in dorsal view, with feebly visible lateral teeth
                  ( Fig. 3D–E ). Endophallus with a compact cluster of 6 spinules ( Fig. 3G ). </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> Female ( Fig. 3H ) differs from the male in having a relatively smaller pronotum
                  without armature, frontoclypeus without process, and prothoracic spur present. </p>
            <p> Variation </p>
            <p> Body length of the paratypes varies from 5.9 to 4.6 mm (males) and 4.7 to 6.0 mm
                  (females). Some of the paratypes have darker elytra. Head and pronotum armature in
                  males paratypes varies from relatively well-developed, similar to that of the
                  holotype , to excavated pronotum with gibbosities beside the excavation and
                  frontoclypeal tubercle ( Fig. 3C ), with intermediate variants ( Fig. 3B ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name> Orphnus medvedevi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. A , D–G . Holotype, ♂
            (ZIN). B–C . Paratypes, ♂ (ZIN). H . Paratype, ♀ (ZIN). A–C , H . Habitus in dorsal
            view. D . Parameres in dorsal view. E . Aedeagus in lateral view. F . Labels. G .
            Endophallus. I . Distributional record map. Scale bars: A–C, H = 1.0 mm; D–E, G = 0.5
            mm. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> The species is known from one locality in north-western Sri Lanka ( Fig. 3I ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
