<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Takiyaella Gonçalves &amp; Domahovski 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5578460</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B087EA790DFFF8FDC3FDF70EB5FD00</uri>
         <article-title>A new genus and five new species of Neocoelidiinae leafhoppers from Brazil (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadellidae) with a key to males</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Takiyaella
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
6E1BFF39-D305-4E7C-982E-D315E686A299
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–13
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type-species
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Takiyaella daniela
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Medium-sized leafhoppers (
Fig. 12
). Head (
Figs 1A
, 
7A
, 
8A
) slightly produced anteriorly, with crown-face transition rounded, without carina; lateral margins of crown, adjacent to eyes, elevated and not carinated. Antennal ledge (
Fig. 1B
) narrow, slightly prominent and weakly carinated. Forewing (
Figs 1D
, 
7D
) with two or three dark maculae on claval commissure; crossvein ʻsʼ missing. Male pygofer (
Figs 3E
, 
8E
) approximately rectangular, ventral margin with sclerotized subapical serrated tooth; caudal margin usually with ventral rounded lobe. Subgenital plates (
Figs 1G
, 
8G
) fused to each other along the basal two-thirds; ventral surface with few apical macrosetae. Connective (
Figs 1H
, 
3H
) Y- or V-shaped. Aedeagus (
Figs 1J
, 
7J
, 
8J
) with one or two pairs of atrial processes, gonopore apical. Second valvula of ovipositor (
Figs 4G
, 
9G
) fused to each other just near base, dorsal margin with several irregular small teeth.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The generic name 
<tp:taxon-name>
Takiyaella
</tp:taxon-name>
(feminine noun) is a tribute to Prof. Dr Daniela Maeda Takiya in recognition of her remarkable contribution to our knowledge of the Brazilian 
<tp:taxon-name>Auchenorrhyncha</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
HEAD AND THORAX. Head, in dorsal view (
Figs 1A
, 
7A
), slightly produced anteriorly, median length of crown approximately equal or slightly less than interocular width; transocular width about 
4
/5 humeral width of pronotum; crown subrectangular, anterior margin rounded, surface flat, texture shagreen; ocellus medium-sized, on anterior margin of head, distant from eye margin, visible in dorsal view; coronal maculae distinct at basal half, between midline and eyes; coronal suture distinct in basal third, evanescent anteriorly. Head, in frontal view (
Figs 1B
, 
10B
), with face slightly higher than wide; frontogenal suture extending to antennal ledge but not reaching ocellus; antennal ledge narrow, slightly prominent, oblique and weakly carinated; frons approximately 1.8 × as long as wide; muscle impressions indistinct; epistomal suture distinct but incomplete, evanescent medially; clypeus 1.5 × as long as maximum width, lateral margins parallel, apex slightly emarginated; maxillary plate produced ventrally, reaching clypeus apex; lorum ellipse-shaped, apical margin not reaching apex of clypeus; gena incompletely covering episternum. Head, in lateral view (
Figs 1C
, 
3C
), with crown-face transition rounded, without carina; lateral margins of crown, adjacent to eyes, elevated and not carinated; antennal pits at same level as an imaginary line tangent to anteroventral angles of eyes; antenna with long flagellum, exceeding half-length of forewing; frons convex. Pronotum (
Figs 1A
, 
5A
) with inconspicuous transverse striae on disc; lateral margins rounded, convergent anterad, and slightly shorter than eye length; posterior margin roundly excavated; in lateral view (
Figs 1C
, 
8C
), slightly declivous; dorsopleural carina present and complete. Mesonotum (
Fig. 8A
) as long as wide. Forewing (
Figs 1D
, 
7D
) mostly semi-hyaline, except for apical cells and apex of anteapical cells hyaline, 3.5 × as long as maximum width; venation indistinct, except apically; two anteapical cells, crossvein sectorial ʻsʼ missing; four apical cells: first to third approximately rectangular, third enlarged apically, fourth rhomboid, base of second more proximal than base of third; appendix narrow; apex rounded. Hind wing with vein R 
4+5
and M 
1+2
preapically convergent, fused to each other at apex, forming single vein. Profemur with AD, AM, and PD rows reduced and poorly defined, with exception of apical setae AD 
1
, AM 
1
, and PD 
1
, respectively; AV and PV rows absent; IC row formed by slightly arched comb of fine setae, beginning at distal half of femur and extending to apex. Protibia, in cross-section, semi-circular; AV row formed by approximately 20 setae, slightly longer and thicker towards apex; AD and PD rows without differentiated setae; PV row with 2–3 widely spaced setae. Metafemur with setal formula 2:2:1, with inner setae of second pair reduced in size. Metatibial AD row with 2– 
4 intercalary
setae between macrosetae; PD, AD, and PV rows with 13– 15, 10–12, and 28–32 macrosetae, respectively; AV row with approximately 11 macrosetae distributed along most of tibia, except in the proximal and distal portions. Metatarsomere I longer than combined length of two distal tarsomeres; plantar surface with two rows of setae, external row with longer and robust setae than inner row; pecten with five platellae. Metatarsomere II pecten with three platellae.
</p>
      <p>
MALE TERMINALIA. Pygofer (
Figs 1E
, 
3E
, 
5E
) approximately rectangular, usually apically expanded with an apical ventral lobe; macrosetae absent; ventral margin little sclerotized medially, with a sclerotized and serrated tooth on apical portion. Valve (
Figs 1G
, 
8G
) without indication of separation with subgenital plates. Subgenital plate (
Figs 3G
, 
5G
) not exceeding pygofer apex; plates fused to each other along the basal two-thirds; ventral surface with few apical macrosetae; in lateral view (
Figs 1F
, 
7F
), deeply concave. Connective (
Figs 1H
, 
7H
) Y- or V-shaped, articulated to aedeagus base, not bifurcated at the point of articulation. Style (
Figs 1I
, 
8I
) with apodeme expanded; ventral margin with median lobe; preapical setae present; preapical lobe moderately developed, slightly produced posterad; apex curved ventrally, hook-shaped. Aedeagus (
Figs 1J–K
, 
5J–K
) with preatrium long and robust; atrium with one or two pairs of processes; shaft curved dorsoanteriorly, usually expanded at apex; gonopore apical. Anal tube (
Figs 3M
, 
5L
, 
8E
) cylindrical, usually with small basiventral process with denticles.
</p>
      <p>
FEMALE TERMINALIA. Sternite VII (
Figs 2C
, 
4C
, 
6C
, 
9C
, 
11A
) subquadrangular; posterior margin widely rounded. ʻInternalʼ sternite VIII membranous. Pygofer (
Figs 2D
, 
4D
, 
6D
, 
9D
, 
11B
) elongate, 1.7 × as long as maximum height; macrosetae distributed near apex and ventral margin. First valvifer (
Figs 2E
, 
4E
, 
6E
, 
9E
, 
11C
) higher than long, dorsal margin straight, posterior margin slightly oblique. First valvula of ovipositor (
Figs 2E
, 
4E
, 
6E
, 
9E
, 
11C
) elongated, moderately curved dorsally; dorsal sculptured area submarginal, present throughout apical half; apex (
Figs 2F
, 
4F
, 
6F
, 
9F
, 
11D
) acute. Second valvifer (
Figs 2I
, 
4I
, 
6I
, 
9I
, 
11G
) higher than long. Second valvula of ovipositor (
Figs 2G
, 
4G
, 
6G
, 
9G
, 
11E
) elongated, moderately curved dorsally in the apical half, fused to each other just near base; apical portion (
Figs 2H
, 
4H
, 
6H
, 
9H
, 
11F
) slightly expanded, dorsal margin with several irregular small teeth. Gonoplac (
Figs 2I
, 
4I
, 
6I
, 
9I
, 
11G
) expanded on apical half; external surface along ventral margin and apex with dentiform cuticular projections and few short and robust setae; apex (
Figs 2J
, 
4J
, 
6J
, 
9J
, 
11H
) rounded or acutely rounded.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
(states of 
Minas Gerais
, 
Paraná
and 
Rio de Janeiro
). Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Takiyaella
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
occur in southern and southeastern 
Brazil
, in the Atlantic Rainforest biome (
Fig. 13
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Takiyaella
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
shares some similarities with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paraphysiana
Chiamolera, Cavichioli &amp; Anderle, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
as follows: (1) crown with anterior margin rounded; (2) crown-face transition without carina; (3) frontogenal suture not reaching ocellus; (4) antennal ledge narrow and slightly prominent; (5) pronotum with posterior margin roundly excavated; and (6) forewing with dark maculae along the anal margin.
</p>
      <p>
However, the new genus can be easily separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paraphysiana
</tp:taxon-name>
due to hind wing with veins R 
4+5
and M 
1+2
preapically convergent, fused at apex, forming single vein, whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paraphysiana
</tp:taxon-name>
R 
4+5
and M 
1+2
are convergent, fused to each other, but they are divergent apically; pygofer without inner ventral processes (present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paraphysiana
</tp:taxon-name>
); subgenital plates without dorsal tooth (present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paraphysiana
</tp:taxon-name>
); style with preapical lobe moderately developed, whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paraphysiana
</tp:taxon-name>
it is strongly developed and produced caudally; paraphysis absent (present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paraphysiana
</tp:taxon-name>
); and the aedeagus with atrial processes (absent in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paraphysiana
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
