<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Onychelmis splendida Linský &amp;
                        Čiamporová-Zaťovičová &amp; Čiampor 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4602503</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B187D7E82BFFC3FDC6FEF7FAFEF8BC</uri>
                  <article-title>A revision of Onychelmis Hinton, 1941 (Coleoptera: Elmidae), with
                        description of new species, DNA barcoding and notes on the geography of the
                        genus</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1263</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis splendida </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 56128631-3C7F-4D7E-941E-DDA1DC318912 </p>
            <p> Figs 3D , 5B , 6G , 9 C–D, 11B, 11F, 12A–B </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Differential diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis splendida </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. can be
                  distinguished from all species of the genus by the combination of the following
                  characters: 1) moderate size (CL: 1.37–1.40 mm ); 2) pro- and mesofemora with
                  tomentum reaching to around middle in males, and behind middle in females ( Fig.
                  6G ); 3) humeri produced; 4) prominent carina on sixth interval absent; 5) elytral
                  punctures absent; 6) shape of aedeagus lanceolate ( Fig. 9 C–D). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The specific epithet <tp:taxon-name> splendida </tp:taxon-name> is from the Latin ʻ
                  splendidus ʼ (ʻshinyʼ) referring to the glabrous, shiny elytra. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype ECUADOR • ♂ “Ecuador, Napo prov. , road to Coca ,
                        Sumaco env., 00°43′29.0″ S , 77°46′01.4″ W , 1109 m a.s.l. , 17. 8. 2013 ,
                        confluence of two larger streams, with gravel, stones, boulders, Čiampor
                        &amp; Čiamporová-Zaťovičová lgt. ”; PUCE . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Fig. 5. Venter and metaventrites of male <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis </tp:taxon-name>
                  spp. A , C . <tp:taxon-name> O. lenkae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , paratype, ♂
                  (PUCE). B . <tp:taxon-name> O. splendida </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , paratype, ♂
                  (PUCE). Arrows show setal tufts. Scale bars: A = 0.5 mm; B–C = 0.3 mm. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes ECUADOR • 3 ♂♂ , 3 ♀♀ ; same collection data as
                        for holotype; PUCE / CCB </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1
                        ♂ ; “Ecuador, Napo prov. , road to Coca , Sumaco env., 00°42′25.7″ S ,
                        77°43′10.0″ W , 1138 m a.s.l. , 17. 8. 2013 , stream ca. 2–3 m wide, fast
                        flowing, with boulders, stones, gravel, submerged wood, Čiampor &amp;
                        Čiamporová- Zaťovičová lgt. ”; PUCE / CCB </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ , 3 ♀♀ ; “Ecuador, Napo prov. , road to Coca ,
                        00°43′39.6″ S , 77°45′56.1″ W , 1129 m a.s.l. , 17. 8. 2013 , small
                        waterfall, Čiampor &amp; Čiamporová-Zaťovičová lgt. ”; PUCE / CCB
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> ECUADOR • 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for holotype; CCB
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> BODY ( Fig. 3D ). Obovate, black dorsally, brown ventrally; length 1.37–1.40 mm ;
                  width 0.64–0.68 mm ; dorsum convex, glabrous with sparse, light yellowish-brown
                  setae. Hairy or scale-like tomentum distributed on following areas: genae, sides
                  of prosternum, mesoventrite, metaventrite and abdomen, epipleura, and medial and
                  lateral portions on bases of femora. </p>
            <p>COLOUR. Head, pronotum and elytra black; venter dark brown to black with reddish
                  tinge; coxae, femora and tarsi dark brown with reddish tinge; trochanters and
                  tibiae brown; basal segments of antennae and tarsal claws pale brown.</p>
            <p> HEAD. Partly retractable into prothoraX, dorsally shiny. Antennae filiform,
                  11-segmented; pedicel about twice as long as scape; remaining segments about 4
                  times as long as scape and pedicel combined; segments 3–10 subrectangular,
                  subequal in length; terminal segment longest, suboval, with pointed apex. Labrum
                  with anterior margin very slightly emarginate medially; anterolateral angles
                  broadly arcuate with numerous golden, recumbent hair-like setae; clypeus shorter
                  and wider than labrum, about 3.5 times as wide as long, anterior margin slightly
                  concave, anterolateral angles rounded; frontoclypeal suture almost straight. Eyes
                  well developed, HW: 0.30–0.31 mm , ID: 0.17–0.18 mm , suboval in lateral view,
                  protruding from head outline in dorsal view, circumocular surface raised. Frons
                  between eyes convex. </p>
            <p> Fig. 6. Tomentum on pro- and mesofemora of <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis
                  </tp:taxon-name> spp. A . <tp:taxon-name> O. leleupi Delève, 1968 </tp:taxon-name>
                  . B . <tp:taxon-name> O. lenkae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. C . <tp:taxon-name> O.
                        lobata </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. D . <tp:taxon-name> O. longicollis ( Sharp,
                        1882 ) </tp:taxon-name> . E . <tp:taxon-name> O. minor </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. F . <tp:taxon-name> O. onorei </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. G . <tp:taxon-name>
                        O. splendida </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. H . <tp:taxon-name> O. whiteheadi
                        Spangler &amp; Santiago, 1991 </tp:taxon-name> . Drawings are schematic,
                  bodies are divided to identical halves: left = male, right = female (note: females
                  unknown for D and H). </p>
            <p> THORAX. Pronotum widest behind middle, PW: 0.41–0.43 mm , PL: 0.47–0.49 mm ; surface
                  shiny, with narrow reticulation along basal margin and posterolateral angles, with
                  dense tiny punctures; sublateral carinae absent, fine raised line indistinct; disc
                  conveX, divided by a broad, deep transverse impression before middle; two
                  prescutellar foveae separated by a raised line extending from base to apical
                  discal half, connecting pronotal halves and merging into them; anterior margin
                  arcuate; posterior margin bisinuate; sides of pronotum convex before and after
                  transverse constriction; lateral margins narrowly rimmed; posterolateral angles
                  orthogonal; anterolateral angles slightly produced. Hypomeron finely
                  microreticulate, widest in middle. Prosternum moderately long in front of
                  procoXae, with anterior margin concave; sides raised around procoxae, forming
                  carinae, not reaching anterior margin, prosternal process long, moderately broad,
                  with posterior margin broadly rounded. Mesoventrite coarse, short and wide, with
                  deep triangular groove for reception of prosternal process; posterior margin
                  around mesocoxae raised. Metaventrite slightly wider than long, shiny; disc convex
                  with very shallow to indistinct, medial, triangular depression in posterior half;
                  discrimen in basal ¾, very thin, almost indistinct; with one prebasal fovea on
                  each side of metaventrite ( Fig. 5B ). Elytra (EL: 0.89–0.92 mm , EW: 0.64–0.68 mm
                  ) convex, widest in anterior ¾; sides strongly declivous; surface shiny, with
                  dense tiny punctures; elytral margin narrowly rimmed; humeri protruding from
                  outline; epipleuron tapering posteriorly; sublateral carina absent; strial
                  punctures absent (in few specimens a partial striation is present). Scutellum
                  subovate, flat. Legs moderately long; femora clavate; tibiae longest. Protibiae
                  with anterior cleaning fringe on apical ⅓; mesotibiae with two cleaning fringes –
                  anterior on apical ⅕ and posterior on apical ⅓; metatibiae with posterior cleaning
                  fringe on apical ⅓. Tarsi 5-segmented, first four segments each with one fine
                  pale, recumbent seta, fifth segment slightly shorter than remaining segments
                  combined; claws with a large subbasal and smaller basal teeth. </p>
            <p> ABDOMEN. With 5 ventrites. First ventrite with basal margin broadly rounded, fifth
                  ventrite longest, apically setose, with posterior margin broadly arcuate. Aedeagus
                  ( Fig. 9 C–D) elongate. Penis elongate, without fibula; corona in basal half; in
                  ventral view concave with rounded apeX; in lateral view evenly narrowed from base
                  to curved apeX. Parameres absent. Phallobase almost 2 times as long as penis,
                  parallel-sided, in ventral view straight, curved in lateral view. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>EXternally similar to male, eXcept metaventrite without prebasal foveae, fifth
                  ventrite more elongate and extension of femoral tomentum greater.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Biology </p>
            <p> Collected from stream ca 7 m wide in deforested area with riffles and pools, close
                  to the confluence with a larger stream, substrate composed of boulders, stones and
                  gravel ( Fig. 11F ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Known from three localities in Napo Province ( Figs 11B, F , 12 A–B). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
