<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Onychelmis lobata Linský &amp;
                        Čiamporová-Zaťovičová &amp; Čiampor 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4600348</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B187D7E837FFDFFDDAFEF7FAFEFE7E</uri>
                  <article-title>A revision of Onychelmis Hinton, 1941 (Coleoptera: Elmidae), with
                        description of new species, DNA barcoding and notes on the geography of the
                        genus</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1263</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis lobata </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: C0675943-40CF-4147-BC50-D35A7F0CF840 </p>
            <p> Figs 3B , 4 , 6C , 8 C–D, 11B, 11F, 12A–B </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Differential diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis lobata </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. can be distinguished
                  from all species of the genus by the combination of the following characters: 1)
                  moderate size (CL: 1.35–1.37 mm ); 2) pro- and mesofemora with tomentum at base in
                  males, and around middle in females ( Fig. 6C ); 3) humeri produced; 4) prominent
                  carina on sixth interval present; 5) elytral punctures shallowly impressed; 6)
                  apex of aedeagus broadly rounded, medially with arcuate projection ( Fig. 8 C–D).
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>The species is named after its larva (to be described in a separate study), which
                  possesses distinct cuticular lobes.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype ECUADOR • ♂; “Ecuador, Napo prov. , road to Coca ,
                        00°43′39.6″ S , 77°45′56.1″ W , 1129 m a.s.l. , 17. 8. 2013 , small
                        waterfall, Čiampor &amp; Čiamporová-Zaťovičová lgt. ”; PUCE .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes ECUADOR • 4 ♂♂ , 5 ♀♀ ; same collection data as
                        for holotype; PUCE / CCB </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1
                        ♂ ; “ Ecuador , Napo prov. , road to Coca , Sumaco env., 00°43′29.0″ S ,
                        77°46′01.4″ W , 1109 m a.s.l. , 17. 8. 2013 , confluence of two larger
                        streams, with gravel, stones, boulders, Čiampor &amp; Čiamporová-Zaťovičová
                        lgt. ”; PUCE / CCB </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂
                        “Ecuador, Napo prov. , road to Coca , Sumaco env., 00°42′25.7″ S ,
                        77°43′10.0″ W , 1138 m a.s.l. , 17. 8. 2013 , stream ca. 2-3 m wide, fast
                        flowing, with boulders, stones, gravel, submerged wood, Čiampor &amp;
                        Čiamporová-Zaťovičová lgt ”; PUCE / CCB </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> ECUADOR • 1 ♂ , 5 ♀♀ , 1 larva ; same collection data as
                        for holotype; CCB </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> BODY. Obovate, black ( Fig. 3B ); length 1.35–1.37 mm ; width 0.62–0.68 mm ; dorsum
                  conveX, glabrous with sparse, light yellowish-brown setae. Hairy or scale-like
                  tomentum distributed on following areas: genae, sides of prosternum, mesoventrite,
                  metaventrite and abdomen, epipleura, and medial and lateral portions on bases of
                  femora. </p>
            <p>COLOUR. Head, pronotum and elytra black; venter, mouthparts, prosternum, coxae,
                  tibiae, tarsi, metaventrite and abdomen brown to dark brown with reddish tinge;
                  trochanters pale brown to reddish brown; basal segments of antennae and tarsal
                  claws pale brown.</p>
            <p> HEAD. Partly retractable into prothoraX, dorsally shiny. Antennae filiform,
                  11-segmented; pedicel about twice as long as scape; remaining segments about 4
                  times as long as scape and pedicel combined; segments 3–10 subrectangular,
                  subequal in length; terminal segment longest, suboval, with pointed apex. Labrum
                  with anterior margin very slightly emarginate medially; anterolateral angles
                  broadly arcuate with numerous golden, recumbent hair-like setae; clypeus shorter
                  and wider than labrum, about 3.5 times as wide as long, anterior margin slightly
                  concave, anterolateral angles rounded; frontoclypeal suture almost straight. Eyes
                  well developed, HW: 0.27–0.30 mm , ID: 0.12–0.15 mm , suboval in lateral view,
                  protruding from head outline in dorsal view, circumocular surface raised. Frons
                  between eyes convex. </p>
            <p> THORAX. Pronotum widest behind middle, PW: 0.41–0.42 mm , PL: 0.47–0.48 mm ; surface
                  shiny, with narrow reticulation along basal margin and posterolateral angles, with
                  dense tiny punctures; sublateral carinae never well-developed, fine raised
                  sublateral lines indistinct; disc conveX, divided by a broad, deep transverse
                  impression before middle; prescutellar foveae separated by a raised line extending
                  from base to middle, connecting pre- and postimpression portions and merging into
                  them; anterior margin arcuate; posterior margin bisinuate; sides of pronotum
                  convex before and after transverse constriction; lateral margins narrowly rimmed;
                  posterolateral angles orthogonal; anterolateral angles slightly produced.
                  Hypomeron finely microreticulate, widest in middle. Prosternum moderately long in
                  front of procoxae, with anterior margin concave; sides raised around procoxae,
                  forming carinae, not reaching anterior margin, prosternal process long, moderately
                  broad, with posterior margin broadly rounded. Mesoventrite coarse, short and wide,
                  with deep triangular groove for reception of prosternal process; posterior margin
                  around mesocoxae raised. Metaventrite slightly wider than long, shiny with
                  setigerous punctures; disc convex with deep, medial, triangular depression in
                  posterior half; discrimen in basal ¾, very thin, indistinct; with prebasal fovea
                  on each side of metaventrite. Elytra (EL: 0.88–0.91 mm , EW: 0.62–0.68 mm )
                  conveX, widest in anterior ¾, sides strongly declivous; surface shiny, with dense
                  tiny punctures; elytral margin narrowly rimmed; humeri protruding from outline;
                  epipleuron tapering posteriorly. Prominent carina on siXth interval reaching ⅘ of
                  elytron. Elytra with ten rows of small, shallowly impressed punctures, separated
                  by 2–4 times puncture diameter, diminishing toward lateral margins and elytral
                  apeX. Scutellum subovate, flat. Legs moderately long; femora clavate; tibiae
                  longest. Protibiae with anterior cleaning fringe on apical ⅓; mesotibiae with two
                  cleaning fringes – anterior on apical ⅕ and posterior on apical ⅓; metatibiae with
                  posterior cleaning fringe on apical ⅓. Tarsi 5-segmented, first four segments each
                  with one fine pale, recumbent seta, fifth segment slightly shorter than remaining
                  segments combined; claws with a large subbasal and smaller basal teeth. </p>
            <p> ABDOMEN. With 5 ventrites. First ventrite with basal margin broadly rounded; fifth
                  ventrite longest, apically setose, with posterior margin broadly arcuate ( Fig. 4A
                  ). Aedeagus ( Fig. 8 C–D) elongate. Penis without fibula; corona in apical half;
                  in ventral view subparallel, apically widened, apeX rounded with medial
                  protuberance; in lateral view curved, evenly narrowed from base to apeX. Parameres
                  absent. Phallobase about as long as penis, parallel-sided, in ventral view
                  straight, slightly curved in lateral view. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> Externally similar to male, except metaventrite without distinct medial, triangular
                  depression in posterior half and without two prebasal foveae, fifth ventrite more
                  elongate ( Fig. 4B ) and eXtension of femoral tomentum greater. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 4. Fifth ventrite of <tp:taxon-name> O. lobata </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. A . Male. B
            . Female. Scale bar = 0.1 mm. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Biology </p>
            <p> Collected from small stream directly below waterfall surrounded by remnants of
                  primary forest, with water flowing between larger stones ( Fig. 11B ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Known from three localities in Napo Province ( Figs 11B, F , 12 A–B). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
