<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba nigrescens Gao &amp; Coca-Abia 2021, comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773330</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B56743A67D0663FDFEFAD1FCE2E2AA</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba nigrescens
(
Moser, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 91–93
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia nigrescens
Moser, 1916: 185
</tp:taxon-name>

(
type
loc.: Madurai, 
India
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia nigrescens
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Frey 1971: 216

, 220, figs 28a–b (in key).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Fig. 91
). Body size 
11.7–13.3 mm
. Dorsal surface glabrous, at most with short setae in each puncture hardly visible. Male antennal club as long as funiculus. Clypeus shorter than frons, almost flat, arcuate laterally, anterior edge emarginate at middle; surface with conspicuous and deep punctures. Frons with punctures similar to those of clypeus; frontal carina blunt and curved backward. Pronotal surface with strong and deep punctures, wrinkled appearance; anterior margin glabrous, widely flanged; posterior margin with a row of punctures and very short pubescence; lateral margins widely serrated and with short setae, elevated at anterior half; anterior angles almost right, moderately projected forward, posterior angles obtuse almost right and marked. Prosternal process slender and sharp. Scutellum glabrous, with punctures uniformly distributed. Elytral surface shiny, with punctures evenly distributed and softer than those of pronotum; epipleuron glabrous, with a few short setae at basal part. Foretibia with dorsal carina moderately developed. Meso- and metatibia with transverse carina complete and interrupted respectively, inner margin of dorsal surface with a few spines. Prepygidium with punctures regularly distributed, stronger at posterior margin. Pygidium with punctures irregularly distributed glabrous, at most with tiny setae in each puncture hardly visible; apex with sparse and short pubescence. Ventrites 1 and 2 with conspicuous decumbent short pubescence regularly distributed. Ventrites 3 and 4 glabrous. Ventrite 5 moderately depressed at posterior half, with a row of long setae. Ventrite 6 with strong and deep punctures, appearance wrinkled, moderately bulging at anterior margin, long pubescence near posterior margin. Male genitalia fits into morphotype VII “ 
Rugaticollis
” above described. Parameres (
Fig. 92
) with notch of dorsal branch moderately developed, only a small concavity at distal end. Ventral branches slightly longer than dorsal one and with apices moderately raised. Endophallus (
Fig. 93
) with an area of soft setae at distal half. Apophysis of temones (
Fig. 93
) separated from each other at both ends. Female genitalia not studied.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
INDIA
• 
♂
; “Madura Ind. or” [Madurai, India]; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrescens
</tp:taxon-name>
” [in red]; “ 
Syntypus
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia nigrescens
Moser, 1916
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by MNHUB 2016”; “ 
Lectotype
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba nigrescens
(
Moser, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao &amp; Coca-Abia det. 2017”; 
MFNB
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paralectotypes

(here indicated)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
INDIA
• 
1 ♂
; “Dekan India”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia nigrescens
</tp:taxon-name>
Type Mos”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrescens
Mos
</tp:taxon-name>
”; “ 
Syntypus
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia nigrescens
Moser, 1916
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by MNHUB 2016”; “ 
Paralectotype
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba nigrescens
(
Moser, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao and Coca-Abia det. 2017”; 
MFNB
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “Dekan India”, “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrescens
</tp:taxon-name>
” [in red]; “ 
Syntypus
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia nigrescens
Moser, 1916
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by MNHUB 2016”; “ 
Paralectotype
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba nigrescens
(
Moser, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao &amp; Coca-Abia det. 2017”; 
MFNB
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Moser (1916)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia nigrescens
</tp:taxon-name>
from a series of specimens from Deccan and Madurai (
India
). We have studied 
three type
specimens (MFNB) (
two males
and another one without abdomen that could be a female), which show external and genital features that characterize the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
and the genital morphotype VII “ 
Rugaticollis
”. Hence, we transfer 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. nigrescens
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
and include it into this genital morphotype. Moreover, we designate 
lectotype
and 
paralectotypes
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
India
(Deccan, Madurai).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Species included in Morphotype VIII “Scutata”
</p>
      <p>The group is composed of two species, which are characterized by antenna 10-segmented, pronotal surface irregularly and scattered punctate (distance between punctures greater than diameter of puncture) and male and female genitalia as specified above.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
