<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba frontalis CH. Bu Gao &amp; M.
            Coca-Abia</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773243</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B56743A62C0631FE11FDDCFD21E184</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae,
            Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba frontalis ( Fairmaire, 1886 ) </tp:taxon-name> (valid species) </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Figs 34–36 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Rhizotrogus frontalis Fairmaire, 1886: 325 </tp:taxon-name> ( type loc.:
         Yunnan , China ). </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba frontalis </tp:taxon-name> – Keith 2005: 98 (combination). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> External morphology of adult ( Fig. 34 ). Body size 17–19.5 mm . Body surface with
         conspicuous pubescence on frons, basal part of elytra and pygidium. Clypeus shorter than
         frons, concave, with anterior edge emarginate at middle. Frontal carina well developed and
         sharp. Pronotum without pubescence on disc; anterior margin with short setae, without
         concavity at each lateral end; lateral margins smooth and glabrous, moderately sinuate at
         posterior half; anterior angles acute, not projected forward, elevated laterally; posterior
         angles obtuse. Prosternal process quadrangular-shaped. Scutellum glabrous, with punctures
         except lateral margins. Elytra with conspicuous pubescence on basal part, disc glabrous;
         epipleuron with pubescence except on apex. Foretibia with strong and sharp carina;
         insertion of inner spur closer third outer tooth than second one. Meso- and metatibia with
         transverse carina interrupted at middle, with a marked dorsal and ventral prominence; inner
         margin of dorsal surface with strong spines. Prepygidium regularly punctate, conspicuous
         short pubescence. Pygidium with punctures of irregular size and distribution; conspicuous
         pubescence on disc, longer toward apex; apical margin moderately widened and raised.
         Ventrites with conspicuous pubescence; ventrite 5 moderately depressed at posterior half,
         with pubescence longer on depressed part. Ventrite 6 flat, with diffuse punctures. Male
         genitalia. Parameres ( Fig. 35 ) with apices of dorsal branches moderately curveted;
         without pubescence or granules. Endophallus ( Fig. 36 ) with raspula of setae and spines
         larger toward distal end. Temones ( Fig. 36 ) with apophysis reduced and separated at
         distal end. Female unknown. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p> Figs 34–36. <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba frontalis ( Fairmaire, 1886 ) </tp:taxon-name> ,
      holotype (MNHN). 34 . Habitus in dorsal view. 35 . Parameres in dorsal (A), ventral (B) and
      lateral (C) views. 36 . Endophallus (everted) and temones in dorsal view. Scale bars: 34 = 5.0
      mm; 35–36 = 1.0 mm. </p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p> Holotype </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> CHINA • ♂ ; “ Yunnan ”; “Museum Paris 1906 Coll. Lèon Fairmaire ”; “
               <tp:taxon-name> Rhizotrog frontalis Fair Yunan </tp:taxon-name> ”; “ Type ”; “
            Holotype <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba frontalis ( Fairmaire, 1886 ) CH. Bu Gao &amp; M.
               Coca-Abia </tp:taxon-name> det. 2018”; “ <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba castanea (Wat.)
               Denis Keith </tp:taxon-name> det. 2003”; MNHN . </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p> Other material </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> CHINA – Guizhou Prov. • 3 ♂♂ , 1 ♀ ; Guiyang ; 6 Oct. 1979 ; C.-J.
            Yang leg.; C.-B. Gao det.; SYAU </tp:material-citation> . – <tp:material-citation>
            Hainan Prov. • 1 ♂ ; Hainan ; 1952; C.-B. Gao det.; SYAU </tp:material-citation> . –
            <tp:material-citation> Sichuan Prov. • 1 ♂ ; Xichang , Mt Lushan , Yuhuangdian ; 1700 m
            a.s.l. ; 8 May 2005 ; J.-Y. Qiu leg.; C.-B. Gao det.; SYAU </tp:material-citation> . –
            <tp:material-citation> Yunnan Prov. • 3 ♂♂ ; Yunnan ; A. Davis leg.; Fairmaire det.;
            Coll. Fairmaire ; MNHN </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 2 ♂♂ , 16 ♀♀ ;
            Kunming ; C.-W. Li leg.; Y.-W. Zhang det.; IZCAS </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 3 ♂♂ , 2 ♀♀ ; Shaotong ; 1981; C.-B. Gao det.; IZCAS
         </tp:material-citation> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> Keith (2005) transferred <tp:taxon-name> Rhizotrogus frontalis </tp:taxon-name> to
            <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba </tp:taxon-name> and synonymized it with <tp:taxon-name> M.
            castanea </tp:taxon-name> based on a series of male specimens labelled with the name of
         collector (Armand David). Indeed, Fairmaire (1886) , in the introduction of the work in
         which he described <tp:taxon-name> R. frontalis </tp:taxon-name> , thanked Armand David for
         the <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> specimens received, which could suggest that
         the types of <tp:taxon-name> R. frontalis </tp:taxon-name> are these specimens labelled
         with the name of that collector. However, Fairmaire (1886) indicated that the description
         of <tp:taxon-name> R. frontalis </tp:taxon-name> was based on only one specimen ;
         therefore, the series studied by Keith (2005) cannot be syntypes . We have examined a male
         specimen of <tp:taxon-name> R. frontalis </tp:taxon-name> preserved in the collection of
         Léon Fairmaire (MNHN) labelled as a type and with an original label with his determination.
         Although Fairmaire (1886) thought that this unique specimen was a female judging from its
         short antennal club, it is actually a male. In fact, and contrary to other
            <tp:taxon-name>Rhizotrogini</tp:taxon-name> , the species of <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba
         </tp:taxon-name> do no show obvious sexual dimorphism in the antennal club, which is very
         short in both sexes. On the other hand, we agree with the transfer of <tp:taxon-name> R.
            frontalis </tp:taxon-name> to <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba </tp:taxon-name> , the features
         of the external morphology and genitalia show that this species belongs to this genus.
         Moreover, the antenna 9-segmented and parameres with two dorsal and two ventral branches
         separated from each other, allow us include it in morphotype I “ <tp:taxon-name>
            Trichophora </tp:taxon-name> ”. In contrast, we do not agree with the synonymy of
            <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba frontalis </tp:taxon-name> with <tp:taxon-name> M. castanea
         </tp:taxon-name> proposed by Keith (2005) , who did not sufficiently justify this synonymy.
         We have compared the type of <tp:taxon-name> M. frontalis </tp:taxon-name> with those of
            <tp:taxon-name> M. castanea </tp:taxon-name> , finding them to differ by the following
         characters ( Table 2 ): head (pubescence on clypeus and frons, frontal carina), pronotum
         (anterior margin, anterior angles), the shape of the prosternal process, elytra
         (pubescence), foretibia (carina, inner spur), the protarsi and mesotarsi (tufts of setae),
         parameres (pubescence and granules at branches) and endophallus (internal structures).
         Accordingly, <tp:taxon-name> M. frontalis </tp:taxon-name> is established herein as valid
         species. The unique type specimen of <tp:taxon-name> M. frontalis ( Fairmaire, 1886 )
         </tp:taxon-name> found in coll. Léon Fairmaire (MNHN) is a holotype by monotypy, and is
         labelled as holotype . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p> Table 2. Differences between holotype of <tp:taxon-name> M. frontalis ( Fairmaire, 1886 )
      </tp:taxon-name> and lectotype and paralectotype of <tp:taxon-name> M. castanea ( Waterhouse,
         1875 ) </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   <p> Character <tp:taxon-name> M. frontalis </tp:taxon-name>
      <tp:taxon-name> M. castanea </tp:taxon-name> Clypeus length shorter than the frons as long as
      the frons Clypeus shape concave flat Frontal pubescence present and long absent or, at most,
      very short hardly noticeable Frontal carina high, sharp. low, not sharp Pronotal anterior edge
      gently wavy behind eyes without wavy behind eyes Anterior angles acute obtuse Prosternal
      process quadrangular shaped rounded with a bulge on ventral face Elytral pubescence Long on
      basal part absent or, at most, very short hardly noticeable Carina of the protibia strongly
      elevated. Sharp gently elevated Protibia, insertion of the inner spur closer than 3th than 2nd
      tooth equidistant between the 2nd and 3th tooth Pro- and metatarsi conspicuous tufts of setae
      inconspicuous tufts of setae Branches of the parameres without pubescence or granules with
      pubescence or granules Endophallum with soft spurs with strong spurs </p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> China ( Hainan , Guizhou , Sichuan , Yunnan ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
