<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Namkongnaia Jeratthitikul &amp; Sutcharit &amp; Ngor &amp; Prasankok 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5593531</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B5A943FFBF6F18FDFAEA97FD78ECD3</uri>
         <article-title>Molecular phylogeny reveals a new genus of freshwater mussels from the Mekong River Basin (Bivalvia: Unionidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Namkongnaia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
77AD43CF-83EC-42B8-B021-A950D4E701A0
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Namkongnaia inkhavilayi
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, by present designation.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new genus is distinguished from other genera in 
<tp:taxon-name>Pseudodontini</tp:taxon-name>
by having a narrow, elongated, and less inflated shell. It is also represented as a distinct clade in multi-locus phylogenetic analyses.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>Shell Medium-sized, thin, narrow and elongated, rather compressed, very inequilateral; anteriorly round; posteriorly round or somewhat pointed; umbonal area not elevated and usually eroded. Ligament very narrow. Hinge without dentition, posterior end of the hinge structure with V-shaped fossette. Anterior adductor muscle scar shallow, ovate, and fused with pedal retractor muscle scars; posterior adductor muscle scar very shallow. Excurrent aperture smooth, shorter than incurrent; incurrent with 1-2 rows of conical papillae. Gills elongated and slightly ribbed; anterior margin of inner gills slightly longer and wider than outer gills.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The generic name “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Namkongnaia
</tp:taxon-name>
” is from the word 
“Namkong”
, a name for the Mekong River used by Thai and Lao peoples, and Greek word 
“naiad”
meaning freshwater mussels. The name of this genus thus means “freshwater mussels from Mekong River”.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Mekong River and its tributaries in 
Laos
, 
Cambodia
, and 
Thailand
(
Fig. 3
; 
Brandt 1974
; 

Ng 
et al.
2020

). The distribution range may include the Mae Klong River Basin in 
Thailand
(
Brandt 1974
), although the taxonomic status of the specimens recorded in 
Brandt (1974)
needs to be confirmed.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new genus is currently composed of two species, which are confirmed by our multi-locus molecular data. Other potential species are probably among those previously recognized under the name ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pilsbryoconcha lemeslei
</tp:taxon-name>
’ by 
Brandt (1974)
. This includes the specimens from ‘Bang Pae’, Mae Klong River Basin, 
Ratchaburi Province
(USNM-786217, SMF-BR2663, and ANSP-H19041). These specimens show elongate and narrow shell, which are diagnostic characters of the genus, but differ from other species by having a minute concave ventral margin, and truncated posterior margin with a pointed posterior end. Further examination of fresh materials and DNA investigation would confirm the taxonomic status of these populations.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
