<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tachycines (Gymnaeta) shiziensis Zhu &amp; Shi 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5237322</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FFE7536D492D06067570CED3B2206C0E</uri>
         <article-title>Description of four new species of the subgenus Tachycines (Gymnaeta) Adelung, 1902 (Orthoptera: Rhaphidophoridae) from caves in China and additional notes on some previously known species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1465</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tachycines
(
Gymnaeta
) 
shiziensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
5C1282B7-963A-4856-B626-1CBD08E99306
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2
, 
8C–D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>The new species is similar to other congeneric species in appearance, but it can easily be distinguished by the shape of the dorsal sclerite of the male genitalia, the dorsal sclerite being trapezoidal, the basal part narrow, with one deep concavity, and the posterior margin being broad and slightly concave.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new species refers to the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Jiangxi Prov.
, 
Ji’an City
, 
Wan’an County
, 
Baoshan Village
, 
Shiziyan
; 

16 Oct. 2013

; 
Ming- Yi Tian
, 
Wei-Xin Liu
, 
Hao-Min Yin
and 
Xin-Hui Wang
leg.; 
HBU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>BODY. Slightly smaller than in other congeneric species.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Fastigium verticis degenerated, indistinct. Eyes oval, protruding forward. Apical segment of maxillary palpus distinctly longer than subapical one, apex inflated, globular.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Pronotum long, anterior margin straight, posterior margin arcuate; lateral lobes longer than high, ventral margin arc-shaped. Mesonotum and metanotum short, posterior margin of mesonotum arcuate, posterior margin of metanotum straight.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore coxa with one small spine; femur unarmed on ventral surface, internal genicular lobe unarmed, external genicular lobe with one long spine; tibia with only two outer spines on ventral surface, apex with one pair of ventral spines, between paired ventral spines with one small spine. Mid femur unarmed on ventral surface, internal and external genicular lobes with one long spine each; tibia unarmed on ventral surface, apex with one pair of ventral spines, between paired ventral spines with one small spine. Hind femur unarmed on ventral surface, internal and external genicular lobes unarmed; tibia with 23–24 inner spines and 21–24 outer spines on dorsal surface, with one pair of dorsal spines in subapical area, and at apex with one pair of dorsal spines and two pairs of ventral spines, interno-dorsal spine slightly shorter than hind basitarsus. Hind basitarsus with one apical spine on dorsal surface, ventral surface with bristles.</p>
      <p>MALE ABDOMEN. Posterior margins of all abdominal tergites relatively straight, abdominal sterna without obvious conical tubercles. Epiproct tongue-shaped, paraproct simple, nearly triangular in lateral view. Cercus extremely long, conical, apex acute. Genitalia with six membranous lobes, apical area of dorso- median lobe with one pair of small lobes, lateral sclerite slender, reaching subapex of dorso-median lobe, dorso-lateral lobes slightly longer than dorso-median lobe, ventro-lateral lobes much shorter than dorso-lateral lobes, ventro-median lobe short; dorsal sclerite trapezoidal, basal part narrow, with one deep concavity, posterior margin broad and slightly concave. Subgenital plate quadrangular, posterior margin slightly concave.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tachycines
(
Gymnaeta
) 
shiziensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–F
. Holotype, ♂ (HBU). 
A–C
. Head and pronotum. 
A
. Frontal view. 
B
. Lateral view. 
C
. Dorsal view. 
D–F
. Apex of abdomen. 
D
. Lateral view. 
E
. Dorsal view. 
F
. Ventral view.
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body uniformly yellowish-brown. Eyes black.</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
      <p>
Measurements
(mm)
</p>
      <p>
Body length: 
♂
: 9.90; length of pronotum: 
♂
: 3.54; length of fore femur: 
♂
: 7.74; length of hind femur: 
♂
: 13.80; length of hind tibia: 
♂
: 14.20; length of hind basitarsus: 
♂
: 2.80.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Jiangxi
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
