<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tachycines (Gymnaeta) quadratus Zhu &amp; Shi 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5237320</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B787ADFF84FF81FD9509847B73330D</uri>
         <article-title>Description of four new species of the subgenus Tachycines (Gymnaeta) Adelung, 1902 (Orthoptera: Rhaphidophoridae) from caves in China and additional notes on some previously known species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1465</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tachycines
(
Gymnaeta
) 
quadratus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
A76373AC-5FF4-4ED9-8496-A4180B9D1456
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1
, 
8A–B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tachycines
(
Gymnaeta
) 
sonlaensis
Gorochov, 1990
</tp:taxon-name>
with regard to the dorsal sclerite of the male genitalia, but differs from the latter by: projection of fastigium verticis is fully reduced; hind tibia has a lower number of dorsal spines (only 11–13 inner spines and 10–14 outer spines instead of 30–40 spines in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T.
(
G.
) 
sonlaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
); interno-dorsal spine is distinctly shorter than hind basitarsus instead of nearly equal in length to hind basitarsus in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T.
(
G.
) 
sonlaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new species derives from the Latin word 

‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>quadratus</tp:taxon-name>

’ referring to the dorsal sclerite of the male genitalia quadrate being quadrangular.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Hunan Prov.
, 
Yongzhou City
, 
Lanshan County
, 
Dibao Cave
; 

2 Oct. 2011

; 
Ming-Yi Tian
leg.; 
HBU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
HBU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>BODY. Medium-sized.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Fastigium verticis fully reduced. Eyes slightly degenerated, oval; medium ocellus oval, located between antennal sockets. Apical segment of maxillary palpus distinctly longer than subapical one, apical area inflated, globular.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Pronotum long, anterior margin straight, posterior margin arcuate; lateral lobes longer than high, ventral margin arc-shaped. Mesonotum and metanotum short, posterior margin of mesonotum arcuate, posterior margin of metanotum straight.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tachycines
(
Gymnaeta
) 
quadratus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–F, I
. Holotype, ♂ (HBU). 
A–C
. Head and pronotum. 
A
. Frontal view. 
B
. Lateral view. 
C
. Dorsal view. 
D–F
. Apex of abdomen. 
D
. Lateral view. 
E
. Dorsal view. 
F
. Ventral view. 
I
. Hind tarsus in lateral view. — 
G–H
. Paratype, ♀ (HBU). 
G
. Subgenital plate. 
H
. Ovipositor in lateral view.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore coxa with one small spine; femur unarmed on ventral surface, internal genicular lobe with one small spine, external genicular lobe with one long spine; tibia with one inner spine and one to two outer spines on ventral surface, apex with one pair of ventral spines, between paired ventral spines with one small spine. Mid femur unarmed on ventral surface, internal and external genicular lobes with one long spine each; tibia with only one outer spine on ventral surface, apex with one inner spine on dorsal surface and one pair of ventral spines, between paired ventral spines with one small spine. Hind femur unarmed on ventral surface, internal and external genicular lobes unarmed; tibia with 11–13 inner spines and 10–14 outer spines on dorsal surface, arranged sparsely, with one pair of dorsal spines in subapical area, and at apex with one pair of dorsal spines and two pairs of ventral spines, interno-dorsal spine distinctly shorter than hind basitarsus. Hind basitarsus unarmed on dorsal surface, ventral surface with bristles.</p>
      <p>MALE ABDOMEN. Posterior margins of all abdominal tergites relatively straight, abdominal sterna with conical tubercles. Epiproct tongue-shaped, paraproct simple, nearly triangular in lateral view. Cercus slender, conical, apex acute. Genitalia with six membranous lobes, apical area of dorso-median lobe with one pair of small lobes, lateral sclerite indistinct, dorso-lateral lobes nearly equal in length to dorsomedian lobe, ventro-lateral lobes nearly equal in length to dorso-lateral lobes, ventro-median lobe short; dorsal sclerite quadrate. Subgenital plate quadrangular, transverse and broad, middle area with conical tubercle, posterior margin straight.</p>
      <p>FEMALE ABDOMEN. Ovipositor longer than half the length of hind femur, slightly curved upward, dorsal margin smooth, apical area of ventral margin denticulate. Subgenital plate nearly triangular, both sides of basal area with one triangulate lobe, apex acute.</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body yellowish-brown. Eyes black, conical tubercles of abdominal sterna black.</p>
      <p>
Measurements
(mm)
</p>
      <p>
Body length: 
♂
: 15.30–15.70, 
♀
: 16.34; length of pronotum: 
♂
: 4.44–4.60, 
♀
: 4.18; length of fore femur: 
♂
: 11.94–12.56, 
♀
: 11.90; length of hind femur: 
♂
: 20.10–20.20, 
♀
: 19.04; length of hind tibia: 
♂
: 22.18–23.14, 
♀
: 22.00; length of hind basitarsus: 
♂
: 3.14–4.10, 
♀
: 3.44; length of ovipositor: 11.94.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Hunan
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
