<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Trypheridium Brancucci 1985</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5237273</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BA87A5897C2A2FBD7A2D55FAACFA18</uri>
         <article-title>A review of the Himalayan genus Trypheridium Brancucci (Coleoptera:
            Cantharidae: Chauliognathinae with description of a new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1467</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Trypheridium Brancucci, 1985 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Figs 2–7 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Trypheridium Brancucci, 1985a: 245 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Trypheridium </tp:taxon-name> – Kazantsev 2004: 30 (catalogue); 2012: 403
         (catalogue). — Kazantsev &amp; Brancucci 2007: 297 (catalogue). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Trypherus nuristanicus Wittmer, 1956 </tp:taxon-name> , by original
         designation. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Trypheridium </tp:taxon-name> is similar to <tp:taxon-name> Trypherus
         </tp:taxon-name> , and distinguished by sexual characters: tergite IX with dorsal and
         ventral blades (“lames tergales et sternales”) very long and asymmetrical ( Figs 3A–D ,
         6E–F ); aedeagus without left paramere, median lobe membranous ( Figs 3F–J , 6G–I ), with
         orifice apically (not preapically as in <tp:taxon-name> Trypherus </tp:taxon-name> );
         female with sternite VII remarkably broad, partly or completely concealing most of sternite
         VIII ( Figs 4G–H , 7B ); bursa copulatrix elongate, with two tubular spermathecae and one
         accessory gland connecting the bursa in its postero-dorsal part ( Figs 5F , 7D ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Re-description ( Figs 6–7 ) </p>
      <p> Coloration </p>
      <p>General coloration pale to sulphur yellow with dark brown to black patches; head yellow
         anteriorly at frons and clypeus and infuscate at vertex and occipital region; antennae dark
         brown to black, the three or four basal antennomeres yellow; pronotum with a transversal
         black band at posterior half; elytra with dark brown to black triangular patches, from the
         base of elytra (not reaching the humeri) and extending posteriorly; wings dark brown; legs
         dark brown or black, usually fore and mid legs light brown with dark spots; abdominal
         tergites and ventrites black in the centre and yellow at the margins. Coloration in females
         usually darker.</p>
      <p> Male </p>
      <p> HABITUS. Length 6.5–8.5 mm . </p>
      <p>HEAD. Head (including the eyes) wider than pronotum; vertex flat, frons concave between the
         eyes, occipital region convex, sides rounded and regularly narrowing behind the eyes. Eyes
         large, oblong, bulging, longer than wide, broadly separated. Fronto-clypeal suture distinct
         laterally, indistinct in the middle; anterior margin of clypeus slightly sinuous, nearly
         straight; labrum membranous. Mandibles arcuate, apex acute, blunt, retinaculum in the same
         plan as incisor, apex rounded, with a small supplementary tooth at the base of retinaculum.
         Maxillary palp with fourth palpomere elongate, narrowing apicad. Antennae not juxtaposed,
         separated by at least the width of antennal sockets; with 11 antennomeres, filiform,
         without modifications; antennomere I slender, without swellings.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Transverse, wider than long, convex; anterior margin broadly arched, lateral
         margins nearly straight, slightly narrowing posteriorly; posterior margin projected
         posteriorly; anterior and posterior angles rounded, barely distinct. Elytra short, 1.2–1.4
         times longer than combined width, slightly narrowed laterally, suture dehiscent
         posteriorly, apex rounded.</p>
      <p> WINGS. With reduced venation, radial cell 2R 1 closed; vein r-m barely visible, vein Cu
         straight, vein Mr fading; transversal vein cu-a absent; Rr extends beyond the joining of
         vein r; vein A x2 well visible, not joining Ax 1+2 and ending near the joining of vein A
         and Ax 1+2 . </p>
      <p>LEGS. Slender, without swellings, teeth or remarkable modifications; apex of fore tibia
         with a pair of tiny spurs; all tarsal claws with broad internal teeth.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Weakly sclerotised; tergites with a pair of small glandular pores on the distal
         corners; pores of tergite VIII in the apex of projections. Tergite VIII long and broad,
         with distal corners projected posteriorly, distal margin arcuate, concave. Tergite IX
         (paraproct) strongly modified in a capsule with a pair of long and asymmetrical lamellar
         projections directed ventrally; left blade (“lame sternale” of Brancucci) longer,
         flattened; right blade (“lame tergale” of Brancucci) shorter, more strongly curved
         ventrally. Tergite X (proctiger) divided posteriorly into two projecting lobes. Sternite
         VIII (ventrite VII) asymmetrical, distal margin sinuous and deeply notched, sides projected
         posteriorly. Sternite IX concealed underneath sternite VIII, elongate, lamellar, weakly
         sclerotised.</p>
      <p>AEDEAGUS. Elongated and weakly sclerotised; left paramere absent, right paramere and the
         prolongation of tegmen elongate and directed posteriorly; left prolongation of tegmen broad
         and lamellar, margins sinuous. Median lobe membranous, short, not twisted, with its broad
         opening located apically.</p>
      <p> Female </p>
      <p>Similar to males, except for eyes slightly smaller and more separated; sternite VII long
         and broad, mostly concealing sternite VIII, distal margin with elongate lobes projecting
         posteriorly. Sternite VIII membranous, broadly rounded, distal margin with a broad rounded
         lobe projecting posteriorly; coxites small, not fused medially, anterior arms very long and
         slender, apparently fused with valvifers, styles elongate, digitiform. Genitalia
         membranous, consisting of a long and broad vagina; oviduct anteriorly in the vagina; bursa
         copulatrix elongate, wrinkled, spiralling; spermatheca formed by two tubular projections;
         accessory gland large, connected by a long winding duct to the postero-dorsal part of bursa
         copulatrix.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Trypheridium </tp:taxon-name> seems to be endemic to the Hindu Kush
         Himalayan Region. The only species described prior to this work has been reported from
         Tajikistan , Afghanistan ( Nuristan ) and Pakistan ( Fig. 8A ). Herein, we report a new
         species of this genus from India ( Fig. 8B ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Key to the species of <tp:taxon-name> Trypheridium Brancucci, 1985 </tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p> 1. Males: right blade of tergite IX bifurcating terminally into two unequal lobes ( Fig.
         3A–D ); tergite X divided into two very long asymmetrical projections ( Fig. 3B ). Females:
         sternite VII long, mostly concealing sternite VIII, projecting beyond the tip of abdomen,
         distal margin with three projections ( Fig. 4G–H
         )................................................................................
            <tp:taxon-name> Trypheridium kashmiricum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </p>
      <p> – Males: right blade of tergite IX undivided ( Fig. 6E–F ); tergite X divided into two
         short asymmetrical lobes ( Fig. 6D, F ). Females: sternite VII shorter, partly exposing
         sternite VIII, distal margin with two projections ( Fig. 7B–C )
         ............................................... <tp:taxon-name> Trypheridium nuristanicum (
            Wittmer, 1956 ) </tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
