<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Trypheridium kashmiricum Zubair &amp; Maqbool &amp; Wachkoo &amp; Biffi 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5237275</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7E80DD2E30863B98A60FF9635056621C</uri>
         <article-title>A review of the Himalayan genus Trypheridium Brancucci (Coleoptera: Cantharidae: Chauliognathinae with description of a new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1467</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Trypheridium kashmiricum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
DF4DAB14-589A-4B50-A37C-9EFC31438D86
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2–5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. nuristanicum
</tp:taxon-name>
in general morphology and coloration, but differs in the structure of male and female terminal abdominal segments. In males, the right blade of tergite IX bifurcates terminally into two unequal lobes and tergite X divides into two very long asymmetrical projections. Sternite VII in females projects beyond the tip of abdomen, mostly concealing sternite VIII, and forms three projections apically.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species epithet is in reference to the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
INDIA
• 
♂
; 
Jammu and Kashmir
, 
Baramulla
, 
Tangmarg
; 
34º05′30″ N
, 
74°33′31″ E
; 

1639 m
a.s.l.

; 

10 Aug. 2018

; 
Zubair R.M.
leg.; 
KUIC 0013
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
INDIA
• 
1 ♂
, 
2 ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
KUIC 0014
to 
KUIC 0016
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
INDIA
• 
1 ♂
; 
Jammu and Kashmir
, 
Baramulla
, 
Tangmarg
; 
34º05′30″ N
, 
74°33′31″ E
; 

1639 m
a.s.l.

; 

10 Aug. 2018

; 
Zubair R.M.
leg.; 
KUIC 0017
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Coloration
</p>
      <p>Head black in vertex and occipital region, yellow in frons and clypeus. Antennae dark brown, except the three and part of fourth basal antennomeres and sometimes underside of latter, yellow; sometimes antennomeres II and III infuscate. Mandibles yellowish with dark-brown apex. Palpi light brown, infuscate at distal palpomeres. Pronotum partly translucent, yellow with transversal black band at posterior half, not reaching lateral and posterior pronotal margins. Elytra sulphur yellow with triangular dark brown patch from base of elytra extending posteriorly along suture up to about posterior third of elytra; integument shinning, covered with fine yellow pubescence. Wings, meso- and metaventrite dark brown to black. Legs: fore and mid coxae yellow, hind coxa partly yellow and partly brown; fore and mid femora yellowish (black in females) except having black patch towards dorsal apex; fore tibia and tarsus yellow; mid tibia testaceous brown and tarsus dark brown; hind legs completely dark brown except yellowish brown basal margin; darker specimens have legs more broadly infuscate. Abdominal ventrites and tergites dark brown to black at the centre and yellow at margins; last ventrites and tergites light to dark brown (especially in females).</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Figs 2–3
)
</p>
      <p>
HABITUS. Length 
7.8 mm
in 
holotype
(
Fig. 2A–C
), 
7.6 mm
in 
paratype
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Head (including eyes) wider than pronotum (
Fig. 2D–E
), 1.3 times as wide as long (across middle of eyes); vertex flat, frons slightly concave between eyes, with pair of longitudinal furrows running between antennae sockets; area around antennal sockets depressed and with carinated margin, forming ridge between antennae that reaches up to vertex; integument smooth and lustrous, with very small punctures and densely covered with short and fine setae. Fronto-clypeal suture defined laterally, indistinct medially. Eyes large, bulging, longer than wide, glabrous; interocular space 1.6 times wider than widest width of eye. Antennae filiform (
Fig. 2F
), slender, 0.56 times body length, covered with short and fine setae; antennomere I 1.68 times length of II, 0.88 times length of antennomere III, 0.84 times length of antennomere IV, antennomeres IV–VI longest, subequal, latter decreasing apicad, XI pointed at apex.
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM. Transverse (
Fig. 2G
) 1.3 times as wide as long, sides narrowed posteriorly, rounded, anterior margin arcuate, anterior angles rounded, not defined, posterior margin projected posteriorly, sinuous; disc slightly arched, integument partly translucent, smooth and lustrous, coarsely punctured and densely covered with fine pubescence. Scutellum with sides parallel, apex truncate. Scutellum trapezoidal, with pair of shallow and broad concavities anteriorly, posterior margin with rounded notch.
</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Short, 0.28 times as long as body length, about 1.89 times length of pronotum, 1.2 times longer than width of both elytra; sides slightly narrowed at posterior third, sutures parallel anteriorly and</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypheridium kashmiricum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
♂, holotype (KUIC 0013). 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B
. Habitus, lateral view. 
C
. Habitus, ventral view. 
D
. Head, frontal view. 
E
. Head, lateral view. 
F
. Antenna. 
G
. Pronotum. 
H
. Hind wing. 
I
. Apex of fore tibia showing a pair of tiny spurs. 
J
. Terminal segments, ventral view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig 3.
Micro images (brightfield and darkfield) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypheridium kashmiricum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
♂, holotype (KUIC 0013), terminal segments genitalia. 
A
. Ventral view. 
B
. Dorsal view. 
C
. Lateral view. 
D
. Ventral view with IX sternite and tergite removed. 
E
. 
IXth
sternite. 
F
. Aedeagus in ventral view. 
G
. Aedeagus in dorsal view. 
H
. Aedeagus in lateral view, left side. 
I
. Aedeagus in dorso-lateral view. 
J
. Aedeagus in lateral view, right side. Abbreviations: VIII St =sternite VIII; VIII Tg =tergite VIII; IX St =sternite IX; IX Tg=tergite IX; IX Tg Lt =left blade of tergite IX; IX Tg Rt =right blade of tergite IX; X Tg=tergite X; Ad =aedeagus; Md Lb=median lobe; Pr Tg=prolongation of tegmen; Rt Pr =right paramere. Scale bars: A–D, H–J= 0.5 mm; E–G=0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>dehiscent from posterior half, apex of each elytron rounded and flattened; integument slightly rugose, almost smooth, with fine punctures and densely covered with short and fine setae.</p>
      <p>
WINGS. With reduced venation (
Fig. 2H
), radial cell 2R1 closed; vein r-m barely visible, vein Cu straight; transversal vein cu-a absent; Rr extends beyond the joining of vein r; vein A 
x2
well visible, not joining Ax 
1+2
and ending near the joining of vein A and Ax 
1+2
.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Slender, increasing in length from fore to hind, without strong modifications. Apex of fore tibia with a pair of very tiny spurs (
Fig. 2I
).
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Weakly sclerotised; tergite VIII globose, longer and wider than preceding ones, distal margin arcuate, concave, posterior angles projected, with conspicuous glandular openings; tergite IX with two elongated, asymmetrical and protruding lamellae (blades) that converge towards the apex, giving it a shape of ‘forceps’ (
Fig. 2J
); right blade curves ventrally and bifurcates terminally into two unequal lobes (
Fig. 3A
); left blade broad, apex rounded (
Fig. 3C
), less sclerotised, almost parallel to abdominal axis; dorsally, tergite IX with pair of glandular openings in apex of short projections, lateral margins rounded, posterior margin slightly arcuate; tergite X large and produced into two unequal, asymmetrical, narrow and elongated lobes (
Fig. 3B–C
). Sternite VIII wider than long, ‘U’ shaped, asymmetrical, forming two narrow and very long asymmetrical lobes (
Fig. 3E
), sternite IX internalised, weakly sclerotised, elongate, flanking the aedeagus laterally to left inside abdomen.
</p>
      <p>
AEDEAGUS. Elongated and weakly sclerotised (
Fig. 3F–G
); left paramere absent, right paramere and prolongation of tegmen directed posteriorly. Right paramere elongated (
Fig. 3H
), ventral face with row of setae, apex flattened, forming rounded lobe; left prolongation of tegmen broad and lamellar (
Fig. 3J
), margins sinuous, apex rounded with tip pointing laterally. Median lobe membranous, short, not twisted, with its broad opening located apically.
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
Fig. 4–5
)
</p>
      <p>
HABITUS. Length 
7.4–7.6 mm
(n =2) (
Fig. 4A–C
).
</p>
      <p>
Similar to male, except for eyes slightly smaller (
Fig. 4D–E
), interocular distance across base of antennae 1.16 times wider than in male; elytra 0.32 times body length, 1.88 times the pronotum length; sternite VII variable (
Fig. 4G–H
), long and projecting posteriorly into 3 flattened lobes: 2 shorter pointed lobes laterally and medial lobe broad, parallel-sided, distal margin, with rounded notch (
Fig. 5A
); sometimes lateral lobes longer, almost as long as medial lobe, and distal margin of medial lobe truncate, not notched. Sternite VIII (
Fig. 5C
) almost completely concealed by sternite VII, membranous, broadly rounded, distal margin with broad rounded lobe projecting posteriorly; tergite VIII rounded on sides basally with wide and deep notch apically forming two apical lobes; coxites small (
Fig. 5E
), not fused medially, anterior arms very long and slender, apparently fused with valvifers, styles elongate, digitiform. Genitalia membranous (
Fig. 5F
); vagina long and broad; bursa copulatrix elongate, wrinkled, spiralling; spermatheca formed by two tubular projections; accessory gland large, connected by long winding duct to the postero-dorsal part of bursa copulatrix.
</p>
      <p>
Biological notes
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
The specimens were collected on walnut tree leaves (
<tp:taxon-name>
Juglans regia
</tp:taxon-name>
L.) infested with walnut aphids, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chromaphis juglandicola
(Kaltenbach, 1843)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Panaphis juglandis
(Goeze, 1778)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
India
(Baramulla, Kashmir) (
Fig. 8A–B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
