<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Evopharciceras formosum Korn &amp; Bockwinkel
            2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536119</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BAFC02FFD1FFC22233F9D398FCD95C</uri>
         <article-title>The pharciceratid ammonoids from the Roteisenstein Formation of Dillenburg
            (Cephalopoda, Ammonoidea)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.771.1503</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Evopharciceras formosum </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: F58EF052-3ED6-4798-81FC-D782A0CC08BF </p>
      <p> Figs 28–29 ; Tables 15–16 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Evopharciceras </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. with thinly discoidal, evolute
         conch at 35 mm dm (ww / dm ~ 0.35; uw/ dm ~0.50) and extremely discoidal, evolute conch at
         65 mm dm (ww /dm ~ 0.30; uw/ dm ~0.50). Whorl profile weakly depressed with convergent
         flanks and broadly rounded venter, umbilical wall steep. Growth lines rather coarse,
         strongly biconvex; ventrolateral shoulder with two spiral grooves in the middle growth
         stage. Outer suture line with high median saddle, symmetric, lanceolate prongs of the
         external lobe, a lanceolate, weakly pouched lateral lobe, a very narrow, acute and small U2
         lobe and a V-shaped U 4 lobe. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> Named after the Latin ‘ <tp:taxon-name> formosum </tp:taxon-name> ’, meaning ‘beautiful’,
         because of the decorated shell. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Holotype GERMANY • Rhenish Mountains , Oberscheld (Grube Beilstein);
            late Givetian (Red Ironstone); Lotz 1901–1902 Coll.; MB.C.30241 . ( Fig. 28A )
         </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Paratype GERMANY • 1 specimen ; Rhenish Mountains , Oberscheld
            (Grube Anna); late Givetian (Red Ironstone); Koch Coll.; MB.C.22173
         </tp:material-citation> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> Paratype MB.C.22173: Laterally deformed, but otherwise well-preserved specimen with 35 mm
         conch diameter in iron-rich micritic limestone. Most of the specimen is covered with shell;
         a quarter of the last volution belongs to the body chamber ( Fig. 28B ). It has a discoidal
         and evolute conch with low coiling rate ( Fig. 28B ); the whorl profile is subcircular with
         shallow umbilical wall, broadly rounded flanks and a broadly rounded venter. One faint
         ventrolateral spiral groove on each side separates flanks and venter. The ornament includes
         lamellar growth lines, which extend with low dorsolateral projection on the umbilical
         margin, a shallow lateral sinus, a prominent, narrow ventrolateral projection and a deep
         ventral sinus. </p>
      <p> The larger holotype MB.C.30241 is a laterally strongly deformed specimen with about 65 mm
         conch diameter in haematitic limestone, showing the suture line ( Fig. 28A ). It has a
         similar conch geometry, but is slightly slenderer. It displays the suture line, which has a
         rather narrow external lobe with high median saddle and narrow and slightly pouched,
         lanceolate prongs. The lateral lobe is also very narrow and lanceolate; the U2 lobe is very
         narrow and the U4 lobe is V-shaped and wider than the U2 lobe ( Fig. 29A ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p> Fig. 28. <tp:taxon-name> Evopharciceras formosum </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. A .
      Holotype MB.C.30241 (Lotz 1901–1902 Coll.) from Oberscheld (Beilstein Mine). B . Paratype
      MB.C.22173 (Koch Coll.) from Oberscheld (Anna Mine). Scale bar units = 1 mm. </p>
   <p> Table 15. Conch dimensions and ratios of selected specimens of <tp:taxon-name> Evopharciceras
         formosum </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </p>
   <p> Specimen dm ww wh uw ah ww / dm ww / wh uw / dm WER IZR MB.C.30241 62.6 18.4 18.3 31.5 14.7
      0.29 1.00 0.50 1.71 0.20 MB.C.22173 35.8 12.4 10.3 18.0 7.3 0.35 1.20 0.50 1.58 0.29 </p>
   <p> Table 16. Conch ontogeny of <tp:taxon-name> Evopharciceras formosum </tp:taxon-name> gen. et
      sp. nov. </p>
   <p> dm conch shape whorl cross section shape whorl expansion 35 mm thinly discoidal; evolute
      (ww/dm ~ 0.35; uw/dm ~ 0.50) weakly depressed; moderately embracing (ww/wh ~ 1.20; IZR ~ 0.25)
      low (WER ~ 1.55) 65 mm extremely discoidal; evolute (ww/dm ~ 0.30; uw/dm ~ 0.50) weakly
      depressed; moderately embracing (ww/wh ~ 1.00; IZR ~ 0.20) low (WER ~ 1.70) </p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Evopharciceras formosum </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. is similar to
            <tp:taxon-name> Extropharciceras metallicum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. but differs in the
         slightly stouter conch and the slightly narrower umbilicus. The suture line provides more
         specific criteria for the separation of the two species: while the E 2 , L and U 2 lobes
         are very narrow and lanceolate in <tp:taxon-name> Evopharciceras </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov.
         , they are wider and tongue- or V-shaped in <tp:taxon-name> Extropharciceras
         </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
