<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Zoosphaerium silens Wesener &amp;
                        Sagorny 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5076196</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BF4B62FFB0E0241C6DFEF38073F86F</uri>
                  <article-title>Seven new giant pill-millipede species and numerous new records of
                        the genus Zoosphaerium from Madagascar (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida,
                        Arthrosphaeridae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.758.1423</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium silens </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 2FA555CB-B805-401A-8730-6DFB6525C585 </p>
            <p> Figs 2B , 3 , 5B , 6 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> The posterior telopods ( Fig. 6H–I ) identify <tp:taxon-name> Z. silens
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. as a member of the <tp:taxon-name> Z. libidinosum
                  </tp:taxon-name> speciesgroup. <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium silens
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. shares the absence of locking carinae with a number of
                  spiny forest species. It differs from all other species except <tp:taxon-name> Z.
                        libidinosum </tp:taxon-name> in the color of the tergites, the glabrous anal
                  shield and the presence of at least two rows of very long endotergal bristles.
                        <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium silens </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. libidinosum </tp:taxon-name> in the wider tarsus (3.5
                  versus 3.8 times as long as wide), the presence of only two rows of endotergal
                  bristles (three rows in <tp:taxon-name> Z. libidinosum </tp:taxon-name> ) and the
                  absence of a lateral triangular projection on the third podomere of the anterior
                  telopods (present in <tp:taxon-name> Z. libidinosum </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Z. silens </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs by more than 14%
                  uncorrected p-distance in the COI gene from <tp:taxon-name> Z. album
                  </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Z. libidinosum </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>‘Silens’ (= ‘quiet’), noun in apposition, after the reduced stridulation ribs in the
                  male.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype MADAGASCAR – Toliara • ♂ ; Parc National de
                        Kirindy Mite , 25.6 km SW of Belo sur Mer ; 20°56.6′ S , 43°52.3′ E ; alt.
                        10 m ; dry deciduous forest; 9 Mar. 2007 ; V. Soarimalala leg.; coll. no.
                        VS- 1348; FMNH-INS 3119887 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratype MADAGASCAR – Toliara • ♀ ; same collection data as
                        for holotype; FMNH-INS 3119887 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> MADAGASCAR – Toliara • 4 ♂♂ ; Rèserve Spéciale
                        dʼAndranomena ; 20°10′31″ S , 44°28′25″ E ; alt. 18 m ; dry deciduous
                        forest; 12 Mar. 2010 ; V. Soarimalala leg.; coll. no. VS-1815; FMNH-INS
                        3119875 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same
                        collection data as for preceding; ZFMK MYR11137 </tp:material-citation> .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> BODY LENGTH. Largest female ( paratype ): length ca 27.2 mm , width of thoracic
                  shield 14.3 mm , of tergite 8 14.8 mm (widest), height of thoracic shield 8.2 mm ,
                  of tergite 8 10.1 mm (highest). </p>
            <p> COLORATION. Some discoloration may have occurred because of preservation in ethanol.
                  Tergites dorsally orange to brown, especially at posterior margin, laterally green
                  except for paratergite depressions which are yellow. Anal shield light brown to
                  yellowish dorsally as well as posteriorly, laterally green. Thoracic shield green,
                  but grooves and margins yellow-brownish ( Fig. 2B ). Head and antennae green, legs
                  basally light brown, apically green. </p>
            <p>HEAD. Wide and short. Eyes with&gt;75 ommatidia. Aberrant ocellus located in antennal
                  groove. Antennae short, with cylindrical joints, protruding posteriorly to leg
                  pair 3. Length of antennomeres 1= 2=3= 4=5&lt;6. A shallow groove present on
                  antennomere 1. Male apical disc with 11 or 12 apical sensory cones. Organ of
                  Tömösváry located in antennal groove.</p>
            <p>GNATHOCHILARIUM AND MANDIBLE. Not dissected.</p>
            <p> Fig. 6. <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium silens </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype
                  (FMNH-INS 3119887). A . Left coxa 2 with gonopore, posterior view. B . Left coxa 1
                  with stigmatic plate, posterior view. C . Left leg 9, posterior view. D . Left
                  anterior gonopod, posterior view. E . Left anterior gonopod, anterior view. F .
                  Left anterior gonopod, lateral view. G . Female subanal plate with washboard. H .
                  Right posterior telopod, posterior view. I . Right posterior telopod, anterior
                  view. J . Left female coxa 2 with vulva, posterior view. Abbreviations: as =
                  apical spine; cl = claw; cr-t = crenulated teeth; cx = coxa; ep = external plate;
                  gp = gonopore; ip = inner plate; o = operculum; pref = prefemur; s-ps =
                  sclerotized spots; sr =stridulation rib; st = stigmatic plate; syn = syncoxite; ta
                  = tarsus; vs = ventral spines. Roman numerals indicate telopoditomeres. Scale bars
                  = 1 mm. </p>
            <p> STIGMATIC PLATES. First plate triangular, apex well rounded, nearly as wide as at
                  base. Mesal margin slightly curved towards coxa. Hairs most abundant on apical
                  margin, very few hairs on basal and lateral margins ( Fig. 6B ). </p>
            <p>PLEURITES. First pleurite weakly modified, slightly extending posteriorly. Other
                  pleurites well-rounded.</p>
            <p>COLLUM. Glabrous with very sparse setae around margins, mostly located at corners on
                  either side of head.</p>
            <p>THORACIC SHIELD. Smooth and glabrous, without protuberances.</p>
            <p>TERGITES. Surface glabrous and matte, lacking small pits. Tips of paratergites of
                  midbody tergites projecting posteriorly.</p>
            <p> ENDOTERGUM. Inner section with numerous short triangular spines and very few longer
                  setae. Middle area above spines with a single row of sparse elliptical cuticular
                  impressions slightly varying in size. Apically two rows of dense marginal
                  bristles, every second bristle strongly protruding above tergite margin ( Fig. 5B
                  ). Bristles with numerous small spines. </p>
            <p>ANAL SHIELD. Large and well-rounded. In both sexes glabrous. Underside lacking
                  locking carinae.</p>
            <p> LEGS. Leg 1 with 1 ventral spine, leg 2 with 1, leg 3 with 5 or 6. First two leg
                  pairs without an apical spine, spine present on leg 3. Leg pairs 4–21 with 8–10
                  ventral spines and an apical spine. On leg 9, femur 1.7 and tarsus 3.5 times as
                  long as wide. All podomeres with setae ( Fig. 6C ). </p>
            <p> Male sexual characters </p>
            <p> GONOPORE. Covered with a single undivided, rounded membranous plate, very wide,
                  located on basal half of coxa ( Fig. 6A ). </p>
            <p> ANTERIOR TELOPODS. Harp with two weak stridulation ribs ( Fig. 6E ). First podomere
                  with numerous setae mainly at lateral margin, as wide as long. Process of second
                  podomere as long as basal fifth of third podomere, not visible in anterior view,
                  with apical mound of a few sclerotized spots juxtaposed to third podomere. Third
                  podomere with an apical sclerotized spot and a lateral crenulated tooth, mesally
                  with an elevated area carrying sclerotized spots ( Fig. 6D, F ); lower area
                  carrying 4 spines ( Fig. 6D, F ). Second and third podomeres sparsely setose. </p>
            <p>POSTERIOR TELOPODS.Movable finger weakly curved; hollowed-out inner margin with two
                  non-sclerotized lobes and ca five smaller sclerotized spines, posterior aspect
                  with ca 15 large crenulated teeth. Fixed finger wider than movable finger, with
                  slightly curved tip; basally with single membranous lobe, on inner margin covered
                  with a few sclerotized spots. Second and third podomeres lacking long hair, almost
                  completely glabrous. First podomere glabrous except for a few setae at mesal
                  margin.</p>
            <p> Female sexual characters </p>
            <p> Washboard with two short interrupted stridulation ribs on each half ( Fig. 6G ).
                  Vulva covering more than ⅔ of coxa surface. Operculum large, ending before coxal
                  margin. Apical margin of operculum wellrounded, reaching apicalmost point
                  medially. Mesal plate reaching up to half of operculumʼs height ( Fig. 6J ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution and ecology </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium silens </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is currently known
                  from the western dry forest of Kirindy-Mite as well as from the dry forest of
                  Andranomena further north ( Fig. 3 ). These populations differ by an uncorrected
                  p-distance of 2.8% ( Table 2 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
