<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Zoosphaerium
                        coquerelianum</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5076198</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BF4B62FFAFE0271C0CFEF38716F81C</uri>
                  <article-title>Seven new giant pill-millipede species and numerous new records of
                        the genus Zoosphaerium from Madagascar (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida,
                        Arthrosphaeridae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.758.1423</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium coquerelianum </tp:taxon-name> species-group </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Species can be identified as members of the <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium
                        coquerelianum </tp:taxon-name> species-group based on morphological
                  characters of the posterior telopods ( Wesener &amp; Wägele 2008 ; Wesener 2009).
                  Telopoditomere 3 only carries small sclerotized teeth and is always slightly
                  longer and&gt;1.5 times as wide as the immovable finger. Similar telopod
                  characters occur in some members of the <tp:taxon-name> Z. platylabum
                  </tp:taxon-name> species-group, but the locking carinae in this group are located
                  close to the last pleurites, while they are positioned close to the anal shield
                  margin in species of the <tp:taxon-name> Z. coquerelianum </tp:taxon-name> group.
                  The speciesgroup now contains 23 described species distributed in humid to
                  subhumid forests all over Madagascar . Species of this group are conspicuously
                  absent from the spiny forest ecosystem and the western dry forest (Wesener 2009;
                  Wesener et al. 2010b ; Sagorny &amp; Wesener 2017 ; Wesener &amp; Anilkumar 2020
                  ). </p>
            <p> Key to the species of the <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium coquerelianum
                  </tp:taxon-name> group </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p> 1. Male harp with two to three stridulation
                  ribs..................................................................................2 </p>
            <p> – Male harp with a single stridulation
                  rib........................................................................................11 </p>
            <p> 2. Tergites glossy, anteriorly shiny light green, posteriorly dark green. Specimen
                  more than 50 mm long. Anal shield not well-rounded, with steep slope. Movable
                  finger of posterior telopods 1.6 times as long as wide, apically with groove
                  ...................................................... <tp:taxon-name> Z. amabile
                        Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Coloration pattern different, or if similar then specimens less than 35 mm long.
                  Anal shield wellrounded or bell-shaped. Movable finger of posterior telopods
                  1.9–2.5 times as long as wide, without apical
                  groove.........................................................................................................................3 </p>
            <p> 3. Antenna with four apical
                  cones.......................................................................................................4 </p>
            <p> – Antenna with&gt;10 apical
                  cones......................................................................................................5 </p>
            <p> 4. Anal shield surface covered with short hairs. Posterior locking carina of anal
                  shield 2.5–3 times as long as anterior carina
                  ............................................. <tp:taxon-name> Z. alluaudi (de
                        Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1902 ) </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Anal shield surface glabrous. Posterior locking carina of anal shield more than
                  3.5 times as long as anterior carina .............................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. voeltzkowianum (de Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897 )
                  </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> 5. Male harp with three stridulation ribs. Endotergum with three rows of marginal
                  bristles, bristles slightly extending beyond tergite. Sclerotized teeth present on
                  antennomeres 1–5. Movable finger of posterior telopods 2 times as long as wide.
                  Posterior locking carina of anal shield four times as long as anterior carina.
                  Male anal shield bell-shaped ....... <tp:taxon-name> Z. trichordum Wesener, 2009
                  </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Male harp with two stridulation ribs. Endotergum with one up to two rows of
                  marginal bristles, bristles not reaching tergite margin. Sclerotized teeth only
                  present up to antennomere 3 or 4......6 </p>
            <p> 6. Only up to eight ventral spines on walking
                  legs.............................................................................7 </p>
            <p> – At least nine ventral spines on walking
                  legs.................................................................................8 </p>
            <p> 7. Movable finger of posterior telopod thick, 2.5 times as long as wide. Leg 3 with
                  an apical spine. On anal shield, second locking carina 2–3 times as long as first
                  ............ <tp:taxon-name> Z. ambatovaky </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </p>
            <p> – Movable finger of posterior telopod very thick, 2 times as long as wide. Leg 3
                  without an apical spine. On anal shield, second locking carina 4–5 times as long
                  as first ..............................................
                  .........................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. muscorum Wesener &amp; Bespalova, 2010 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> 8. Male anal shield well-rounded, with slight bell shape. Posterior locking carina
                  of anal shield six times as long as anterior carina. Up to 10 ventral spines on
                  walking legs ..............................
                  ....................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. bambusoides Wesener &amp; Bespalova, 2010
                  </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Male anal shield well-rounded. Posterior locking carina of anal shield three to
                  four times as long as anterior carina. Usually more than 10 ventral spines on
                  walking legs.............................9 </p>
            <p> 9. Leg 3 without an apical spine. Specimens only slightly more than 30 mm long.
                  Tergites jadelike green with thin brown posterior margin, texture glossy.
                  Operculum of vulva deeply notched, strongly extending beyond coxa. Apical disc
                  with ca 14 apical cones ...............................................
                  ..........................................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. smaragdinum Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Leg 3 with an apical spine. Specimens more than 50 mm long. Tergites never
                  jade-like, not glossy. Operculum of vulva not protruding above coxal margin.
                  Apical disc with more than 20 apical
                  cones................................................................................................................................................10 </p>
            <p> 10. Specimens more than 60 mm long. Tergites dark-green, covered with numerous large
                  pits and short setae. Sclerotized teeth present on antennomeres 1–3, disc with ca
                  45 apical cones. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles .........
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. villosum Wesener &amp; Sierwald, 2005 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Specimens less than 60 mm long. Tergites light-brown, glabrous. Sclerotized teeth
                  present on antennomeres 1–4, disc with 20–30 apical cones. Endotergum with a
                  single row of marginal bristles
                  ..............................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. bemanevika Sagorny &amp; Wesener, 2017 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> 11. Movable finger 3 times as long as wide
                  ................................................ <tp:taxon-name> Z. ambrense
                        Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Movable finger &lt;2.5 times as long as
                  wide....................................................................................12 </p>
            <p> 12. Antenna with four apical cones. Movable finger of posterior telopods at inner
                  margin with two membranous
                  lobes...........................................................................................................................13 </p>
            <p> – Antenna with&gt;10 apical cones. Movable finger of posterior telopods at inner
                  margin with a single membranous
                  lobe............................................................................................................................17 </p>
            <p> 13. Process of second podomere of anterior telopod not visible in anterior view.
                  Fifth antennomere with a field of sensilla basiconica. Collum with isolated, long
                  setae. Endotergum with one row of large cuticular impressions and a second row of
                  much smaller impressions; bristles long, strongly protruding above tergite
                  ........................................................... <tp:taxon-name> Z.
                        bilobum Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Process of second podomere of anterior telopod visible in anterior
                  view.................................14 </p>
            <p> 14. Podomere 3 of anterior telopod with crenulated
                  teeth...................................................................15 </p>
            <p> – Podomere 3 of anterior telopod without crenulated
                  teeth.............................................................16 </p>
            <p> 15. Collum glabrous, with a few setae at corners on either side of head. Endotergum
                  with two rows of regularly distributed circular impressions, marginal bristles
                  strongly protruding above tergite. Sensilla basiconica present on antennomeres 1
                  and 2. Anal shield weakly bellshaped
                  ................................................................ <tp:taxon-name>
                        Z. trigrioculatum Wesener &amp; Bespalova, 2010 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Collum glabrous, anterior margin with two rows of setae. Endotergum with a single
                  row of elliptical cuticular impression, marginal bristles protruding to margin.
                  Sensilla basiconica absent. Anal shield well rounded
                  .................................. <tp:taxon-name> Z. bartolozzi Anilkumar &amp;
                        Wesener, 2020 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> 16. Collum glabrous. Endotergum with a single row of large cuticular impressions,
                  marginal bristles slightly protruding above tergite margin. Second leg with 4 or 5
                  ventral spines. Anal shield tapering
                  ........................................................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. isalo Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Collum glabrous. Endotergum with a single row of slightly rounded elliptical
                  cuticular impressions, marginal bristles protruding to margin. Second leg with 6
                  or 7 ventral spines. Anal shield well rounded
                  .................................................................. <tp:taxon-name>
                        Z. taiti Anilkumar &amp; Wesener, 2020 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> 17. First pair of stigmatic plates greatly enlarged, with a well-rounded
                  tip......................................18 </p>
            <p> – First pair of stigmatic plates triangular, tapering towards
                  tip.......................................................19 </p>
            <p> 18. Operculum of vulva ending clearly before coxal margin, deeply notched, divided
                  into two large, well-rounded, similar-sized lobes. Third podomere of anterior
                  telopod laterally with ca five large sclerotized teeth. Sensilla basiconica on
                  first antennomere absent. Posterior locking carina of anal shield two times as
                  long as anterior carina.Endotergal marginal bristles protruding up to tergite
                  margin. Movable finger of posterior telopods thick, 1.9 times as long as wide
                  ...... <tp:taxon-name> Z. tampolo Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Operculum of vulva ending before coxal margin, elongated into a single median
                  lobe, lobe only shallowly notched at tip. Third podomere of anterior telopod
                  without any large sclerotized teeth. Sensilla basiconica on first antennomere
                  present. Locking carinae of anal shield of equal length. Endotergal marginal
                  bristles very short, ending far before tergite margin. Movable finger of posterior
                  telopods thick, 2.1 times as long as wide ............... <tp:taxon-name> Z.
                        ignotum Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> 19. Tergite texture orange-peel like. Collum covered with isolated, long hairs. Body
                  size of adult female&gt; 50 mm . Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles and
                  a single row of large circular cuticular
                  impressions........................................................................................................20 </p>
            <p> – Tergite texture glossy or smooth. Collum glabrous. Body size of adults &lt; 35 mm
                  . Endotergum with a single row of marginal bristles and either without or with two
                  rows of cuticular
                  impressions.........................................................................................................................................22 </p>
            <p> 20. Posterior locking carina on anal shield 2.5 times as long as anterior carina.
                  Third podomere of anterior telopods without large sclerotized teeth. Anal shield
                  glabrous ............................................
                  ...........................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. coquerelianum (de Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897 )
                  </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Posterior locking carina on anal shield&gt;4 times as long as anterior carina.
                  Third podomere of anterior telopods with at least three large sclerotized teeth.
                  Anal shield covered with short
                  hair.............................................................................................................................................21 </p>
            <p> 21. Third podomere on anterior telopods with 3 or 4 crenulated teeth. Endotergal
                  marginal bristles very short, protruding up to ⅓ of distance to tergite margin.
                  Tips of vulvar operculum widely separated
                  .................................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. mangabe Wesener, 2020 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Third podomere on anterior telopods with ca seven large sclerotized teeth.
                  Endotergal marginal bristles protruding up to tergite margin. Tips of vulvar
                  operculum fused ......................................
                  .............................................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. tainkintana Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> 22. Tergites glossy. Female anal shield bell-shaped, in male with steep slope. Fixed
                  finger of posterior telopods wide, only slightly curved towards movable finger.
                  Movable finger 1.8 times as long as wide, on posterior side with ten small
                  sclerotized teeth. Sclerotized teeth on antenna only present on first antennomere.
                  Endotergum without cuticular impressions ......... <tp:taxon-name> Z. viridissimum
                        Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Tergites matte. Anal shield well-rounded. Fixed finger of posterior telopods
                  slender, strongly curved towards movable finger. Movable finger 2.4 times as long
                  as wide, on posterior side with ca 25 small sclerotized teeth. Sclerotized teeth
                  present on antennomeres 1–3. Endotergum with a single row of large and a second
                  row of smaller circular cuticular impressions ...............
                  .........................................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. denticulatum Wesener, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
