<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Zoosphaerium ambatovaky Wesener
                        &amp; Sagorny 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5076200</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BF4B62FFAAE0221C43FEF3806DF855</uri>
                  <article-title>Seven new giant pill-millipede species and numerous new records of
                        the genus Zoosphaerium from Madagascar (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida,
                        Arthrosphaeridae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.758.1423</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium ambatovaky </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 42C1A931-D533-4FF6-B76A-CAB8F7E1461D </p>
            <p> Figs 2C , 3 , 5C , 7 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> The presence of only 7 or 8 ventral spines on the walking legs in <tp:taxon-name> Z.
                        ambatovaky </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , especially in combination with a
                  glossy green color, two stridulation ribs on the male harp and more than 10 apical
                  cones on the antenna, is only shared with <tp:taxon-name> Z. muscorum Wesener
                        &amp; Bespalova, 2010 </tp:taxon-name> . The new species differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> Z. muscorum </tp:taxon-name> in the presence of an apical
                  spine on the third leg pair (absent in <tp:taxon-name> Z. muscorum
                  </tp:taxon-name> ), the movable finger of the posterior telopod being 2.5 times as
                  long as wide (2 times as long as wide in <tp:taxon-name> Z. muscorum
                  </tp:taxon-name> ) and the second locking carina of the anal shield being 2–3
                  times as long as the first (4–5 times as long as the first in <tp:taxon-name> Z.
                        muscorum </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> ‘Ambatovaky’, noun in apposition, after the forest of Ambatovaky, the only known
                  locality for this species ( Fig. 3 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype MADAGASCAR – Toamasina • ♂ ; Rés. Speciale
                        Ambatovaky , Sandrangato River ; 16°46′22″ S , 49°15′56″ E ; alt. 450 m ;
                        rainforest; 20 Feb. 2010 ; B.L. Fisher et al. leg.; coll. no. BLF24311;
                        CASENT 9068294 /1. </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> BODY LENGTH. Holotype male: length ca 44 mm , width of thoracic shield 23.1 mm , of
                  tergite 5 24.4 mm (widest), height of thoracic shield 14.1 mm (highest). </p>
            <p> COLORATION. Some discoloration may have occurred because of preservation in ethanol.
                  Head, collum, thoracic shield and tergites shiny green with a conspicuous narrow
                  light posterior margin ( Fig. 2C ). Anal shield of a different color, jade-like
                  green. Antennae green, legs basally dark green, apically brownish. </p>
            <p>HEAD. Eyes with&gt; 95 ommatidia. Antennae long, with cylindrical joints, protruding
                  posteriorly to leg pair 4. Length of antennomeres 1&gt;2&gt; 3=4= 5&lt;6. A
                  shallow groove present on antennomere 1. Male apical disc with 45/35 apical
                  sensory cones. Organ of Tömösváry located in antennal groove.</p>
            <p>GNATHOCHILARIUM AND MANDIBLE. Not dissected.</p>
            <p> STIGMATIC PLATES. First stigmatic plate triangular, apex well rounded, nearly as
                  wide as at base, slightly turned towards coxa. Hair most abundant on apical
                  margin, very few hairs on basal and lateral margins ( Fig. 7C ). </p>
            <p>PLEURITES. First pleurite well-rounded, not projecting.</p>
            <p>COLLUM. Glabrous.</p>
            <p>THORACIC SHIELD. Smooth and glabrous, without protuberances.</p>
            <p> Fig. 7. <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium ambatovaky </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype
                  (CASENT 9068291). A . Left leg 9, posterior view. B . Left coxa 2 with gonopore,
                  posterior view. C . Left coxa 1 with stigmatic plate, posterior view. D . Left
                  anterior gonopod, anterior view. E . Left anterior gonopod, posterior view. F .
                  Left anterior gonopod, lateral view. G . Left female coxa 2 with vulva, posterior
                  view. H . Female subanal plate with washboard. I . Right posterior telopod,
                  posterior view. J . Right posterior telopod, anterior view. Abbreviations: as =
                  apical spine; cl = claw; cr-t = crenulated teeth; cx = coxa; ep = external plate;
                  fe = femur; gp = gonopore; ip = inner plate; o = operculum; pof = postfemur; pref
                  = prefemur; s-ps = sclerotized spots; sr = stridulation rib; st = stigmatic plate;
                  ta = tarsus; ti = tibia; vs = ventral spines. Roman numerals indicate
                  telopoditomeres. Scale bars = 1 mm. </p>
            <p>TERGITES. Surface glabrous and shiny, lacking small pits. Tips of paratergites of
                  midbody tergites projecting posteriorly.</p>
            <p> ENDOTERGUM. Inner section with numerous short triangular spines and longer setae.
                  Middle area above spines with a single row of sparse circular cuticular
                  impressions slightly varying in size. Apically with 1–2 rows of short marginal
                  bristles, protruding to ⅔ of distance of tergite margin ( Fig. 5C ). Bristles with
                  numerous small spines. </p>
            <p>ANAL SHIELD. Male anal shield bell-shaped, without hairs, glabrous. Underside with
                  two black locking carinae, posterior one 2–3 times as long as anterior one, both
                  located close to anal shield margin.</p>
            <p>LEGS. Leg 1 with 4 ventral spines, leg 2 with 6 or 7, leg 3 with 6. First two leg
                  pairs without an apical spine, spine present on leg 3. Leg pairs 4–21 with 7 or 8
                  ventral spines and an apical spine. On leg 9, femur 2 and tarsus 4.5 times as long
                  as wide. All podomeres with setae (Fig.).</p>
            <p> Male sexual characters </p>
            <p> GONOPORE. Covered with a single undivided, rounded membranous plate, covering ¼ of
                  surface of coxa. Gonopore located on basal half of joint ( Fig. 7B ). </p>
            <p> ANTERIOR TELOPODS. Harp with two stridulation ribs, one long and well pronounced rib
                  located laterally of a less pronounced and shorter mesal rib ( Fig. 7D ). First
                  podomere with only a few setae, restricted to apical parts of lateral margins, 1.5
                  times as wide as long. Process of second podomere nearly as long as basal ⅔ of
                  third podomere, not visible in anterior view, and with an apical mound of a few
                  sclerotized spots juxtaposed to third podomere ( Fig. 7E–F ). Third podomere with
                  an apical brown sclerotized spot and a field of elevated sclerotized spots at
                  inner margin below brown spot; two small spines located below sclerotized spot (
                  Fig. 7F ); depression lateral to field of spots with one small sclerotized spine,
                  lateral margin with up to 6 crenulated teeth ( Fig. 7E–F ). Second podomere
                  densely setose, third podomere with setae mainly apically and laterally. </p>
            <p> POSTERIOR TELOPODS. Movable finger (podomere 3) 2.5 times as long as wide, weakly
                  curved towards immovable finger (process of podomere 2). Shallowly hollowed-out
                  inner margin with five sclerotized spines, three positioned apically and two in
                  middle of cavity next to small membranous lobe. Additional sclerotized spine at
                  base of movable finger. Posterior aspect with ca 12 small crenulated teeth ( Fig.
                  7H ). Immovable finger thinner and shorter than movable finger, curved towards the
                  latter. Sclerotized spine located on anterior side near base of immovable finger.
                  Inner part of immovable finger apically covered with a few sclerotized spots (
                  Fig. 7I ). Movable finger glabrous on both sides except for a few hairs
                  basolaterally. Second podomere in posterior view setose, in anterior view with a
                  few setae on finger. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution and ecology </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Zoosphaerium ambatovaky </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is currently
                  known only from the type locality, a lowland rainforest close to the Ille Sainte
                  Marie ( Fig. 3 ). This species seems to be closely related to <tp:taxon-name> Z.
                        muscorum </tp:taxon-name> from the montane forest of Anjanaharibe-Sud, the
                  only species with which it shares the presence of only 7 or 8 ventral spines on
                  the walking legs, as well as a glossy green color, two stridulation ribs on the
                  male harp and more than 10 apical cones on the antenna. A female <tp:taxon-name>
                        Zoosphaerium </tp:taxon-name> from the same forest (CASENT 9068291B) belongs
                  to a different species. The forest of Ambatovaky is isolated and shrinking rapidly
                  ( Rakotondrasoa et al. 2017 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
