<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Zoosphaerium piligerum</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5076212</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03BF4B62FF9FE0151C2CFEF38716FB69</uri>
         <article-title>Seven new giant pill-millipede species and numerous new records of the genus Zoosphaerium from Madagascar (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida, Arthrosphaeridae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.758.1423</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Zoosphaerium piligerum
</tp:taxon-name>
species-group

</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Species can be identified as members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Z. piligerum
</tp:taxon-name>
species-group based on morphological characters of the posterior telopods (
Wesener &amp; Wägele 2008
), which are slender and greatly elongated. The species-group now contains four described species distributed in the eastern rainforests at higher elevations (Wesener 2009).
</p>
      <p>

Key to species of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zoosphaerium piligerum
</tp:taxon-name>
species-group

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Antenna with four apical cones. Endotergum without cuticular impressions. Third podomere of anterior telopods lateral of cavity without sclerotized teeth. Body length &lt;
20 mm
. Movable finger of posterior telopods&gt;4.5 times as long as wide ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Z. micropiligerum
Wesener, 2009
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Antenna with&gt;10 apical cones. Endotergum with a single row of circular cuticular impressions. Third podomere of anterior telopods with at least two large, sclerotized teeth. Body length of mature females&gt; 
35 mm
. Movable finger of posterior telopods ≤ 3.5 times as long as wide.......2

</p>
      <p>

2. Anal shield bell-shaped. Posterior telopod fixed finger strongly curved, ca 25% shorter than movable finger. Operculum of vulva protruding above coxal margin. Endotergum with two rows of marginal bristles, slightly extending beyond tergite margin ......................................................... ..................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Z. piligerum
(de 
Saussure &amp; Zehntner, 1897
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Anal shield well rounded. Posterior telopod fixed finger slightly curved, only slightly shorter than movable finger. Operculum of vulva not reaching coxal margin. Endotergum with a single row of marginal bristles, not reaching tergite margin.....................................................................3
</p>
      <p>

3. Tergites matte, covered with short setae, dark brown. Third podomere of anterior telopods laterally with 3 or 4 crenulated teeth. Legs with 10–12 ventral spines ................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Z. spinopiligerum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Tergites glossy, black. Third podomere of anterior telopods laterally with 1 or 2 crenulated teeth. Legs with 8 or 9 ventral spines ..................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Z. pseudopiligerum
Wesener, 2009
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
