<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophryotrocha lipscombae Lu &amp; Fauchald 2000</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4570315</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03C5B70FE948FFABFE6788E46C43F992</uri>
         <article-title>Four new species and further records of Dorvilleidae (Annelida, Polychaeta) from deep-sea organic substrata, NE Atlantic</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Ophryotrocha
cf. 
lipscombae
Lu &amp; Fauchald, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 9
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophryotrocha lipscombae
Lu &amp; Fauchald, 2000: 486
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1–4 (
type
locality: continental slope 
110 miles
south of Woods Hole, 
Massachusetts
, NW Atlantic, depth 
1830 m
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MOROCCO
• 
1 spec.
(formalin); GoC, Mercator MV; 
35°17.916′ N
, 
06°38.709′ W
; 

354 m
depth

; 

2 Mar. 2008

; Stn 64PE284_12750W; 
wood substratum
; 
DBUA0002284.01
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
PORTUGAL
• 
51 specs
(2 hologenophores, 49 paragenophores; ethanol); WIM, Estremadura Spur; 
39°17.295′ N
, 
10°01.045′ W
; 

327 m
depth

; 

1 Jun. 2017

; Stn PES_ROVL17D01-pick#3W; 
wood substrata
; 
DBUA0002285.01
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description of the material examined in this study
</p>
      <p>
Body robust and compact (
Fig. 9A
), with the same width throughout, only tapering at the pygidium. Largest specimen 
2.5mm
long and 
0.43 mm
wide for 38 chaetigers (
Fig. 3
).All segments with a transversal band of cilia. Prostomium short, broadly rounded, slightly trilobed (more evident in smaller specimens; 
Fig. 9B
), without eyes. Antennae and palps spherical, very small, may appear to be absent (only visible under the microscope). Peristomium achaetous, with two rings half the length of the following segments. Delimitation between the prostomium and the first ring of the peristomium almost imperceptible. Jaw apparatus dark and relatively large (
Fig. 9B
). Mandibles rod-like; in larger specimens, the anterior end is cut in two levels, with the inner lower level toothed (teeth often worn) (
Fig. 9
C–E); in smaller specimens, the anterior end of mandibulae is mainly straight with small elevations at the outer tips and distinctly toothed (
Fig. 9I
). Maxillae with a pair of falcate forceps (
Fig. 9F
), seven pairs of free denticles (D1–7) (
Fig. 9
G–H) and five pairs of accessory plates (
Fig. 9
; the fifth plate was lost when detachjing the denticles, 
Fig. 9
G–H)); forceps with a main fang followed by 1–2 large and several very small teeth (
Fig. 9J
); D1 comb-like, with about 18 large and small teeth alternating (
Fig. 9F
); distal denticles plate-like, with up to 8 large and small teeth irregularly alternating (
Fig. 9
G–H). Parapodia uniramous, with broadly conical acicular lobes, sub-acicular lobes and ovoid dorsal cirri fused to the acicular lobe (
Fig. 9N
); ventral cirri apparently absent. Aciculae slightly protruding in all parapodia. Sub-acicular lobes with harpoon-like protruding acicula with acute tip and subdistal tooth (
Fig. 9M
). Supra-acicular chaetae simple, subdistally serrated, tapering abruptly into a large main fang (
Fig. 9
K–L). Sub-acicular chaetae compound with very short serrated blades abruptly tapering into a main fang; heterogomph shafts distally serrated (
Fig. 9O
). Pygidium with terminal anus and 2 very small ovoid anal cirri.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophryotrocha lipscombae
Lu &amp;Fauchald, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
(DBUA0002285.01). Stereo (A–B) and compound (C–O) microscope images. 
A
. Complete specimen, dorsal view. 
B
. Prostomium of a smaller specimen, ventral view. 
C
. Mandibular and maxillary apparatus, ventral view. 
D–E
. Anterior tip of mandible of larger specimens. 
F
. Maxillary carrier, forceps and basal denticles, dorsal view. 
G–H
. Maxillarydistal denticles and accessory plates from right and left sides, respectively. 
I
. Anterior tip of mandible of smaller specimen. 
J
. Maxillary forceps and basal denticles, dorsal view. 
K–L
. Supra-acicular chaetae, mid-body parapodium. 
M
. Sub-acicular hook, mid-body parapodium. 
N
. Anterior parapodium, posterior view. 
O
. Sub-acicular chaetae, mid-body parapodium. Number 1 refers to free denticle 1.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophryotrocha lipscombae
</tp:taxon-name>
is only known from its original description based on specimens collected from Woods Hole (NW Atlantic) at a depth of 
1830 m
(
Lu &amp; Fauchald 2000
). This species is considered to be unique among the dorvilleids based on the presence of five pairs of accessory plates associated with the denticles of the maxillae (
Lu &amp; Fauchald 2000
). Other distinctive characteristics are the presence of teeth below the main fang of the maxillary forceps and the clear fusion between the prostomium and the peristomium. All these characteristics are present in the specimens from the 
Estremadura
Spur (WIM, NE Atlantic) and the single specimen from Mercator MV (GoC, NE Atlantic) examined in this study. The minor differences registered for the specimens from the NW Atlantic concern features that may have been overlooked or misinterpreted, such as: the absence of distal teeth on the mandibulae of larger specimens, which may be worn (in our specimens these teeth are mostly worn and the ones that are present are difficult to detect); the absence of prostomial palps (in our specimens the antennae and palps are tiny and could only be detected under the optical microscope); the absence of dorsal cirri on parapodia (in our specimens the dorsal cirri appear almost entirely fused with the acicular lobes and thus are difficult to distinguish (
Fig. 9N
); figure 1d of the original description illustrates a similar structure); and the tips of the supra- and sub-acicular chaetae, which in our specimens are more abruptly tapered into a distinct main fang (only visible under high magnification). The phylogenetic analysis segregates this species from the others within the tree (
Fig. 2
). The two sequenced specimens were from WIM, the K2P value from the H3 alignment between the two specimens is 0.00 and the K2P values to the nearest species in the tree, 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. maculata
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. hartmanni
</tp:taxon-name>
, is 0.09. However, there are no DNA sequences for the West Atlantic 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. lipscombae
</tp:taxon-name>
specimens to compare with. Furthermore, it was not possible to examine the 
type
material that is deposited in the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History. If the similarity at the morphological and molecular level is confirmed, then this study extends the geographic and upper limit of the bathymetric distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. lipscombae
</tp:taxon-name>
to the NE Atlantic and to a depth of 

327 m
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology and distribution
</p>
      <p>
NE Atlantic specimens: from the 
Estremadura
Spur (West Iberian Margin) to the Gulf of Cadiz (Moroccan Margin) in wood substrata, at 
327–354 m
depth (present study).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Original distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. lipscombae
: NW
</tp:taxon-name>
Atlantic, south of Woods Hole, in sediment, at a depth of 
1830 m
(
Lu &amp; Fauchald 2000
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
