<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophryotrocha scutellus Wiklund, Glover &amp;
            Dahlgren 2009</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4570321</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03C5B70FE94EFFA2FE3588BD6D83F83E</uri>
         <article-title>Four new species and further records of Dorvilleidae (Annelida, Polychaeta)
            from deep-sea organic substrata, NE Atlantic</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Ophryotrocha scutellus Wiklund, Glover &amp; Dahlgren, 2009 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Figs 11–12 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> MOROCCO • 11specs (plus2cf.)(formalin), 2specs (slide
            preparation);GoC,Mercator MV; 35°17.916′N , 06°38.709′ W ; 354 m ; 2 Mar. 2008 ; Stn
            64PE284_12750W; wood substrata ; DBUA0002288.01 </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 1 spec. cf. (formalin); same locality as for preceding; 3 Mar.
            2008 ; Stn 64PE284_12752A; alfalfa substratum ; DBUA0002288.02 </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 1 spec. (ethanol); same collection data as for preceding; 19 May
            2009 ; Stn B09- 14b_01W; wood substratum ; DBUA0002287.05 </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 1 spec. (ethanol), 7 specs (formalin), 3 specs (slide
            preparation); GoC, Meknès MV; 34°59.091′ N , 07°04.424′ W ; 698 m ; 20 May 2009 ; Stn
            B09-14b_03W; wood substrata ; DBUA0002287.03 </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 3 specs (ethanol), 1 spec. (formalin); same locality and date as
            for preceding; Stn B09-14b_03A; alfalfa substrata ; DBUA0002287.04
         </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 4 specs (ethanol), 1 spec. (formalin), 1
            spec. (slide preparation, hologenophore); GoC, Darwin MV; 35°23.523′ N , 07°11.513′ W ;
            1100 m ; 19 May 2009 ; Stn B09-14b_02A; alfalfa substrata ; DBUA0002287.01
         </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 spec. (ethanol); same locality and date
            as for preceding; Stn B09-14b_02C; carbonate substratum ; DBUA0002287.02
         </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      <p> Additional material </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> PORTUGAL • 6 specs (ethanol); WIM, Setúbal Canyon ; 38°16.856′ N ,
            09°06.734′ W ; 1000 m depth ; 22 Aug. 2012 ; on bone material from a cow carcass;
            DBUA0001557.01-02 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> SWEDEN • 12 specs (ethanol); coastal Skagerrak ; 58°53.1′ N ,
            11°06.4′ E ; 125 m depth ; on bone material from a minke whale carcass; DBUA0002348
         </tp:material-citation> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description (amended) </p>
      <p> Size of WIM and GoC specimens varies within 1.55–2.70 mm long and 0.24–0.39 mm wide for
         18–24 chaetigers. Skagerrak specimens are larger, up to 3.60 mm long and 0.75 mm wide for
         31 chaetigers ( Fig. 3 ). Body dorso-ventrally flattened, with similar width throughout the
         body, abruptly ending with pygidium in smaller specimens ( Fig. 11A ) or tapering slightly
         at posterior end in larger ones. Prostomium broadly rounded, dorso-ventrally flattened,
         with a transverse ridge between the antennae, without eyes ( Fig. 11A ). Antennae and palps
         long, digitiform; antennae inserted mid-dorsally on the prostomium; palps inserted
         laterally. Peristomium achaetous, with two rings slightly narrower and shorter than the
         following segments. Jaw apparatus heavily sclerotized, well visible through the specimen
         body, usually with an apparent rhombus shape ( Fig. 11 A–B).The morphology of mandibles and
         maxillary forceps varies with the specimen size ( Fig. 12 A–J). Mandibles rod-like; smaller
         specimens with straight and clearly dentate anterior end and long apophyse, well surpassing
         the cutting edge, with a diagonal connection to the shaft ( Fig. 12A ); with growth, the
         teeth wear out ( Fig. 12B ) and the cutting edge becomes short and more curved forward,
         without teeth, the apophyse becomes thicker with an almost vertical connection to the shaft
         ( Fig. 12 D–E). Maxillae of P-type; forceps falcate, comb-like, slightly wider with up to
         20 large teeth on the right side, and narrower with up to 26 thinner teeth on the left side
         ( Fig. 12 F–G); with growth, the teeth of the left forcep become irregular ( Fig. 12H )
         resulting in a clear alternation in size in larger specimens ( Figs 11D , 12 I–J); eleven
         free denticles (D1–11), D1 similar to forceps (always with even teeth), D2 to D11
         shovel-like, D4 to D11 usually directed inwards ( Fig. 11 H–I); carrierlike structure with
         a toothed ridge on each side near the forceps (see details in Fig. 11D ) and with a
         posteriorly fimbriate handle ( Fig. 11D ). Parapodia uniramous ( Fig. 11C ); pre-chaetal
         lamellae of median parapodia very long, cirriform; dorsal and ventral cirri digitiform,
         long (dorsal longer than ventral); sub-acicular lobes conical, about two-thirds the length
         of pre-chaetal lamellae in smaller specimens, becoming shorter in larger specimens ( Fig.
         12 K–N), with a needle-like acicula ( Fig. 11E ). Chaetae long and stiff; supra-acicular
         chaetae simple, slightly flattening and tapering distally to a fine tip, very lightly
         serrated, 7 per fascicle ( Fig. 11G ); sub-acicular chaetae compound with bifurcate,
         sub-distally serrated shafts, and falcate, very lightly serrated blades ( Fig. 11F ), 7–9
         per fascicle. Pygidium with terminal anus, a pair of cirriform anal cirri and a very short
         (almost imperceptible) median stylet. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p> Fig. 11. <tp:taxon-name> Ophryotrocha scutellus Wiklund, Glover &amp; Dahlgren, 2009
      </tp:taxon-name> . Stereo (A, C) and compound (B, D–I) microscope images.A–C: DBUA0002288.01;
      D–G: DBUA0002287.03(L1); H: DBUA0002287.03 (L3); I: DBUA0002348. A . Entire specimen, dorsal
      view. B . Maxillary apparatus through body tissue, dorsal view. C . Mid-body parapodium,
      posterior view. D . Maxillae, dorsal view (left forcep and first denticles broken), arrows
      show details of the teeth ridges at the base of the maxillary carriers. E . Needlelike chaeta
      of sub-acicular lobe. F . Compound sub-acicular chaetae, mid-body parapodium. G .
      Supraacicular chaeta, mid-body parapodium. H . Maxillae of a specimen from GoC, dorsal view. I
      . Maxillae of a specimen from off Sweden, dorsal view. The maxillae in H and I are in the
      process of moulting, thus including functional and replacement sets. Numbers refer to free
      denticles. </p>
   <p> Fig. 12. <tp:taxon-name> Ophryotrocha scutellus Wiklund, Glover &amp; Dahlgren, 2009
      </tp:taxon-name> . Mandibulae, maxillae and parapodial development from smaller to larger
      specimens. Compound microscope images. A, F, K: DBUA0002288.01 (L5); B, G: DBUA0002287.03
      (L3); C, H, L: DBUA0002288.01 (L6); D, I, M: DBUA0002287.03 (L2); E, J, N: DBUA0002348. A–E .
      Mandibulae, ventral view. F–J . Maxillae, dorsal view. K–N . Mid-body parapodia. The maxillae
      in G, I–J are in the process of moulting, thus including functional and replacement sets. </p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> This species was originally described from a minke whale carcass deployed at a depth of
         125 m off Sweden and organically enriched sediments beneath a fish farm in Norway , at a
         depth of 104 m ( Wiklund et al. 2009 ). Later, seven specimens of the same species were
         retrieved from an experimentally implanted cow carcass at the Setúbal Canyon (WIM), 1000 m
         depth ( Ravara et al. 2015 ). The present study extends the distribution of <tp:taxon-name>
            O. scutellus </tp:taxon-name> to GoC where it occurred associated with experimentally
         deployed alfalfa and wood substrata and control samples (carbonate cubes), at a depth of
         354–1100 m . The specimens from the GoC and WIM are overall smaller than the ones
         originally described from Sweden and Norway ( Fig. 3 ) and exhibit some variation in the
         mandibular and maxillary morphology, apparently associated with growth ( Fig. 12 ).
         However, the larger specimens of the southern locations entirely match the morphology of
         the northern ones. The morphological identification was furthermore confirmed with
         molecular analyses for both the larger and the smaller specimens. The specimen from GoC
         (DBUA0002287.01) sequenced here falls among previously published <tp:taxon-name> O.
            scutellus </tp:taxon-name> sequences (Genbank accession numbers GQ415506 and KP731544
         -48) with within-species K2P values from the H3 alignment of 0.009–0.01, and a K2P value of
         0.10 to the nearest species in the tree, <tp:taxon-name> O. chemecoli </tp:taxon-name> sp.
         nov. A similar variability in length and corresponding variation in the mandible morphology
         has earlier been described for other species, such as <tp:taxon-name> O. sadina
         </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> O. lusa </tp:taxon-name> ( Ravara et al . 2015 : figs
         15, 25, respectively). Differing from what was stated in the original description, the
         specimens of <tp:taxon-name> O. scutellus </tp:taxon-name> studied here have eleven pairs
         of free denticles (instead of seven) in the maxillary apparatus, and the left forcep of the
         larger specimens have uneven teeth. These characters were also found in the specimens from
         off Sweden examined here ( Figs 11–12 ). Thus, the original description is here amended
         accordingly. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p> Ecology and distribution </p>
      <p> NE Atlantic: from Norway to the Gulf of Cadiz (Moroccan Margin). Found in mammal
         carcasses, organically enriched sediment beneath fish farms, wood, alfalfa and carbonate
         substrata, at a depth of 104–1100 m ( Wiklund et al. 2009 ; Ravara et al. 2015 ; present
         study). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
