<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes kozloffi
Higgins, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 8B, E, H
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
WASHINGTON STATE
• 
1 ♂
; 
San Juan Island
, 
North Bay
, 
Argyle Lagoon
; 
48°31′ N
, 
123°01′ W
; 

1 m
b.s.l.

; 

9 Aug. 1975

; 
E. Kozloff
leg.; 
muddy sand gravel, rich in organic matter
; 
USNM-53337
. Specimen mounted for LM.
</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
WASHINGTON STATE
• 
4 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
USNM-53339
. Specimen mounted for LM

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
The description by 
Higgins (1977a)
does not state clearly from which habitat the 
type
material was collected, but sampling was done by E. Kozloff who probably collected the species from muddy sand gravel, rich in organic matter (
Kozloff 1972
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 8.
Comparative light micrographs showing selected details of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. pacificus
Schmidt, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A
. Holotype, ♀ (USNM-53335). 
D–G
. Paratype (USNM-53336). 
B, E, H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. kozloffi
Higgins, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
. Holotype, ♀ (USNM-53337). 
C, F, I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. sublicarum
Higgins, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
. Paratype, ♀ (USNM-54399). 
A–C
. Segments 8 to 9, dorsal view, showing presence of glandular cell outlets type 2 on segment 8. 
D–F
. Segments 6 to 8, ventral view, position and appearance of sexually dimorphic female papillae. 
G–I
. Segments 10 to 11, with midlateral tubes on segment 10, and lateral terminal spines.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
CANADA
– 

British Columbia

• 
2 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Vancouver Island
, 
Clover Point
; 
48°24′14″ N
, 
123°21′04″ W
; 0 m b.s.l.; 

May 2015

; 
M. Herranz
leg.; intertidal brown algae (see 
Herranz &amp; Leander 2016
); 
NHMD- 100304
to 
100305
and 
NHMD-616637

• 

1 ♀
; 
Archaeology Beach
; 
51°39′52″ N
, 
128°05′50″ W
; 0 m b.s.l.; 

July 2015

; 
M. Herranz
leg.; intertidal brown algae (see 
Herranz &amp; Leander 2016
); 
NHMD-100306

.
</p>
      <p>
All specimens mounted for LM. Numerous additional specimens from the same localities, mounted for LM and SEM, are stored in Herranz’ personal reference collection. See 
Table 1
for an overview.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
The species was recently redescribed by 
Herranz &amp; Leander (2016)
, and the specimens follow this rather accurate description. The only details that should be added regard the intracuticular substructures related to the female papillae on segments 6 to 8, and middorsal spine length. Female papillae are present in ventrolateral positions on segments 6 and 7 (
Fig. 8E
), and they have a short, somewhat rhomboid intracuticular tube leading to the rounded outlet. Female papillae on segment 8 are ventromedial (
Fig. 8E
), and the intracuticular substructures are crescentic with a small protuberance in the curved part of the structure. Middorsal spine of segment 8 extends well onto segment 9, but never reaches posterior margin of segment (
Fig. 8B
). It was furthermore confirmed that laterodorsal glandular cell outlets 
type
2 are present on segment 8 only (
Fig. 8B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
