<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Stenothemus laticornis Y. Yang &amp; H. Liu 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5038622</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03C7082F3C578F0EFE29F99DFE25FA5A</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the species of Stenothemus from Southwest China (Coleoptera, Cantharidae), with the descriptions of five new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1409</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus laticornis
Y. Yang &amp; H. Liu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
C54780B5-A2AF-4FC8-B8A7-6AE3D067D8DF
</p>
      <p>
Figs 7F
, 
9E
, 
11A‒C
, 
12D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
It appears to resemble 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. hajeki
Švihla, 2011
</tp:taxon-name>
(from 
China
: N 
Yunnan
), but differs in the following characters: apices of femora yellow, while uniformly black in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. hajeki
</tp:taxon-name>
; antennae almost reaching apices of elytra, while clearly exceeding them in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. hajeki
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Švihla 2011
: fig. 19); aedeagus: ventral processes of parameres strongly approaching each other, distinctly thickened apically and bent dorsally, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. hajeki
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Švihla 2011
: figs 93‒95) the slightly approach each other, and are slightly thickened and bent ventrally.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific name is derived from the Latin ‘ 
latus
’ (‘wide’) and ‘ 
cornus
’ (‘horn’), referring to its flattened and widened antennae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Chongqing
, 
Chengkou
, 
Zuolan
, 
Qixin
; 
32.180º N
, 
108.485º E
; 

1070 m
a.s.l.

; 

9 Jul. 2017

; 
Y. Zhou
leg.; 
MHBU
HBU(E) 
410045
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
CHINA
‒ 

Chongqing

• 
1 ♂
; 
Chengkou
, 
Dong’an
, 
Shengjiaping
; 
31.791º N
, 
109.241º E
; 

1819 m
a.s.l.

; 

16 Jun. 2017

; 
Y. Zhou
leg.; 
MHBU
HBU(E) 
410046
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Chengkou
, 
Xianyi
, 
Mingyue
; 

1184 m
a.s.l.

; 

24 Jun. 2017

; 
Y. Zhou
leg.; 
MHBU
HBU(E) 
410047
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Body length (both sexes): 7.2‒8.0 mm (
7.2 mm
in 
holotype
); width: 
1.5‒1.8 mm
(
1.7 mm
in 
holotype
).
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 9E
)
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body black, clypeus, mouthparts and bases of femora light yellow, pronotum testaceous, lightened at anterior angles. Body densely covered with short, semi-recumbent pale pubescence.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Subquadrate, surface densely and finely punctate, each side with a smooth and rectangular impression behind antennal socket; eyes strongly protruding, head width across eyes 1.5 times wider than pronotum; terminal maxillary palpomeres long-triangular, widest at basal ⅔; antennae filiform, almost reaching apices of elytra, antennomeres II about 1.1 times as long as wide at apices, III about 2.9 times longer than II, IV‒XI flattened and each with a small and smooth oval impression in middle of outer edge, IV widest, V to XI gradually narrowing towards apex, XI slightly longer than X, pointed at apex.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 11.
Aedeagus of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus laticornis
Y. Yang &amp; H. Liu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (MHBU HBU(E) 410045). 
A
. Ventral view. 
B
. Dorsal view. 
C
. Lateral view. Scale bar = 0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 12.
Female reproductive system, ventral view. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus singularicollis
(Pic, 1933)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(MHBU, Shaanxi). 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. gracilis
Y. Yang &amp; X. Yang
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype (IZAS IOZ(E) 225787). 
C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. flavicollis
Y. Yang &amp; S. Ge
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype (MHBU HBU(E) 410039). 
D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. laticornis
Y. Yang &amp; H. Liu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype (MHBU HBU(E) 410047). Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Subquadrate, about 1.1 times as long as wide, anterior margin arcuate, anterior angles obtuse, subrounded, lateral margins slightly sinuate, posterior margin slightly sinuate and narrowly bordered, posterior angles sub-rectangular, disc strongly convex on posterolateral parts, surface finely and densely punctate.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Nearly parallel-sided, about 3.6 times as long as humeral width, 4.6 times as long as than pronotum, surface finely and densely punctate, with hardly visible longitudinal costae.</p>
      <p>
AEDEAGUS (
Fig. 11A‒C
). Moderately swollen laterally at basal part, strongly reduced in diameter apically; basal piece nearly as long as dorsal plate of each paramere, with a large, bifurcate conjoined middle nodule at base of ventral side; ventral processes of parameres strongly approaching each other, short and distinctly thickened apically, bent dorsally in lateral view; dorsal plates slightly longer than ventral processes, strongly narrowed near base, approaching each other, apex acute; apical parts of laterophyses depressed and separated from each other, apex wide-triangular and weakly exceeding middle emargination between dorsal plates.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Similar to male, but body stouter than male, eyes small, less protruding, head width across eyes 1.4 times wider than pronotum, antennae shorter and roughly extending to elytral mid-length, IV‒XI without impressions; elytra about 3.2 times as long as humeral width.</p>
      <p>
ABDOMINAL STERNITE VIII (
Fig. 7F
). Moderately narrowed posteriorly, lateroapical angles widely rounded, posterior margin widely and roundly emarginate in middle and feebly sinuate on both sides, behind the notch with a membrane which is sclerotized and triangularly bilobed at apex.
</p>
      <p>
INTERNAL ORGAN OF REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM (
Fig. 12D
). Vagina stout, with median oviduct situated at ventroapical part, vagina abruptly narrowed in apical part and extended into a short duct which diverticulum and spermathecal duct are arising from; diverticulum moderately long, about 0.58 times adult body length, evenly thinned apically, slender tube-shaped and spiral; spermathecal duct moderately long but much shorter than diverticulum; spermatheca slender tube-shaped and spiral, obviously thinner than spermathecal duct and nearly as long as diverticulum, with basal part extended into a short tube, at opening of accessory gland. Accessory gland thin in basal part and the remainder moderately thin, obviously shorter than spermatheca.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Chongqing
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
