<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Stenothemus Bourgeois 1907</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5038624</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03C7082F3C548F30FF67FA1BFADCFD4B</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the species of Stenothemus from Southwest China (Coleoptera, Cantharidae), with the descriptions of five new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1409</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>
1. Pronotum subrounded, with protruding and acute posterior angles ................................................. 2
</p>
      <p>
– Pronotum subquadrate, with nearly rectangular and obtuse posterior angles .................................. 7
</p>
      <p>
2. Elytra yellow, with irregular dark brown markings .......................................................................... 3
</p>
      <p>
– Elytra yellow or brown, without dark markings ............................................................................... 4
</p>
      <p>

3. Aedeagus (
Fig. 2G‒I
): ventral process of each paramere nearly parallel to dorsal plate in lateral view, laterophyses feebly exceeding middle emargination between dorsal plates; female reproductive system (
Fig. 4C
): spermathecal duct very long, slightly longer than diverticulum ............................ .................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
diffusus
Wittmer, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Aedeagus (
Fig. 6A‒C
): ventral process of each paramere at an obvious angle to dorsal plate in lateral view, laterophyses clearly exceeding middle emargination between dorsal plates; female reproductive system (
Fig. 8A
): spermathecal duct moderately long, much shorter than diverticulum .............................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. grahami
Wittmer, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
4. Aedeagus: dorsal plate of each paramere acute at apex .................................................................... 5
</p>
      <p>
– Aedeagus: dorsal plate of each paramere rounded at apex ............................................................... 6
</p>
      <p>

5. Body larger, more than 
7.5 mm
in length; aedeagus (
Švihla 2004
: figs 155‒156): apical part of dorsal plate strongly narrowed, middle emargination between dorsal plates very deep, longer than half its length .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
jindrai
Švihla, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body smaller, 
6.6 mm
in length; aedeagus (
Fig. 10G‒I
): apical part of dorsal plate slightly narrowed, middle emargination between dorsal plates moderately deep, nearly as long as half its length ........ ...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jindraimimus
Y. Yang &amp; X. Yang
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

6. Body yellow, pronotum darkened at anterior angles; aedeagus (
Švihla 2004
: figs 161‒163): dorsal plates of parameres separated from each other, ventral process of each paramere slightly thickened apically ............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. benesi
Švihla, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body brown, pronotum lightened at anterior angles; aedeagus (
Fig. 2A‒C
): dorsal plates of parameres approaching each other, ventral process of each paramere distinctly thickened apically .................. ............................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. shaanxiensis
Švihla, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. nov.
</p>
      <p>

7. Body uniformly black (
Fig. 1E
) ..................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
dundai
Švihla, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Body at least bicolored ..................................................................................................................... 8
</p>
      <p>

8. Pronotum distinctly widened anteriorly; aedeagus (
Fig. 6D‒F
): dorsal plates of parameres conjoined, with a rounded emargination in middle of apical margin .... 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. minutissimus
(Pic, 1933)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</p>
      <p>
– Pronotum nearly parallel-sided; aedeagus: dorsal plates of parameres separated ............................ 9
</p>
      <p>
9. Middle antennomeres without smooth impressions in males ......................................................... 10
</p>
      <p>
– Middle antennomeres with smooth impressions in males ...............................................................11
</p>
      <p>

10. Head, pronotum and scutellum testaceous, elytra yellow .... 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
singularicollis

(Pic, 1933)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Head and pronotum black brown, scutellum yellow, elytra black (
Fig. 5C
) .. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
tryznai
Švihla, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
11. Antennae flattened or thickened, very long, almost reaching apices of elytra in males ................. 12
</p>
      <p>
– Antennae simple filiform, moderately long, at most extending to ¾ length of elytra in males ...... 13
</p>
      <p>

12. Antennomeres IV‒XI flattened; aedeagus (
Fig. 11A‒C
): ventral process distinctly thickened apically, bent dorsally in lateral view; apex of laterophyses exceeding middle emargination between dorsal plates ..................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. laticornis
Y. Yang &amp; H. Liu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Antennomeres IV‒XI cylindrically thickened; aedeagus (
Fig. 10A‒C
): ventral process slightly narrowed apically, bent ventrally in lateral view; apex of laterophyses not reaching middle emargination between dorsal plates ............................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chongqingensis
Y. Yang &amp; H. Liu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

13. Pronotum yellow, nearly as long as wide; aedeagus (
Fig. 10D‒F
): lateroapical part of dorsal plate longitudinally ridged; female reproductive system (
Fig. 12C
): diverticulum and spermatheca extremely long, diverticulum much shorter than spermatheca ........................................................... ................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. flavicollis
Y. Yang &amp; S. Ge
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
– Pronotum reddish brown or black, distinctly longer than wide; aedeagus: dorsal plate not ridged; female reproductive system: diverticulum and spermatheca moderately long, diverticulum much or slightly longer than spermatheca .................................................................................................... 14
</p>
      <p>

14. Aedeagus (
Fig. 2D‒F
): ventral process of each paramere moderately long, apex of laterophyses not reaching middle emargination between dorsal plates; abdominal sternite VIII (
Fig. 3B
): lateroapical angles widely rounded, posterior margin roundly emarginate in middle, sclerotized membrane simple, without rectangular longitudinal sclerite ............................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. davidi
(
Pic, 1926
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Aedeagus (
Fig.6G‒I
): ventral process of each paramere short, apex of laterophyses clearly exceeding middle emargination between dorsal plates; abdominal sternite VIII (
Fig. 7D
): lateroapical angles triangular and protruding, posterior margin rectangularly emarginate in middle, sclerotized membrane with a rectangular sclerite present at center and a small longitudinal sclerite on each side ............... ................................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. gracilis
Y. Yang &amp; X. Yang
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Note
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus kansuensis
Pic, 1933
</tp:taxon-name>
is not included in the key because the 
type
was not located by us.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
