<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Echinoderes aureus Adrianov, Murakami &amp; Shirayama 2002</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4420017</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0F2CFE85F9C8E35DD0CFD0C40D556310</uri>
         <article-title>Description, redescription and revision of sixteen putatively closely related species of Echinoderes (Kinorhyncha: Cyclorhagida), with the proposition of a new species group - the Echinoderes dujardinii group</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes aureus
Adrianov Murakami &amp; Shirayama, 2002: 51–57
</tp:taxon-name>
, figs 2–6, table 1.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes lanceolatus
Chang &amp; Song, 2002: 204–210
</tp:taxon-name>
, figs 1–2. 
Syn. nov.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes lanceolatus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 


Sørensen 
et al
. 2012: 162

, 180, 183

. — 

Neuhaus 2013
: tables 2, 6


.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Emended diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes
</tp:taxon-name>
with slender middorsal spines on segments 4 to 8, and lateroventral spines on segments 6 to 9; middorsal spines on posterior segments reach well beyond the posterior margin of their respective segments and overlap ca 50% of the following segment. Tubes present in ventrolateral positions on segment 2, in lateroventral positions on segment 5, and in midlateral positions on segment 10. Incomplete midventral, intracuticular fissure present on anterior half of segment 2. Glandular cell outlets 
type
1 distributed in following pattern on dorsal side: middorsal on segments 1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 10 and 11 (two longitudinally aligned outlets on segments 10 and 11), and paradorsal on segments 4, 6, 8 and 9. Glandular cell outlets 
type
2 are not present on any segment. Tergal extensions of segment 11 are relatively slender, pointed and well-spaced, with strong pectinate fringe between extensions; sternal extensions short, nearly straight. Females with female papillae in ventrolateral positions on segments 7 and ventromedial positions on 8.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
JAPAN
• 
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Honshu Island
, 
Tanabe Bay
; 
33°42′12″ N
, 
135°22′54″ E
; 0 m b.s.l.; 

Mar. 2001

; 
A. Adrianov
, 
C. Murakami
and 
Y. Shirayama
leg.; brown algae (
<tp:taxon-name>
Padina arborescens
</tp:taxon-name>
) in tidal pool; 
SMBL-397
, 
SMBL-398
. Specimens mounted for LM

.
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
and additional 
paratypes
were not available.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
JAPAN
• 
1 ♀
; 
Honshu Island
, 
Tanabe Bay
; 
33°41′31″ N
, 
135°20′10″ E
; 0 m b.s.l.; 

12 Sep. 2012

; 
H. Yamasaki
leg.; 
detritus and mixed sediment in tidal pool
; 
ICHUM-6124
•

2 ♀♀
, 
2 ♂♂
; 
Tanegashima
, 
Mihama Beach
; 
30°44′35″ N
, 
130°59′39″ E
; 0 m b.s.l.; 

3 Mar. 2014

; 
H. Yamasaki
leg.; detritus and mixed sediment in tidal pool; 
NHMD-664219
, 
NHMD-664220
, 
ICHUM-6125
, 
ICHUM-6126
.

</p>
      <p>
REPUBLIC OF KOREA
• 
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Jeju Island
, 
Munseum Islet
; 
33°13′31″ N
, 
126°33′55″ E
; 0 m b.s.l.; 

26 Feb. 1999

; 
J. Lee
and 
Y.H. Song
leg.; intertidal macroalgae; 
NHMD-662029
, 
NHMD-662030
•

2 ♀♀
, 
3 ♂♂
; 
Jeju Island
, 
Beomseom Islet
; 
33°13′03″ N
, 
126°30′52″ E
; 0 m b.s.l.; 

3 Mar. 2000

; 
J. Lee
and 
Y.H. Song
leg.; intertidal macroalgae; 
NHMD-662031 to NHMD-662033
, 
NHMD-662034 to NHMD-662036.
</p>
      <p>
All specimens are mounted for LM. One of the specimens from Beomseom Islet was designated as 
paratype
for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes lanceolatus
</tp:taxon-name>
. In addition to these specimens, photographs of the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. lanceolatus
</tp:taxon-name>
, also collected at Beomseom Islet, were examined. No specimens mounted for SEM were available. See 
Table 1
for an overview.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
The appearance of the species generally follows the description provided by 

Adrianov 
et al.
(2002a)

, hence the following notes only provide additional information not included in the original description. The presence of an incomplete midventral, intracuticular fissure on anterior half of segment 2 is confirmed from all examined specimens (
Fig. 1E
). Our observations also confirmed the presence of rounded ventromedial, intra- or subcuticular markings on segment 1, but it should be stressed that these markings can be very difficult to visualize, and seem to get even harder to see in older specimens. We can furthermore confirm the absence of glandular cell outlets 
type
2 on any segment. Middorsal spines are thin, and the spine of segment 8 extends well beyond the posterior segment margin and overlaps half of segment 9 (
Fig. 1I
). Female papillae forming a short, tubular intracuticular structure are present in ventrolateral positions on segment 7 and ventromedial positions on segment 8 (
Fig. 1H
). Tergal plates of segment 11 have conspicuously strong pectinate fringes in the area between the tergal extensions (
Fig. 1J
). Seta-like fringe tips not observed from neither tergal nor sternal extensions. Lateral terminal accessory spines short (about 
⅓
of lateral terminal spine length), and conspicuously thick and stout (
Fig. 1J
).
</p>
      <p>
The distribution of cuticular structures, i.e., sensory spots, glandular cell outlets, tubes, and spines is summarized in 
Table 2
. Distribution of sensory spots generally follows the original species description, but with several differences. Dorsal series: original description: paradorsal sensory spots on segment 2 present in males; specimens examined herein: paradorsal sensory spots absent on segment 
2 in
males, but middorsal sensory spot present in both sexes. Original description: one pair of laterodorsal sensory spots on segment 2 present in males; specimens examined herein: two pairs of laterodorsal sensory spots on segment 2 present in both sexes (
Fig. 1D
). Original description: midlateral sensory spots on segment 3 absent in males; specimens examined herein: midlateral sensory spots on segment 3 present in both sexes. Original description: laterodorsal sensory spots on segment 3 present in females; specimens examined herein: these sensory spots are present in both sexes but appear in midlateral rather than laterodorsal positions (
Fig. 1D
). Original description: laterodorsal sensory spots on segments 4 to 7 present in males; specimens examined herein: these sensory spots appear in midlateral rather than laterodorsal positions (
Fig. 1
F–G), and are also present on segment 8. Original description: no mention of laterodorsal or midlateral sensory spots on segments 
4 to 8 in
females; specimens examined herein: midlateral sensory spots present on segments 
4 to 8 in
females (
Fig. 1
F–G). Original description: subdorsal sensory spots on segments 5 and 7 absent in males; specimens examined herein: subdorsal sensory spots on segments 5 and 7 present in males. Original description: one pair of subdorsal sensory spots on segment 6 present in females; specimens examined herein: two pairs of subdorsal sensory spots on segment 6 present in females (
Fig. 1G
). Original description: no mention of laterodorsal sensory spots on segment 
9 in
any sex; specimens examined herein: laterodorsal sensory spots present on segment 
9 in
both sexes. Original description: segments 10 and 11 have a middorsal sensory spot anterior to a middorsal glandular cell outlet 
type
1; specimens examined herein: segments 10 and 11 have two middorsal, longitudinally aligned glandular cell outlets 
type
1. The distribution of glandular cell outlets 
type
1 on the dorsal side of segments 1 to 9 fits the original description. Ventral series: Original description: ventromedial sensory spots on segment 
1 in
males; specimens examined herein: ventromedial sensory spots absent on segment 
1 in
both sexes. Original description: ventromedial sensory spots are illustrated on segments 2 to 10; specimens examined herein: these structures are glandular cell outlets 
type
1 (
Fig. 1E, H, K
), and not sensory spots; however besides these outlets, both sexes have ventromedial sensory spots on segments 5 and 7, and ventrolateral ones on segment 9; males furthermore with ventrolateral sensory spots on segment 10.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
