<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Stenothemus flavicollis Y. Yang &amp; S. Ge 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5033126</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3A66E7CDCEA0C67CC2C3085D4333F37D</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the species of Stenothemus from Southwest China (Coleoptera, Cantharidae), with the descriptions of five new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1409</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus flavicollis
Y. Yang &amp; S. Ge
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D0040599-E6AA-4A07-ACC5-EC916A4E9D9E
</p>
      <p>
Figs 7E
, 
9C
, 
10D‒F
, 
12C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
It resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. limbatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
, but can be distinguished by the following characters: tibiae black (orange in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. limbatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
); aedeagus: basal piece with a large middle nodule at base of ventral side, lateroapical part of dorsal plate with a longitudinal ridge, apical parts of laterophyses narrowly separated from each other, clearly exceeding middle emargination between dorsal plates (while middle nodule small, dorsal plate not ridged at lateroapical part, apical parts of laterophyses widely separated and just reaching middle emargination in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. limbatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
, see 

Yang 
et al
. 2021

: figs 
3g
‒i); female abdominal sternite VIII: posterior margin rectangularly emarginate in middle, membrane behind the middle emargination triangularly bilobed at apex (while roundly emarginate in middle, membrane behind the middle emargination tapered at apex in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. limbatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
, see 

Yang 
et al
. 2021

: fig. 8c); female reproductive system: diverticulum and spermatheca extremely long (relatively short in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. limbatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
, see 

Yang 
et al
. 2021

: fig. 6c).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific name is derived from the Latin ‘ 
flavus
’ (‘yellow’) and ‘ 
collum
’ (‘neck’), referring to its yellow pronotum.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Hubei
, 
Yichang
, 
Dalaoling Forestry Farm
; 

3 May 2015

; 
T.F. Qiu
leg.; 
MHBU
HBU(E) 
410029
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
CHINA
‒ 

Hubei

• 
8 ♂♂
, 
5 ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MHBU
HBU(E) 
410030 to 410042
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; 
Yichang
, 
Dalaoling Forestry Farm
; 

4 May 2015

; 
T.F. Qiu
leg.; 
MHBU
HBU(E) 
410043
, 
410044
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Body length (both sexes): 
6.5‒9.7 mm
(
7.2 mm
in 
holotype
); width: 1.0‒2.0 mm (
1.7 mm
in 
holotype
).
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 9C
)
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body black, clypeus, mouthparts, antennomeres I, prothorax, coxae and femora and posterior margins of abdominal ventrites yellow. Body densely covered with short, semi-recumbent yellow pubescence.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Subquadrate, surface densely and finely punctate, each side with a smooth and rectangular impression behind antennal socket; eyes moderately protruding, head width across eyes 1.5 times wider than pronotum; terminal maxillary palpomeres long-triangular, widest in middle; antennae filiform, roughly extending to ⅔ length of elytra, antennomeres II about 2.2 times as long as wide at apices, III about 1.6 times longer than II, IV‒XI each with a smooth longitudinal impression in middle of outer edge, VII longest, XI distinctly longer than X, XI slightly thickened, pointed at apex.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Subquadrate, about 1.1 times as long as wide, anterior margin arcuate, anterior angles subrounded, lateral margins nearly parallel and slightly sinuate, posterior margin slightly sinuate and narrowly bordered, posterior angles sub-rectangular, disc strongly convex on posterolateral parts, surface finely and densely punctate.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Nearly parallel-sided, about 3.8 times as long as humeral width, 4.8 times longer than pronotum, surface finely and densely punctate, with hardly visible longitudinal costae.</p>
      <p>
AEDEAGUS (
Fig. 10D‒F
). Moderately swollen laterally at basal part, reduced apically in diameter; basal piece nearly as long as dorsal plate of each paramere, with a large, bifurcate conjoined middle nodule at base of ventral side; ventral processes of parameres approaching each other, short and slightly thickened apically, bent ventrally in lateral view; dorsal plates slightly longer than ventral processes, abruptly narrowed near base and approaching each other, apex acute and directed ventrally, lateroapical part with a ridge; apical parts of laterophyses depressed and separated from each other, apex acute and clearly exceeding middle emargination between dorsal plates.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
Aedeagus (A, D, G = ventral view; B, E, H = dorsal view; C, F, I = lateral view). 
A‒C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus chongqingensis
Y. Yang &amp; H. Liu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (MHBU HBU(E) 410028). 
D‒F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. flavicollis
Y. Yang &amp; S. Ge
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (MHBU HBU(E) 410029). 
G‒I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jindraimimus
Y. Yang &amp; X. Yang
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (IZAS IOZ(E) 1389239). Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Similar to male, but body stouter than male, eyes small, less protruding, head width across eyes 1.3 times wider than pronotum, antennae shorter and roughly extending to elytral mid-length, IV‒XI without smooth longitudinal impressions; elytra about 3.4 times as long as humeral width.</p>
      <p>
ABDOMINAL STERNITE VIII (
Fig. 7E
). Moderately narrowed posteriorly, lateroapical angles widely rounded, posterior margin widely and rectangularly emarginate in middle and feebly sinuate on both sides, behind the notch with a membrane which is sclerotized and triangularly bilobed at apex.
</p>
      <p>
INTERNAL ORGAN OF REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM (
Fig. 12C
). Vagina elongate, with median oviduct situated at ventroapical part, vagina abruptly narrowed in apical part and extended into a short duct which diverticulum and spermathecal duct are arising from; diverticulum extremely long, about 0.99 times adult body length, evenly thinned apically, slender tube-shaped and spiral; spermathecal duct slightly long but much shorter than diverticulum; spermatheca slender tube-shaped and spiral, obviously thinner than spermathecal duct and much longer than diverticulum, with basal part extended into a short tube, at opening of accessory gland.Accessory gland thin in basal part and remainder moderately thin, obviously shorter than spermatheca.
</p>
      <p>
Variation within species
</p>
      <p>Sometimes posterior margin of pronotum arcuate.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Hubei
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
