<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Brachymelecta
                        larreae</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4967791</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03CBE758FFA33F41FDC92F3A6478FAC0</uri>
                  <article-title>Brachymelecta Linsley, 1939, previously the rarest North American
                        bee genus, was described from an aberrant specimen and is the senior synonym
                        for Xeromelecta Linsley, 1939</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.754.1393</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta larreae ( Cockerell, 1900 ) </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 4D , 6E , 14A , 15, 17 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Bombomelecta larreae Cockerell, 1900: 361 </tp:taxon-name> ( ♀ ). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Bombomelecta azygos Viereck, 1903: 181 </tp:taxon-name> ( ♂ ).
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="vernacular_names">
            <p> Proposed common name </p>
            <p>Creosote digger-cuckoo bee.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Unique within the genus to <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name> are each of
                  the following morphological features: the mandibles are bidentate, each with an
                  inner preapical tooth as well as the usual apical tooth (rutellum) ( Fig. 14A );
                  the mesoscutum does not have any spots or bands of differentiated hairs but is
                  instead covered in dense, uniformly golden-yellow hairs ( Fig. 15A–C ); the
                  mesoscutellum has no spines or well-defined mammiform tubercles, although the
                  mesoscutellum is bigibbous to some degree ( Fig. 15D ); in both sexes the
                  mesotibiae have black hairs only ( Fig. 15A, C ); and T1–T4 lack well-defined
                  fasciae, although ill-defined apical bands of golden-yellow hairs are sometimes
                  present ( Fig. 15A–B ). <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta larreae </tp:taxon-name> is
                  more likely to be confused with some <tp:taxon-name> Melecta spp. </tp:taxon-name>
                  than other species of <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> , but in
                  North American <tp:taxon-name> Melecta </tp:taxon-name> the inner ramus of each
                  tarsal claw is narrow, pointed, and thus resembles the outer ramus and T1 has
                  long, pale hairs, similar in length to those on the dorsum of the mesosoma,
                  whereas in <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name> the inner ramus of each
                  tarsal claw of the mid- and hind legs is broad, lobe-like, and thus does not
                  resemble the outer ramus (as in all <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta spp.
                  </tp:taxon-name> ) and any pale hairs on T1 (the hairs may be entirely black) are
                  distinctly shorter than those on the dorsum of the mesosoma. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 14. Mandibles of female. A . <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta larreae ( Cockerell, 1900
                  ) </tp:taxon-name> (CNC 891712), each mandible has a single inner
            (preapical/almost submedial) tooth (blue arrow). B . <tp:taxon-name> B. interrupta (
                  Cresson, 1872 ) </tp:taxon-name> (CNC 891714), each mandible has both an inner
            basal tooth as well as an inner preapical (almost submedial) tooth (blue arrows). </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Primary type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> USA • ♂ , <tp:taxon-name> B. azygos </tp:taxon-name>
                        holotype; Nevada ; ANSP 10128 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> ♀ , <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name>
                        holotype ; New Mexico , Mesilla Park , Doña Ana County ; 9 May 1900 ; T.D.A.
                        Cockerell leg.; USNM 534229 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> DNA barcoded material </p>
            <p>Available, but not BIN-compliant. Specimen examined and sequenced:</p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> USA • 1 ♂ ; California , Anza-Borrego Desert State Park ;
                        33.2580° N , 116.4110° W ; 26 Feb. 2015 ; K.J. Hung leg.; BOLD sample ID:
                        CCDB-29918 H07; PCYU SDC.20015 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Non-barcoded material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> USA • 2 ♂♂ ; California , Apple Valley ; 12 May 1955 ; W.R.
                        Richards leg.; CNC 891709 , 891711 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for preceding; 20 May
                        1955 ; W.R.M. Mason leg.; CNC 899531 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 3 ♀♀ , 5 ♂♂ ; California , Argus Mountains , Inyo
                        County ; 22 May 1937 ; E.C. Van Dyke leg.; CAS </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; California , Helendale , San Bernardino County
                        ; 16 May 1955 ; W.R.M. Mason leg.; CNC 891710 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 4 ♀♀ ; California , Lone Pine , Inyo County ; 24 May
                        1937 ; E.C. Van Dyke leg.; CAS </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; California , Red Mountain ; 16 May 1955 ;
                        J.E.H. Martin leg.; CNC 891712 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; California , Victorville , San Bernardino
                        County ; 20 May 1955 ; W.R. Richards leg.; CNC 891708
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; Texas , Big Bend National
                        Park ( near Chilicotal Mountain ); 3 May 1959 ; J.F. McAlpine leg.; CNC
                        891716 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 15. <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta larreae ( Cockerell, 1900 ) </tp:taxon-name> . A,
            D. Female (CNC 891708). A . Habitus, lateral view. B . Female (CNC 891716), habitus,
            dorsal view. C . Male (CNC 899531), habitus, lateral view. D . Axillae and
            mesoscutellum, dorsal view. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Redescription </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Length 12.3 mm ; ITW 3.3 mm ; head length 3.4 mm ; head width 3.9 mm ;
                  fore wing length 11.0 mm. </p>
            <p>INTEGUMENT COLORATION. Dark brown to black except as follows. Mandible with apical
                  third golden yellow. Mandible with basal two-thirds, propodeum, legs, excluding
                  black tibial spurs, and much of metasoma with reddish tinge. Fore wing dusky
                  throughout except around third submarginal crossvein and second recurrent vein,
                  where dusky subhyaline. Hind wing dusky subhyaline.</p>
            <p>PUBESCENCE. Face with hairs densest around antennal socket, predominantly pale yellow
                  but more extensively black in lower paraocular area and on clypeus. Upper
                  paraocular and frontal areas and vertexal area (except along preoccipital ridge)
                  mostly exposed. Head with dense, erect hairs along preoccipital ridge entirely
                  black except medially where some hairs pale yellow. Genal beard hairs entirely
                  black. Mesoscutum sparsely hairy except densely hairy anteriorly and along
                  margins, with hairs entirely golden yellow. Axilla dorsally with hairs
                  predominantly golden yellow; laterally with hairs predominantly black.
                  Mesoscutellum, metanotum, and much of propodeum (except behind base of hind wing)
                  with erect, predominantly black hairs; hairs otherwise golden yellow. Mesopleuron
                  (except around pronotal lobe where some hairs pale yellow) and metapleuron each
                  covered in sparse, black hairs not obscuring underlying integument. Legs with dark
                  brown to black hairs only. Profemur with posteroventral fringe of dense hairs.
                  Tibiae sparsely hairy. T1 with apical fascia reduced to pair of small patches of
                  golden-yellow tomentum. T2–T4 with ill-defined apical bands of golden-yellow
                  hairs, darker/interrupted medially. Exposed metasomal sterna with short, appressed
                  black hairs.</p>
            <p>SURFACE SCULPTURE.Labrum sparsely punctate (many i&gt;2d). Clypeus with punctures
                  more or less equally dense throughout (most i≤1d). Frontal area below median
                  ocellus with impunctate shiny triangular area. Small impunctate shiny spot lateral
                  to lateral ocellus. Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum with coarser punctures than
                  metasomal terga. Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum with punctures equally dense (most
                  i≤1d) and similar in size. Mesopleuron densely punctate (most i≤1d) but with most
                  interspaces welldefined, shining. Discs of metasomal terga with punctures very
                  fine, sparse (most i&gt;1d), interspaces dull due to tessellate surface
                  microsculpture.</p>
            <p>STRUCTURE. Mandible bidentate, with small inner tooth approximately ⅖ length of
                  mandible from apex as well as usual large apical tooth (rutellum). Maxillary
                  palpus with five palpomeres. Scape with greatest length 2.3 × greatest width. F2
                  nearly as long as wide (L/ W ratio = 0.9). Mesoscutellum moderately bigibbous.
                  Lateral surface of propodeum posterior to spiracle relatively flat and unmodified.
                  Fore wing with three submarginal cells. T6 with narrow, V-shaped but apically
                  rounded pygidial plate with median longitudinal ridge.</p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p>Description as for female except for usual secondary sexual characters and as
                  follows: head with black hairs only; scape shorter, with greatest length 1.9 ×
                  greatest width; F2 shorter, wider than long (L/W ratio = 0.7); mesotibia with
                  patch of very dense short, appressed dark brown to black hairs, occupying nearly
                  entire dorsal surface; T7 with slight median emargination; S4 and S5 each with
                  apical/subapical fringe of dense curved black hairs.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta larreae </tp:taxon-name> is found in the Chihuahuan,
                  Mojave, and Sonoran deserts of North America ( Fig. 4D ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Ecology </p>
            <p> Host records </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
            <p> Floral records </p>
            <p> The holotype of <tp:taxon-name> Bombomelecta larreae </tp:taxon-name> was collected
                  from the flowers of <tp:taxon-name> Larrea tridentata (Sessé &amp; Moc. ex DC.)
                        Coville </tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>Zygophyllaceae</tp:taxon-name> ).
                  Linsley (1939) reported this species on <tp:taxon-name> Eriodictyon Benth.
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Ericameria Nutt. </tp:taxon-name> (as
                        <tp:taxon-name> Stenotopsis </tp:taxon-name> ), and <tp:taxon-name> Stanleya
                        Nutt. Floral </tp:taxon-name> records from data contributors to Discover
                  Life ( Ascher &amp; Pickering 2020 ) compiled by J. Pickering are as follows:
                        <tp:taxon-name> Dalea </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Encelia actonii
                        Elmer </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Eriodictyon trichocalyx A. Heller
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Eriogonum fasciculatum Benth. </tp:taxon-name>
                  , and <tp:taxon-name> Hyptis Jacq. </tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Lamiaceae</tp:taxon-name> ). The label of one examined
                  voucher specimen further indicates that this species has been collected from
                        <tp:taxon-name> Hyptis emoryi Torr. </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Linsley (1938) identified the holotype of <tp:taxon-name> Bombomelecta azygos
                  </tp:taxon-name> as the male of <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name> and
                  synonymized the former name under the latter. The holotypes of both
                        <tp:taxon-name> B. azygos </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae
                  </tp:taxon-name> were examined in the present study, and we agree with Linsley’s
                  treatment. </p>
            <p> This species exhibits unusual sexual dimorphism in that in females many if not most
                  hairs around the antennal sockets and behind the ocelli are pale yellow, whereas
                  in males the hairs on the head are entirely black. Although in this species the
                  mesoscutellum can be entirely mutic (i.e. without tubercles), in some specimens of
                        <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name> the mesoscutellum has a pair of
                  very small and thus ill-defined tubercles. Based on known records, adults of
                        <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name> are active from late February to
                  early June. </p>
            <p> Although BIN-compliant sequences are presently not available for <tp:taxon-name> B.
                        larreae </tp:taxon-name> , a partial sequence, 338 bp in length, is
                  available for a male specimen (BOLD sample ID: CCDB-29918 H07), which was included
                  in the matrix used to construct a phylogeny for <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta
                  </tp:taxon-name> (vide infra). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
