<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Brachymelecta Linsley 1939</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4967789</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03CBE758FF853F6CFDAF2E6F63F9FC7E</uri>
         <article-title>Brachymelecta Linsley, 1939, previously the rarest North American bee genus,
            was described from an aberrant specimen and is the senior synonym for Xeromelecta
            Linsley, 1939</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.754.1393</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta Linsley, 1939 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta Linsley, 1939: 458 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Xeromelecta Linsley, 1939: 450 </tp:taxon-name> , syn. nov. </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Melectomorpha </tp:taxon-name> Linsley, 1939: 451 , syn. nov. </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Nesomelecta Michener, 1948: 15 </tp:taxon-name> , syn. nov. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis for <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> (previously <tp:taxon-name> Xeromelecta
         </tp:taxon-name> ) is an exclusively New World genus of small to mid-sized ( 8–16 mm )
         non-metallic anthophoriform bees, for which the following morphological features in
         combination constitute a diagnosis: the inner ramus of each tarsal claw of the mid- and
         hind legs is broad, lobe-like, and thus does not resemble the outer ramus ( Fig. 2A–B )
         (this feature is unique among North American <tp:taxon-name>Melectini</tp:taxon-name> but
         also exhibited by many species of <tp:taxon-name> Melecta </tp:taxon-name> from the Old
         World (e.g., <tp:taxon-name> M. albifrons </tp:taxon-name> ) as well as many other groups
         of cleptoparasitic bees, Michener 2007 ); the distitarsi of all legs have arolia ( Hurd
         &amp; Linsley 1951 : pl. 11f); the marginal cell of each fore wing extends little (if at
         all) beyond the third submarginal crossvein (or, if the wing has only two submarginal
         cells, the second submarginal crossvein, which is equivalent morphologically to the third
         because it is the second that is lost) (e.g., Fig. 3A ; see also Engel &amp; Michener 2012
         : fig. 4 to see this feature in the M. ? <tp:taxon-name> mucida </tp:taxon-name> holotype
         ); vein cu-v of each hind wing is distinctly longer than the second abscissa of vein M+Cu (
         Engel &amp; Michener 2012 : fig. 5) (this feature is unique to
            <tp:taxon-name>Ericrocidini</tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name>Melectini</tp:taxon-name> ,
         and <tp:taxon-name>Rhathymini</tp:taxon-name> , Roig- Alsina &amp; Michener 1993; Michener
         2007 ); in both pairs of wings, most closed cells are hairless and the region beyond the
         veins of each wing is strongly papillate (e.g., Fig. 3A ; see also Engel &amp; Michener
         2012 : figs 4–5 to see this feature in the M. ? <tp:taxon-name> mucida </tp:taxon-name>
         holotype ); and most pale hairs (if present) on T1 are distinctly shorter than the longest
         hairs on the mesosoma (e.g., Fig. 3A–C ). </p>
      <p> All species of <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> except <tp:taxon-name> B.
            larreae </tp:taxon-name> have well-defined metasomal fasciae comprised of short,
         appressed, branched pale hairs (e.g., Fig. 3A–C ), and may thus superficially resemble
         other cleptoparasitic <tp:taxon-name>Apidae</tp:taxon-name> (subfamily
            <tp:taxon-name>Nomadinae</tp:taxon-name> ), most notably various
            <tp:taxon-name>Epeolini</tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Ericrocis Cresson, 1887
         </tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>Ericrocidini</tp:taxon-name> ), and <tp:taxon-name>
            Hexepeolus Linsley &amp; Michener, 1937 </tp:taxon-name> (
            <tp:taxon-name>Hexepeolini</tp:taxon-name> ). <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta
         </tp:taxon-name> can be readily distinguished from the aforementioned taxa by the length of
         the marginal cell of the fore wing, which in the non-melectine nomadines extends well
         beyond the third submarginal crossvein (or second submarginal crossvein if the wing has
         only two submarginal cells). In contrast to <tp:taxon-name>Epeolini</tp:taxon-name> and
            <tp:taxon-name> Hexepeolus </tp:taxon-name> (but not <tp:taxon-name> Ericrocis
         </tp:taxon-name> ), female <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> in ventral view
         show six recognizable metasomal sterna, with S6 tapering (in female <tp:taxon-name>
            Nomadinae sensu Michener 2007 </tp:taxon-name> , S6 is largely if not entirely retracted
         and commonly emarginate or bifid). <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> can be
         further distinguished from any <tp:taxon-name>Epeolini</tp:taxon-name> by their axillae,
         which in the latter are produced to rounded lobes, angles, or spines (in <tp:taxon-name>
            Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> , the axillae continue the contour of the mesoscutellum,
         as in <tp:taxon-name> Ericrocis </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Hexepeolus
         </tp:taxon-name> ). Species of <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> , especially
            <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name> , may also be confused with <tp:taxon-name>
            Melecta </tp:taxon-name> , but in New World <tp:taxon-name> Melecta spp.
         </tp:taxon-name> the inner ramus of each tarsal claw is narrow, pointed, and thus resembles
         the outer ramus ( Fig. 2C ), and T1 has long, pale hairs, similar in length to those on the
         dorsum of the mesosoma. Additionally, whereas in male <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta
         </tp:taxon-name> from North America each flagellomere except F1 is distinctly wider than
         long (L/ W ratio ≤ 0.8), in male <tp:taxon-name> Melecta </tp:taxon-name> each flagellomere
         is at most as wide as long (L/W ratio = 0.9–1.0). In males of the Antillean species of
            <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> , the flagellomeres are longer, as in
            <tp:taxon-name> Melecta </tp:taxon-name> , but given that the three species are the only
         melectines known to occur in the Caribbean, they can easily be separated from all other
         melectine genera by geography. The absence of arolia in <tp:taxon-name> Zacosmia
         </tp:taxon-name> readily distinguishes the genus from both <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta
         </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Melecta </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> We present <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> as the replacement name for
            <tp:taxon-name> Xeromelecta </tp:taxon-name> at the generic level. This nomenclatural
         act was prompted by the recognition of the lectotype of <tp:taxon-name> Melecta californica
         </tp:taxon-name> and holotype of M. ? <tp:taxon-name> mucida </tp:taxon-name> as belonging
         to the same species. The holotype of M. ? <tp:taxon-name> mucida </tp:taxon-name> agrees
         with the diagnosis for the genus <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> provided
         herein, which corresponds to the former genus <tp:taxon-name> Xeromelecta </tp:taxon-name>
         . Most notably, the inner ramus of each tarsal claw of the mid- and hind legs is broad,
         lobe-like, and thus does not resemble the outer ramus, as in all species formerly placed in
            <tp:taxon-name> Xeromelecta </tp:taxon-name> (see Fig. 2A–B ). In their redescription of
            <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta mucida , Engel &amp; Michener (2012) </tp:taxon-name> also
         noted the similarity between the tarsal claws of the M. ? <tp:taxon-name> mucida
         </tp:taxon-name> holotype and <tp:taxon-name> X. californica </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <p> Evidence that the morphological features exhibited by the holotype of M. ? <tp:taxon-name>
            mucida </tp:taxon-name> fall within the range of variation observed within
            <tp:taxon-name> B. californica </tp:taxon-name> is presented in the ‘Remarks’ section
         for <tp:taxon-name> B. californica </tp:taxon-name> (vide infra). <tp:taxon-name> Melecta
            californica </tp:taxon-name> was described earlier, so the epithet ‘ <tp:taxon-name>
            californica </tp:taxon-name> ’ is the senior synonym to be used in reference to the
         species. Prior to the present study, the name used for this species was <tp:taxon-name>
            Xeromelecta californica </tp:taxon-name> . The name <tp:taxon-name> Xeromelecta
         </tp:taxon-name> was elevated to the rank of a genus by Hurd &amp; Linsley (1951) , after
            <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> had already been established as a generic
         name, by Linsley (1939) . The two names were published simultaneously, but <tp:taxon-name>
            Xeromelecta </tp:taxon-name> was originally described as a subgenus of <tp:taxon-name>
            Melecta </tp:taxon-name> whereas <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> was
         described as a separate genus altogether into which M. ? <tp:taxon-name> mucida
         </tp:taxon-name> was placed, the first among what are now understood to be its congeners to
         be placed in a new genus. According to article 24.1. of the code of the International
         Commission on Zoological Nomenclature (ICZN), when synonyms are published simultaneously
         but proposed at different ranks, the name proposed at the higher rank takes precedence.
         Therefore, even though M. ? <tp:taxon-name> mucida </tp:taxon-name> is herein regarded as a
         junior synonym at the species level, <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> is
         regarded as the senior synonym for the genus. </p>
      <p> Fig. 2. Metadistitarsus of male, lateral view. A . <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta
            californica ( Cresson, 1878 ) </tp:taxon-name> (photo of <tp:taxon-name> Melecta
         </tp:taxon-name> ? <tp:taxon-name> mucida </tp:taxon-name> holotype (ANSP 2294), herein
         synonymized under <tp:taxon-name> B. californica </tp:taxon-name> ), in which the inner
         ramus (blue arrow) of each tarsal claw is broad, lobe-like, and thus does not resemble the
         outer ramus. B . <tp:taxon-name> B. californica </tp:taxon-name> (photo of <tp:taxon-name>
            M. californica </tp:taxon-name> lectotype (ANSP 2292)), in which the inner ramus (blue
         arrow) of each tarsal claw is broad, lobe-like, and thus does not resemble the outer ramus.
         C . <tp:taxon-name> Melecta thoracica Cresson, 1875 </tp:taxon-name> (BOLD sample ID:
         LRBBC1476; PCYU LRB09-3186), in which the inner ramus (blue arrow) of each tarsal claw is
         narrow, pointed, and thus resembles the outer ramus. </p>
      <p> Since <tp:taxon-name> B. mucida </tp:taxon-name> was established as the type species of
         its genus by original designation and monotypy, its senior synonym ( <tp:taxon-name> B.
            californica </tp:taxon-name> ) is herein regarded as the type species for the genus
            <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> . Under its former genus, the type
         species was placed in the subgenus <tp:taxon-name> Melectomorpha </tp:taxon-name> . Since
         article 44 of the code of the ICZN stipulates that (in a genus containing subgenera) the
         subgenus that contains the type species must be denoted by the same name as the genus, the
         subgenus <tp:taxon-name> Melectomorpha </tp:taxon-name> is herein recognized as no longer
         valid. Besides, according to the results of our phylogenetic analysis (presented below),
            <tp:taxon-name> Melectomorpha </tp:taxon-name> is paraphyletic, with its two members,
            <tp:taxon-name> B. californica </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> B. interrupta
         </tp:taxon-name> , not sister to one another but with <tp:taxon-name> B. interrupta
         </tp:taxon-name> sister to <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name> , the only species
         in the subgenus <tp:taxon-name> Xeromelecta </tp:taxon-name> . Although <tp:taxon-name>
            Nesomelecta </tp:taxon-name> was found to constitute a natural group, to maintain its
         status as a valid subgenus would require the other three species of <tp:taxon-name>
            Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> to each be placed in their own separate subgenus or for
            <tp:taxon-name> B. interrupta </tp:taxon-name> to be placed in the same subgenus as
            <tp:taxon-name> B. larreae </tp:taxon-name> . As four or even three subgenera for a
         genus of six species is arguably a case of overclassification, the names <tp:taxon-name>
            Xeromelecta </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Melectomorpha </tp:taxon-name> , and
            <tp:taxon-name> Nesomelecta </tp:taxon-name> are herein synonymized under
            <tp:taxon-name> Brachymelecta </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
