<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Lutites profundus Korn &amp; Hairapetian &amp; Ghaderi &amp; Leda &amp; Schobben &amp; Akbari 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5604813</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03CC87BFFF9DFF85FE50F9DFFEBDF981</uri>
         <article-title>The Changhsingian (Late Permian) ammonoids from Baghuk Mountain (Central Iran)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Lutites profundus
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
BB88C301-E69F-4E4B-8B25-F086D3BC6EEC
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 53
; 
Table 27
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
with conch reaching 
125 mm
dm. Subadult stage with subcircular, compressed whorl profile (ww/wh =0.70–0.80) and rounded venter; about 13 coarse ventrolateral nodes per volution. Adult stage with subtrapezoidal, compressed whorl profile (ww/wh =0.70–0.75), flat or concave venter and angular ventrolateral shoulder; weak dorsolateral ribs and elongated ventrolateral nodes. Prongs of external lobe trifid; altogether about 19 notches of E,A and L lobes.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From the Latin ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
profundus
</tp:taxon-name>
’, meaning ‘deep’, because of the deep external lobe.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain E section
; Hambast Formation; illustrated in 
Fig. 53
; 
MB.C.30003
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
IRAN
• 
1 specimen
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain C section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.30002
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 specimen
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain E section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.30004
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 specimen
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain G section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.30005
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 specimens
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain H section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.30006
to 
MB.C.30008
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MB.C.30003 is a rather well-preserved specimen with 
86 mm
conch diameter, in which two whorls can be studied (
Fig. 53A
). One third of the last volution belongs to the body chamber and the last four septa of the phragmocone are crowded. In the adult stage, the compressed whorl profile (ww/ wh= 0.75) shows a broadly rounded umbilical margin with an oblique umbilical wall. The whorl profile is widest on the inner flank, from where the concave flanks converge towards the angular ventrolateral shoulder. The venter is concave in this growth stage. Half a volution back the venter is flat and another half whorl back, a rounded venter can be seen belonging to a subcircular, compressed whorl section (ww/wh =0.80). The sculpture experiences a change in strength during the last volution. The penultimate volution has ten coarse ventrolateral nodes, which are connected with weak and rounded radial ribs. These nodes become weaker and more numerous at the end of the phragmocone, but they are still present on the body chamber (12 on a distance of 120 degrees). Here, they are elongate and alternate, in their positions, with low umbilical ribs.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 53.
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites profundus
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A
. Lateral and dorsal view, holotype MB.C.30003, section E, float. 
B
. Suture line, holotype MB.C.30003, at 60.0 mm dm, 19.6 mm wh. 
C
. Whorl profile proportions. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bar units =1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Table 27.
Conch dimensions (partly estimated) and ratios of selected specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites profundus
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
from Baghuk Mountain.
</p>
      <p>
Specimen
dm
ww
wh
uw
ah
ww/dm
ww/wh
uw/dm
WER
IZR
MB.C.30005
95.0
–
32.0
40.4
30.5
–
–
0.43
2.17
0.05
MB.C.30005
65.0
16.5
22.5
27.3
–
0.25
0.73
0.42
–
–
MB.C.30003
86.2
21.2
28.2
37.8
27.7
0.25
0.75
0.44
2.17
0.02
MB.C.30003
60.2
16.2
20.5
24.8
–
0.27
0.79
0.41
–
–
MB.C.30002
78.0
18.0
28.0
33.0
–
0.23
0.64
0.42
–
–
</p>
      <p>
The suture line of the 
holotype
has a narrow and deep external lobe (deeper than the adventive lobe) with parallel flanks in the lower part. Its prongs are parallel-sided with asymmetric base and possesses three small notches. The ventrolateral saddle is narrow and asymmetric; it borders the adventive lobe that is widest near its base. It shows two groups of five very narrow notches. The nearly symmetric and inverted U-shaped lateral saddle is higher than the ventrolateral saddle. The asymmetric lateral lobe with less steep dorsal flank has also two groups of narrow notches, a ventral group with two and a dorsal group with three notches (
Fig. 53B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Lutites profundus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. lyriformis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
but differs in the much coarser sculpture of the terminal body chamber, which shows only very weak ribs in the latter species but ventrolateral nodes in 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. profundus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
All the other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
with a slender conch also show a much weaker sculpture.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Stratigraphic range
</p>
      <p>
Upper part of the Hambast Formation; 1.60 to 
1.20 m
below the extinction horizon (
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites profundus
Zone
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
