<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Guiodytes inexpectatus
Tian &amp; Zhou
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
EA3D7117-F8F3-4F45-848A-9E3879ABCBF8
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1
, 
3F
, 
4F
, 
9
, 
10D
, 
11
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. bedosae
Tian, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
, which also occurs in Longzhou County, by the similar character configuration of the head and elytra and the seven-setose labrum present in both species. It is easily separated from the latter species by its much larger body, conspicuously emarginate labrum, the strongly protruding fore angles of the pronotum and the special elytral setiferous chaetotaxy.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The species epithet refers to the unexpected discovery of this new species. The single specimen was encountered by Jiajun Zhou (the second author) after diving in the cave. It is his first discovery of a new cave beetle.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♀
, broken on the left supra-antennal plate; 
Guangxi
, 
Longzhou
, 
Xiadong
, 
Zhuzhu Dong
; 
22°24′10.75″ N
, 
106°38′52.36″ E
; alt. 

170 m

; 

18 Oct. 2020

; 
J. Zhou
leg.; 
SCAU
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
7.5 mm
; width: 
2.4 mm
. Habitus as in 
Fig. 9.
</p>
      <p>BODY. Moderately depigmented, concolorous brown.</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Stout (
Fig. 3F
), much longer than wide from apex of mandible, HLm/HW=1.44, or slightly shorter than wide when measured from apex of labrum, HLl/HW=0.97; clypeus strongly transverse and with anterior margin slightly, median part moderately concave, bisetose at base, frontoclypeal sulcus well marked, clypeal wings not projecting, nearly at same level as clypeus, distinctly separated from clypeus and supra-antennal plates by notches; supra-antennal plates well developed, reflexed margined, strongly convex, smooth and glabrous; frons and vertex moderately convex, with transverse rugosity; with two setiferous pores, situated at posterior end of supra-antennal plates and before neck constriction, respectively, frontal furrows distinct, wide, slightly divergent towards middle of frons, strongly divergent posteriorly; frontal carinae blunt, wide, parallel; eyes completely lacking; genae well developed, not parallel-sided, sides tumid; neck constriction distinct, wide; labrum transverse, frontal margin conspicuously emarginate as a semicircular incision, seven-setose along frontal part, with six cilia on both sides; mandibles short and stout. Palpomeres ensiform, glabrous, apical segments of maxillary palpomere about twice as long as penultimate one, labial palpomeres subequal; labial palpomere two bisetose on inner margin; ligula unisetose at apex; labial suture well marked; mentum well developed, with two pairs of setae, one pair situated beneath median tooth, the other at base near lateral margin, with two large and deep concavities near base; median tooth simple, blunt at apex, lateral lobes wide, gently and obliquely truncated; basal foveae slightly convex; submentum narrow, quadrisetose. Antennae filiform, elongated, reaching elytral base; scapus unisetose subapically, pedicellus smooth and glabrous, pubescent from antennomere three; antennomere three slightly longer than pedicellus, then gradually decreasing in length towards penultimate segment, which is slightly shorter than terminal segment. Underside of head rough.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
Habitus of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Guiodytes inexpectatus
Tian &amp; Zhou
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (SCAU).
</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Pronotum peltate (
Fig. 3F
), much wider than head, PW/HW =1.47, slightly shorter than wide, PL/PW=0.90; disc moderately convex; anterior margin unbordered, indistinctly convex in median portion, margin with a row of cilia throughout, anterior transverse line marked with punctation, fore angles strongly protruding; widest at end of second third, gently and gradually narrowed anteriorly, with conspicuous notch before posterior angle, posterior angle large, with two conspicuously toothed projections between posterior angle and basal constriction; with two lateral setiferous pores, anterior seta at about anterior fifth, posterior one slightly before notch at posterior angle; reflexed lateral margin slightly crenulate, lateral channel broad throughout, narrower before anterior seta, wider between anterior and posterior lateral setae, ending at notch of posterior angle; basal constriction wide, unbordered, with narrow transverse carina; median line engraved, wide, not joining basal constriction. Peduncle short, scutellum small. Prosternum and propleura smooth, with sparse punctures.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
Female genitalia of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Guiodytes
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
, ventral view. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. deharvengi
Tian, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. bedosae
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. cavicola
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. inexpectatus
Tian &amp; Zhou
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (SCAU).
</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Abdominal ventrites more or less punctured; ventrite seven with two pairs of subapical setae, widely separated at each side.</p>
      <p>
WINGS. Elytra elongate ovate, strongly convex, wider than pronotum, EW/PW= 1.29, much longer than wide, EL/EW =1.67; widest at about one third from apex, slightly contracted anteriad and moderately and regularly contracted posteriad; base with a pair of setiferous punctures at base of stria one, intervals two and three each with a pair of small tubercles at base; shoulders broadly obtuse, with two large teeth on each side; apex pointed; sides distinctly crenulate from base to apical third, then indistinctly continued towards apex; elytral striae broad and well marked, with large and isolated punctures, only striae six and seven ending before reaching basal margin of elytron; intervals slightly convex; intervals six and seven carinate at base, joining and continuing into humeral tooth, interval eight carinate throughout, joining with seven before reaching base; arrangement of elytral setiferous chaetotaxy as in 
Fig. 3F
: nine and six foveolate setiferous dorsal pores on interval three and five, respectively, pores nearly regularly arranged; with series of setiferous pores in marginal channel, uninterrupted and small, with several large pores bearing much longer setae. Hind wings reduced.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 11.
<tp:taxon-name>
Guiodytes inexpectatus
Tian &amp; Zhou
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (SCAU), found in the Zhuzhu Dong cave.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Moderately elongated; proleg stout, profemur moderately dilated, smooth, with a long seta and several short ones; protibia well developed, with distinct and complete carina dorsally, sulcus distinct, quadridentate; lateral teeth blunt at apex, lowest lateral much shorter than others, upper two stoutensiform; subapical spur elongate-ensiform, blunt at apex, shorter and more slender than uppermost lateral teeth; protarsi slender, tarsomere longer than tarsomeres two to four combined; meso- and metalegs slender, with width of tarsomeres in both narrower than in proleg; mesotibia gradually dilated towards apex, with an elongated tuber-like subapical spur, longer than wide and furnished with an isometric seta.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
Fig. 10D
). Similar to those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. cavicola
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 10B
), gonosubcoxite IX stout, with one long seta and two short setae at median portion of outer margin; gonocoxite IX curved and slender, apex very sharp, with three dorsal and three ventral setae, plus two short and sturdy ensiform setae on outer margin.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
         <p>
Distribution
</p>
         <p>
China
(
Guangxi
: Longzhou County) (
Fig. 1
). Known only from Zhuzhu Dong cave (
Fig. 11
). The cave is not easy to access due to the extremely narrow entrance as well as the vertical depth of three meters after the entrance. Then, it reaches a relatively wider and flat passage. But the ventilation of the passage is inadequate, causing the collector to experience symptoms of shortness of breath and chest distress. The single specimen was found on the muddy surface near the bank of an underground river, which is 50 meters from the entrance.
</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:nomenclature/>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>

1. Labrum not or slightly emarginate; pronotum with fore angles not or slightly protruding (
Figs 3
A- E); elytral interval three with four or five dorsal setiferous pores, elytral interval five without dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4
) .................................................................................................................... 2

</p>
            <p>

– Labrum conspicuously emarginate as a semicircular incision; pronotum with fore angles strongly protruding (
Fig. 3F
); elytral interval three with nine dorsal setiferous pores, elytral interval five with six dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4F
) (Longzhou: Zhuzhu Dong cave) ............................................... ................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G
. 
inexpectatus

Tian &amp; Zhou
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
            <p>

2. Elytral interval three with four dorsal setiferous pores (
Figs 4B, C
) ................................................ 3

</p>
            <p>

– Elytral interval three with five dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4A, D–E
) ............................................ 4

</p>
            <p>

3. Body smaller (
5.2 mm
); head stouter, labrum seven-setose, palpomeres slightly stouter, antennae shorter and stouter; entire lateral margin of elytra crenulated throughout, striae composed of larger punctures, interval six faintly carinated near base (
Fig. 4B
) (Longzhou: Paoma Dong cave)............ ........................................................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. bedosae
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– Body larger (
7 mm
); head slender, labrum five-setose, palpomeres slender, antennae longer and more slender; lateral margin of elytra crenulated on basal half, smooth on apical half, striae composed of smaller punctures, interval six strongly carinated near base (
Fig. 4C
) (Du’an: three caves) ............. ......................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. cavicola
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

4. Body larger (
9.2–9.5 mm
); frontal carinae long and nearly parallel-sided; pronotum wider than long; elytra with striae smaller and denser punctured, elytral intervals six to eight carinated near base, four and five not carinated (
Fig. 4A
) ........................................................................................................ 5

</p>
            <p>

– Body smaller and more slender (
4.5 mm
); frontal carinae short and not parallel-sided; pronotum longer than wide; elytra with striae composed of larger and sparser punctures, elytral intervals six to eight carinated throughout, four and five carinated near base (
Fig. 4D
) (Huanjiang: Dapo Dong cave) .................................................................................................................................................... ........................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. weii
Huang &amp; Faille
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
            <p>

5. Body more depigmented, of light brown colour; pronotum shorter and stouter, with remarkably emarginate anterior margin (
Fig. 3A
); elytral intervals slightly vaulted, elytral striae broad and well marked, with large isolated punctures (
Fig. 4A
) (Huanjiang: Ji Dong cave, formerly called Shuiku Dong) ......................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. deharvengi
Tian, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– Body less depigmented, of reddish-brown colour; pronotum longer and more slender, with anterior margin almost not emarginate (
Fig. 3E
); elytral intervals rather strongly vaulted, elytral striae narrow and deep, with small isolated punctures (
Fig. 4E
) (Huanjiang: Huang Dong cave) .......................... ............................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. yueliangensis
Huang &amp; Tian
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Labrum not or slightly emarginate; pronotum with fore angles not or slightly protruding (
Figs 3
A- E); elytral interval three with four or five dorsal setiferous pores, elytral interval five without dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4
) .................................................................................................................... 2

</p>
      <p>

– Labrum conspicuously emarginate as a semicircular incision; pronotum with fore angles strongly protruding (
Fig. 3F
); elytral interval three with nine dorsal setiferous pores, elytral interval five with six dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4F
) (Longzhou: Zhuzhu Dong cave) ............................................... ................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G
. 
inexpectatus

Tian &amp; Zhou
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

2. Elytral interval three with four dorsal setiferous pores (
Figs 4B, C
) ................................................ 3

</p>
      <p>

– Elytral interval three with five dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4A, D–E
) ............................................ 4

</p>
      <p>

3. Body smaller (
5.2 mm
); head stouter, labrum seven-setose, palpomeres slightly stouter, antennae shorter and stouter; entire lateral margin of elytra crenulated throughout, striae composed of larger punctures, interval six faintly carinated near base (
Fig. 4B
) (Longzhou: Paoma Dong cave)............ ........................................................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. bedosae
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body larger (
7 mm
); head slender, labrum five-setose, palpomeres slender, antennae longer and more slender; lateral margin of elytra crenulated on basal half, smooth on apical half, striae composed of smaller punctures, interval six strongly carinated near base (
Fig. 4C
) (Du’an: three caves) ............. ......................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. cavicola
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

4. Body larger (
9.2–9.5 mm
); frontal carinae long and nearly parallel-sided; pronotum wider than long; elytra with striae smaller and denser punctured, elytral intervals six to eight carinated near base, four and five not carinated (
Fig. 4A
) ........................................................................................................ 5

</p>
      <p>

– Body smaller and more slender (
4.5 mm
); frontal carinae short and not parallel-sided; pronotum longer than wide; elytra with striae composed of larger and sparser punctures, elytral intervals six to eight carinated throughout, four and five carinated near base (
Fig. 4D
) (Huanjiang: Dapo Dong cave) .................................................................................................................................................... ........................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. weii
Huang &amp; Faille
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

5. Body more depigmented, of light brown colour; pronotum shorter and stouter, with remarkably emarginate anterior margin (
Fig. 3A
); elytral intervals slightly vaulted, elytral striae broad and well marked, with large isolated punctures (
Fig. 4A
) (Huanjiang: Ji Dong cave, formerly called Shuiku Dong) ......................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. deharvengi
Tian, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body less depigmented, of reddish-brown colour; pronotum longer and more slender, with anterior margin almost not emarginate (
Fig. 3E
); elytral intervals rather strongly vaulted, elytral striae narrow and deep, with small isolated punctures (
Fig. 4E
) (Huanjiang: Huang Dong cave) .......................... ............................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. yueliangensis
Huang &amp; Tian
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
