<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Paratirolites lanceolobatus Korn &amp; Hairapetian &amp; Ghaderi &amp; Leda &amp; Schobben &amp; Akbari 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5608705</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B63E90EC0A4909B46AC48E52C4CED77C</uri>
         <article-title>The Changhsingian (Late Permian) ammonoids from Baghuk Mountain (Central Iran)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites lanceolobatus
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
EA9569C5-F88F-4487-A528-878A60FB4CE1
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 25
; 
Table 10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites
</tp:taxon-name>
with conch reaching 
90 mm
dm. Subadult stage with weakly trapezoidal, weakly depressed whorl profile (ww/wh =1.10–1.30) and broadly rounded venter; about 12 radial ribs ending in coarse conical ventrolateral nodes per volution. Adult stage with rectangular and weakly compressed whorl profile (ww/wh = 0.85–1.00), flattened, weakly tectiform venter and subangular ventrolateral shoulder; numerous rounded ventrolateral nodes. Prongs of external lobe lanceolate and usually unsubdivided; altogether 11–15 notches of E, A and L lobes.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From the Latin’ 
lancea
’, meaning ‘lance’, because of the lanceolate prongs of the external lobe.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain B section
; 
Hambast Formation
; illustrated in 
Fig. 25A
; 
MB.C.29769
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
IRAN
• 
18 specimens
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain 1 section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29751
to 
MB.C.29768

• 

3 specimens
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain E section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29770
to 
MB.C.29772

• 

1 specimen
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain G section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29773

• 

2 specimens
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29774
to 
MB.C.29775

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MB.C.29769 is a comparatively well-preserved individual with 
73 mm
conch diameter; a little more than half of the last whorl belongs to the partly corroded body chamber. The last two and a half whorls of the phragmocone are better preserved (
Fig. 25A
). The beginning of the terminal body chamber is at 
50 mm
diameter; it is well identifiable by the crowding of two septa. This boundary is not identical with spontaneous changes in conch shape and sculpture. At the beginning of the body chamber, the whorl profile is trapezoidal with a flattened, broadly rounded venter; at the end, the whorl profile is slightly trapezoidal with weakly diverging flanks. The rounded, weakly tectiform venter is delimited from the flanks by rounded ventrolateral shoulders. The sculpture shows three ontogenetic stages: (1) The inner whorls (up to 
10 mm
dm) appear to be smooth without ribs or nodes. (2) The intermediate stage (between 10 and 
50 mm
dm) shows radial ribs that end in coarse conical ventrolateral nodes (12 per volution in the smaller growth stage and more densely arranged in the larger stage), which weaken at the beginning of the body chamber. (3) The main portion of the body chamber shows smoothening of the sculpture.
</p>
      <p>
The suture line of 
holotype
MB.C.29769 possesses a parallel-sided external lobe with very narrow, lanceolate non-serrated prongs. The ventrolateral saddle is rather narrow (much narrower than the external lobe) and weakly inflated; it is followed by a rather broad, drop-shaped adventive lobe that is multiply serrated, a wide and broadly rounded lateral saddle and a V-shaped, weakly serrated lateral lobe (
Fig. 25E
).
</p>
      <p>
The smaller 
paratype
MB.C.29770 with 
55 mm
conch diameter resembles the 
holotype
in conch proportions and sculpture, but appears to enter the adult growth stage at a smaller conch diameter with a maximum phragmocone diameter of 
38 mm
(
Fig. 25C
). Very coarse ventrolateral nodes are present in an interval of about 270 degrees of the phragmocone. The suture line of this specimen also shows nonserrated prongs of the external lobe.
</p>
      <p>
Suture lines of the further 
two paratypes
MB.C.29751 and MB.C.29757 (both at about 
11 mm
whorl height) demonstrate, when compared with the 
holotype
, the variability within the Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Common to all 
three specimens
are the simple prongs of the external lobe, which in the 
paratypes
MB.C.29751 and MB.C.29757 is less deep as the adventive lobe. All 
three specimens
show an asymmetric adventive lobe that appears to be dorsally inclined (
Fig. 25E–G
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Table 10.
Conch dimensions (partly estimated) and ratios of selected specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites lanceolobatus
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
from Baghuk Mountain.
</p>
   <p>
Specimen
dm
ww
wh
uw
ah
ww/dm
ww/wh
uw/dm
WER
IZR
MB.C.29769
73.3
22.6
26.6
29.6
24.1
0.31
0.85
0.40
2.22
0.09
MB.C.29751
65.2
19.5
22.3
29.5
20.5
0.30
0.87
0.45
2.13
0.08
MB.C.29770
53.5
17.8
17.9
24.1
16.5
0.33
0.99
0.45
2.09
0.08
MB.C.29752
51.9
16.2
17.4
21.4
16.0
0.31
0.93
0.41
2.09
0.08
MB.C.29773
51.5
17.9
16.4
23.7
15.8
0.35
1.09
0.46
2.08
0.04
MB.C.29757
51.2
–
17.2
22.7
16.7
–
–
0.44
2.20
0.03
MB.C.29758
31.6
16.8
11.4
12.7
11.0
0.53
1.47
0.40
2.35
0.04
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new species shows some similarities to species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dzhulfites
</tp:taxon-name>
, particularly in the reduced depth of the external and lateral lobes. It may thus represent a link between the two genera. The low stratigraphic position at the base of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites
Limestone
</tp:taxon-name>
supports this hypothesis.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites lanceolobatus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
differs in the non-serrated prongs of the external lobe from most of the other species of the genus. Similar species are the Transcaucasian 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. trapezoidalis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. birunii
</tp:taxon-name>
, but both possess an adult body chamber with numerous small nodes at the angular ventrolateral shoulder. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites robustus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is the most similar of the Central Iranian species but differs in the wider whorl profile (ww/wh= 1.20 at 
70 mm
dm) from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. lanceolobatus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(ww/wh =0.85). Furthermore, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. robustus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
has bifid prongs of the external lobe.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Stratigraphic range
</p>
      <p>
Upper part of the Hambast Formation; 3.85 to 
2.80 m
below the extinction horizon (
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites lanceolobatus
Zone
</tp:taxon-name>
to lower part of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites kittli
Zone
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
