<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Paratirolites coronatus Korn &amp; Ghaderi 2016</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5608709</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8014EB42437C3E5B3B123F501AD00277</uri>
         <article-title>The Changhsingian (Late Permian) ammonoids from Baghuk Mountain (Central Iran)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 31
; 
Table 14
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites coronatus
Korn &amp; Ghaderi
</tp:taxon-name>
in 


Korn 
et al.
, 2016: 860


, text-figs 17–18.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites
</tp:taxon-name>
with conch reaching 
125 mm
dm. Subadult stage with trapezoidal, moderately depressed whorl profile (ww/wh =1.60–1.90) and flattened tectiform venter; 15 coarse conical ventrolateral nodes per volution. Adult stage with extremely trapezoidal and moderately depressed whorl profile (ww/wh =1.60–1.90), flattened tectiform venter and subangular ventrolateral shoulder; weak ventrolateral nodes. Prongs of external lobe trifid or multiply serrated; altogether 11–24 notches of E, A and L lobes.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
West Azerbaijan
, 
Aras Valley section
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites
Limestone
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
2.90 m
below the top; illustrated by 

Korn 
et al.
(2016

: text-fig. 17A); 
MB.C.25095
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
IRAN
• 
1 specimen
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain E section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29842
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 31.
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites coronatus
Korn &amp; Ghaderi, 2015
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A
. Lateral and dorsal view, specimen MB.C.29842, section E, float. 
B
. Suture line, specimen MB.C.29842, at 48.7 mm dm, 17.8 mm wh. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bar units=1 mm.
</p>
   <p>
Table 14.
Conch dimensions (partly estimated) and ratios of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites coronatus
Korn &amp; Ghaderi
</tp:taxon-name>
in 

Korn 
et al.
(2016)

from Baghuk Mountain.
</p>
   <p>
Specimen
dm
ww
wh
uw
ah
ww/dm
ww/wh
uw/dm
WER
IZR
MB.C.29842
54.5
34.0
19.4
24.6
18.7
0.62
1.75
0.45
2.32
0.04
MB.C.29842
41.2
24.0
12.7
17.9
–
0.58
1.89
0.43
–
–
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Specimen MB.C.29842 is a fully chambered specimen with 
55 mm
conch diameter and allows the study of one and a half whorls (
Fig. 31A
). It has a strongly trapezoidal, depressed whorl profile (ww/wh =1.75), weakly sinuous flanks, an angular ventrolateral shoulder and a flattened tectiform venter. Half a volution earlier, the venter is weakly flattened but still rounded and another half volution back, the venter is broadly rounded. The sculpture changes during the last volution of the phragmocone; strong conical nodes at the beginning of this volution are transformed into smaller, longitudinally elongated nodes, which have a position at the ventrolateral shoulder.
</p>
      <p>
The suture line of specimen MB.C.29842 has a V-shaped external lobe with concave flanks and symmetric, narrowly V-shaped simple prongs. The ventrolateral saddle is asymmetric and dorsally inclined and the asymmetric, nearly parallel-sided adventive lobe has nine little notches. The lateral lobe is nearly flat at its base and subdivided in small equally sized notches (
Fig. 31B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites coronatus
</tp:taxon-name>
is the paratirolitid with the widest conch, resulting from the coronate ventrolateral shoulder. Therefore, it cannot be confused with any other species. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratirolites coronatus
</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. vediensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and the other species in the more strongly trapezoidal whorl profile of the adult stage.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Stratigraphic range
</p>
      <p>Upper part of the Hambast Formation; precise horizon at Baghuk Mountain not known.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
