<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Guiodytes yueliangensis Huang &amp;
                        Tian 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5572583</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03CC663BFFB7FF98FE3DA2EEFE48FD52</uri>
                  <article-title>Three new species of the subterranean genus Guiodytes from Guangxi,
                        China (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Clivinini)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.774.1537</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes yueliangensis Huang &amp; Tian </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 54A7DD47-8EAB-4A9A-9C49-2E6383B4842A </p>
            <p> Figs 1 , 3E , 4E , 5D , 7–8 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> This new species belongs to the group with distinctly projecting clypeal wings and
                  is close to <tp:taxon-name> G. deharvengi Tian, 2014 </tp:taxon-name> , which also
                  occurs in the same karst area in Huanjiang County, by the similar character
                  configuration of head and elytra, but it is easily separated from the latter
                  species by the missing central pore on the frons of the head and the flattened
                  neck constriction. In addition, the pronotum, with the anterior margin almost not
                  emarginate, is much longer, its median line is much narrower, and the anterior
                  transverse line is finely developed. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The species epithet is derived from Yueliang Shan (Moon Mountain in Chinese), a
                  famous karst landscape with a naturally-formed moon-like cavern passing through it
                  ( Fig. 8A ). The type locality, Huang Dong, is one of the caves of this landscape.
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype CHINA • ♂ , broken on the left supra-antennal
                        plate; Guangxi , Huanjiang , Shuiyuan , Sancai , Neiwen , Huang Dong ;
                        24°50′05.74″ N , 108°05′1.86″ E ; alt. 354 m ; 6 Jun. 2017 ; S. Huang leg.;
                        SCAU . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Length: 9.3 mm ; width: 2.9 mm . Habitus as in Fig. 7. </p>
            <p>BODY. Well-pigmented, concolorous dark brown.</p>
            <p> HEAD. Stout ( Fig. 3E ), from apex of mandible slightly longer than wide, HLm/HW=
                  1.06, or shorter than wide when measured from apex of labrum, HLl/HW = 0.82;
                  clypeus strongly transverse and moderately emarginate, surface of median part
                  moderately convex, bisetose at base, with flattened clypeofrontal sulcus, clypeal
                  wings fused, divided from supra-antennal plates by distinct notches;
                  supra-antennal plates rounded and well developed, reflexed margined, strongly
                  convex, smooth and glabrous; frons and vertex fairly convex; laterally with two
                  setiferous pores, situated at posterior end of supra-antennal plates and at level
                  of neck constriction, respectively; frontal furrows deep, conspicuously widened,
                  subparallel at middle of frons, divergent posteriorly; frontal carinae blunt but
                  well marked, not parallelsided; eyes completely lacking; genae well developed,
                  anteriorly conically raised laterally then sinuated, sides nearly vertically
                  truncated; neck constriction distinct, relatively wide; labrum transverse,
                  slightly emarginate, slightly wider than clypeus, seven-setose, ciliate laterally;
                  mandibles of moderate size. Palpomeres ensiform, glabrous, apical segments of both
                  maxillary and labial palpomeres much longer than penultimate ones, respectively;
                  labial palpomere two bisetose on inner margin; ligula unisetose at apex; labial
                  suture well marked, deeply and widely furrowed in median portion; mentum well
                  developed, with two pairs of setae, one pair situated beneath mental tooth,
                  posterior one localized in centre of two large, deep concavities restricted at
                  base near lateral margin; median tooth simple, pointed at apex, lateral lobes
                  wide, obliquely truncated; submentum narrow, quadrisetose. Antennae filiform,
                  elongate, reaching over base of pronotum; scapus unisetose subapically, pedicellus
                  smooth and glabrous, pubescent from antennomere three; pedicellus slightly longer
                  than antennomere three, then gradually decreasing in length towards penultimate
                  segment, antennomeres five to ten subelongate, penultimate segment slightly
                  shorter than terminal one. Underside of head rough. </p>
            <p> Fig. 7. Habitus of <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes yueliangensis Huang &amp; Tian
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂ (SCAU). </p>
            <p> Fig. 8. Huang Dong cave, type locality of <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes yueliangensis
                        Huang &amp; Tian </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. A . Mountain massif Yueliang
                  Shan. B . Entrance. C . Specimen of <tp:taxon-name> G. yueliangensis Huang &amp;
                        Tian </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂ (SCAU), found in the cave. </p>
            <p> THORAX. Pronotum peltate ( Fig. 3E ), much wider than head, PW/HW=1.25, slightly
                  shorter than wide, PL/PW=0.96; disc strongly convex and with noticeable rugosity;
                  anterior margin unbordered, slightly convex in median portion, margin barely
                  emarginate, anterior transverse line fine and traceable, fore angles protruding;
                  widest slightly behind middle, gently curved and gradually narrowed anteriorly,
                  more evidently contracted towards posterior angles; with distinct teeth at
                  posterior angles, lateral margin between posterior angles and basal constriction
                  with one conspicuous and one minute toothed projections before basal constriction;
                  with two lateral setiferous pores, anterior one at about apical quarter, posterior
                  one at basal angle, just before tooth at posterior angle; reflexed lateral margin
                  nearly smooth, lateral channel with uneven surface, narrower before anterior seta,
                  wider between anterior and posterior lateral setae, interrupted by tooth of
                  posterior angle; basal constriction wide, with noticeable transverse carina;
                  median line deeply furrowed but faint when joined with transverse line in front.
                  Peduncle short, scutellum small. Prosternum and propleura smooth, with dense and
                  isodiametric punctuation. </p>
            <p>ABDOMEN. Abdominal ventrites also densely punctured; ventrites four to six each with
                  a pair of setae; ventrite seven with two pairs of subapical setae, widely
                  separated at each side.</p>
            <p> WINGS. Elytra elongate ovate, wider than pronotum, EW/PW= 1.29, much longer than
                  wide, EL/ EW=1.84; strongly convex, widest at middle, gently contracted anteriad
                  and posteriad; base with pair of basal setiferous pores located at beginning of
                  stria one, joined with an additional tubercle at base of interval two; shoulders
                  broadly obtuse, with two teeth on each side; apex pointed; sides distinctly
                  crenulated from base to apical third, then very feebly marked towards apex;
                  elytral striae punctatestriate, narrow and deep, with small and isolated
                  punctures, only striae six and seven ending before reaching basal margin of
                  elytron; intervals distinctly convex; intervals seven and eight joined near base,
                  then joined to interval six at base, intervals six to eight carinated near base;
                  arrangement of elytral setiferous chaetotaxy as in Fig. 4E : five foveolate
                  setiferous pores present on interval three; marginal channel with uninterrupted
                  series of small setiferous pores and several large pores bearing much longer
                  setae. Hind wings reduced. </p>
            <p>LEGS. Legs moderately elongated; proleg stout, profemur moderately dilated, smooth,
                  with several sparsely distributed setae; protibia well developed, with distinct
                  and complete carina dorsally, sulcus indistinct, quadridentate; lateral teeth
                  blunt at apex, lowest lateral tooth unobtrusive, upper three stoutensiform and
                  moderately protruded anteriorly toward apex; subapical spur elongate-ensiform,
                  blunt at apex, much longer and more slender than uppermost lateral teeth; protarsi
                  slender, tarsomere one very long, much longer than tarsomeres two to four
                  combined; meso- and meta-legs slender, with width of tarsomeres in both narrower
                  than in proleg; mesotibia gradually dilated towards apex, with elongated
                  tuber-like subapical spur, distinctly longer than wide and furnished with
                  isometric seta.</p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Fig. 5D ). Moderately sclerotized; aedeagus similar to that of
                        <tp:taxon-name> G . deharvengi Tian, 2014 </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 5A );
                  median lobe strongly arcuated ventrally, elongated and blunt at apex; copulatory
                  piece irregular, elongated, strongly sclerotized in basal and frontal part;
                  parameres asymmetrical, large one with three setae, small one with four setae. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> China ( Guangxi : Huanjiang County) ( Fig. 1 ). Known only from Huang Dong cave (
                  Fig. 8B ). The cave is still preserved as a natural environment and the entrance
                  opens at the middle of the hill. The cave is not well explored and its length
                  remains unknown. The passages in the cave are complicated, and most of them are
                  moist and wet. The single beetle specimen was collected in a wet place about 100 m
                  from the entrance ( Fig. 8C ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
