<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Guiodytes weii Huang &amp; Faille
                        2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5572581</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03CC663BFFBCFF9CFDF1A2CBFB71FD9C</uri>
                  <article-title>Three new species of the subterranean genus Guiodytes from Guangxi,
                        China (Coleoptera: Carabidae: Clivinini)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.774.1537</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes weii Huang &amp; Faille </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: E0CD76FD-36A6-48D6-BDEE-21A62C3FDABD </p>
            <p> Figs 1–2 , 3D , 4D , 5C , 6 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> This new species is most similar to <tp:taxon-name> G. deharvengi Tian, 2014
                  </tp:taxon-name> , which also occurs in Huanjiang County, by the similar character
                  configuration of the head and elytra. It is easily separated from the latter
                  species by the clypeal wings not projecting anteriorly. Moreover, its body shape
                  is much smaller and more slender, the elytral stria punctures are larger and
                  sparser, and intervals four and five are carinated near the base. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 1. Map of Guangxi (China) with the occurrences of <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes Tian,
                  2013 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> This new species is dedicated to Mr. Guofu Wei ( Center of World Natural Heritage,
                  Huanjiang) for his support during our biospeleological investigations. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype CHINA • ♂ ; Guangxi , Huanjiang , Jiale , Dapo
                        Dong ; 25°06′06.78″ N , 108°31′12.48″ E ; alt. 211 m ; 5 Dec. 2016 ; A.
                        Faille leg.; SCAU . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 2. Habitus of <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes weii Huang &amp; Faille </tp:taxon-name> sp.
            nov. , holotype, ♂ (SCAU). </p>
      <p> Fig. 3. Head and pronotum of species of <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes Tian, 2013
            </tp:taxon-name> . A . <tp:taxon-name> G. deharvengi Tian, 2014 </tp:taxon-name> . B .
                  <tp:taxon-name> G. bedosae Tian, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> . C . <tp:taxon-name> G.
                  cavicola Tian, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> . D . <tp:taxon-name> G. weii Huang &amp;
                  Faille </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂ (SCAU). E . <tp:taxon-name> G.
                  yueliangensis Huang &amp; Tian </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂ (SCAU). F .
                  <tp:taxon-name> G. inexpectatus Tian &amp; Zhou </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ,
            holotype, ♀ (SCAU). </p>
      <p> Fig. 4. Left elytron of species of <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes Tian, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> .
            A . <tp:taxon-name> G. deharvengi Tian, 2014 </tp:taxon-name> . B . <tp:taxon-name> G.
                  bedosae Tian, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> . C . <tp:taxon-name> G. cavicola Tian, 2013
            </tp:taxon-name> . D . <tp:taxon-name> G. weii Huang &amp; Faille </tp:taxon-name> sp.
            nov. , holotype, ♂ (SCAU). E . <tp:taxon-name> G. yueliangensis Huang &amp; Tian
            </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂ (SCAU). F . <tp:taxon-name> G. inexpectatus Tian
                  &amp; Zhou </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♀ (SCAU). Dorsal pores indicated
            by white points. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Length: 4.5 mm ; width: 1.1 mm . Habitus as in Fig. 2. </p>
            <p>BODY. Slightly depigmented, concolorous brown.</p>
            <p> HEAD. Stout ( Fig. 3D ), from apex of mandible much longer than wide, HLm/HW=1.41,
                  or slightly longer than wide when measured from apex of labrum, HLl/HW =1.06;
                  distinctly narrower than pronotum, HW/ PW=0.67; clypeus with fused wings
                  transverse, moderately convex medially, bisetose at base, anterior margin slightly
                  bisinuate, bordered, clypeal wings not protruding anteriorly; supra-antennal
                  plates well developed, gently rounded, reflexed, margined, strongly convex, smooth
                  and glabrous; frons and vertex moderately convex, with longitudinal pore at
                  middle; laterally with two setiferous pores, situated at posterior end of
                  supra-antennal plates and at level of neck constriction, respectively; frontal
                  furrows deep, wide, distinctly divergent posteriorly; frontal carinae distinct,
                  slightly convergent to neck constriction; frontoclypeal sulcus not deep but
                  distinct; eyes completely lacking; genae well developed, subparallelsided, sides
                  nearly vertically truncated; neck constriction distinct, slightly stepped; labrum
                  transverse, slightly wider than clypeus, seven-setose, ciliate laterally, straight
                  at anterior margin; mandibles of moderate size. Palpomeres ensiform, glabrous,
                  apical segments of both maxillary and labial palpomeres much longer than
                  penultimate ones, respectively; labial palpomere bisetose on inner margin; ligula
                  unisetose at apex; labial suture well marked, deeply and widely furrowed in median
                  portion; mentum well developed, with two pairs of setae, one pair situated beneath
                  mental tooth, the other at base near lateral margin, and with two large and deep
                  concavities near base; median tooth simple, blunt at apex, lateral lobes wide,
                  gently and obliquely truncated; submentum narrow, quadrisetose. Antennae filiform,
                  rather short, reaching posterior angles of pronotum; scapus unisetose subapically,
                  pedicellus smooth and glabrous, pubescent from antennomere three; pedicellus
                  slightly longer than antennomere three; antennomeres five to ten subelongate,
                  terminal segment slightly longer than penultimate. Underside of head rough. </p>
            <p> THORAX. Pronotum peltate ( Fig. 3D ), much wider than head, slightly longer than
                  wide, PL/PW=1.06; disc smooth, moderately convex; anterior margin slightly
                  concave, beaded in median line; fore angles slightly protruding; widest at
                  beginning of posterior third, gently and gradually narrowed anteriorly, strongly
                  contracted towards posterior angles; posterior angles with obtuse teeth, lateral
                  margin between posterior angles and basal constriction with two conspicuously
                  toothed projections; with two pairs of lateral setiferous pores, anterior one at
                  about anterior quarter, posterior one at basal angle and distinctly removed from
                  channel; reflexed lateral margin with slight notches, lateral channel narrow
                  before anterior seta, distinctly widened between anterior and posterior lateral
                  setae, ending before posterior seta; basal constriction wide, basal carina narrow;
                  median line engraved, deep, wide, distinctly joining basal constriction,
                  surpassing anterior transverse line without joining. Peduncle short, scutellum
                  small. Prosternum and propleura smooth, with dense and isodiametric abdominal
                  punctuation. </p>
            <p>ABDOMEN. Ventrites also densely punctured, ventrites four to six each with a pair of
                  setae; ventrite seven with two pairs of subapical setae, widely separated at each
                  side.</p>
            <p> WINGS. Elytra elongate ovate, wider than pronotum, EW/PW= 1.27, much longer than
                  wide, EL/ EW=1.86; strongly convex; widest behind middle, gently contracted
                  anteriad and posteriad; base finely bisinuate, with a pair of additional tubercles
                  followed by a basal setiferous puncture located at base of interval two; shoulders
                  broadly obtuse, with sharp tooth; apex of elytra pointed; sides distinctly
                  crenulated from base to apical quarter; elytral striae punctate-striate, wide and
                  deep, with large and isolated punctures, only striae six and seven ending before
                  reaching basal margin of elytron; intervals distinctly convex; intervals one to
                  four unbordered at base; intervals seven and eight joined near base, then joined
                  to interval six at base, intervals six to eight carinated throughout, intervals
                  four and five carinated near base; arrangement of elytral setiferous chaetotaxy as
                  in Fig. 4D , five foveolate setiferous pores on interval three; marginal channel
                  with uninterrupted series of small setiferous pores and several large pores
                  bearing much longer setae. Hind wings reduced. </p>
            <p>LEGS. Moderately elongated; proleg stout, profemur distinctly dilated, smooth, with a
                  long seta and two shorter ones; protibia well developed, with distinct and
                  complete carina dorsally, sulcus indistinct, quadridentate; lateral teeth blunt at
                  apex, lowest lateral one much shorter than others, upper two stoutensiform;
                  subapical spur elongate-ensiform, blunt at apex, shorter and more slender than
                  uppermost lateral teeth; protarsi slender, tarsomere one longer than tarsomeres
                  two to four combined; meso- and meta-legs slender, with width of tarsomeres in
                  both narrower than in proleg; mesotibia gradually dilated towards apex, with an
                  elongated, tuber-like subapical spur, longer than wide and furnished with an
                  isometric seta.</p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Fig. 5C ). Moderately sclerotized; aedeagus similar to those of
                        <tp:taxon-name> G. deharvengi Tian, 2014 </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 5A ) and
                        <tp:taxon-name> G. cavicola Tian, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 5B ), median
                  lobe gently arcuated ventrally, whereas strongly </p>
            <p> Fig. 5. Male genitalia of species of <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes Tian, 2013
                  </tp:taxon-name> , median lobe and parameres, lateral view. A . <tp:taxon-name> G.
                        deharvengi Tian, 2014 </tp:taxon-name> . B . <tp:taxon-name> G. cavicola
                        Tian, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> . C . <tp:taxon-name> G. weii Huang &amp; Faille
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂ (SCAU). D . <tp:taxon-name> G.
                        yueliangensis Huang &amp; Tian </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂
                  (SCAU). </p>
            <p> arcuated in <tp:taxon-name> G. deharvengi </tp:taxon-name> , or evidently bisinuate
                  in <tp:taxon-name> G. cavicola </tp:taxon-name> , blunt at apex; parameres
                  asymmetrical, one much longer and broader than the other, both parameres with
                  three long setae at apex. </p>
            <p> Fig. 6. Dapo Dong cave, type locality of <tp:taxon-name> Guiodytes weii Huang &amp;
                        Faille </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. A . Entrance. B . A flatworm (Turbellaria)
                  in the cave. C . Guofu Wei taking pictures in the Dapo Dong cave. D . A bat
                  observed in the cave. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> China ( Guangxi : Huanjiang County) ( Fig. 1 ). Known only from Dapo Dong cave. This
                  cave opens at the bottom of a hill near a country road in the village of Jiale.
                  The entrance is narrow, but accessible ( Fig. 6A ). It is about 90 m long with a
                  short and narrow side passage inside. A large part of the passage is dry, but
                  there are some moist places. The single blind beetle specimen was discovered on
                  the moist wall about 30 m from the entrance at the left side of the main passage.
                  Other syntopic cave animals were observed during the investigation in the cave,
                  for instance, a flatworm and a bat.( Fig. 6B, D ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
