<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tafana humahuaca De Oliveira &amp; Brescovit 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4658743</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/168092128046C35A604D48728A5A09D0</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision and cladistic analysis of ghost spiders of the genus Tafana Simon, 1903 (Araneae: Dionycha, Anyphaenidae), with the descriptions of twelve new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.742.1291</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tafana humahuaca
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
16D23428-F7B9-48A6-93EE-95B3AE8F97DC
</p>
      <p>
Figs 15
, 
32J
, 
35
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tafana humahuaca
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resemble those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. riveti
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. nevada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
by having the short embolus, but differ by having the apophysis at the base of the embolus truncated, extremely short and with excavation between the base of the embolus and the apophysis (
Fig. 15C–E
). Females resemble those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tafana nevada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
by having the epigynal plate, but differ by having atrium narrow in the anterior region, small hood with lateral lobes extremely curved in the anterior region (
Figs 15F–G
, 
32J
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific name, a noun in apposition, is a tribute to ‘Quebrada de Humahuaca’, a deep canyon located in 
Jujuy Province
, the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
ARGENTINA
• 
1 ♂
; 
Jujuy Province
, 
Santa Bárbara
; [
24°18′31″ S
, 
64°39′37″ W
]; 

Oct. 1969

; 
G. Williner
leg.; 
MACN-Ar 41787
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
ARGENTINA
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 

Oct. 1962

; 
MACN-Ar 41788
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
holotype
, MACN-Ar 41787)
</p>
      <p>
COLOR. Exemplar probably discolored. Carapace orange (
Fig. 15A
). Labium, sternum and endites yellow. Chelicerae yellow. Legs I–III yellow with spots on the articles. Abdomen with dark spots (
Fig. 15A
).
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Total length 5.3, carapace length 2.3, width 1.7. Clypeus height 0.06. Eye diameters and interdistances: AME 0.06, ALE 0.1, PME 0.1, PLE 0.08; AME–AME 0.02, AME–ALE 0.02, PME– PME 0.1, PME–PLE 0.08, ALE–PLE 0.02. Chelicerae 0.8 long, with five promarginal teeth and four retromarginal denticles.</p>
      <p>LEG MEASUREMENTS. I—lost; II—femur 1.7/ patella 0.73 /tibia 1.7/ metatarsus 1.6 /tarsus 0.84 / total 6.57; III—1.6 / 0.7/ 1.4 /1.4 / 0.7/ 5.8; IV—lost.</p>
      <p>LEG SPINATION. II—tibia v2-1-2, p1-1-0; III—tibia v1-2-0, p0-1-0, metatarsus v2-1-0, p0-1-0.</p>
      <p>
PALP. Retrolateral tibial apophysis conical with apex curved; cymbium with retrolateral projection more rounded; embolus short; ventral tegular process near the median apophysis and sclerotized; sperm duct in vertical position with secondary looping reaching the apex of the tegulum; median apophysis slender and curved apically (
Fig. 15C–E
).
</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Length 2.7, epigastric furrow 0.6 from tracheal spiracle, spiracle 1.0 from base of spinnerets.</p>
      <p>
Female
(
paratype
, MACN-Ar 41788)
</p>
      <p>
COLOR. Exemplar probably discolored. Coloration as in males of this species (
Fig. 15B
).
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Total length 3.2, carapace length 2.4, width 1.3. Clypeus height 0.06. Eye diameters and interdistances: AME 0.08, ALE 0.1, PME 0.1, PLE 0.1; AME–AME 0.04, AME–ALE 0.04, PME– PME 0.16, PME–PLE 0.12, ALE–PLE 0.04. Chelicerae 1.1 long, with four promarginal teeth and five retromarginal denticles.</p>
      <p>LEG MEASUREMENTS. I—femur 1.6 /patella 0.8/ tibia 1.4/ metatarsus 1.3/ tarsus 0.8 /total 5.9; II— 1.9/ 0.8/ 1.1 /1.15 / 0.6 /5.55; III—1.3/ 0.63 / 0.8/ 1.2/ 0.5/ 4.43; IV—1.9 / 0.8/ 1.5/ 2.1/ 0.65 / 6.95.</p>
      <p>LEG SPINATION. I—tibia v2-2-0, metatarsus v2-0-0; II—tibia v1-1-0; III—tibia v1-2-2, p1-1-0, r1-1-0, metatarsus v2-1-2; IV—tibia v1-2-2, p1-1-1.</p>
      <p>
EPIGYNUM. Hood semicircular and sclerotized; short atrium; lateral lobes over copulatory ducts. Internally, copulatory ducts narrow; primary spermathecae large and oval; secondary spermathecae above the primary spermathecae and rounded; fertilization ducts long (
Fig. 15F–G
).
</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Length 3.2, epigastric furrow 0.7 from tracheal spiracle, spiracle 1.3 from base of spinnerets.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from 
Jujuy
, 
Argentina
(
Fig. 35
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
