<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pseudopolydora achaeta Radashevsky &amp;
            Hsieh 2000</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1519</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03CF9F22FF98AE6F6E8830E0FDA5FD26</uri>
         <article-title>Pseudopolydora (Annelida: Spionidae) from the Arabian Gulf,
            Kuwait</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1519</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora achaeta Radashevsky &amp; Hsieh, 2000 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Fig. 3 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora achaeta Radashevsky &amp; Hsieh, 2000: 223−226
         </tp:taxon-name> , figs 4–5, 11a. </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora achaeta </tp:taxon-name> – Lana et al . 2006: 50 . —
         Zvyagintsev et al . 2011: 53 . — Abe et al . 2014: 3−5 ; 2016: 654−656 , fig. 3; 2019:
         6−11. — Bogantes et al . 2021: 581 , fig. 2a–b. </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora aff. achaeta </tp:taxon-name> – Abe &amp; Sato-Okoshi 2021:
         56−57 , fig. 9a–b (larval morphology). </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora sp. A </tp:taxon-name> – Radashevsky &amp; Migotto 2006 :
         fig. 1c. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> Two specimens were found in Sulaibikhat Bay, Kuwait , comprising 20-chaetiger anterior
         fragment of a small juvenile and a 70-chaetiger complete female about 16 mm long and 0.8 mm
         wide (MIMB 40934; Fig. 3A–B ). Transverse bands of diffused black pigment present on dorsal
         side of up to 15 anterior chaetigers; small middorsal melanophores present from chaetigers
         4−6 to chaetigers 10−12. Prostomium anteriorly weakly incised, notched or almost blunt,
         posteriorly extending to end of chaetiger 2 as a low caruncle. Occipital antenna present.
         Chaetiger 1 reduced, weakly separated from peristomium, with small notopodial and well
         developed neuropodial lamellae; notochaetae absent; neurochaetae comprising 1−5 very fine,
         hair-like capillaries. Chaetiger 5 same in size as chaetigers 4 or 6, with dorsal superior
         and ventral capillaries same in shape and number as those chaetae on chaetigers 4 or 6; two
         kinds of heavy spines arranged in a vertical slightly curved double row; noto- and
         neuropodial postchaetal lamellae present ( Fig. 3 C−E). Anterior-row spines pennoned, with
         curved pointed tip, without subdistal constriction ( Fig. 3F ), up to 22 in a series;
         posterior-row spines simple falcate ( Fig. 3G ), up to 19 in a series. Bidentate hooded
         hooks in neuropodia from chaetiger 8, up to 15 in a series. Branchiae from chaetiger 7 to
         chaetiger 15. Pygidium flaring disc with wide dorsal gap and dorso-lateral processes ( Fig.
         3H–I ). Glandular pouches in neuropodia from chaetiger 1, largest and paired in each
         neuropodium in chaetigers 6 and 7, single in other neuropodia. </p>
      <p> MG staining </p>
      <p> Intensely stained ventral and lateral sides and notopodial postchaetal lamellae of 15–16
         anterior chaetigers, outer edges of branchiae ( Fig. 3C ); narrow transverse bands on
         dorsal side of branchiate chaetigers. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora achaeta </tp:taxon-name> was originally described from the
         South China Sea, Taiwan , as a common polychaete inhabiting tubes in soft sediments in
         brackish-water environments ( Radashevsky &amp; Hsieh 2000 ). Since then, the species was
         reported from Paraná and São Paulo ( Brazil ) ( Lana et al . 2006 ; Radashevsky &amp;
         Migotto 2006 ), Sea of Japan ( Russia ) ( Zvyagintsev et al . 2011 ), Pacific side of
         Honshu Island ( Japan ) ( Abe et al . 2014 , 2016 , 2019; Abe &amp; Sato-Okoshi 2021 ), and
         from Florida ( USA ) ( Bogantes et al . 2021 ). Here, for the first time, we report it for
         the Arabian Gulf ( Kuwait ). The only female had small oocytes up to 65 µm in diameter
         developing from chaetiger 15 onwards ( Fig. 3J ). The morphology of the specimens fits the
         diagnostic characters of <tp:taxon-name> P. achaeta </tp:taxon-name> . The same pattern of
         methylene green staining was observed in the type specimens of <tp:taxon-name> P. achaeta
         </tp:taxon-name> from Taiwan (MIMB 3401). The wide distribution of this species outside of
         its native area in the Northwest Pacific can be explained by unintentional human-mediated
         transportations of larvae with ballast water of ships, followed by successful invasions.
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p> Fig. 3. Adult morphology of <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora achaeta Radashevsky &amp; Hsieh,
         2000 </tp:taxon-name> (formalin-fixed and stained with MG specimens, MIMB 40934). A .
      Anterior end of a small juvenile, dorsal view, palps missing. B . Chaetigers 5–14 of a
      70-chaetiger female, dorsal view. C . Chaetigers 3–15 of a 70-chaetiger female, left lateral
      view. D . Chaetigers 4–6, left lateral view, showing vertical arrangement of heavy spines in
      notopodium of chaetiger 5. E . Parapodia of chaetiger 5. F . Heavy spines from notopodium of
      chaetiger 5, focused on anterior-row spines with a pennoned distal end. G . Same, focused on
      posteriorrow falcate spines. H . Posterior end, dorsal view. I . Same, right lateral view. J .
      Middle female chaetigers, left lateral view. Abbreviations: arrow showing the direction
      towards the posterior end of the body; ch5 = ch7 = chaetigers 5 and 7; ne = nephridium; su =
      dorsal superior capillary chaetae; ve = ventral capillary chaetae. Scale bars: A, D–E = 100
      µm; B–C, H–J = 200 µm; F–G = 20 µm. </p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> South China Sea: Taiwan ; Japan : Pacific side of Honshu Island; Brazil : Paraná , São
         Paulo ; Atlantic USA : Florida ; Arabian Gulf: Kuwait . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
