<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pseudopolydora auha Radashevsky &amp; Malyar &amp; Pankova 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5544471</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CEEAD59BAA6ECB64226C0C1896C18A73</uri>
         <article-title>Pseudopolydora (Annelida: Spionidae) from the Arabian Gulf, Kuwait</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1519</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopolydora auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1D
, 
11
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Caruncle to end of chaetiger 6. Branchiae present beyond the middle of the body. Pygidium bilobed.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name refers to the 
type
locality of the species in the intertidal of Auha Island, Arabian Gulf.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
KUWAIT
• 
1 spec.
; Arabian Gulf, 
Auha Is.
; 
29.3764° N
, 
48.4391° E
; 

29 Jan. 2017

; 
Vasily I. Radashevsky
leg.; low intertidal; from shell limestone encrusted by coralline alga; 
MIMB 40907
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
KUWAIT
• 
1 spec.
; same collection data as for holotype; GenBank 16S gene 
MW904103
, GenBank 18S gene 
MW904112
, GenBank 28S gene 
MW904156
, GenBank Histone 3 gene 
MW923741
; used entirely for molecular analysis
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Two complete individuals in good condition with palps were found together in a shell limestone encrusted by coralline alga. The 22-chaetiger individual is designated as the 
holotype
. The 42-chaetiger 
paratype
was examined and then used entirely for molecular analysis.
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
about 
2 mm
long, 
0.37 mm
wide with 22 chaetigers (
Fig. 11A
). 
Paratype
about 
5 mm
long, with 42 chaetigers. Pigmentation absent on body and palps. Prostomium anteriorly bifid, with two short triangular lobes (
Fig. 11A
), posteriorly extending to end of chaetiger 6 as a low caruncle in both types. Occipital antenna present on caruncle between palps. Two pairs of black eyes arranged trapezoidally, comprising one pair of median eyes, and one pair of lateral eyes situated anteriorly and set wider apart. Palps as long as 15–20 chaetigers, with frontal longitudinal groove lined with fine cilia, and short compound non-motile cilia arising directly from palp surface sparsely arranged in line on sides of groove and sparsely scattered on lateral and abfrontal palp surfaces.
</p>
      <p>Chaetiger 1 with short capillaries in neuropodia, and small lamellae in both rami; notochaetae absent. Chaetiger 2 notochaetae all slender capillaries with narrow limbation.Anterior-row notopodial capillaries on chaetiger 3 with slightly enlarged wing; capillaries on chaetiger 4 with wing slightly larger than on chaetigers 3. Anterior-row capillaries on chaetigers 3, 4, 6 and 7 arranged in J-shaped series; posteriorrow capillaries on these chaetigers arranged in vertical series. Posterior notopodia with a few long alimbate capillary chaetae.</p>
      <p>
Chaetiger 5 slightly larger than chaetigers 4 or 6, with dorsal superior capillaries, two kinds of notopodial spines arranged in a double U-shaped row, and ventral capillaries; noto- and neuropodial postchaetal lamellae same as on chaetiger 4 (
Fig. 11D
). Dorsal superior capillaries slightly shorter and fewer than those capillaries on chaetiger 4. Ventral capillaries same in size, number and arrangement (in three groups) as those on chaetiger 4. Newly developed spines in posterior upper part of U-shaped row slightly larger than older spines in anterior upper part of row. Outer (anterior-row) notopodial spines 
4–6 in
a series, with distal part of stem enlarged, with concavity on top and large triangular tooth on its side directed upwards and facing towards the inside of the U-shaped row of spines; fine bristles arising from tooth and concavity forming a long flag-like pointed transparent tip which is usually broken in worn old spines in the anterior upper part of row (
Fig. 11E
). Inner (posterior-row) notopodial spines 
4–5 in
a series, falcate, with short rounded distal part geniculate, with subdistal bulbous swelling bearing very short fine bristles and facing towards the inside of the U-shaped row of spines (
Fig. 11E
).
</p>
      <p>
Hooks in neuropodia from chaetiger 8, up to 
20 in
a series, not accompanied by capillaries, in posterior chaetigers situated on top of prominent fleshy neuropodial lobes. Hooks bidentate, with upper tooth closely applied to main fang; upper part of shaft with constriction; lower part of shaft bent at right angle (
Fig. 11F
).
</p>
      <p>
Branchiae from chaetiger 7 to chaetiger 
15 in
holotype
, and to chaetiger 
24 in
paratype
, on chaetiger 7 slightly shorter than those on chaetiger 8, full-sized from chaetigers 9–10, free from notopodial postchaetal lamellae, flattened, with surfaces oriented perpendicular to body axis, with longitudinal ciliation (extension of nototroch) running on inner edge.
</p>
      <p>Pygidium bilobed, with two semi-oval lateral lobes, white due to many spindle-shaped glandular cells with striated content.</p>
      <p>Glandular pouches in neuropodia from chaetiger 1, largest and paired in each neuropodium in chaetigers 6 and 7, single in other neuropodia.</p>
      <p>Digestive tract without ventral buccal bulb and gizzard-like structure, without pigmentation.</p>
      <p>Nephridia from chaetiger 4 onwards.</p>
      <p>
MG staining
</p>
      <p>Intensely stained anterior part of the prostomium in front of eyes, and dorso-lateral sides of the peristomium. Weakly stained lateral sides of chaetigers and scattered glandular cells on the ventral side of chaetigers.</p>
      <p>
Habitat
</p>
      <p>
The 
two types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
were found together in a shell limestone encrusted by a coralline alga. Whether the worms made the burrows themselves or occupied empty holes made by other organisms remains uncertain.
</p>
      <p>
Reproduction
</p>
      <p>
Both examined individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
were juveniles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
In the Arabian Gulf, adults of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
appear very similar to those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. antennata
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. melanopalpa
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(see below). They all have heavy spines in the notopodia of chaetiger 5 of the same morphology, branchiae beyond the middle of the body, and the bilobed pygidia with dorsal and ventral clefts (characters shared by all members of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. antennata
</tp:taxon-name>
-complex, see below in the Discussion). However, they can be distinguished by the prostomium shape, length of the caruncle, and palp pigmentation. In 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. antennata
</tp:taxon-name>
, the prostomium is anteriorly bifurcated, with two long pointed antero-lateral processes (to which the name of the species was referred), whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. melanopalpa
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
the prostomia are incised, with two short lobes. In 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. antennata
</tp:taxon-name>
, the caruncle extends posteriorly maximum to the end of chaetiger 4, whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. melanopalpa
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
the caruncle extends to the end of chaetiger 5, and in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
it extends to the end of chaetiger 6.
</p>
      <p>
Adults of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
appear very similar to those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. uphondo
Simon, Sato-Okoshi &amp; Abe, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. eriyali
Simon, Sato-Okoshi &amp; Abe, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
both of which were described from 
South Africa
by 

Simon 
et al
. (2019)

. They share the characters of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. antennata
</tp:taxon-name>
-complex (see below in the Discussion); the morphological differences between the three species are very subtle (see 

Simon 
et al
. 2019

: table 1) although genetically they are well separated (
Fig. 2
). Adult 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. eriyali
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
have caruncles extending to the end of chaetiger 6, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. uphondo
</tp:taxon-name>
the caruncle extends to the end of chaetiger 5. Additional specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
should be examined to understand the morphological variability of this species and the differences between this species and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. eriyali
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. uphondo
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 11.
Adult morphology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopolydora auha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (MIMB 40907), formalin-fixed and stained with MG). 
A
. Anterior end, dorsal view. 
B
. Posterior chaetigers, ventral view. 
C
. Posterior end, left lateral view. 
D
. Notopodium of chaetiger 5. 
E
. Notochaetae of chaetiger 5. 
F
. A series of hooded hooks from neuropodium of chaetiger 12. Abbreviations: 
arrow
showing the direction towards the inside of the U-shaped row of spines of chaetiger 5; 
an
= anterior-row spine from notopodium of chaetiger 5; 
no
= notopodial postchaetal lamella; 
po
= posterior-row spine from notopodium of chaetiger 5; 
su
= dorsal superior capillary chaetae. Scale bars: A = 100 µm; B–D = 50 µm; E–F = 20 µm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Arabian Gulf: 
Kuwait
(
Fig. 1D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
