<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pseudopolydora kuwaiti Radashevsky
                        &amp; Malyar &amp; Pankova 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1519</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03CF9F22FF87AE7A6D04367FFDEFF86F</uri>
                  <article-title>Pseudopolydora (Annelida: Spionidae) from the Arabian Gulf,
                        Kuwait</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1519</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 1C , 5E , 12–16 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora sp. C </tp:taxon-name> − Al-Kandari et al . 2019: 9
                  . — Radashevsky et al . 2020: table 1, fig. 1. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>Prostomium anteriorly notched to weakly incised, with two rounded lobes. Palps with
                  up to 11 yellow bands. Occipital antenna absent. Anterior-row capillaries in
                  notopodia from chaetiger 7 to chaetigers 9−14 with wide subtriangular, pennoned
                  limbation. Chaetiger 5 larger than chaetigers 4 and 6, dorsally overlapping
                  anterior part of chaetiger 6; lower (anterior-row) notopodial spines, with distal
                  part of stem enlarged, cup-shaped, with a concavity on top and long pennoned,
                  pointed tip. Pygidium small and fleshy, disc-like to cup-shaped, with dorsal gap
                  to incision.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The name refers to the type locality of the species in Kuwaiti waters. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Holotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> KUWAIT • 1 spec. ; Arabian Gulf , Al-Judailiat ; 29.377° N
                        , 47.759° E ; 4 Feb. 2015 ; Vasily I. Radashevsky leg.; low intertidal; fine
                        sand; MIMB 40853 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> KUWAIT • 8 specs; Arabian Gulf , Khor Al-Subiya (
                        Al-Shumaima ); 29.658° N , 48.1327° E ; 25 Nov. 2014 ; low intertidal; muddy
                        sand + gravel around oyster aggregations; MIMB 40708 </tp:material-citation>
                  • <tp:material-citation> 2 specs; northwest of Failaka Is. ; 29.4722° N , 48.2965°
                        E ; 22 Dec. 2014 ; middle intertidal; on stone; MIMB 40709
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 2 specs; south of Boubyan Is. ;
                        29.6478° N , 48.3156° E ; 23 Dec. 2014 ; low intertidal; on stone; MIMB
                        40710 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 45 specs; Boubyan Is.
                        ; 29.649° N , 48.3136° E ; 24 Jan. 2015 ; low intertidal; on empty shells
                        and stones; MIMB 40711 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1
                        spec. ; Boubyan Is. ; 29.7897° N , 48.3727° E ; 25 Jan. 2015 ; upper
                        intertidal; on stone; MIMB 40712 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 17 specs; same collection data as for holotype; MIMB
                        40713 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 2 specs; Al-Doha (
                        Aushairij ); 29.388° N , 47.821° E ; 5 Feb. 2015 ; low intertidal; shells,
                        sand, gravel, stone; MIMB 40854 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 spec. ; Al-Bedaa ; 29.3228° N , 48.092° E ; 2 Mar.
                        2016 ; low intertidal; sand; MIMB 40855 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 3 specs; Auha Is. ; 29.3764° N , 48.4391° E ; 29 Jan.
                        2017 ; low intertidal; from shell limestone encrusted by coralline alga;
                        MIMB 40856 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 spec. ; Ras
                        Ajuza , Kuwait City ; 29.3913° N , 47.9967° E ; 29 Apr. 2017 ; low
                        intertidal; sandy tube attached to the rock; MIMB 40857
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> KUWAIT • 2 specs; Auha Is. ; 29.3764° N , 48.4391° E ; 29
                        Jan. 2017 ; low intertidal; from dead coral encrusted by coralline algae and
                        from shell of the gastropod <tp:taxon-name> Indothais scalaris (Shubert
                              &amp; J.A. Wagner, 1829) </tp:taxon-name> ; used in molecular
                        analysis; VIR 19871 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 spec.
                        ; east of Failaka Is. ; 29.3916° N , 48.3989° E </tp:material-citation> ; </p>
            <p> l 4 Feb. 2017 ; low intertidal; from gastropod shell occupied by hermit crab;
                  examined but not preserved; VIR 20287 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Adults up to 6 mm long, 0.4 mm wide with 35 chaetigers ( Fig. 12A ). Fine black
                  pigment usually scattered on dorsal and ventral sides of head and 10−13 anterior
                  chaetigers ( Fig. 13A–C ). Up to 11 yellow bands (branched chromatophores) present
                  on each palp when alive ( Figs 12A–C, E , 13B , 14A ), not visible after fixation.
                  Prostomium anteriorly usually notched or weakly incised, with two rounded lobes (
                  Figs 12B , 13D ), occasionally blunt ( Fig. 13A ), posteriorly extending to end of
                  chaetiger 2 as a low caruncle ( Fig. 14C ). Usually two pairs of black eyes
                  present. Occipital antenna absent ( Fig. 12D ). Palps as long as 15−20 chaetigers,
                  with longitudinal frontal groove lined with fine cilia, short motile compound
                  cilia regularly arranged in one row along ciliated groove, and non-motile cilia
                  arising from palp surface and scattered on lateral and abfrontal surfaces. </p>
            <p> Chaetiger 1 with short capillaries in neuropodia, short notopodial postchaetal
                  lamellae and well-developed neuropodial lamellae; notochaetae absent. Notochaetae
                  of chaetigers 2−4 and 6, and neurochaetae of chaetigers 1−7 slender capillaries
                  with narrow wing. Anterior-row capillaries in notopodia from chaetiger 7 to
                  chaetigers 9−14 (chaetiger 12 in holotype ) with wide subtriangular, pennoned
                  limbation ( Figs 14C , 15A–B ), up to five in a series; superior and posterior-row
                  notochaetae in these chaetigers slender capillaries with narrow wing; superior
                  capillaries longer than posterior-row capillaries, with long narrow wing.
                  Posterior notopodia with a few long alimbate capillary chaetae. </p>
            <p> Chaetiger 5 larger than chaetigers 4 and 6, dorsally overlapping anterior part of
                  chaetiger 6, with up to four dorsal superior capillaries, two kinds of notopodial
                  spines arranged in a curved diagonal or almost horizontal double row, and ten
                  ventral capillaries; notopodial lamellae lacking but neuropodial postchaetal
                  lamellae present, same as on chaetigers 4 and 6 ( Figs 12B, F , 13A ). Dorsal
                  superior capillaries shorter and fewer than those capillaries on chaetigers 4 and
                  6. Ventral capillaries same in size, number and arrangement (in three groups) as
                  those on chaetiger 4. Lower (anterior-row) notopodial spines, with distal part of
                  stem enlarged, cup-shaped, with concavity on top and long pennoned, pointed distal
                  tip ( Fig. 15C ), up to ten in a series. Upper (posterior-row) notopodial spines
                  simple falcate ( Fig. 15C ), up to seven in a series. Newly developed spines in
                  posterior part of curved series slightly larger than older spines in anterior part
                  of series ( Fig. 12F ). </p>
            <p> Hooks in neuropodia from chaetiger 8, up to 11 in a series, not accompanied by
                  capillaries. Hooks bidentate, with upper tooth closely applied to main fang; upper
                  part of shaft with constriction; lower part of shaft bent at right angle in hooks
                  in posterior neuropodia ( Fig. 15D–E ). </p>
            <p> Branchiae from chaetiger 7 to chaetiger 16 (chaetiger 16 in holotype ), up to ten
                  pairs, fewer in small individuals ( Figs 5E , 14B ), free from notopodial
                  postchaetal lamellae, flattened, with surfaces oriented perpendicular to body
                  axis, with longitudinal ciliation (extension of nototroch) on inner anterior edge. </p>
            <p>In immature individuals and females, short nototroch present on chaetiger 3 and
                  longer nototrochs with longer cilia from chaetiger 7 onwards, each composed of
                  single row of ciliated cells extending onto branchiae on branchiate chaetigers. In
                  males, nototrochs present from chaetiger 2 onwards, each composed of two rows of
                  ciliated cells (anterior row extending onto branchiae; posterior row running only
                  across chaetiger), and additional intersegmental transverse ciliary rows present
                  from chaetiger 3, situated on anterior edge of chaetigers; cilia of nototrochs
                  longer than those of intersegmental rows. In both sexes, nototrochs on branchiate
                  chaetigers as transverse ciliary bands, on postbranchiate chaetigers gradually
                  becoming U-shaped, with arms directed posteriorly. One or two pairs of short
                  compound motile cilia usually present on dorsal side of each of chaetigers 4 and
                  5.</p>
            <p> Pygidium small and fleshy, disc-like to cup-shaped, with dorsal gap to incision (
                  Fig. 13E–F ), white due to numerous fusiform glandular cells with striated
                  content. </p>
            <p> Glandular pouches in neuropodia from chaetiger 1, largest in chaetigers 6 and 7,
                  single pouch in each neuropodium ( Fig. 15D ). </p>
            <p>Digestive tract without ventral buccal bulb and gizzard-like structure. Oesophagus
                  narrow, extending through 7−8 anterior chaetigers.</p>
            <p>Main dorsal blood vessel transformed into gut sinus in anterior part of midgut. Heart
                  body absent. Blood red, without globules or other elements.</p>
            <p> Fig. 12. Adult morphology of <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name>
                  sp. nov. (live individuals, MIMB 40713). A . Left lateral general view, female, in
                  reflected light, showing white chromatophores on palps. B–D . Anterior ends, in
                  transmitted light, dorsal (B) and left lateral (C–D) view. E . Fragment of palp
                  with chromatophore and inner blood vessel. F . Chaetigers 4–6, left lateral view,
                  showing curved diagonal row of heavy spines in notopodium of chaetiger 5.
                  Abbreviations: ho = hooded hooks; no = notopodial postchaetal lamella; pe =
                  pennoned capillary notochaetae; su = dorsal superior capillary chaetae; ve =
                  ventral capillary chaetae. Scale bars: A = 200 µm; B–D = 50 µm; E = 20 µm. </p>
            <p>Nephridia from chaetiger 4 onwards. In female fertile chaetigers, paired nephridia on
                  each chaetiger opening to exterior via common middorsal nephridiopore anteriorly
                  to nototroch.</p>
            <p> Habitat </p>
            <p> Adult <tp:taxon-name> P. kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. inhabit silty tubes in
                  muddy sand intertidally and in shallow waters and also bore in live mollusc
                  shells, dead corals and shell limestone encrusted by coralline algae. While the
                  species is comparatively rare, the population density in some local places can
                  reach a maximum of one thousand individuals per 1 m 2 . In hard substrata, worms
                  occasionally form aggregations of 1−3 individuals per 1 cm 2 . </p>
            <p> Reproduction </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is gonochoristic.
                  Both in females and males, gametes developed from chaetiger 12 to chaetigers 16−29
                  ( Fig. 14D ). Paired testes or ovaries were attached to segmental blood vessels in
                  fertile chaetigers. </p>
            <p> Fig. 13. Adult morphology of <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name>
                  sp. nov. (live individuals, MIMB 40713). A–D . Anterior ends, dorsal (A, D) and
                  ventral (B–C) view. E–F . Posterior ends, left lateral (E) and dorsal (F) view.
                  Scale bars: A = 500 µm; B–C = 200 µm; D = 100 µm; E = 50 µm. </p>
            <p> Oogenesis was partly intraovarian ( Fig. 15F ). Developed coelomic oocytes were
                  spherical, about 100 µm in diameter. Oocyte envelope was smooth, less than 1 µm
                  thick. </p>
            <p>Spermatogonia proliferated in testes; spermatogenesis occurred in the coelomic
                  cavity. Spermatids, each 3−4 µm in diameter, were joined in octads. Spermatozoa
                  were introsperm with pointed acrosome about 1.5 µm long, straight elongated
                  nucleus about 1.5 µm in diameter and 6 µm long, midpiece 3.5 µm (head + midpiece
                  about 11 µm long), and a flagellum about 32 µm long (the precision of measurement
                  of spermatids and parts of head of spermatozoa were at maximum to the nearest 0.5
                  µm and flagellum to the nearest 2 µm).</p>
            <p> Fig. 14. Adult characteristics of <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora kuwaiti
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. A . Relationships between number of yellow bands on palp
                  and total number of chaetigers. B . Relationships between distribution of
                  branchiae (referring to number of the last branchiate chaetiger) and total number
                  of chaetigers. C . Relationships between caruncle length (in chaetiger numbers)
                  and total number of chaetigers, and distribution of pennoned capillaries in
                  notopodia (referring to number of the last chaetiger with pennoned capillaries)
                  and total number of chaetigers. D . Relationships between distribution of gametes
                  (referring to number of the first and the last chaetigers with gametes) and total
                  number of chaetigers. </p>
            <p> Larval development in the plankton </p>
            <p> The spermatophores and egg capsules, typically produced by <tp:taxon-name>
                        Pseudopolydora </tp:taxon-name> , were not observed in <tp:taxon-name>
                        Pseudopolydora kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. The 10−14-chaetiger larvae
                  of this species were collected in plankton in March 2016 . The 14-chaetiger larvae
                  were easily identified by the specific heavy spines in the notopodia of chaetiger
                  5. Small larvae, with heavy spines not yet developed, were identified by the
                  specific pigmentation, revealed in larger larvae. </p>
            <p> 10-chaetiger larvae </p>
            <p>Larvae 500−550 µm long. Posterior middle part of prostomium slightly inflated as a
                  caruncle but not extending over chaetiger 1. Nuchal ciliary patches on sides of
                  caruncle at level of prototroch. Palps as long as about half of chaetiger 1.
                  Notopodia with only provisional serrated bristles. Short adult capillaries in
                  neuropodia of chaetigers 2−7. Heavy spines in chaetiger 5 and branchiae not yet
                  developed. Hooks in neuropodia from chaetiger 8. Pygidium semispherical.
                  Gastrotrochs on chaetigers 3, 5 and 7. Glandular pouches absent. One pair of
                  protonephridia in chaetiger 1.</p>
            <p> Fig. 15. Chaetal and gamete morphology of <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora kuwaiti
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. (live individuals, MIMB 40713). A . Notopodia of
                  chaetigers 8 and 9, showing pennoned capillaries in the anterior row of
                  notochaetae. B . Notopodium of chaetiger 10, showing pennoned capillaries in the
                  anterior row of notochaetae. C . Chaetae of chaetiger 5. D . A series of hooded
                  hooks and glandular pouch from neuropodium of chaetiger 10. E . A series of hooded
                  hooks from a posterior neuropodium. F . Female fertile chaetigers, left lateral
                  view, showing vitellogenic oocytes in ovaries. Abbreviations: no = notopodial
                  postchaetal lamella; su = dorsal superior capillary chaetae; ve = ventral
                  capillary chaetae. Scale bars: A–E = 20 µm; F = 50 µm. </p>
            <p> 11-chaetiger larvae </p>
            <p> Larvae 550−600 µm long, with palps as long as 1−2 chaetigers. Notopodia with only
                  provisional serrated bristles. Short adult capillaries in neuropodia of chaetigers
                  1−7; those in chaetiger 1 shorter and fewer than in succeeding chaetigers, 1−2 in
                  a tuft. Notopodia of chaetiger 5 with 1−2 anterior-row spines with pointed distal
                  tip, and one posterior-row heavy falcate spine among provisional serrated
                  bristles. Branchiae not yet developed. Hooks in neuropodia from chaetiger 8.
                  Glandular pouches in neuropodia from chaetiger 3 onwards; pouches in chaetigers
                  3−5 each composed of one small glandular cell; from chaetiger 6 onwards, each
                  pouch composed of two cells. One pair of protonephridia in chaetiger 1. </p>
            <p> 12−13-chaetiger larvae </p>
            <p> Larvae 650−700 µm long, with palps as long as 2−3 chaetigers ( Fig. 16A ). Short
                  adult capillaries in neuropodia of chaetigers 1−7. Chaetiger 5 with two kinds of
                  heavy spines in notopodia, comprising three anterior-row spines and two
                  posterior-row falcate spines. Single capillary chaetae with pennoned limbation in
                  notopodia of chaetigers 7 and 8. Short branchial buds on chaetiger 7. Gastrotrochs
                  on chaetigers 3, 5, 7 and 11. Glandular pouches in neuropodia from chaetigers 2−3.
                  Protonephridia in chaetigers 1 and 2; metanephridia from chaetiger 4 onwards. </p>
            <p> 14-chaetiger larvae </p>
            <p> Larvae 700−750 µm long and up to 200 µm wide in middle part ( Fig. 16 B−E). Intense
                  pigmentation comprising small melanophores and fine yellowish pigment scattered
                  all along body, in anterior part of prostomium, in pharynx and in pygidium;
                  distinct chromatophores absent. A small black spot present between median and
                  lateral eyes on each side of prostomium. Small middorsal melanophores in anterior
                  part of chaetiger 1 and on pygidium at level of telotroch; chaetiger 1 melanophore
                  occasionally heavily ramified and hardly discernible. Small paired dorsal
                  melanophores from chaetiger 3 onwards. Small dorso-lateral melanophores from
                  chaetigers 3−4 onwards, usually indistinct, difficult to recognize. Single small
                  lateral melanophores on either side on anterior edge of chaetiger 2; in some
                  larvae, lateral melanophores appearing as indistinct spots of diffused black
                  pigment. </p>
            <p>Prostomium anteriorly wide and rounded, posteriorly extending to middle of chaetiger
                  1 as a low narrow caruncle. Nuchal organs large round ciliary patches on sides of
                  caruncle on anterior half of chaetiger 1. Occipital antenna absent. Three pairs of
                  black eyes arranged almost in a transverse line, comprising one pair of small
                  rounded median eyes and two pairs of lateral eyes; lateral eyes on each side
                  situated close to each other and appearing as one comma-shaped eye. One pair of
                  spherical unpigmented ocelli, each about 17 µm in diameter, present in front of
                  pigmented eyes. One pair of compound motile cilia, each about 20 µm long, situated
                  near median eyes, and one pair of compound cells, each about 75 µm long, situated
                  near lateral eyes. One pair of palps arising from posterior dorso-lateral edges of
                  peristomium, posterior to prototroch; each palp as long as about four chaetigers.
                  Shallow frontal longitudinal groove on palps densely ciliated.</p>
            <p>Prototroch and telotroch well developed. Nototrochs and grasping cilia from chaetiger
                  3 onwards. Triangular neurotroch extending over ventral peristomial lip from mouth
                  to end of chaetiger 1. Two small ciliated cells present on each side of
                  neurotroch. Ventral ciliated pit absent. Gastrotrochs on chaetigers 5, 7 and 11,
                  each composed of six large cells with numerous long cilia.</p>
            <p>Provisional serrated bristles in all notopodia including chaetiger 5; those in
                  anterior chaetigers up to 175 µm long, gradually becoming shorted in succeeding
                  chaetiger. Short adult capillaries in notopodia from chaetiger 2, and in
                  neuropodia in chaetigers 1−7. Single capillary chaetae with flag-like limbation in
                  notopodia of chaetigers 7 and 8.</p>
            <p>Chaetiger 5 with two kinds of heavy spines in notopodia in addition to short adult
                  capillaries and long provisional bristles. Spines comprising 3−4 anterior-row
                  spines with wide cup-shaped distal end of stem bearing long transparent pointed
                  tip, and 2−3 posterior-row simple falcate spines.</p>
            <p>Hooks in neuropodia from chaetiger 8 onwards, up to five in a series, not accompanied
                  by capillaries. Hooks bidentate, with upper tooth closely applied to main fang,
                  with outer hood; lower part of shaft bent almost at right angle.</p>
            <p>Branchiae short, on chaetigers 7 and 8. Pygidium semispherical, divided into two
                  rounded lobes by vertical median furrow and bearing four short papillae.</p>
            <p>Lateral sensory organs, each 4−5 µm in diameter, with thin non-motile cilia up to 20
                  µm long situated between noto- and neuropodia from chaetiger 1 onwards, including
                  chaetigers 3−5.</p>
            <p> Numerous oval to spherical glandular cells with striated content present in anterior
                  part of prostomium, on dorsal side of chaetigers, in pygidium and palps ( Fig. 16E
                  ). </p>
            <p>Glandular pouches in neuropodia from chaetigers 1−2, very small in first chaetigers,
                  large in chaetigers 6 and 7, gradually diminishing in size in succeeding
                  chaetigers.</p>
            <p>Large lateral lips and small ventral lip of peristomium lined with numerous short
                  cilia and forming voluminous vestibulum. Compound motile cilia up to 65 µm long
                  present on lateral and ventral sides of lateral peristomial lips. Narrow
                  oesophagus extending through three chaetigers. Gizzard-like structure absent in
                  digestive tract. Numerous lipid globules up to 10 µm in diameter present in wall
                  of voluminous midgut.</p>
            <p>Circulatory system developed and functional; blood transparent, without pigment.</p>
            <p>Two pairs of protonephridia in chaetigers 1 and 2. Metanephridia from chaetiger 4
                  onwards.</p>
            <p> Fig. 16. Larval and juvenile morphology of <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora kuwaiti
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Live larvae in reflected (A–C) and transmitted (D–E)
                  light. A . 13-chaetiger larva, dorsal view. B . 14-chaetiger larva, left lateral
                  view. C . The same, ventral view. D . The same, dorsal view. E . The same,
                  anterior end. F . 21-chaetiger juvenile, left lateral view. Scale bars: A–D = 100
                  µm; E = 50 µm; F = 500 µm. </p>
            <p> Settlement and metamorphosis </p>
            <p> 14-chaetiger larvae </p>
            <p>Larvae about 700 µm long easily settled and underwent gradual metamorphosis in Petri
                  dishes. They started crawling and in the absence of sediment built transparent
                  mucous tubes. The metamorphosis comprised loss of larval features, such as
                  provisional bristles in notopodia, proto-, telo-, neuro-, gastrotrochs and
                  grasping cilia, nototrochs on chaetigers 3−5, and also the transformation of the
                  head and rapid elongation of the palps. The prostomium became distinctly separated
                  from the peristomium. Nuchal organs transformed from oval ciliary patches to
                  longitudinal narrow ciliary bands on the posterior sides of the prostomium.
                  Lateral peristomial lips became reduced and transformed into dorso-lateral ciliary
                  folds of the foregut. The ventral peristomial lip enlarged and formed the adult
                  peristomium and basement for the palps. Unpigmented ocelli in the prostomium and
                  larval protonephridia in chaetigers 1 and 2 became reduced and disintegrated.</p>
            <p> 20−21-chaetiger juveniles </p>
            <p> Juveniles about 2 mm long, with remains of yellowish pigment scattered on head and
                  pygidium ( Fig. 16F ). Prostomium anteriorly narrow and rounded, posteriorly
                  extending over 1−2 chaetigers. Occipital antenna absent. Palps as long as 12−15
                  chaetigers, without yellowish chromatophores or one chromatophore present on each
                  palp. Capillary chaetae with pennoned limbation in notopodia of chaetigers 7−10.
                  Branchiae on chaetigers 7−10. Glandular pouches in neuropodia from chaetiger 1.
                  Metanephridia from chaetiger 4 onwards. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Adult <tp:taxon-name> P. kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. appear similar to the
                  Asian Pacific <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora diopatra Hsieh, 1992 </tp:taxon-name>
                  . Both have yellow ramified chromatophores on palps, caruncles without occipital
                  antenna extending to the end of chaetiger 2, and small cup-shaped pygidia ( Hsieh
                  1992 ). They differ from other <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora </tp:taxon-name> by
                  having greatly enlarged chaetiger 5 (instead of chaetiger 5 being similar in size
                  to chaetigers 4 and 6) with the notopodial heavy spines arranged in a diagonal
                  instead of a vertical double row, and also by the unique morphology of the
                  pennoned spines, which have a stem with a cup-shaped distal end and a long pointed
                  tip which is easily broken at the base. The two species differ from each other
                  genetically but morphologically are very similar and can only be distinguished by
                  small paired melanophores on the ventral side of the anterior chaetigers which are
                  present in <tp:taxon-name> P. diopatra </tp:taxon-name> from the Asian Pacific and
                  absent in <tp:taxon-name> P. kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. from the Arabian
                  Gulf. </p>
            <p> Larvae of <tp:taxon-name> P. kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. appear similar to
                  those of <tp:taxon-name> P. arabica </tp:taxon-name> (see Radashevsky &amp;
                  Al-Kandari 2020 ). Both occur in the plankton at the same time, have gastrotrochs
                  on chaetigers 3, 5, 7 and 11, and are intensely pigmented with yellow and black
                  pigments. They differ in that the larvae of <tp:taxon-name> P. arabica
                  </tp:taxon-name> may postpone metamorphosis in the absence of substratum and
                  attain 1250 µm long with 23 chaetigers, whereas the largest larvae of
                        <tp:taxon-name> P. kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. caught from the
                  plankton were 750 µm long with 14 chaetigers. The developed 15−17-chaetiger larvae
                  of <tp:taxon-name> P. arabica </tp:taxon-name> have one to three yellow ramified
                  chromatophores on each palp, paired dorsal melanophores from chaetigers 6−7,
                  dorso-lateral melanophores from chaetiger 4 to chaetigers 6−10, and one pair of
                  small melanophores in lateral peristomial lips. In <tp:taxon-name> P. kuwaiti
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , chromatophores on palps appear in juveniles; the
                  developed larvae have paired dorsal melanophores from chaetiger 3 onwards, and
                  dorso-lateral melanophores from chaetigers 3−4 onwards; melanophores in lateral
                  peristomial lips are absent. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Pseudopolydora kuwaiti </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is the only
                  species of the genus inhabiting soft sediments as well as boring into mollusc
                  shells and dead corrals encrusted by coralline algae. Our genetic analysis
                  confirmed the conspecificity of the tube-dwelling and shell-boring individuals (
                  Fig. 2 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Arabian Gulf: Kuwait ( Fig. 1C ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
