<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Alcathousiella Monne 2005</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5055985</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03D293124269512BFDD8968FFD2DFC4C</uri>
         <article-title>A review of the genus Alcathousiella Monné, 2005 (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1411</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alcathousiella
Monné, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Alcathousiella
Monné, 2005: 11
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amniscus
Bates, 1863: 103
</tp:taxon-name>

(not Dejean, 1835).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Alcathous
Thomson, 1864: 24
</tp:taxon-name>

, type species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alcidion polyrhaphoides
White, 1855
</tp:taxon-name>
(original designation); not 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alcathous
Stål, 1863
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Hemiptera</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Alcathous</tp:taxon-name>
–

Thomson 1865: 353

. — 

Monné 1995: 43

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amniscus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Lacordaire 1872: 761

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Alcathousiella
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Monné 2012: 66

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Among the genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Acanthocinini</tp:taxon-name>
with modified antennomere III (
Fig. 14
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alcathousiella
</tp:taxon-name>
can be distinguished by the scape strongly pedunculate-clavate with a spiniform projection at the inner side of the apex.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>HEAD. As long as wide; lower eyes lobes slightly longer than genae; upper eyes lobes separated by about twice width of an upper eye lobe. Antennal tubercles strongly elevated distally from middle. Median groove distinct from clypeus to area behind upper eyes lobes, posteriorly covered by anterior margin of prothorax. Antennae filiform, 11-segmented, longer than body in both sexes. Scape pedunculatedclavate, clave starting at posterior third; reaching humeral area of elytra, inner side of apex with a spine-shaped projection in both sexes. Apex of antennomere III in males, with an internal spine-shaped projection.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Pronotum with dense greyish pubescence; with five prominent tubercles, four broadly rounded (two larger at anterior half and two smaller ones posteriorly) and one, elongate and postmedian. Punctures arranged in transverse rows on anterior and posterior margins (at posterior margin, obliquely converging towards middle). Additional punctures scattered throughout pronotal disk. Sides of prothorax with prominent median conical tubercle. Prosternum micropunctate, moderately densely pubescent. Metaventrite in males with dense erect setae obscuring integument (setae can also extend to middle of abdominal ventrite I). Prosternal process usually ⅓ procoxal width; mesoventral process slightly wider than half of mesocoxal diameter.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Lacking erect setae; pubescence nearly obscuring integument, generally forming symmetrical patterns. Elytral surface with small tubercles on anterior third; anterior fifth with central basal crest; prominent basal crest with an erect tuft of setae apically; prominent area surrounding central basal crest rounded with small tubercles. Humeri rounded.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Femora strongly pedunculate-clavate; meso and metafemora with peduncles about as long as claves; profemora with short peduncle; tibiae elongate, slightly widened toward apex. Protarsomeres in males with dense bristly setae; metatarsomere I equal to or slightly longer than remaining metatarsomeres together.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Male with ventrite V deeply semicircularly notched and projected as minute spine; tergite V slightly notched or subtruncate.</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Antennomere III lacking acute internal spine at apex. Abdominal ventrite V, gradually narrowed from base to apex, apex subtruncate; tergite V acute apically, slightly surpassing the elytral apices. Protarsomere lacking dense bristly setae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
