<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Oplognathus helmenreichi Ohaus 1905</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1471</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03D38784E15C453CFDA1FC65FBDFF998</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the genus Oplognathus MacLeay, 1819 (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Rutelinae: Rutelini)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1471</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1c–e
, 
2b–d
, 
3c–d
, 
4i–m
, 

6
, 
7e

–h, 
8c, f
, 9
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905: 322
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus helmenreichi
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Ohaus 1914a: 301

(species description); 1918: 12 (catalogue). — 

Blackwelder 1944: 235

(catalogue).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus helmreicheni
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Ohaus 1914a: 302
(species description)

; 1918: 12 (catalogue); 1934: 42 (catalogue). — 

Blackwelder 1944: 235

(catalogue).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmreicheni
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Machatschke 1972: 5
(catalogue).

— 

Krajcik 2007: 90
(catalogue).

<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Machatschke 1972: 5
(catalogue).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus helmreicheni
var. 
maculicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Ohaus 1914a: 302
(description, infrasubspecific name, unavailable).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Elytra reddish brown to orange yellow; male with clypeus moderately trilobate, lobes distinctly rounded, sides parallel (
Figs 1c–e
, 
3c–d
); antennal club 1.8× longer than antennomeres 2–7 combined (
Fig. 3c– d
); females with club length 1.5× longer than antennomeres 2–7 combined; last maxillary palpomere cylindrical in both sexes (
Fig. 4l
); mentum longer than wide, anterior margin slightly sinuous, posterior angles rounded (

Fig. 
4m

). Elytral striae distinctly marked; elytral epipleuron of female slightly dilated; mesoventral process long, apex rounded, never reaching anterior coxae (
Fig. 8c, f
); apex of the mesotibia with 7–13 spinules; apex of metatibia with 14–22 spinules in both sexes.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
(
Figs 1c
, 
2b
)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
ARGENTINE
• 
♂
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
; “ 
Buenos Aires
” [white typewritten label]; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pelidnota Helmenreichi
</tp:taxon-name>
Buenos Aires
” [white handwritten label]; “ 

Typus

!” [red typewritten label]; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus Helmenreichi
Ohaus
</tp:taxon-name>
” [red handwritten label]; 
ZMHB
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Syntypes

COUNTRY UNKNOWN • 
♂
, syntype of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Figs 1d
, 
2c
)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
“ 
Typus
!” [red typewritten label]; “Helmr.” [white handwritten label]; “ 
H. Helmenreichi
Ohs. 
<tp:taxon-name>
v. 
maculicollis
Ohs.
</tp:taxon-name>
” [red handwritten label]; “SYNTYPE 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus helmenreicheni
var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by 
MFNB 2017
” [red typed label]; 
ZMHB
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
♀
, 
syntype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus
helmenreichi

var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Figs 1e
, 
2d
); “♀” [white typewritten label with black border]; “Cotype” [red typewritten label]; “Helmr.” [white handwritten label]; “SYNTYPE 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus helmenreicheni
var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by 
MFNB 2017
” [red typed label]; 
ZMHB
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Additional material
(
six specimens
)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
COUNTRY UNKNOWN • “Ohaus determin. 1913 
Hopl. Helmenreichi
<tp:taxon-name>
v. 
maculicollis
Ohs.
</tp:taxon-name>
Cotype 
♀
”; 
NHMW
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
BRAZIL
– 

Minas Gerais

• 
4 ♂♂
; 
Leme do Prado
, 
Estação Ecológica de Acauã
; 

23 Dec. 2003

; 
M.F. Vasconcelos
leg.; 
UFMG-ICO
</tp:material-citation>
. – 
<tp:material-citation>
Paraná

• 
1 ♂
; 
Curitiba
; 

3 Aug. 2010

; 
Oliveira
leg.; 
CERPE
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>

Male 
holotype

(
Figs 1c
, 
3c
, 
4i–m
, 
6a–c
, 
7e–f
)
</p>
      <p>
SIZE. Total length: 
17.6 mm
; width across prothorax: 
9.1 mm
.
</p>
      <p>COLOUR. General aspect metallic dark green and reddish brown; head, pronotum, legs and venter metallic green, elytra reddish brown.</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Clypeus with surface rugose, densely punctate, larges punctures, gradually coalescent from disc to margins; apex trilobate, lobes rounded, sides parallels with the slightly converging apex. Frontoclypeal suture obsolete, sinuous, forming an angle on disc. Clypeus and frons subequal in length. Frons subquadrangular, moderately punctate, more densely posteriorly, with medium to large punctures, coalescent in the margins (
Fig. 3c
). Maxillary palpi with last palpomere cylindrical, sensorial area oval, occupying two thirds of dorsal area (
Fig. 4l
). Mentum near 1.2× longer than wide, anterior margin weakly sinuous, almost straight, posterior angles rounded (

Fig. 
4m

); surface sparsely punctate with scattered setae, punctures large. Antennal club 1.8× longer than antennomeres 2–7 combined.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Pronotum with surface moderate to densely punctate, increasing density towards sides; anterior angles acute; sides slightly truncate (
Fig. 3c
). Propleuron slightly concave, surface rugose, and moderately setose. Scutellar plate moderately punctate, punctures bigger on disc. Elytral striae distinctly marked; first interstriae with puncture thin, dense. Epipleuron flattened, sparsely setose, minute setae. Mesoventral process long with rounded apex, never reaching procoxal base (
Fig. 8c, f
); surface punctate and densely setose. Metasternum densely punctate and densely setose. Procoxa densely punctate and sparsely setose. Profemur sparsely punctate and sparsely setose. Mesofemur moderately punctate and densely setose. Metafemur flattened, broad, sparsely punctate, and with sparse posterior setae. Protibia with surface densely punctate, bigger punctures, C-shaped punctures on disc; apex with 10 distinct setae. Mesotibia with two transverse carinae: proximal carina marked by four spinules, distal carina marked by five spinules, surface moderately punctate and sparsely setose, short setae; apex with 11 spinules. Metatibia similar to mesotibia, but more robust and with 19 apical spinules.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Pygidium subtrapezoidal, apex slightly rounded, surface rugose, minute setae sparsely disposed on margins. Ventrites with surface sparsely setose, fine and short setae. Parameres similar in length, irregularly V-shaped bifurcated, bifurcation base rounded; apical lobes well defined, left lobe smaller than right lobe; left lateral expanded in lateral view, parabolic expansion; right expansion obsolete (
Figs 6a–c
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
Head and pronotum details. 
a
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
, male specimen (ZMHB). 
b
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
, syntype, ♂ (ZMHB). 
c
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
, holotype, ♂ (ZMHB). 
d
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
, syntype, ♂ (ZMHB). Scale bar = 1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Male variation
</p>
      <p>
Size: total length: 17.2–19.0 mm; width across prothorax: 
7.5–9.1 mm
. General aspect orange-brown; head, pronotum and scutellar plate may have yellowish maculae (
Fig. 1d–e
). Suture frontoclypeal vary in the degree of sinuosity. Pronotum can be more or less truncate at sides. Surface of mesofemur varies from moderately to densely punctate. Mesotibia with proximal and distal carina marked by 4–7 spinules; apex truncate with 7–13 spinules. Metatibia with 14–22 spinules in the apex, distal carina with 5–11 spinules, and proximal carina with 5–8. Parameres vary from parabolic curvature of the aedeagus to the truncate curvature, as well as, in the degree and shape of lateral expansion, it can be longer and more parabolic (
Figs 6d–f
, 
7e–h
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
Fig. 1e
)
</p>
      <p>Similar to males in general aspects, differentiating in the following aspects: pronotal maculae more elongate; clypeus rounded; frontoclypeal suture distinct, with central curvature; antennal club 0.7× smaller than in males, 1.5× longer than antennomeres 2–7 combined. Pronotum with parallel sides and anterior angles more rounded. Elytral epipleuron slightly rounded, distinct depression above epipleuron. Protarsomere I as long as protarsomeres II–IV combined.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 4.
Mouthparts. 
a–d
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
(ZMHB). 
e–h
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
(ZMHB). 
i–m
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
(ZMHB). 
a, e, i
. Right mandible. 
b, f, j
. Right maxilla. 
c, g, l
. Detail of the last maxillary palpomere. 
d, h, m
. Mentum. Scale bar = 1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type locality
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
</tp:taxon-name>
was originally described from 
Buenos Aires
(
Argentina
) (
Ohaus 1905
), and this locality was later contested by the author (
Ohaus 1914a
) while describing the variety, 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
var. 
macullicolis
</tp:taxon-name>
. This species can actually be found in the north and northeast of Minas Gerais state in the Jequitinhonha River Valley (
Ohaus 1914a
). Accordingly, after the examination of three more males from the same region, we agree with 
Ohaus (1914a)
and disregard the occurrence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Argentina
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 5.
Aedeagus in dorsal (a, e) y lateral view (b–c, d, f). 
a–c
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
(ZMHB). 
d–f.
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
, syntype, ♂ (ZMHB). Scale bar = 1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
We consider the type of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
</tp:taxon-name>
a 
holotype
since 
Ohaus (1905)
mentions only a single specimen. For 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmreicheni
var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus (1914a)
</tp:taxon-name>
had multiple specimens available. ICZN (1999, Article 45.6.1.) states that a name “is infrasubspecific if its author expressly gave it infrasubspecific rank, or if the content of the work unambiguously reveals that the name was proposed for an infrasubspecific entity”. Furthermore, the Article 45.6.4. (ICZN 1999) clarifies that a name “is subspecific if first published before 1961 and its author expressly used one of the terms “variety” or “form” (including use of the terms “var.”, “forma”, “v.” and “f.”), unless its author also expressly gave it infrasubspecific rank, or the content of the work unambiguously reveals that the name was proposed for an infrasubspecific entity, in which case it is infrasubspecific”. In the time Ohaus described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
he already clearly separated between species, subspecies and varieties as an article from the same year (see 
Ohaus 1914b
) shows where he described new taxa on the species, subspecies and infrasubspecific levels. Therefore, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
is an unavailable name. Although the pair of 
syntypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
examined have some distinct characteristics of the 
holotype
– such as yellowish colour, smaller size, less dense punctures and the male genitalia almost parallel sided, the other specimens examined show many similarities both with the 
syntypes
and with the 
holotype
. The variation of these characteristics was also observed within the other species of the genus. Despite these variations, mouthpart characters (like mentum shape, maxillary palpus shape) and mesoventral process remained constant in the 
eight specimens
examined. Thus, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
does not present a unique combination of character states that justify validating it to species or subspecies status.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Brazil

: 
Minas Gerais
: Grão Mogol, Leme do Prado. 
Paraná
: Curitiba? (Fig. 9).
</p>
      <p>
No other specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
</tp:taxon-name>
was subsequently collected in 
Buenos Aires
, or anywhere else in 
Argentina
(
Ohaus 1914a
). One part of the material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
was labelled “Helm., Brasilia, XXII, 1853” and the other part “Serra do Grão Mogor, 1846” [Municipality of Grão Mogol, 
Minas Gerais
]. 
Ohaus (1914a)
then made it clear that the most probable locality of this species would be the north of 
Minas Gerais State
(Grão Mogol) and not 
Buenos Aires
, corresponding to the known distribution of the genus. Thus, we agree with 
Ohaus (1914a)
and disregard 
Buenos Aires
as a locality for this species, as well as for the genus 

<tp:taxon-name>Oplognathus</tp:taxon-name>
.

One male of the examined material is labelled as being from Curitiba, 
Paraná
, South of 
Brazil
, but the origin is doubtful, since this single specimen was found in a didactic collection of the Federal University of 
Paraná
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
