<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Oplognathus bahianus Ohaus 1912</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5559944</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C5F6CDBF89F562E944E588EC4A7D4F32</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the genus Oplognathus MacLeay, 1819 (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Rutelinae: Rutelini)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1471</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1f–g
, 
2a
, 
3b
, 
4e–h
, 
5d–f
, 
7i–m
, 
8b, e
, 9
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus bahianus
Ohaus, 1912: 650
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus bahianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Ohaus 1918: 12

(catalogue); 1934: 42 (catalogue). — 

Blackwelder 1944: 235

(catalogue).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus bahianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Machatschke 1972: 5

(catalogue). — 

Krajcik 2007: 90

(catalogue).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Male with truncate, strongly, trilobate clypeus, rounded in females; clypeus with divergent sides (
Fig. 3b
). Antennal club of the males 1.5× longer than antennomeres 2–7 combined. Male with last maxillary palpomere fusiform (

Fig. 
4g

), cylindrical in females. Mentum broad, as long as wide, anterior margin notched, posterior angles rounded (
Fig. 4h
). Elytral striae distinctly marked. Mesoventral process short and slightly flat, with apex slightly rounded (
Fig. 8b, e
). Apex of the mesotibia with 9–12 spinules and apex of the metatibia with 18–20 spinules, females with 24–27 spinules at the apex of the metatibia.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 6.
Aedeagus in dorsal (a, e) and lateral view (b–c, d–f). 
a–c
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
, holotype, ♂ (ZMHB). 
d–f
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
, syntype, ♂ (ZMHB). Scale bar = 1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Syntype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
, 
syntype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Figs 1f
, 
2a
); “ 
Typus
!” [red typewritten label]; “ 
C. Bts. Obrth.
” [white handwritten label]; “SAntonio da 
Barra Prov.
de 
Bahia
Ch. Pujol
1890” [white typewritten label]; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus bahianus
Ohs.
</tp:taxon-name>
” [red handwritten label]; 
ZMHB

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
(
six specimens
)
</p>
      <p>
BRAZIL
– 

Minas Gerais

• 
1 ♂
; Berizal; 

15 Dec. 2007

; 
Grossi
, 
Rafael
&amp; 
Parizotto
leg.; 
CERPE

• 

1 ♂
; 
Berizal
; 

Dec. 2001

; 
P. Grossi
leg.; 
CERPE

• 

3 ♂♂
, 
1 ♀
; 
Águas Vermelhas
; 

Nov. 1991

; 
E. Grossi
leg.; 
EPGC

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Syntype
male

(
Figs 1f
, 
3b
, 
4e–f
, 
5d–f
, 
8b, e
)
</p>
      <p>
SIZE. Total length: 
20.8 mm
; width across prothorax: 
10.5 mm
.
</p>
      <p>COLOUR. General aspect with dorsal surface yellow gold and ventral surface metallic green; head, legs, and pygidium from cooper to reddish brown with metallic green reflections.</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 3b
). Clypeus subquadrangular, surface rugose, sparsely setose; apex strongly trilobate, truncate, margins bowed inward, sides clearly divergent; ventral surface moderately punctate and moderately setose. Frontoclypeal suture straight. Clypeus 1.3× longer than frons. Frons densely punctate, punctures coalescent laterally. Last maxillary palpomere fusiform, distinctly flattened (

Fig. 
4g

); sensorial area oval, occupying two thirds of dorsal surface. Mentum 1.05× wider than long, subequal, anterior margin notched, posterior angles rounded (
Fig. 4h
); surface densely punctate, large punctures; surface sparsely setose, setae as long as the length of the labial palpus. Antennal club 1.5× longer than the antennomeres 2–7 combined.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Pronotum with surface moderately and uniformly punctate, thin punctures; surface glabrous; anterior angles rounded; maculae obsolete: two anterolateral maculae as cooper slight spots, and two lateral maculae heterogeneous (
Fig. 3b
). Propleuron concave, moderately setose and moderately punctate. Scutellar plate sparsely punctate. Elytra with 10 deeply marked striae, interstriae practically obsolete in general, first interstriae with dense puncture; epipleuron flattened, glabrous. Mesoventral process short with rounded apex, never reaching the apex of the mesocoxa, surface sparsely setose and densely punctate (
Fig. 8b, e
). Metasternum densely punctate, and densely setose. Procoxa rugose, surface sparsely setose. Profemur moderately setose. Mesofemur flattened, surface densely, and uniformly punctate; moderately setose. Metafemur flattened, broader, surface moderately, and uniformly punctate; moderately setose. Protibia moderately setose in the medial-inner portion, external portion sparsely setose; surface densely punctate, not uniform, big punctures, coalescent on the lateral portion; apex with a group of 11 setae. Mesotibia with surface sparsely setose dorsally, setae longer than wide mesotibia; surface densely setose ventrally; densely punctate, punctures big and small, not uniformly scattered; external surface with two carinae, proximal one short, marked by 3 spinules, and a distal complete, and oblique carina with 8 spinules; apex truncate with 13 spinules. Metatibia similar to mesotibia, but with 19 spinules on the apex.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Pygidium subtrapezoidal, sparse setae disposed in the margins, disc glabrous. Ventrites with surface sparsely setose posteriorly in the ventrites II–IV, and restricted to the lateral of ventrite VI, moderate punctuation. Parameres transverse, apex emarginated like V-shaped, with the left side distinctly shorter and broader, the right side slightly sinuous, base notched, concave; right lateral paramere divergent, straight, toward the apex with a concavity; apex with an only oblique lobe, transverse and anterior face straight; left lateral paramere broadly rounded and expanded ventrally, long expansion, apically of two lobes, external lobe projecting outwardly; base of parameres sinuous with median recess in V-shape (
Fig. 5d–f
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
Variation in male genitalia. 
a–d
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
(a-b: CEMT; c-d: ZMHB). 
e–h
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
(ZMHB). 
i–m
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
(CERPE). Scale bar = 1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Male variation
</p>
      <p>
Size: total length: 20.0– 
20.8 mm
; width across prothorax: 10.0– 
10.5 mm
. Frontoclypeal suture can be slightly sinuous. Mentum can have the anterior margin more or less curved, but all specimens show the notched 
type
; mentum vary from 1.3–1.8× longer than frons. Pronotal and elytral punctation are distinctly marked, but 
one specimen
has them very smooth. Surface on the scutellar plate varies from sparsely to moderately punctate. Mesoventral process is predominantly short with a rounded apex, 
one specimen
has it more acute. Apex of protibia vary from 9–12 setae. Proximal carina of mesotibia varies by 2–3 spinules, and the distal carina varies by 5–9 spinules; apex truncate with 9–13 spinules. Metatibia with 18–20 spinules in the apex, distal carina with 7–11 spinules, and proximal carina with 3–5 spinules. Parameres vary in the degree of lateral inclination, lobes of parameres may be more or less pronounced, the lateral projections vary in length (
Fig. 7i–m
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
(

Fig. 
1g

)
</p>
      <p>
Similar to the male, differing from it in the following aspects: body usually more truncate, globose, distinctly convex. Total length: 
22.1 mm
, width across prothorax: 
11.1 mm
. Head with rounded clypeus, convergent sides; antennal club 0.7× shorter than in male. Last maxillary palpomere cylindrical, sensorial area straighter. Pronotal maculae obsolete; elytral epipleuron broader; protibial spur distinctly thinner; tarsal claws similar, without differentiation, anterior tarsus shorter; apex of metatibia with 24–27 apical spinules. Sixth sternite subtriangular, and more densely punctate almost rugose.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type locality
</p>
      <p>
Brazil

. 
Bahia
: [Santo Antônio da Barra], currently the municipality of Condeúba (Fig. 9).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 8.
Patterns of mesoventral process. 
a, d
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
(MZUSP). 
b, e
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
(ZMHB
)
. 
c, f
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
(CERPE
)
. Scale bar = 1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Ohaus (1912)
did not state the number of specimens and therefore, we consider the single type specimen as a 
syntype
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus bahianus
</tp:taxon-name>
is the most distinctive species of the genus, with the males presenting a strongly trilobed clypeus. However, this character does not fit the original diagnosis of the genus (based on the type species 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. kirbii
</tp:taxon-name>
), where the clypeus was described with this character being less evident. Although being a secondary sexual character, the clypeus has been used as the main diagnostic character of the genus. After this study, despite concerning only one sex, the trilobed cypleus is the best character to distinguish 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bahianus
</tp:taxon-name>
. Another relevant character to distinguish this species is the mesoventral process, which is not salient and simply rounded, vs acute and salient in the two other species.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
.

Bahia
: Condeúba; 
Minas Gerais
: Águas Vermelhas, Berizal (Fig. 9).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus bahianus
</tp:taxon-name>
was described by 
Ohaus (1912)
from Santo Antônio da Barra in 
Bahia
. This locality received the denomination of Condeúba in 1889, and is located in the south-central region of the state in the 
Bahia
Semiarid Region, near the north of Jequitinhonha Valley. This species has the northernmost distribution in 
Brazil
, being also found in the north of 
Minas Gerais
in the Jequitinhonha
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9. Geographic distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
. River Valley Region, an ecotone characterized by transition from the Atlantic Forest, Cerrado and Caatinga, with a high degree of endemism.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
