<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1a–b
, 
2e
, 
3a
, 
4a–d
, 
5a–c
, 
7a–d
, 
8a, d
, 9
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819: 160
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Areoda kirbii</tp:taxon-name>
–

Dejean 1837: 172

(catalogue). — 

Guérin-Méneville 1844: 98

, pl. 24 bis fig. 10 (catalogue). 

<tp:taxon-name>Oplognathus kirbyi</tp:taxon-name>
–

Laporte 1840: 124

(re-description). — 

Machatschke 1972: 5

(catalogue). 

<tp:taxon-name>Hoplognathus kirbii</tp:taxon-name>
–

Burmeister 1844: 428

(re-description). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus kirbyi
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Lacordaire 1856: 365

(catalogue). — 

Ohaus 1905: 322

(species diagnosis); 1912: 650 (species diagnosis); 1915: 257 (general characterization); 1918: 12 (catalogue); 1934: 42 (catalogue). — 

Blackwelder 1944: 235

(catalogue).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Krajcik 2007: 90

(catalogue).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Colour golden yellow with metallic green reflections; pronotum usually with two spots or elongate maculae (
Figs 1a–b
, 
3a
). Male with slightly trilobate clypeus (
Fig. 3a
); clypeus rounded in females, length of clypeus approximately 1.5× longer than length of frons; antennal club 1.3× longer than antennomeres 2–7 combined; last maxillary palpomere cylindrical in both sexes (
Fig. 4c
); mentum longer than wide, anterior margin sinuous, posterior angles distinctly acute (
Fig. 4d
). Pronotum with posterior border interrupted at middle, with scattered setae on maculae; epipleuron dilated on anterior half; mesoventral process acute (
Fig. 8a, d
); apex of mesotibia with 9–11 spinules; apex of the metatibia with 16–19 spinules; females with 9–10 and 18–23 spinules at the apex of meso and metatibiae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Neotype

(by present designation) 
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; “[illegible, probably “Adelaid”]” [handwritten label]; “Bowring. 63-47*” [white typewritten label]; “So named in Reiches Collection. C. W.” [white typewritten label, C.W. indicating NHMUK entomology C.O. Waterhouse]; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hoplognathus kirbyi
McLeay
</tp:taxon-name>
” [handwritten by Waterhouse on reverse of previous label]; “ 
NHMUK 010806029
” [white typewritten label with QR code] (
Fig. 2e
); “NEOTYPUS 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
Carvalho, Seidel &amp; Grossi
</tp:taxon-name>
des.” [red typewritten label]; 
NHMUK
.

</p>
      <p>
Additional material
(
21 specimens
)
</p>
      <p>
BRAZIL
– 
State unknown
• 
2 ♂♂
; “ 
Brasilia
, 
Virmond
”; 
ZMHB

• 

2 ♂♂
; “ 
Brasilia
”; 
ZMHB
. – 

Espírito Santo

• 

1 ♂
; 
Palmital
; 

15 Dec. 1908

; 
F.J. Zikán
leg.; 
CEIOC
. – 

Rio de Janeiro

• 

1 ♂
; 
Engenheiro Paulo
de Frontin
, 
Instituto Zoobotânico Morro Azul
; 

28 Dec. 2002

; 
F. Racca Filho
leg.; 
CERPE

• 

2 ♂♂
; 
NHMUK
. – 

São Paulo

• 

1 ♂
; 
“Bosque d.S.”
; 

30 Oct. 1926

; 
F. Ohaus
leg.; 
ZMHB

• 

1 ♂
; 
Saude
; 

15 Oct. 1920

; 
CEMT

• 

1 ♂
; 
Saude
; 

18 Dec. 1914

; 
MNRJ

• 

1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; 
Jabaquara
; 

Oct. 1938

; 
Dirings
leg.; 
MZUSP

• 

1 ♂
; 
Jabaquara
; 
Feb.
[1]936; IBSP-IB

• 

1 ♀
; 
Jabaquara
; 
Dec.
[1]933; IBSP-IB

• 

1 ♀
; 
Jabaquara
; 

2 Dec.

[19]39; 
MNRJ

• 

1 ♀
; 
Mogy das Cruzes
; 
H. Rüderw
leg.; 
ZMHB

• 

1 ♂
; 
Parque do Estado de Paulo
; 

30 Nov.

[19]37; 
Zellibor-Hauff
leg.; 
CEMT

• 

1 ♂
; 
J. Metz
leg.; 
ZMHB

• 

1 ♂
; 
Ypiranga
; 

14 Jan. 1927

; 
F. Ohaus
leg.; 
NHMUK
. – 

Minas Gerais

• 

1 ♂
; 
Manhumi
[ri]n; 

15 
Dec.

[19]35; 
MNRJ

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
SIZE. Total length 
19.15–22 mm
; width across prothorax: 8.0– 
10.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR. General aspect golden yellow with green reflection, ventral surface metallic green; head and legs reddish brown to metallic green; pygidium greenish brown with green reflections (
Fig. 1a
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Clypeus subquadrangular, surface rugose; apex weakly trilobate, lateral lobes almost straight, central lobe rounded; margins bowed inward, slightly widening from base to apex; ventral surface moderately punctate (
Fig. 3a
). Frontoclypeal suture distinct, straight. Length of clypeus about 1.5× longer than frons. Frons distinctly punctate, surface glabrous. Last maxillary palpomere cylindrical (
Fig. 4c
). Mentum 1.2× longer than wide, anterior margin sinuous, posterior angles distinctly acute
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1. a–b
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
a
. Neotype, ♂ (NHMUK). 
b
. Female specimen (MZUSP). 
c
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
, holotype, ♂ (ZMHB). 
d–e
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
d
. Syntype, ♂ (ZMHB). 
e
. Syntype, ♀ (ZMHB). 
f–g
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
f
. Syntype, ♂ (ZMHB). 
g
. Female specimen (EPGC). Scale bar = 5 mm.
</p>
      <p>
(
Fig. 4d
); surface densely punctate, and sparsely setose, setae as long as length of last labial palpomere. Antennal club 1.3× longer than antennomeres 2–7 combined.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Pronotum with surface moderately punctate; anterolateral maculae as spots with up to three setae on maculae; anterior angles acute (
Fig. 3a
). Propleuron slightly concave, surface moderately setose. Scutellar plate densely and uniformly punctate. Elytra with obsolete striae; first interstriae with punctuation sparse to moderate; each epipleuron slightly dilated on anterior half of elytron. Epipleuron concave with surface sparsely punctate, and sparsely setose. Mesoventral process long with apex acute, never reaching procoxal base, moderately setose and moderately punctate (
Fig. 8a, d
). Metasternum densely punctate, and densely setose. Procoxa densely punctate and sparsely setose. Profemur moderately punctate, moderately setose on lateral carina, setae shorter than wide on profemur. Mesofemur flattened, surface moderately punctate, and moderately setose. Metafemur flattened, broader, with surface sparsely punctate, and sparsely setose posteriorly. Protibia densely setose laterally, sparsely setose at disc, with setae shorter than wide on protibia, apex with 9–14 setae; densely punctate, big punctures; tibial spur as long as protarsomere I. Mesotibia sparsely setose dorsally, setae shorter than wide on mesotibia, and densely setose ventrally, with setae longer than wide on mesotibia; densely punctate; with two carinae, one proximal formed by 3–5 spinules, and one distal formed by 5–7; apex truncate with 9–11 apical spinules. Metatibia similar to mesotibia, but with 16–19 apical spinules; proximal carina with 2–4 spinules; and distal carina with 6–8 spinules.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Pygidium transverse, subtrapezoidal, surface sparsely setose, setae fine, and medial-posteriorly disposed. Ventrites in general aspect convex, ventrites II–IV with a slight central concavity, and with sparse setae and sparse punctures posteriorly. Parameres transverse, broader, apex V-shaped, left side slightly shorter, base rounded; left side of parameres expanded in lateral view, expansion parabolic, and with two apical lobes, almost with same length; right side of parameres sinuous, with two apical lobes, outer lobe shorter; paramere base almost straight, with discrete sinuosity (
Figs 5a–c
, 
7a–d
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
Fig. 1b
)
</p>
      <p>
Similar to males, differing in the following aspects: Total length: 21.2–22.0 mm; width across prothorax: 
10.1–10.4 mm
. Clypeus rounded, frontoclypeal suture weakly sinuous; elytral epipleuron more strongly dilated; protibia thinner; mesotibia varying from 9–10 spinules, and metatibia varying from 18–23; protarsomere I longer in length, protarsomere V not dilated; tarsal claws similar in length and width.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
Labels. 
a
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus bahianus
Ohaus, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
, syntype, ♂. 
b
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
Ohaus, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
, holotype, ♂. 
c–d
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. helmenreichi
var. 
maculicollis
Ohaus, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
c
. Syntype ♂. 
d
. Syntype ♀. 
e
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
, neotype, ♂.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type locality
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
MacLeay, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
is currently considered lost, and could not be traced in any of the likely collections. A 
neotype
is designated to stabilize the nomenclature. We selected the oldest historical specimen, one that was received by NHMUK with Bowring’s collection in 1863 [accession number 47]. The 
neotype
fits the drawing of 
Guérin-Meneville (1844)
, the earliest illustration of the species (25 years after the description) which helps ensure that we selected the correct taxon. 
MacLeay (1819)
provided only “ 
Brazil
” as the type locality. Since 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. kirbii
</tp:taxon-name>
is a Brazilian endemic it is not a problem that the collecting data of the 
neotype
are illegible.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Brazil

. 
Espírito Santo
: Palmital; 
Minas Gerais
: Manhumirin; 
Paraná
; 
Rio de Janeiro
: 
Engenheiro Paulo
de Frontin; 
São Paulo
: 
São Paulo
(Fig. 9).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Oplognathus kirbii
</tp:taxon-name>
can be found in the mountainous regions of the states of 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
São Paulo
, 
Espírito Santo
and 
Minas Gerais
, besides being recorded in literature for the state of 
Paraná
(specimens from 
Paraná
have not been confirmed here), inhabiting humid areas of the Atlantic Forest, unlike the other species of the genus, found in areas of Mata Seca in the north of 
Minas Gerais
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
