<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Oplognathus MacLeay
                        1819</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5572904</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03D38784E1574537FDCFF96BFAC4F91D</uri>
                  <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the genus Oplognathus MacLeay, 1819
                        (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Rutelinae: Rutelini)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1471</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus MacLeay, 1819 </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus MacLeay, 1819: 159 </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 1a–g ). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus </tp:taxon-name> – Latreille 1829: 553 (catalogue). —
                  Laporte 1840: 124 (catalogue). — Machatschke 1970: 157 (synonymy observation);
                  1972: 5 (catalogue). — Ratcliffe &amp; Jameson 1989: 135 (general
                  characterization). — Jameson 1990: 415 (phylogeny). — Krajcik 2007: 90
                  (catalogue). — Grossi &amp; Vaz-de-Mello2015: 221 (collecting report).—
                  Carvalho&amp; Grossi2018:369 (general characterization). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus </tp:taxon-name> – Burmeister 1844: 428
                  (re-description). — Lacordaire 1856: 365 (catalogue). — Ohaus 1905: 322 (species
                  description); 1912: 650 (species description); 1914a: 301 (species description);
                  1915: 257 (general characterization); 1918: 11 (catalogue); 1934: 41
                  (re-description). — Blackwelder 1944: 235 (catalogue). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p> Type species </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus kirbii MacLeay, 1819 </tp:taxon-name> , by monotypy.
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Males with quadrangular, trilobate clypeus ( Fig. 3a–d ), rounded in females ( Fig.
                  1b, e, g ); clypeus extending beyond labrum in ventral view in both sexes;
                  mandibles with three teeth in incisive area ( Fig. 4a, e, i ); maxillae with six
                  teeth ( Fig. 4b, f, j ); antennae with 10 antennomeres ( Fig. 3a–d ); elytra with
                  10 striae ( Fig. 1a–g ); mesoventral process present ( Fig. 8a–f ); parameres
                  asymmetrical ( Figs 5–7 ), each paramere with two apical lobes, and one lateral
                  projection. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Redescription </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> SIZE. Total length: 17.4–22.4 mm ; width across prothorax: 8.0– 11.4 mm . </p>
            <p> COLOUR. General aspect light yellow varying from yellowish to reddish metallic
                  green, with golden and green reflexes; ventral surface metallic green; pronotum
                  sometimes with black maculae; elytral margins metallic green or copper ( Fig. 1a,
                  c–d, f ). </p>
            <p> HEAD ( Fig. 3 ). Reddish brown and/or metallic green. Clypeus subquadrate, surface
                  rugose, setose, apex trilobate, apical and lateral margins elevated; clypeus
                  produced beyond labrum in ventral view. Frontoclypeal suture usually distinct,
                  straight or sinuous. Frons predominantly rectangular, surface glabrous, distinctly
                  punctate, punctures dense; ocular canthus intruding a third of the eye’s length,
                  with scattered yellow setae. Labrum transverse, widely bilobed, setose, never
                  visible from above. Mandibles laminar, rounded, intimately joined to labrum, with
                  three incisive teeth ( Fig. 4a, e, i ). Maxillae setose, galea with six teeth,
                  palpi 4-segmented, last palpomere longer than other three combined, varying from
                  cylindrical to fusiform ( Fig. 4b–c, f–g, j, l ). Mentum sinuous, bilobed or
                  notched, ventral surface setose; labial palpus inserted dorsally on mentum,
                  3-segmented; last palpomere enlarged ( Fig. 4d, h, m ). Antenna with 10
                  antennomeres, antennal club 1.3 to 1.8× longer than antennomeres 2–7 combined. </p>
            <p> THORAX. Pronotum convex, transverse, about 1.8 times wider than longer, beaded;
                  pronotal bead incomplete posteriorly at middle; surface varying from sparse to
                  densely punctate; punctures small to moderate; maculae varying from two distinct
                  anterolateral spots to two complete elongated maculae; some specimens with spots
                  and maculae obsolete or absent. Each elytron with 10 distinctly punctate striae,
                  punctures fine to moderate, interstriae almost smooth, punctures visible from 10×
                  of magnification; humeri rounded, smooth; elytral apex straight. Hind wings full
                  developed with a group of setae at AA 1+2, setae long and fine, longer than width
                  of first axillar sclerite; AP 3+4 softly setose at base, with fine and minute
                  setae; R 3+4 sclerotized, disc with a distinct row of short setae. Mesoventral
                  process acute, elongated, but never extended beyond anterior procoxal base ( Fig.
                  8 ). Metafemur with anterior and posterior margins rounded, distinctly developed
                  that other femora, with at least twice the mesofemoral width. Protibia tridentate,
                  teeth reducing in size from apex to base, proximal tooth sometimes obsolete; inner
                  apex with one tiny spur; ventral surface distinctly dilated, convex. Mesotibia
                  with surface rugose, and two oblique carinae: proximal carina with 2–7 spinules,
                  and distal carina with 4–9 spinules, distal carina longer; mesotibial apex
                  truncate with 7–13 spinules and two spurs, inner spur slightly longer. Metatibia
                  wider than mesotibia, with inner margin distinctly rounded, apical spinules
                  varying from 14–22; spurs distinctly short, and flattened, apex less acute than
                  spinules; proximal carina with 2–8 spinules and distal carina with 6–11 spinules.
                  Protarsomere V thickened; inner claw stronger with a basal obtuse tooth. Meso- and
                  metatarsomere ornamented with lateral setae, and inner apical spinules. Meso- and
                  metatarsal claws curved, simple, unequal in thickness; unguitractor plate present
                  with two apical setae. </p>
            <p> ABDOMEN. Pygidium flat to weakly convex, subtrapezoidal, transverse, surface rugose
                  and setose; longer setae often on posterior sides. Ventrites metallic green,
                  slightly convex, surface weakly punctate, punctures sparse, with scattered setae,
                  sternites V and VI about twice as long as sternite IV. Parameres asymmetrical,
                  each paramere with 1–2 distal lobes, left lateral expanded with a long projection,
                  apical bifurcation wide, V-shaped ( Figs 5–7 ). </p>
            <p> Female ( Fig. 1b, e, g ) </p>
            <p>Similar to male, differing in the following aspects:</p>
            <p> SIZE. Total length: 17.2–22.1 mm ; width across prothorax: 7.5–11.1 mm . </p>
            <p>HEAD. Apex rounded, never with projections; antennal club distinctly smaller.</p>
            <p>THORAX. Pronotum more densely punctate. Elytra more convex, with dilated external
                  margins, and elytral epipleuron wider in ventral view; legs thinner, anterior
                  claws subequal, simple, not dilated.</p>
            <p>ABDOMEN. Sternum and pygidium more convex.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Brazil . Bahia : Condeúba; Espírito Santo : Palmital; Minas Gerais : Águas
                  Vermelhas, Berizal, Manhumirim, Grão Mogol, Leme do Prado; Paraná : Curitiba; Rio
                  de Janeiro : Rio de Janeiro ; São Paulo : São Paulo (Fig. 9). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Nomenclatural history </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus </tp:taxon-name> was described by MacLeay (1819)
                  without ‘H’ at the beginning of the name, but later Burmeister (1844) redescribed
                  the genus as “ <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus </tp:taxon-name> ”, justifying that it
                  would be the correct spelling for the name. Lacordaire (1856) also pointed the
                  “error” of MacLeay, and uses <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus </tp:taxon-name> as a
                  valid name, indicating “ Aplognathus ” as original wrong spelling, but not
                  specifying the cause of the error. Since then, the name <tp:taxon-name>
                        Hoplognathus </tp:taxon-name> has been widely used, including the
                  description of the new species, generating more synonyms, such as <tp:taxon-name>
                        Hoplognathus bahianus </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus
                        helmenreichi </tp:taxon-name> . Only Machatschke (1970) comments that
                        <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus </tp:taxon-name> is a synonym, but when using
                        <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus </tp:taxon-name> , the spelling appears as “
                  Oplongnathus ”. Already in his catalogue, Machatschke (1972) cites “
                        <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus </tp:taxon-name> ” using the original spelling,
                  which proves to be a typing error in the previous publications. Ratcliffe &amp;
                  Jameson (1989) note this fact and show the correct use “ <tp:taxon-name>
                        Oplognathus MacLeay </tp:taxon-name> (not <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus
                  </tp:taxon-name> as in Burmeister 1844 ; Ohaus 1918 , 1934 ; Blackwelder 1944 )”,
                  because according to Article 23 (ICZN 1999), the Principle of Priority, the oldest
                  name should be used. In the original description, MacLeay (1819) does not detail
                  the etymology of <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus </tp:taxon-name> , but the Hoplo
                  prefix, from the Greek Hoplon, means ‘any tool or implement of armour and shield’
                  while Gnathus, from the Greek, means ‘mandible, mouth’, possibly due to the
                  distinct shape of the clypeus of the males. Perhaps, this explains the insistence
                  of later authors ( Burmeister 1844 ; Lacordaire 1856 ) to use the spelling
                        <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus </tp:taxon-name> , instead of <tp:taxon-name>
                        Oplognathus </tp:taxon-name> , as correct. However, as there is no written
                  indication of this, and the addition of ‘H’ is not a clear, obvious and necessary
                  correction of the name, <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus </tp:taxon-name> must be
                  maintained, following the original description and not its subsequent spelling
                  (ICZN 1999, Art. 33). </p>
            <p> Although Burmeister corrected the name of the genus, this does not mean that Ohaus
                  intended to describe <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus bahianus </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus helmenreichi </tp:taxon-name> in a genus other
                  than <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus </tp:taxon-name> . Thus, the author’s name is
                  written here without brackets, since the species is basically in its original
                  combination. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus kirbii </tp:taxon-name> was cited by Laporte (1840) as
                        <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus kirbyi </tp:taxon-name> and since then, both
                  spellings were widely used, in addition to <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus kirbii
                  </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus kirbyi </tp:taxon-name> , it is
                  common to find four spellings for this species throughout the literature. There
                  are no details for replacing ‘i’ with ‘y’, but we can suppose Laporte (1840) to
                  make this change on the assumption that MacLeay intended to honour the naturalist
                  William Kirby. ICZN (1999, Article 58.2) states that the use of ‘i’ and ‘y’ are
                  ‘variant spellings’ deemed to be identical. However, as MacLeay (1819) makes the
                  description with no detail about etymology, it is prudent to keep the original
                  spelling <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus kirbii </tp:taxon-name> and not to use the
                  subsequent spellings (ICZN 1999, Art. 33). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus helmenreichi </tp:taxon-name> was described for the
                  first time based on a single specimen in the collection of W.J.C. Weber by Ohaus
                  (1905) with this spelling (for the specific epithet) and the locality Buenos Aires
                  , Argentina . Later, Ohaus wrote that he found ( Ohaus 1914a: 22 ) several
                  specimens of this species in the Museum of Vienna, but he described them as a
                  variety “ <tp:taxon-name> var. maculicollis </tp:taxon-name> ”. These specimens
                  were labelled “Helmr.”, realizing that the name of the collector was Helmreichen
                  and not Helmenreich, as published in Ohaus (1905) . Although Ohaus (1914a) has
                  described the variety as “ <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus helmreicheni var.
                        maculicollis </tp:taxon-name> ” in the original publication, the correct
                  name is <tp:taxon-name> Hoplognathus helmenreichi var. maculicollis
                  </tp:taxon-name> (as written on the original label). In this case, Ohaus (1914a)
                  made an unjustified emendation almost 10 years after the original publication of
                  the species, not being recognized by the Code to validate a name (ICZN 1999, Art.
                  19.1, 33.2). Still, the latter spelling is used as valid, violating the Principle
                  of Priority (ICZN 1999, Art. 23.9). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Key to adult species of <tp:taxon-name> Oplognathus MacLeay, 1819 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p> 1. Males with weakly trilobed clypeus, sides usually parallel; last maxillary
                  palpomere cylindrical; mentum longer than wider, anterior margin sinuous;
                  mesoventral process long (exceeding the anterior margin on mesocoxae, never
                  exceeding the procoxae); (if female, clypeus rounded) ....... 2 </p>
            <p> – Males with strongly trilobed clypeus, sides clearly divergent ( Fig. 3b ); last
                  maxillary palpomere fusiform ( Fig. 4g ); mentum as long as wide, anterior margin
                  notched ( Fig. 4h ); mesoventral process short (not exceeding the anterior margin
                  on mesocoxae), slightly flat ( Fig. 8b, e ); (if female, the clypeus rounded, and
                  last maxillary palpomere cylindrical). Brazil : Bahia , Minas Gerais
                  ...............
                  ....................................................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> O. bahianus Ohaus, 1912 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> 2. Body distinctly bicoloured. Pronotum dark green with yellow maculae. Elytra
                  reddish brown to orange yellow; size varying from 17.2 mm to 18.6 mm in length (
                  Fig. 1c–e ); anterior margin of mentum slightly sinuous ( Fig. 4m ); females
                  without dilated epipleuron, simple. Brazil : Minas Gerais , Paraná
                  ......................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> O. helmenreichi Ohaus, 1905 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p> – Body colour uniformly yellowish golden, sometimes with spots or maculae on
                  pronotum. Elytra golden yellow, with greenish reflections; size varying from 19.15
                  mm to 22.0 mm in length ( Fig. 1a– b ); females with distinctly dilated
                  epipleuron. Brazil : Espírito Santo ; Minas Gerais ; Paraná ; Rio de Janeiro ; São
                  Paulo
                  ........................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> O. kirbii MacLeay, 1819 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
