<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Zephronia viridisoma Rosenmejer &amp; Enghoff &amp; Moritz &amp; Wesener 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5213033</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E71B3C3FB3E44A292DAE9F251AE567A5</uri>
         <article-title>Integrative description of new giant pill-millipedes from southern Thailand (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida, Zephroniidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/253b791f-78ff-42ac-8047-e92449ba4e47</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia viridisoma
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
272E06C8-2DE5-4722-A7D5-D85002D68424
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2B
, 
6B
– 
12
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Posterior telopod typical for the genus, not differing from those of other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia
species.
</tp:taxon-name>
Small (
25– 28 mm
long) green species (
Fig. 2B
), surface appearing glabrous, dull, with a single medium sized locking carina at the anal shield and a strongly projecting pleurite 1 (
Fig. 9A
). One of the few 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia
species
</tp:taxon-name>
with just a single apical spine on the legs (
Fig. 9B
), differing in this character from all other described Thai 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia
species
</tp:taxon-name>
which have 2–5 apical tarsal spines. Male antennomere 6 swollen (
Fig. 7A
) but not axe-shaped, with &lt;50 apical cones. Endotergum with three dense rows of long marginal setae (
Fig. 6B
). Palpi of gnathochilarium with sensory cones arranged in clusters (
Fig. 8C–D
). Anterior telopod podomere 3 with an elevated process at posterior side carrying sclerotized teeth. Podomere 4 short and narrow.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Derivatio nominis
</p>
      <p>Named after the overall green colour of living individuals of the species, noun in apposition.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
THAILAND
• 
♂
; 
Nakhon Si Thammarat Province
, 
Sichon District
, 
Khao Lark Waterfall
; 
9°03′6″ N
, 
99°47′24″ E
; 

25 Aug. 2007

; 
Chulalongkorn University expedition of millipede workshop
leg.; 
dense jungle on limestone
; 
NHMD 621695
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
THAILAND
• 
2 ♂♂
, 
4 ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
NHMD 621696
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
ZFMK
MYR8786
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; CT scan voucher; 
ZFMK
MYR8787
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(based on 
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>
SIZE. Length 
25.6 mm
. Width of thoracic shield 
12.1 mm
, of widest segment (8) 
13 mm
. Height of thoracic shield 
7.1 mm
, of highest segment (8) 
7.7 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR. Head medium brown, faded from green. Antennae medium brown. Legs medium brown, tarsal claws apically dark brown. Tergites light brown, faded green medially, with darker brown posterior margin. Paratergite tips medium brown with darker edges. Anal shield dark green, edges faded to brown (
Fig. 2B
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 7A–C
). Number of ommatidia 50 (
Fig. 7B
). Organ of Tömösváry placed midway between ocelli and antennal groove (
Fig. 7A
), with its typical coral-like inner structure (
Fig. 7C
).
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNAE (
Fig.7A,D
). Reaching leg pair3,6visible antennomeres.Antennomere lengths:6&gt;1&gt;2=3&gt;4=5. Antennomere 6 apically swollen, number of apical cones 32/44.
</p>
      <p>
EPIPHARYNX (
Fig. 8A
). With an extraordinarily large inner tooth.
</p>
      <p>
MANDIBLE (
Fig. 8E–F
). Inner tooth 3-cusped. Pectinate lamellae with 6 or 7 rows of teeth. Condylus at anterior margin with two ridges.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia viridisoma
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ (ZFMK MYR8786), head, scanning elelctron micrographs. 
A
. Lateral view. 
B
. Right eye. 
C
. Organ of Tömösváry. 
D
. Left antenna, lateral view. Abbreviations: Ant = antenna; IL = incisura lateralis; O = ommatidia; TO = organ of Tömösváry.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia viridisoma
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ (ZFMK MYR8786), mouthparts, scanning electron micrographs. 
A
. Epipharynx, ventral view. 
B
. Gnathochilarium, underside. 
C
. Gnathochilarium frontal view at lateral palps and central pads. 
D
. Detail of sensory cones at lateral palps. 
E
. Right mandible, dorsal view. 
F
. Right mandible, mesal view. Abbreviations: 3iT = 3-combed inner tooth; Co = condylus; cP = central pads; Endo = endochilarium; eT = external tooth; iA = inner area; LL = lamellae linguales; LP = lateral palpi; Me = mentum; Mp = molar plate; pL = pectinate lamellae; St = stipes; T = tooth of epipharynx.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia viridisoma
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ (ZFMK MYR8786), legs and pleurite (laterotergite), scanning electron micrographs. 
A
. First pleurite. 
B
. Left midbody leg, posterior view. 
C
. Leg, femur, detail of sclerotized teeth. 
D
. Surface of midbody tergite. Abbreviations: Cx = coxa; Fe = femur; Led = ledge; Po = postfemur; Pr = protuberance; Pre = prefemur; Sp = small triangular spines; Ta = tarsus; Tib = tibia.
</p>
      <p>
GNATHOCHILARIUM (
Fig. 8B–D
). Lamellae linguales with numerous long setae, medially glabrous. Stipes and mentum with numerous long setae in a regular patter. Sensory cones on gnathochilarium palps in clusters (
Fig. 8D
).
</p>
      <p>COLLUM. With short setation, evenly distributed across surface.</p>
      <p>THORACIC SHIELD. Thoracic shield grooves wide and deep, with 9 sclerotized ledges along inner ridge of grooves.</p>
      <p>
TERGITES (
Fig. 9D
). Tergites glabrous, with dull orange skin like surface. At high magnification tiny setae and knobs become visible. Paratergite tips on posterior half projecting backwards (
Fig. 12A–B
).
</p>
      <p>
ENDOTERGUM (
Fig. 6B
). With a regular flat margin. Outer zone with three dense rows of irregular marginal setae, some of them extending beyond posterior margin. A single row of rounded cuticular impressions present next to marginal ridge. Intersegmental membrane smooth, without cones and with very few setae.
</p>
      <p>
STIGMATIC PLATE (
Fig. 10A
). First plate with a rounded sub-triangular apex. More posterior plates similar to those of other representatives of the family, half-covered by the pleurites (
Fig. 12C
).
</p>
      <p>
PLEURITES (
Figs 9A
, 
12D
). Pleurite 1 projecting strongly, with sharp apex. Pleurite 2 projecting slightly less than 1 and with more rounded apex (
Fig. 12D
). Projection absent from pleurite 3 (
Fig. 12D
).
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Ventral spines on leg 1 1/1, on leg 2 3/2, on leg 3 4/4. Apical spine on leg 3 absent. A single apical spine and 5 or 6 ventral spines on midbody legs (
Fig. 9B
). Femur regularly shaped, 2.2 times longer than wide, sclerotized ledge of medium length, inner margin apically with 5 or 6 small rounded triangular spines on ventral side (
Fig. 9B–C
). Tarsus 4.2 times longer than wide.
</p>
      <p>
ANAL SHIELD. Well-rounded and glabrous. Ventral side with dark coloured. A medium-sized locking carina placed slightly closer to pleurite than margin (
Fig. 12D
).
</p>
      <p>
MALE GONOPORE (
Fig. 10B
). Inconspicuous, consisting of large membranous opening located directly at mesal margin.
</p>
      <p>
ANTERIOR TELOPODS (
Fig. 10C–E
). With long setae medially on the first 2 podomeres, covering posterior part on podomere 2. Podomere 1 rectangular, as long as wide. Podomere 
2 in
anterior view as wide as but slightly narrower than podomere 1. Immovable finger barely visible in anterior view (
Fig. 10D
), short, not protruding up to podomere 4 (
Fig. 10C
). Podomere 3 long and wide, with rounded projection on posterior side, bearing 3 crenulated teeth. Podomere 4 very narrow and short, with 3 large spines near apex, and a smaller spine near edge to podomere 3.
</p>
      <p>
POSTERIOR TELOPODS (
Fig. 10F–G
). Podomere 2 setose, immovable finger straight, apically tapering, with rows of small circular sclerotized spots. Membranous lobe between podomere 3 and 4 bearing 2 elongated processes, fused at base. Podomere 3 with 8 or 9 small crenulated teeth on posterior side. Membranous lobe on podomere 3 with single spine. Podomere 4 slightly curved towards immovable finger, membranous lobe with 2 spines. Setation on podomere 2 primarily on anterior side.
</p>
      <p>

Description of female 
paratype
</p>
      <p>
Length 
25.6 mm
. Width of thoracic shield 
12.3 mm
, of widest tergite (8) 
13.7 mm
. Height of thoracic shield: 
8.4 mm
, of highest tergite (8) 
9.3 mm
. Antennae reaching leg pair 3. Apical cones left/right:
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia viridisoma
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (NHMD 621695), drawings. 
A
. Coxa of first left leg with stigmatic plate, posterior view. 
B
. Coxa of second left leg with gonopore, posterior view. 
C
. Left anterior telopod, lateral view on podomeres 2–4. 
D
. Left anterior telopod, anterior view. 
E
. Left anterior telopod, posterior view. 
F
. Right posterior telopod, posterior view. 
G
. Right posteiror telopod, anterior view. Abbreviations: cr-t = crenulated teeth; Cx = coxa; Go = gonopore; St = stigmatic plate. Scale bars = 1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
25/25. Subanal plate well rounded. Vulvae (
Fig. 11
): with a large pointed operculum (Op). External lateral plate (EP) and inner mesal plate (IP) fused at bottom.
</p>
      <p>
Another female 
paratype
was used for microcomputed tomography. The resulting volume rendering is shown in 
Fig. 12
. While this approach revaled no significant additional details it serves to illustrate morphology of the specimen in an excellent way, much better than any photograph.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
