<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sphaerobelum aesculus Rosenmejer &amp; Enghoff &amp; Moritz &amp; Wesener 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5572835</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/248502A0DC0B3778373911D6E0F56998</uri>
         <article-title>Integrative description of new giant pill-millipedes from southern Thailand (Diplopoda, Sphaerotheriida, Zephroniidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/253b791f-78ff-42ac-8047-e92449ba4e47</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sphaerobelum aesculus
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
84D3714E-5CF8-4063-8A4D-40BF8CBEBFB0
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2A
, 
3–5
, 
6A
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Differs from all other species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaerobelum
</tp:taxon-name>
in the shape of the posterior telopod, where there is a swelling at the tip of the immovable finger, but the swelling does not extend above the margin (
Fig. 5B
arrow). Such a swelling is currently unknown from any other giant pill-millipede species.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Derivatio nominis
</p>
      <p>
Named after the horse chestnut tree 
Aesculus hippocastanum
L., for the resemblance of the rolled-up female to a horse chestnut. Noun in apposition.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
THAILAND
• 
♂
; 
Phuket Island
, 
Forest in Kathu district
; 

14 Feb.1989

. 
M. Andersen
and 
A.R. Rasmussen
leg.; 
in and under old logs
; 
NHMD 621693
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
THAILAND
• 
1 ♀
; 
Nakhon Si Thammarat Prov.
, 
Khao Luang NP
; 
8°43′25.2″ N
, 
99°40′7.7″ E
, 

355 m
a.s.l.

; 

10–12 Oct. 2003

; 
ATOL Expedition 2003
leg.; 
NHMD 621694
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(based on 
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>
SIZE. Length 
23.8 mm
. Width of thoracic shield 
10.5 mm
, of widest segment (9) 
11.1 mm
. Height of thoracic shield 
6.2 mm
, Height of highest segment (7) 
7 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR. Head, antenna, legs and tergites golden light brown. Posterior margin of tergites and paratergite tips medium brown. Anal shield medially brown, with lighter colour at edges (
Fig. 2A
). HEAD. Number of ommatidia 55. Antennae (
Fig. 3A–C
): Antennomere lengths: 6&gt;1&gt;2=3=4=5. Antennae short, barely reaching first leg pair. Sixth antennomere apically slightly swollen (
Fig. 3A
), number of apical cones 52/56 (
Fig. 3B
). Mandible: not dissected. Gnathochilarium: lingual lamella with numerous long setae, medially glabrous.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
Map of Thailand, collection localities of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaerobelum aesculus
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zephronia viridisoma
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, and habitus photographs: 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. aesculus
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀ (NHMD 621694); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Z. viridisoma
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype, ♀ (ZFMK MYR8787). Scale bars = 1 cm.
</p>
      <p>COLLUM. With few setae spread thinly along borders.</p>
      <p>THORACIC SHIELD. Thoracic shield grooves wide and deep, with 3 sclerotized ledges along inner ridge.</p>
      <p>
TERGITES. Paratergite tips on posterior half projecting backwards. Tergites glabrous with dull leather-like surface (
Fig. 3D–E
). At high magnification tiny setae become visible.
</p>
      <p>
ENDOTERGUM (
Fig. 6A
). With a regular flat margin. Outer zone with two rows of irregular
</p>
      <p>MARGINAL SETAE. Not extending beyond posterior margin, but reaching ⅔ of the outer area. Anterior part of marginal ridge flat. Intersegmental membrane smooth, without cones and with a row of setae with large glabrous gaps.</p>
      <p>
FIRST STIGMATIC PLATE (
Fig. 4A
). With a well-rounded apex.
</p>
      <p>PLEURITES. Pleurite 1 projecting posteriorly with sharp apex. Pleurite 2 with rounded apex projecting slightly.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Ventral spines on leg 1 4/4, on leg 2 3/5, on leg 3 3/4. Apical spine absent on leg 3. Three apical and 4 or 5 ventral spines on midbody legs (
Fig. 4C
). Inner margin of femur with 8–12 small teeth, but not excavated. Femur 2, tarsus 4 times as long as wide.
</p>
      <p>ANAL SHIELD. Well-rounded and glabrous. Ventral side with a single small locking carina, placed ⅓ from pleurite.</p>
      <p>
MALE GONOPORE. Located at mesal margin of coxa (
Fig. 4B
), large, covered by a membranous plate.
</p>
      <p>
ANTERIOR TELOPODS (
Fig. 4D–F
). Podomere 1 rectangular, as long as wide, covered with setae anteriorly, with extra long setae medially, and posteriorly glabrous. Podomere 2 with long immovable finger visible laterally in anterior view. Finger curving inwards against podomere 3. Podomere 3 cylindrical twice as long as wide. Suture between podomere 3 and 4 barely visible in posterior and lateral views. Podomere 4 very short, just ¼ of length of podomere 3, with one short and dark spine on apex.
</p>
      <p>
POSTERIOR TELOPODS (
Fig. 5A–B
). Podomere 1 as long as wide, covered in setae anteriorly, and nearly glabrous posteriorly. Podomere 2 with wide immovable finger. Immovable finger straight, only slightly tapering towards apex, bearing an oval membranous spot on posterior side. The membrane between podomere 2 and 3 with single membranous lobe, angled. Podomere 3 with sparse setation. Podomere 3 ca 3 times longer than wide, towards immovable finger with membranous ledge, a single spine, posterior side with row of 9 or 10 crenulated teeth. Podomere 4 short, straight, ca 2.5 times as long as wide, with a short membranous ledge and 2 spines towards immovable finger.
</p>
      <p>
Female from Khao Luang NP
Length 
45 mm
. Width of thoracic shield 
23 mm
, of widest segment (9) 
24.6 mm
. Height of thoracic
</p>
      <p>
shield 
12.6 mm
, of highest segment (8) 
15.2 mm
.Antennae reaching leg pair 2. Apical cones on antennae 43/34. Subanal plate well rounded. Vulvae (
Fig. 5C
): small, with a narrow operculum (Op), only reaching bottom part of prefemur. External lateral plate (EP) and inner mesal plate (IP) almost completely fused.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaerobelum aesculus
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (NHMD 621693), scanning electron micrographs. 
A
. Right antenna, lateral view. 
B
. Right antenna, disc. 
C
. Detail of apical cone. 
D
. Tergite surface of midbody ring. 
E
. Tergite surface at very high magnification. Abbreviations: ac = apical cone; sb = sensilla basiconica.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaerobelum aesculus
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesenersp.
</tp:taxon-name>
nov., holotype, ♂ (NHMD 621693), drawings. 
A
. First left coxa with stigmatic plate, posterior view. 
B
. Second left coxa with gonopore, posterior view. 
C
. Left leg 9, posterior view. 
D
. Left anterior telopod, posterior view. 
E
. Left anterior telopod, anterior view. 
F
. Left anterior telopod, lateral view on podomeres 2–4. Abbreviations: as = apical spine; cl = claw; Cx = coxa; Fe = femur; Go = gonopore; Po = postfemur; Pre = prefemur; St = stigmatic plate; Ta = tarsus; Ti = tibia; vs = ventral spines. Scale bars = 1 mm.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphaerobelum aesculus
Rosenmejer &amp; Wesener
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
drawings. 
A–B
. Holotype, ♂ (NHMD 621693), 
C
. ♀ (NHMD 621694). 
A
. Left posterior telopod, anterior view. 
B
. Left posterior telopod, posterior view, arrow points to swelling of immovable finger. 
C
. Left second coxa and prefemur with female vulva. Abbreviations: Cx = coxa; EP = external, lateral plate; IP = inner, mesal plate; Op = operculum; Pre = prefemur. Scale bars = 1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
If the female from Khao Luang (
Fig. 2A
) is indeed conspecific with the male 
holotype
, the species appears to have a wide area of distribution stretching from 
Phuket
Island at least 
160 km
to the east (
Fig. 2
). Unpublished data from a larger inventory project (see, e.g., Wesener 
et al.
2021) of giant pill-millipedes in the surroundings of 
Krabi
, half way between 
Phuket
Island and Khao Luang, did not recover this species among the numerous specimens, hinting at a patchy distribution and specific microhabitat requirements of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. aesculus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
