<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Eponisiella shandongensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
A24188AA-9CDC-4642-9A1A-20B862BA6AB5
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3–4
, 
13–20
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The salient features of the new species include: tegmina (
Fig. 16
) with three transverse brown bands apically; ventral and dorsal margins of anal tube (
Fig. 18
) each with a dentate productions at apex in lateral view; gonostyli (
Fig. 19
) with two bumps near middle and third in caudoventral view; aedeagus (
Figs 18, 20
) trifurcate.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The new species is named after its collecting location in the 
Shandong Province
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Shandong Province
, 
Yellow River Delta Nature Reserve
; 
37°72′ N
, 
118°95′ E
; 

4 Aug. 2014

; 
Wei-Bin Zheng
leg.; 
IEGU
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
2 ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
IEGU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length including tegmina: male 
3.01 mm
(N = 1), female 
3.10–3.14 mm
(N = 2).
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. General color grayish white (
Figs 3–4
). Eyes grayish brown. Frons pale brown, with weak brownish stripe in middle. Clypeus and antenna yellowish-brown. Vertex, pronotum and mesonotum with yellowish-brown stripe in middle, pronotum and mesonotum with two ocherous patches on both sides. Tegmina with longitudinal veins and adjacent parts of membrane with dark patterns, with three transverse brown bands apically. Wings waxy white with pale veins.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD AND THORAX. Head (
Figs 3
, 
13
) significantly narrower than pronotum. Vertex shorter in middle than wide at base (1:2.11), posterior margin slightly convex, with two triangular posterolateral areolets widely separated from each other, not nearly approaching in middle line. Frons (
Fig. 14
) approximately rectangular, without median carina, longer in middle line than wide at widest portion (about 1.61: 1), lateral carinae with dense row of sensory pits along outer margin. Clypeus (
Fig. 14
) without lateral carinae, elevated medially, median carina present. Frontoclypeal suture nearly straight. Rostrum elongate, surpassing hind-coxae. Pronotum (
Fig. 13
) short, wider than maximum width of head (including eyes) (1.38: 1), lateral carinae sinuate, median carina absent. Mesonotum (
Fig. 13
) about 4.83 × as long as pronotum in midline, with weak median carina. Tegmina (
Fig. 16
) broadened apically, longer than maximal width (2.03: 1). A2 of wing (
Fig. 17
) not reaching margin. Metatibiotarsal formula: (3+5)-7-5.
</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA. Pygofer (
Figs 18–19
) in lateral view with dorsocaudal angle strongly produced; in caudoventral view, strongly concave medially, each side with finger-like process with hairs lateroapically, slightly curved outwardly. Anal tube stout (
Figs 15, 18
) in lateral view, ventral margin of anal tube waved, apex of ventral and dorsal margins each with dentate productions; in dorsal view, bifurcate; anal style short. Aedeagus (
Figs 18, 20
) trifurcate in lateral view, little shorter than anal tube, lower part of aedeagus slightly blunt, bifurcate at apex, upper one bends to form protrusion. Gonostyli (
Figs 18– 19
) in lateral view, curved at middle, inner side concave medially producing angular production; in caudoventral view, two bumps near middle and third, respectively.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Shandong
) (
Fig. 21
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. matsumurai
Tsaur, Yang &amp; Wilson, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
, but differs from the latter in: (1) aedeagus trifurcate (aedeagus bifurcate in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. matsumurai
</tp:taxon-name>
); (2) gonostyli with two bumps near middle and third in caudoventral view (gonostyli with three bumps near middle in caudoventral view in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. matsumurai
</tp:taxon-name>
); (3) inner side of gonostyli medially producing an angular production (inner side of gonostyli concave medially without an angular production in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. matsumurai
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
