<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Cixius madeirensis China 1938</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4680936</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03D77A7DFFDEF711FD9FD9C5B313FC62</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomy of the Cixiidae (Hemiptera, Fulgoromorpha) from the Madeira
            archipelago</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.744.1295</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Cixius madeirensis </tp:taxon-name> China, 1938 </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Figs 3A–B , 5A , 8A–B , 9A–N </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Cixius madeirensis </tp:taxon-name> China, 1938: 50–51 , fig. 21
         (description, illustrations, records). </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Cixius madeirensis </tp:taxon-name> – Lindberg 1961: 55 (records, habitat).
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> This species is easily recognizable by its size, smaller to <tp:taxon-name> C. wollastoni
         </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. and <tp:taxon-name> C. verticalis </tp:taxon-name> , and brown
         colouration. It differs from the other Madeira <tp:taxon-name> Cixius </tp:taxon-name> in
         the following characters: (1) the basal half of the vellum is hump-shaped but is much
         narrower on the outer margin than in <tp:taxon-name> C. verticalis </tp:taxon-name> ; the
         apex is blunt, not scythe-shaped as in <tp:taxon-name> C. wollastoni </tp:taxon-name> sp.
         nov. and <tp:taxon-name> C. verticalis </tp:taxon-name> ; (2) the medioventral expansion of
         the theca is digitiform and more conspicuous and longer. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> MADEIRA ISLANDS – Porto Moniz • 2 ♀♀ ; Chão da Ribeira ; 500 m
            a.s.l. ; 30 Apr. 2002 ; Énio Freitas leg.; on <tp:taxon-name> Diplazium caudatum
            </tp:taxon-name> ; UMACI </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 5 ♂♂ , 2 ♀♀ ;
            same collection data as for preceding; 21 May 2002 ; Énio Freitas leg.; UMACI
         </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for
            preceding; 11 Apr. 2003 ; Dora Pombo leg.; DAPC </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for preceding; 28 Jul. 1997 ; I.
            Silva leg.; UMACI </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; Ribeira da
            Janela ; 800 m a.s.l. ; 12 Sep. 2001 ; Énio Freitas leg.; on <tp:taxon-name> Pteridium
               aquilinum </tp:taxon-name> ; UMACI </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation>
            13 ♂♂ , 4 ♀♀ ; Vereda do Paul da Serra , Chão da Ribeira ; 1200 m a.s.l. ; 23 Jul. 2002
            ; Rúben Gouveia leg.; on <tp:taxon-name> P. aquilinum </tp:taxon-name> ; UMACI . – São
            Vicente • 1 ♀ ; Chão Louros ; 710 m a.s.l. ; 9 May 2000 ; Joana Barreto leg.; UMACI . – </tp:material-citation>
         <tp:material-citation> Santana • 1 ♂ ; Levada Ribeiro Frio , Portela ; 1000 m a.s.l. ; 9
            Aug. 2001 ; Énio Freitas leg.; on <tp:taxon-name> Clethra arborea </tp:taxon-name> ;
            UMACI </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; Pico das Pedras , Queimadas
            ; 800 m a.s.l. ; 7 Sep. 2001 ; Énio Freitas leg.; on <tp:taxon-name> Hydrangea
               macrophylla </tp:taxon-name> ; UMACI </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation>
            1 ♂ ; same collection data as for preceding; Fábio Reis leg.; on <tp:taxon-name> P.
               aquilinum </tp:taxon-name> ; UMACI </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1
            ♀ ; Ribeiro Frio ; 1000 m a.s.l. ; 12 Jun. 2002 ; Énio Freitas leg.; on <tp:taxon-name>
               C. arborea </tp:taxon-name> ; UMACI </tp:material-citation> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p> Fig. 8. Female genitalia. A–B . <tp:taxon-name> Cixius madeirensis </tp:taxon-name> China,
      1938 from Vereda do Paul da Serra, 23 Jul. 2002, on <tp:taxon-name> Peteridium aquilinum
      </tp:taxon-name> (L.) Kuhn. C–D . <tp:taxon-name> Cixius verticalis Noualhier, 1897
      </tp:taxon-name> from Chão da Ribeira (500 m a.s.l.), 30 Apr. 2002, on <tp:taxon-name>
         Diplazium caudatum (Cav.) Jermy. E </tp:taxon-name> –F . <tp:taxon-name> Tachycixius
         chaoensis </tp:taxon-name> ( China, 1938 ) from Ponta de São Lourenço, 11 May 2001, on
         <tp:taxon-name> Suaeda vera Forssk. ex J.F.Gmel. G </tp:taxon-name> –H . <tp:taxon-name>
         Hyalesthes portonoves Remane &amp; Hoch, 1986 </tp:taxon-name> . G . Specimen from Porto
      Novo, 25 Apr. 2003, on <tp:taxon-name> G. salicina Lam. H . </tp:taxon-name> Specimen from
      Cristo Rei, 26 Apr. 1998, on <tp:taxon-name> G. salicina </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Redescription </p>
      <p> BODY MEASUREMENTS (mm). See Table 1. </p>
      <p> COLOURATION. General light golden brown coloration ( Fig. 3A–B ). Vertex light brown, most
         specimens have two small paler spots that fade to the level of the anterior margin of the
         eyes ( Fig. 9B ). Areolar carinae dark brown. Lateral pits on the frons, clypeus, carinae,
         genae, lora and the 2 nd segment of the antenna, yellowish to light brown, often darker in
         females. Lateral ocelli glowing yellow. Reddish-brown eyes. Pronotum and tegula as in
            <tp:taxon-name> C. wollastoni </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Mesonotum brownish-black;
         lateral carinae, posterior margins and posterolateral margins close to tegula fulvous; in
         lighter individuals, the area between the lateral carinae is light brown and, in females,
         it is almost entirely brown. Tegmina yellowish and translucent; pale veins with brown
         setiferous tubercles; stigma yellowish to dark brown ( Figs 3A–B , 5A ). Some males and
         females have three narrow faint brown oblique stripes ( Fig. 3B ). The band on the first
         third is larger, wider and bifurcates from the middle, giving rise a short oblique band
         towards ⅓ of clavus base, and another reaching the clavus lateromedially. The last band
         forms a dark brown spot below the claval vein fork. The other two strips are short,
         reaching the subcostal vein. The females are darker than the males and the setiferous
         tubercles and markings are also more distinctive ( Fig. 3A–B ); legs, abdomen, and tegmina
         as in <tp:taxon-name> C. wollastoni </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. but, in darker specimens, the
         brown marks of the tegmina are more intense and extensive. </p>
      <p> HEAD. Vertex apex from round to slightly angular ( Fig. 9B ); posterior margin roundish
         and about 1.8 times as wide as in the anterior margin of eyes as long. The medial carina of
         the frons ridged, tapering along clypeus. Epistomal suture wave-shaped, the crest is lower
         than in <tp:taxon-name> C. wollastoni </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. and <tp:taxon-name> C.
            verticalis </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 9A ). Medial ocellus reduced or obsolete. </p>
      <p> THORAX. Pronotum, mesonotum, tegula, setiferous tubercles along the veins and lateral
         spines of the metatibiae and the first metatarsus as in <tp:taxon-name> C. wollastoni
         </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , but the tegmina is almost 2 times as long as wide ( Fig. 5A ). </p>
      <p> MALE GENITALIA. Lateral lobes of the pygofer roundish with distal end more or less
         truncated, similar to a trapezium ( Fig. 9F, H ). The caudoventral margin of the anal tube
         concave ( Fig. 9G ), lateral lobes arc-shaped, wider distally and bent rostrally ( Fig. 9J
         ). Lamella of the parameres subtriangular, gradually expanding ventrodistally; proximal
         margin almost straight and distal margin convex ( Fig. 9I ). The vellum of aedeagus and
         basal thorns as in <tp:taxon-name> C. verticalis </tp:taxon-name> but the smallest spine
         longer and more curved; expansion of vellum hump-shaped in its basal half; apex blunt. The
         proximal margin of theca ends in a solid ventral spine like a finger of variable size,
         while the ventromedial projection is large and digitiform ( Fig. 9K–N ). </p>
      <p> FEMALE GENITALIA. Seventh sternite with truncate inverted caudal margin ( Fig. 8B ).
         Gonoplac ensiform and curved upwards; long, about 5 times as long as wide, reaching almost
         the level of the dorsal margin of the anal tube and exceeding this in half of its length;
         the dorsal margin pubescent ( Fig. 8A ). Nineth tergite truncated caudally. Wax secreting
         field ellipse-shaped and shallowly excavated, approximately 1.5 times as wide as long; not
         separated medially by a distinctive ridge; scattered long hairs denser near the mediodorsal
         margin. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p> Fig. 9. <tp:taxon-name> Cixius madeirensis </tp:taxon-name> China, 1938 . A–G, I–N .
      Specimens from Vereda do Paul, 23 Jul. 2002, on <tp:taxon-name> Pteridium aquilinum
      </tp:taxon-name> (L.) Kuhn. H . Specimen from Chão da Ribeira, 28 Jul. 1997. A . Head (frontal
      view). B . Head, pronotum, and scutellum (dorsal view). C–D . Head (dorsal view). E . Anal
      tube (dorsal view). F . Pygofer (ventral view). G . Anal tube (caudal view). H . Pygofer
      (lateral view). I . Left paramere. J . Anal tube (left lateral view). K–N . Aedeagus (K–L,
      right and left lateral view; M–N, dorsal and ventral view). </p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution and ecology </p>
      <p> Endemic to Madeira Island. Widespread in north and south Madeira ; occurs in wet areas of
         laurel forest between 500 and 1200 m . Adult specimens were collected from April to
         September preferentially on <tp:taxon-name> Clethra arborea </tp:taxon-name> trees and on
         the fern <tp:taxon-name> Diplazium caudatum </tp:taxon-name> , an endemic species of
         Macaronesia, and were also found on <tp:taxon-name> Pteridium aquilinum </tp:taxon-name>
         ferns and <tp:taxon-name> Hydrangea macrophylla (Thunb.) Ser. </tp:taxon-name> bushes. This
         species was reported by Lindberg exclusively from native vegetation ( Lindberg 1961 ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> The distal margin of the anal tube, style, and aedeagus are very well shown by China
         (1938) , except that the flagellum hump is more pronounced than in China’s description,
         possibly because this thin and almost transparent membrane is difficult to observe. In
         contrast, Lindberg’s drawings (1954), which he attributed to <tp:taxon-name> C. verticalis
         </tp:taxon-name> (see above), show the hump characteristic of the flagellum and that the
         ventral process is smoother than in China’s illustrations. The blunt apex of the aedeagus,
         the small curved right lateral spine and the ventral spine-like projection of the proximal
         margin of the base depicted by China and Lindberg are similar, but the parameres and the
         anal tube are different. </p>
      <p> The values of BL, MW, ML and WL in males and females of <tp:taxon-name> C. madeirensis
         </tp:taxon-name> are smaller than in <tp:taxon-name> C. verticalis </tp:taxon-name> ( Table
         1 ) including PW, the only measurement with some degree of overlap (Welch t-test, t (23.98)
         = 68.24, p &lt;0.01). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
