<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Cixiidae Spinola 1839</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4665623</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EB57DDF591EAB632742E27C667823812</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomy of the Cixiidae (Hemiptera, Fulgoromorpha) from the Madeira archipelago</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.744.1295</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>

Key of Madeiran 
<tp:taxon-name>Cixiidae</tp:taxon-name>
based on males

</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Mesonotum with 3 carinae (
Figs 4B
, 
7B
, 
9B
, 
10B
) ......................................................................... 2

</p>
      <p>

– Mesonotum with 5 carinae (
Figs 11B
, 
12B
, 
13A
) ............................................................................ 5

</p>
      <p>

2. Body length &lt;
5 mm
; vertex tongue-shaped, posterior margin quadrangular (
Fig. 10B
); medial carina of frons smooth, reaching the posterior margin of the postclypeus (
Fig. 10A
); apical margin of tegmina oval with tubercles on the apical margin between the veins (
Figs 3E
, 
10I
); first metatarsus with 6 spines distally .............................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tachycixius chaoensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(

China
, 1938

)

</p>
      <p>

– Body length&gt; 
5 mm
; shape of vertex different, posterior margin concave (
Figs 4B
, 
7B
, 
9B–D
); medial carina of frons distinctively ridged, extending along the frons and the clypeus (
Figs 4A
, 
7A
, 
9A
); apical margin of the tegmina rounded, usually without tubercles on the apical margin between veins, if present they are few (
Fig. 5A–C
); first metatarsus with 8 spines distally .......................... 3

</p>
      <p>

3. Body length 
5.06–5.67 mm
; light brown body (
Fig. 3A–B
); anterior margin of the vertex rounded or slightly acute, slightly concave at the back (
Fig. 9B–D
); mesonotum light brown; tegmina light golden brown, almost 2 times as long as wide, with small brown setiferous tubercles along the longitudinal veins ................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. madeirensis
</tp:taxon-name>
China
, 1938

</p>
      <p>

– Body length&gt; 
5.90 mm
; light blackish to dark brown body; anterior margin of the vertex acute and posterior margin distinctively concave (
Fig. 4B
, 
7B
); mesonotum black; tegmina whitish, 2.75 times as long as wide, with large black setiferous points along the longitudinal veins ............................. 4

</p>
      <p>

4. Body length&gt; 
7.20 mm
. Vertex slightly acute at the anterior margin and concave at posterior margin (
Fig. 7B
); ventral margin of the aedeagus with a finger-shaped expansion; the largest lateral thorn curves distally forming an angle of 90º; 
vellum
gibbous, without dorsal denticle and the ventral margin distinctively curved distally (
Fig. 7K–N
) ................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. verticalis
Noualhier, 1897
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body length &lt;
7.20 mm
. Vertex distinctly acute at the anterior margin and tongue-shaped at the posterior margin (
Fig. 4B
); ventral margin of the aedeagus with a wave-shaped expansion; the larger lateral thorn is curved and does not form a 90º angle distally; 
vellum
subtrapezoid, with a small dorsal denticle and the ventral margin almost straight distally (
Fig. 4K–N
) .... 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. wollastoni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

5. Body length&gt; 
5 mm
; first metatarsus with more than 10 spines. Aedeagus with a long, hook-shaped thorn along the right lateral side and 3 smaller thorns distally on the left side of the aedeagus, two of them much longer (
Fig. 13D–E
) ....................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pentastiridus leporinus
(
Linnaeus, 1761
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body length &lt;
5 mm
; first metatarsus with less than 10 spines. Aedeagus with two long, thin thorns on the left lateral side (
Figs 11I–M
, 
12I–M
) ..................................................................................... 6

</p>
      <p>

6. Vertex often short, lateral margins usually converging anteriorly (
Fig. 11B
); in lateral view, dorsal thorn of aedeagus wider and longer than the ventral thorn, both converging distally (
Fig. 11I–M
)... .................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. madeires
Remane &amp; Hoch, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Vertex often long, lateral margins usually parallel (
Fig. 12B
); in lateral view, dorsal thorn of aedeagus more slender and shorter than the ventral thorn, both distally parallel or divergent (
Fig. 12I–M
) .... ............................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. portonoves
Remane &amp; Hoch, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
