<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Aenigmatoconcha eunetis Pholyotha
                        &amp; Panha, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5528140</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03DE8788A425FFA43889FCEAFC764665</uri>
                  <article-title>Systematic revision of the limestone karst-restricted land snail
                        genus Aenigmatoconcha (Eupulmonata: Helicarionidae), with description of a
                        new species</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.767.1487</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha eunetis Pholyotha &amp; Panha </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 98AD360F-93A3-4A8E-BE1A-5C991DBC358F </p>
            <p> Figs 1 , 2F–H , 7E–F , 9 , 10D </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>Shell medium-sized and pale yellowish white. Aperture ovate-lunate in shape and
                  vertically open. Genitalia with very long and slender penis with many tiny conical
                  penial pilasters inside. Radular teeth arranged in wide-angle U-shaped row, teeth
                  with oblong shape, monocuspid.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The specific name ʻ <tp:taxon-name> eunetis </tp:taxon-name> ʼ is from the Greek
                  word meaning ʻspousesʼ, honouring the authors of genus <tp:taxon-name>
                        Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> , who are married. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype THAILAND • 1 sh (width 13.9 mm , height 7.4 mm );
                        Uthai Thani Province , Lan Sak District , Limestone outcrops at Tham Namthip
                        Bureau of Monks ; 15°26′00.3″ N , 99°35′18.7″ E ; CUMZ 7931 .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes THAILAND • 1 sh , 7 sp ; same collection data as
                        for holotype; CUMZ 7933 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 12
                        sp ; same collection data as for holotype; CUMZ 7932 </tp:material-citation>
                  • <tp:material-citation> 2 sh ; same collection data as for holotype; NHMUK
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> THAILAND • 1 sp ; Uthai Thani Province , Lan Sak District ,
                        Limestone outcrops at Hup Pa Tat ; 15°22′36.5″ N , 99°37′49.5″ E ; CUMZ 7934
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 6 sp; same collection data as for
                        preceding; CUMZ 7935 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 3 sh ,
                        27 sp ; Uthai Thani Province , Nong Chang District , Limestone outcrops at
                        Wat Khao Bang Kraek ; 15°18′07.9″ N , 99°41′04.5″ E ; CUMZ 7936
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> SHELL ( Fig. 7E–F ). Depressed to globosely depressed, medium-sized (width 12.6–14.2
                  mm , height 6.1– 7.1 mm ), thin and translucent. Shell surface smooth, and
                  polished, and pale yellowish white. Whorls: 5–5½, regularly increasing in size,
                  separated by shallow suture. Spire rather elevated; varix usually present; last
                  whorl well-rounded. Aperture very obliquely oval-lunate in shape; peristome
                  simple. Columellar margin simple and slightly expanded near umbilicus. Umbilicus
                  open and deep. </p>
            <p> Fig. 8. Genital system of <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha sumonthai Tumpeesuwan
                        &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2018 </tp:taxon-name> , specimen CUMZ 7922 from the type
                  locality. A . General view of genitalia; inset showing flagellum encircled with a
                  loose tissue before clearing it out. B . Internal structure of penis; inset
                  showing penial sculpture. C . Internal structure of epiphallus and epiphallic
                  caecum. White arrow indicates the junction between the penis and epiphallus. </p>
            <p> EXTERNAL FEATURES ( Fig. 2F–H ). Living snails with reticulated skin and pale
                  yellowish to slightly dark grey body. Five well-developed mantle lobes: left and
                  right shell lobes translucent, same colour as body, covered by tiny whitish dots,
                  right shell lobe smaller than left shell lobe. Dorsal lobes broad and
                  crescent-shaped: right dorsal lobe larger than both anterior and posterior left
                  dorsal lobes. Caudal fossa present; caudal horn raised and rather large, and same
                  colour as body. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Fig. 9 ). Atrium (at) enlarged and very short. Penis (p) very long and
                  slender with rather thick penial sheath (ps) covering from atrium to almost middle
                  of penis. Inner sculpture of penis with small conical penial pilasters (pp), and
                  three prominent longitudinal folds along entire length of penis chamber.
                  Epiphallus (e1 + e2) approximately half of penis length: e1 elongate and slender,
                  and e2 very short and bulbous. Inner sculpture of e1 nearly smooth with small,
                  thin, and longitudinal folds, and e2 densely papillate. Epiphallic caecum (ec)
                  straight, short, and approximately as long as e2; penial retractor muscle (prm)
                  thin and attached at tip. Flagellum (fl) small, rather short, and approximately as
                  long as e2. Vas deferens (vd) very long, thin, and convoluted. Vagina (v) short,
                  enlarged, thickened and cylindrical. Gametolytic sac (gs) short and bulbous;
                  gametolytic duct (gd) long, enlarged near vagina then becoming smaller and very
                  slender. Free oviduct (fo) long, cylindrical, and encircled with dense tissue near
                  vagina. </p>
            <p> RADULA ( Fig. 10D ). Teeth arranged in wide-angle U-shape with half row consisting
                  of about 97–98 teeth at middle plate. Central tooth symmetrical monocuspid,
                  elongated oblong-shaped with curved cusp, and slightly smaller than lateral tooth.
                  Lateral and marginal teeth undifferentiated, asymmetrical monocuspid and elongated
                  oblong-shaped with curved cusp; outermost teeth gradually becoming smaller. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha eunetis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. occurs in a few
                  isolated limestone hills in Uthai Thani Province .This new species lives on
                  limestone karsts, where snails tend to hide themselves in rock crevices and
                  shelter during the daytime. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha eunetis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. clearly differs
                  from all congeners in having 1) the longest penis, 2) penial internal sculpture
                  consisting of longitudinal folds and small conical penial pilasters, and 3) inner
                  sculpture of epiphallus (e2) densely papillae. For comparison, <tp:taxon-name> A.
                        clivicola </tp:taxon-name> has oblique trapezoidshaped penial pilasters,
                        <tp:taxon-name> A. mitis </tp:taxon-name> has oblique wrinkled penial
                  pilasters with a longitudinal fold, and <tp:taxon-name> A. sumonthai
                  </tp:taxon-name> has very small conical penial pilasters without longitudinal
                  fold. In addition, for the inner sculpture of epiphallus (e2), <tp:taxon-name> A.
                        clivicola </tp:taxon-name> has irregularly oblique trapezoid and small
                  conical papillae. <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha mitis </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> A. sumonthai </tp:taxon-name> have loose papillae arranged
                  in oblique rows, but the former has relatively fewer rows and papillae are
                  significantly larger in size than the latter. Moreover, radular teeth of only
                        <tp:taxon-name> A. eunetis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. are arranged in
                  wide-angle U-shaped row and oblong-shaped teeth, while radular teeth of other
                        <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha species </tp:taxon-name> are arranged in
                  V-shaped rows and spatulate in shape. </p>
            <p> Discussion </p>
            <p> Each of the four <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha species </tp:taxon-name> forms a
                  well-defined clade in the COI phylogeny. <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha
                  </tp:taxon-name> can be divided into two groups based on the genital characters (
                  Figs 1–2 ; Table 2 ). Group I ( Fig. 2 ) has a long epiphallic caecum and short
                  penial caecum, and contains one species, <tp:taxon-name> A. clivicola
                  </tp:taxon-name> , which is restricted to northeasthern Thailand ( Fig. 1 ). Group
                  II ( Fig. 2 ) has a short epiphallic caecum and no penial caecum; this group
                  contains <tp:taxon-name> A. mitis </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> A. sumonthai
                  </tp:taxon-name> , and <tp:taxon-name> A. eunetis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. This
                  group occurs from central to southern Thailand along the Tenasserim Range ( Fig. 1
                  ). The COI tree showed very low nodal support for the relationships among the two
                        <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> groups and the other two
                  helicarionid genera. Although the phylogenetic relationships among <tp:taxon-name>
                        Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Sophina </tp:taxon-name>
                  and <tp:taxon-name> Chalepotaxis </tp:taxon-name> remain unresolved, the genital
                  characters of both groups of <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> were
                  clearly distinct from <tp:taxon-name> Sophina </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>
                        Chalepotaxis </tp:taxon-name> . In the phylogenetic tree of the 28S gene,
                  moreover, these three genera were confirmed as different genera, but the
                  systematic position of two <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha species
                  </tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name> A. clivicola </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> A. sumonthai </tp:taxon-name> ) is unresolved ( Sutcharit et
                  al. 2020a ). Further research should include on more genes and more taxa of the
                  Southeast Asian helicarionoids to better understand the phylogenetic relationships
                  and morphological evolution of these groups. </p>
            <p> Fig. 9. Genital system of <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha eunetis Pholyotha &amp;
                        Panha </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , paratype CUMZ 7933 from Uthai Thani
                  Province. A . General view of genitalia. B . Internal structure of penis; inset
                  showing penial sculpture. C . Internal structure of epiphallus and epiphallic
                  caecum. White arrow indicates the junction between the penis and epiphallus. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> can be distinguished from almost
                  all other Southeast Asian helicarionoid genera by their unique milky to pale
                  whitish-horny and umbilicate shell. Other helicarionoids with a whitish shell
                  include <tp:taxon-name> Macrochlamys psyche Vermeulen et al. , 2019
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Sarika lactoconcha Pholyotha &amp; Panha, 2020
                  </tp:taxon-name> , and <tp:taxon-name> Sarika consepta (Benson, 1860)
                  </tp:taxon-name> . However, the relatively medium to large-sized shells (shell
                  width larger than 15 mm ), narrowly perforate umbilicus, genital structure, and
                  radula with triangular teeth of these three species clearly differentiate them
                  from all <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha species </tp:taxon-name> ( Vermeulen et
                  al. 2019 ; Pholyotha et al. 2020 a , 2020b). The greatest similarity in shell
                  characters occurred in <tp:taxon-name> Sophina </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> Chalepotaxis </tp:taxon-name> , but their genitalia are
                  obviously different. The distinctive characters between <tp:taxon-name>
                        Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Chalepotaxis
                  </tp:taxon-name> have been reported ( Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan 2017 ;
                  Sutcharit et al. 2020a ). However, Tumpeesuwan and Tumpeesuwan (2017) did not
                  report the presence of a “penial sheath” and a “flagellum” in <tp:taxon-name> A.
                        clivicola </tp:taxon-name> (the type species). In fact, they stated that the
                  absence of a penial sheath in <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> is
                  a diagnostic difference between <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name>
                  and <tp:taxon-name> Chalepotaxis </tp:taxon-name> . Yet, in the present work, the
                  four <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha species </tp:taxon-name> clearly exhibited a
                  well-developed penial sheath and flagellum. Hence, the only difference between
                        <tp:taxon-name> Chalepotaxis </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>
                        Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> is the presence of a flagellum in the
                  latter ( Páll-Gergely et al. 2016 ). In addition to the genitalia without a dart
                  apparatus, the presence of well-developed anterior and posterior left dorsal lobes
                  is a significant character of <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  while <tp:taxon-name> Sophina </tp:taxon-name> has an undivided left dorsal lobe
                  and a dart apparatus (Blanford &amp; Godwin-Austen 1908; Sutcharit et al. 2020a ).
                  However, information on the mantle lobe morphology of <tp:taxon-name> Chalepotaxis
                  </tp:taxon-name> was not available for comparison. </p>
            <p> Fig. 10. Radula morphology of <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha spp. A
                  </tp:taxon-name> . <tp:taxon-name> A. clivicola Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan,
                        2017 </tp:taxon-name> , specimen CUMZ 7929 from Loei Province. B .
                        <tp:taxon-name> A. mitis ( Pfeiffer, 1863 ) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. ,
                  specimen CUMZ 7687 from Kanchanaburi Province. C . <tp:taxon-name> A. sumonthai
                        Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2018 </tp:taxon-name> , specimen CUMZ 7922
                  from Chumphon Province. D . <tp:taxon-name> A. eunetis Pholyotha &amp; Panha
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , paratype CUMZ 7933 from Uthai Thani Province. Central
                  tooth in yellow. Scale bars: A–C = 100 μm; D = 50 μm. </p>
            <p> Among Southeast Asian helicarionoid genera with uniform and spatulate-shaped radula,
                        <tp:taxon-name> Sophina </tp:taxon-name> is the only genus that a dart
                  apparatus present in genitalia, but a flagellum absent. While genitalia of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> lack dart apparatus, but
                  contain the flagellum, and genitalia of <tp:taxon-name> Chalepotaxis
                  </tp:taxon-name> lack both organs. Generally, some characters of genital anatomy,
                  such as a penial caecum, penial verge, dart apparatus, or flagellum, have been
                  hypothesized to evolve repeatedly during the evolution of land snails, and have
                  been noticed in many groups of terrestrial pulmonate snails ( Solem 1966 ;
                  Hausdorf 1998 ; Hyman &amp; Ponder 2010 ; Hirano et al. 2014 ; Köhler &amp;
                  Criscione 2015 ; Köhler et al. 2020 ; Sutcharit et al. 2020a ). However, the
                  classification of these three genera based on the presence or absence of the dart
                  apparatus and flagellum is consistent with the molecular phylogeny ( Sutcharit et
                  al. 2020a ). </p>
            <p> From the East of Tenasserim Range to northeastern Thailand , three <tp:taxon-name>
                        Aenigmatoconcha species </tp:taxon-name> occurred in a few limestone karsts,
                  while only <tp:taxon-name> A. mitis </tp:taxon-name> occurs in many limestone
                  karsts from central to western Thailand ( Fig. 1 ). <tp:taxon-name>
                        Aenigmatoconcha clivicola </tp:taxon-name> is confined to Loei Province ,
                  northeastern Thailand , while <tp:taxon-name> A. eunetis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  to Uthai Thani Province , central Thailand , and <tp:taxon-name> A. sumonthai
                  </tp:taxon-name> to Chumphon Province , southern Thailand . The isolation explains
                  the degree of endemism and the very high genetic divergence among sister lineages
                  (9.7% to 12.0%) within <tp:taxon-name> Aenigmatoconcha </tp:taxon-name> .
                  Regarding the West of Tenasserim Range, <tp:taxon-name> Sophina </tp:taxon-name>
                  also reveals a high degree of endemism and localization with a pattern of one
                  outcrop for one lineage in the Salween Basin, Southern Myanmar . These phenomena
                  can be generally observed in karst-restricted animals because a very large number
                  of ecological niches in karst ecosystems promote their evolutionary
                  diversification and evolution of remarkably different lifestyles ( Clements et al.
                  2006 ; Foon et al. 2017 ; Grismer et al. 2020 ; Sutcharit et al. 2020a ).
                  Therefore, our discovery enhances the understanding of karst biodiversity and
                  supplements the information on terrestrial snails in Thailand available for
                  efforts to establish well-planned and knowledge-based conservation procedures for
                  Thai limestone protection in the future. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
