<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2017: 182–184
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
</tp:taxon-name>
– Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan 2018: 171.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha clivicola
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
, by original designation.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>Shell dextral with 5–5½ convex whorls, strongly depressed to globosely depressed, medium-sized, thin to slightly solid, translucent, and pale milky to whitish-horny in colour. Shell surface smooth, glossy, and varix usually present. Body whorl well-rounded to slightly-shouldered. Suture shallow. Aperture slightly to very crescentic in shape with simple lip. Umbilicus open and deep.</p>
      <p>
Table 3.
Average genetic divergences among 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sophina
Benson, 1859
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chalepotaxis
Ancey, 1887
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarika
Godwin-Austen, 1907
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Ariophantidae Godwin-Austen, 1883</tp:taxon-name>
) and among species within each of these genera from the mitochondrial COI gene fragment sequences estimated by uncorrected 
p
-distances.
</p>
      <p>
Genera
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Chalepotaxis
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sophina
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sarika
</tp:taxon-name>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
</tp:taxon-name>
0.087
–
–
–
<tp:taxon-name>
Chalepotaxis
</tp:taxon-name>
0.130
–
–
–
<tp:taxon-name>
Sophina
</tp:taxon-name>
0.125
0.141
0.095
–
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarika
</tp:taxon-name>
0.119
0.140
0.123
0.008
</p>
      <p>
Animal with reticulated skinand whitish, yellowish, pale fleshy grey to dark brown body with tiny whitish dots irregularly scattered over entire body. Mantle lobes well-developed (two shell lobes and three dorsal lobes; see 
Figs 3
, 
5A
). Shell lobes can cover most, if not all of the shell and are retracted when disturbed. Left and right shell lobes very thin, translucent, ovate to triangular in shape; right shell lobe (rsl) smaller than left shell lobe (lsl). Dorsal lobes enlarged, crescent-shaped, covering body, and smaller than shell lobes. Anterior left dorsal lobe (ant-ldl) and posterior left dorsal lobe (post-ldl) smaller than right dorsal lobe (rdl). Sole tripartite, lateral foot margin, caudal fossa, and caudal horn present.
</p>
      <p>Genitalia with moderately long to very long penis, thick penial sheath, short to long epiphallus, small flagellum, and short vagina. Gametolytic organ with short gametolytic duct and bulbous gametolytic sac. Oviduct with large lobules; prostate gland running alongside oviduct.</p>
      <p>Radular teeth arranged in anteriorly V-shaped or wide-angle U-shaped rows; central tooth symmetrical monocuspid and spatulate or oblong in shape; lateral and marginal teeth undifferentiated, asymmetrical monocuspid and spatulate or oblong in shape, and outermost teeth gradually reduced in size.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 3.
Schematic drawing of living species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
, emphasizing the relative size, position and arrangement of mantle lobes (two shell lobes and three dorsal lobes).
</p>
   <p>
Table 4.
Average inter- and intra-specific 
p
-distances of the mitochondrial COI gene fragment sequences on species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   <p>
Aenigmatoconcha
spp.

<tp:taxon-name>
A
</tp:taxon-name>
. clivicola

<tp:taxon-name>A. mitis</tp:taxon-name>
      <tp:taxon-name>
A. sumonthai
</tp:taxon-name>
      <tp:taxon-name>
A. eunetis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
A. clivicola
</tp:taxon-name>
0.002
–
–
–
<tp:taxon-name>
A. mitis
</tp:taxon-name>
0.112
0.042
–
–
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sumonthai
</tp:taxon-name>
0.120
0.102
0.034
–
<tp:taxon-name>
A. eunetis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
0.106
0.099
0.097
0.027
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibit allopatric distributions and are restricted to limestone karsts in 
Thailand
(
Fig. 1
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
