<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Beltrana reticulata Gonçalves &amp; Domahovski &amp; Mejdalani &amp; Takiya 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4770548</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03DF879C0B52EC56FDEA5977910AFAF1</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera from South America and some taxonomic changes in Gyponini (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadellidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1363</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Beltrana reticulata
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
2F33353D-4741-476E-B6A8-FA2F74B33A35
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1
, 
6A–B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Pygofer (
Fig. 1F
) with apex distinctly truncated, ventral margin expanded posteroventrally, forming subquadrate lobe; in dorsal view (
Fig. 1G
), with small preapical inner lobe. Subgenital plate (
Fig. 1F, H
) with small sclerotized dorsal tooth near apex. Style (
Fig. 1I–J
) with knob-shaped apex bearing numerous denticles. Aedeagus (
Fig. 1K–L
) with pair of short and acute apical processes.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet alludes to the reticulated venation of forewing (
Fig. 1D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
FRENCH GUIANA
• 
♂
; 
French Guiana
, 
Kaw Mountain Reserve
, 

0.5 km
Rt. Rd. de Kaw

, the hole; 

1 Feb. 2008

; 
H. Romack
leg.; DNA voucher Entomologia, 
DZRJ ENT 2812
; 
USNM
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Beltrana reticulata
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (USNM). 
A
. Head and thorax, dorsal view. 
B
. Head, ventral view. 
C
. Head and thorax, lateral view. 
D
. Forewing. 
E
. Sternite VIII. ventral view. 
F
. Pygofer, anal tube, valve, and subgenital plate, lateral view. 
G
. Pygofer lobe and anal tube, dorsal view (arrow indicates the inner lobe). 
H
. Subgenital plate, ventral view (outer margin at top of figure). 
I
. Style and connective, dorsal view. 
J
. Style, lateral view. 
K
. Aedeagus, lateral view. 
L
. Aedeagus, posterior view. Scale bars: A–C=1.0 mm; D =2.0 mm; E–L=0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
FRENCH GUIANA
• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; DZRJ-AUCH #249; 
DZRJ
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Total length: male 
12.3–12.5 mm
(n =2).
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Yellow (
Fig. 6A–B
). Crown (
Fig. 1A
) mostly orange, anterior and posterior margins yellow; ocelli yellow. Pronotum (
Fig. 1A
) with anterior three-fourths yellow and posterior fourth dark yellow. Forewing (
Fig. 1D
) yellow, translucent, with dark yellow venation. Legs (
Fig. 6B
) yellow.
</p>
      <p>HEAD AND THORAX. External morphological characters as in generic description.</p>
      <p>
MALE TERMINALIA. Sternite VIII (
Fig. 1E
) subrectangular, about 1.5 times as wide as long; lateral margins slightly rounded; posterior margin rectilinear. Pygofer in lateral view (
Fig. 1F
) trapezoidal, length approximately twice maximum height; apex distinctly truncated; macrosetae distributed only near apex, presence of few short and robust setae near apex; ventral margin expanded posteroventrally, forming subquadrate lobe; in dorsal view (
Fig. 1G
), with small preapical inner lobe. Subgenital plate in lateral view (
Fig. 1F
) not produced posteriorly as far as pygofer apex; in ventral view (
Fig. 1H
), subtriangular, basal half of external margin expanded laterally, bearing short setae on apical half; apical half narrowing progressively towards apex; internal margin sinuous; dorsal surface with small, sclerotized tooth near apex; apex rounded. Connective (
Fig. 1I
) approximately three-fifths of length of style; arms broad. Style (
Fig. 1I
), in dorsal view, with apodeme very short, spatulate, and strongly flattened laterally; apophysis elongated, flattened laterally; dorsal margin expanded laterally, forming preapical lamella; in lateral view (
Fig. 1J
), outer lobe indistinct; apex sclerotized, knob-shaped, with numerous small lateral and ventral denticles. Aedeagus (
Fig. 1K–L
) with preatrium reduced; dorsal apodeme developed dorsally, not expanded laterally; shaft tubular and very elongated, curved anteriorly; apex with pair of short and acute processes directed dorsally.
</p>
      <p>FEMALE TERMINALIA. Female unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
