<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Fulana Gonçalves &amp; Domahovski &amp; Mejdalani &amp; Takiya 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773843</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8261E54C62F3F1D035251081327A4E2D</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera from South America and some taxonomic changes in Gyponini (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadellidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1363</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fulana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D3D2E937-9B40-42BB-AAC4-F821B4D22CB5
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2–3
, 
6C–F
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Fulana brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, by present designation and monotypy.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Medium-sized leafhoppers (
Fig. 6C–F
). Head in dorsal view (
Fig. 2A
) short, median length of crown about 2.5 times smaller than interocular width; crown transversely striated; ocellus large, closer to anterior margin of crown; in lateral view (
Fig. 2C
), with crown-face transition distinct and narrow, bicarinate. Pronotum (
Fig. 2A
) with punctures. Forewing (
Fig. 2D
) covered by numerous small brown spots, appendix narrow. Male pygofer (
Fig. 2F–G
) with inner basiventral process; lateral lobe partly separated from base by flexible membranous line. Subgenital plate (
Fig. 2H
) with ventral surface covered by long filiform setae. Connective (
Fig. 2I
) longitudinally linear. Aedeagus (
Fig. 2K–L
) simple, without apodemal processes. Second valvula of ovipositor (
Fig. 3G–H
) with few teeth restricted to apical fourth.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The generic name is feminine. 
<tp:taxon-name>Fulana</tp:taxon-name>
, together with 
<tp:taxon-name>Beltrana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Sicrana</tp:taxon-name>
, forms a very popular expression in 
Brazil
(“Fulana, Sicrana e 
<tp:taxon-name>Beltrana</tp:taxon-name>
”), which refers to unspecified people or people whose actual names should not be mentioned.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
HEAD AND THORAX. Head in dorsal view (
Fig. 2A
) short; median length of crown about 2.5 times smaller than interocular width; crown with anterior margin slightly sinuous; surface adjacent to ocelli slightly concave between ocellus and eye; texture transversely striated; transocular width of head six-sevenths of humeral width of pronotum; ocellus large, close to anterior margin of crown and slightly closer to eye than to median line; coronal suture distinct, extending to near anterior margin of crown. Head in ventral view (
Figs 2B
, 
3A
) with face wider than high; frontogenal suture distant from eye margin by basal width of clypeus and surpassing antennal ledge, extending to anterior margin of crown; oriented obliquely downward in relation to frons; frons approximately as wide as long, lateral margins strongly convergent ventrally; epistomal suture distinct; clypeus approximately 1.2 times as long as maximum width, lateral margins divergent apically, apex slightly emarginated; maxillary plate produced ventrally as far as clypeus apex; gena with ventrolateral margin straight on mid-length and slightly excavated below eye margin. Head in lateral view (
Fig. 2C
) with crown-face transition distinct and narrow, bicarinate; frons and clypeus flattened. Pronotum (
Fig. 2A
) with conspicuous transverse striae and punctures on disc and posterior half; lateral margins straight, convergent anterad, slightly shorter than eye length; posterior margin straight; in lateral view (
Fig. 2C
), moderately declivous; head and pronotum in continuous slope. Mesonotum (
Fig. 2A
) as long as wide; scutellum (
Fig. 2C
) slightly swollen. Forewing (
Fig. 2D
) translucent, covered by numerous small brown spots; long and narrow, approximately 3.3 times as long as wide; venation distinct; appendix very narrow and bordering first to second apical cells. Profemur with AD, AM, and PD rows reduced and poorly defined, with exception of apical setae AD1, AM1, and PD 
1
, respectively; AV and PV rows formed by 2–3 setae; IC row formed by slightly arched comb of fine setae, beginning at distal half of femur and extending to AM 
1
. Protibia in cross-section semi-circular; AV row formed by long setae, slightly longer and thicker towards apex; AD row without differentiated setae; PD row with 7–8 setae; PV row with 6–7 setae. Metafemur with setal formula 2:2:1. Metatibia PD, AD, and AV rows with 26–31, 13–14, and 16–19 macrosetae, respectively; AD row with 1– 
4 intercalary
setae between macrosetae; PV row with setae of apical half formed by sequence of a thicker and 2–4 thinner setae. Metatarsomere I with two rows of setae, inner row consisting of larger and more robust setae than those of outer row; apex with 6 platellae; metatarsomere II apex with 2–3 platellae.
</p>
      <p>
MALE TERMINALIA. Sternite VIII (
Fig. 2E
) long, fully hiding subgenital plates. Pygofer (
Fig. 2F–G
) with inner basiventral process adjacent to ventral margin; lobe partly separated from base by flexible membranous cleft. Subgenital plate (
Fig. 2H
) with ventral surface covered by long filiform setae. Connective (
Fig. 2I
) longitudinally linear. Aedeagus (
Fig. 2K–L
) simple, without apodemal processes.
</p>
      <p>
FEMALE TERMINALIA. Second valvula of ovipositor (
Fig. 3G
) elongated, slightly higher along apical fourth; apical portion (
Fig. 3H
) with dorsal margin bearing minute and uniform denticles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
(
Bahia
, 
Minas Gerais
, 
Paraná
, 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
Santa Catarina
, and 
São Paulo
states).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
An unpublished study based on 182 morphological characters combined with sequence data (28S and 16S rDNA and cytochrome oxidase subunit I) recovered 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fulana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
as the sister group to all other gyponines except 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chilenana
DeLong &amp; Freytag, 1967
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Gonçalves 2016
). In fact, the genera 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fulana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chilenana
</tp:taxon-name>
share plesiomorphic characteristics with other tribes of 
<tp:taxon-name>Iassinae</tp:taxon-name>
, which are absent in other 
<tp:taxon-name>Gyponini</tp:taxon-name>
genera: (1) male pygofer with lateral lobe partly separated from base by flexible membranous cleft; and (2) presence of basiventral inner process on the male pygofer.
</p>
      <p>
The new genus resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alapona
DeLong, 1980
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ponana
Ball, 1920
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dumorpha
DeLong &amp; Freytag, 1975
</tp:taxon-name>
because of its slightly anteriorly produced and transversely striated crown; ocellus closest to the anterior margin of the crown; forewing with dark spots; and metatibia with intercalary setae between macrosetae of the AD row. However, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fulana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alapona
</tp:taxon-name>
by the lack of flaps in the aedeagus (
Fig. 2K–L
), from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ponana
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Alapona
</tp:taxon-name>
by its thinner crown-face transition (
Fig. 2C
), and from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ponana
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dumorpha
</tp:taxon-name>
by its aedeagus without apodemal processes (
Fig. 2K
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
