<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Beltrana Gonçalves &amp; Domahovski &amp;
            Mejdalani &amp; Takiya 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4770542</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03DF879C0B53EC50FD225E67900BFA8C</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera from South America and some taxonomic changes in Gyponini
            (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadellidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1363</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Beltrana </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 4C0DFFC6-7F48-457C-97C6-361C182A69DC </p>
      <p> Figs 1 , 6A–B </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Beltrana reticulata </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. , by present
         designation and monotypy. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> Medium-sized leafhoppers ( Fig. 6A–B ). Head in dorsal view ( Fig. 1A ) moderately
         produced anteriorly, median length of crown slightly less than interocular width; in
         lateral view ( Fig. 1C ), with crown-face transition with anterior margin foliaceous and
         bicarinate. Forewing ( Fig. 1D ) with venation densely reticulated, appendix very narrow.
         Male pygofer ( Fig. 1F ) without membranous apical digitiform process. Subgenital plate (
         Fig. 1F, H ) fully sclerotized. Aedeagus ( Fig. 1K–L ) simple, without apodemal processes.
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> The generic name is feminine. <tp:taxon-name>Beltrana</tp:taxon-name> , together with
            <tp:taxon-name>Fulana</tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>Sicrana</tp:taxon-name> , forms
         a very popular expression in Brazil (“Fulana, Sicrana e
            <tp:taxon-name>Beltrana</tp:taxon-name> ”), which refers to unspecified people or people
         whose actual names should not be mentioned. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> HEAD AND THORAX. Head in dorsal view ( Fig. 1A ) moderately produced anteriorly, median
         length of crown slightly less than interocular width; transocular width about six-sevenths
         humeral width of pronotum; crown with anterior margin broadly rounded, surface mostly flat,
         slightly concave medially, with subtle oblique striae between ocelli and adjacent to
         anterior margin; ocellus medium-sized, equidistant between median line and eye margin,
         closer to posterior than anterior margin of crown; coronal suture distinct only on basal
         portion of crown. Head in ventral view ( Fig. 1B ) with face slightly higher than wide;
         frontogenal suture distant from eye margin by slightly less than maximum width of clypeus
         and extending to anterior margin of crown; antennal ledge carinated and adjacent to
         anterior margin of crown, obliquely ascending and not extending over frons; frons
         approximately 1.7 times as long as wide; epistomal suture indistinct; clypeus approximately
         1.3 times as long as maximum width, lateral margins parallel, apex slightly emarginated;
         maxillary plate produced ventrally, not reaching clypeus apex; gena excavated just below
         eye, ventrolateral margin slightly excavated. Head in lateral view ( Fig. 1C ) with
         crown-face transition distinct and foliaceous, with two carinae; frons concave below
         anterior margin of crown. Pronotum ( Fig. 1A ) with transverse striae on disc and posterior
         half; lateral margins straight, convergent anterad, and approximately as long as eye
         length; posterior margin excavated; in lateral view ( Fig. 1C ), moderately declivous,
         continuous with head declivity. Mesonotum ( Fig. 1A ) longer than wide; scutellum ( Fig. 1C
         ) flat. Forewing ( Fig. 1D ) hyaline, long, and narrow, approximately 3.2 times as long as
         maximum width; venation distinct and densely reticulated; appendix very narrow. Profemur
         with AD, AM, and PD rows reduced and poorly defined, with exception of apical setae AD 1 ,
         AM 1 , and PD 1 , respectively; AV and PV rows formed by 4–5 setae; IC row formed by
         slightly arched comb of fine setae, beginning at distal third of femur and extending to AM
         1 . Protibia, in cross-section, semi-circular; AV row formed by long setae, slightly longer
         and thicker towards apex; AD and PD rows without differentiated setae; PV row with 5 setae.
         Metafemur with setal formula 2:2:1. Metatibial AD row without intercalary setae between
         macrosetae; PD, AD, and AV rows with 26–28, 13–14, and 19–20 macrosetae, respectively.
         Metatarsomere I with outer setal row indistinct, apex with 5 platellae. Metatarsomere II
         apex with 4 platellae. </p>
      <p> MALE TERMINALIA. Pygofer ( Fig. 1F ) without membranous apical digitiform process.
         Subgenital plate ( Fig. 1F, H ) fully sclerotized. Connective ( Fig. 1I ) T-shaped.
         Aedeagus ( Fig. 1K–L ) simple, without apodemal processes. </p>
      <p>FEMALE TERMINALIA. Female unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> French Guiana . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> An unpublished phylogenetic hypothesis based on 182 morphological characters combined with
         sequence data (28S and 16S rDNA and cytochrome oxidase subunit I) recovered <tp:taxon-name>
            Beltrana </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. as the sister group of the clade <tp:taxon-name>
            Reticana DeLong &amp; Freytag, 1964 </tp:taxon-name> + <tp:taxon-name> Chloronana DeLong
            &amp; Freytag, 1964 </tp:taxon-name> ( Gonçalves 2016 ). <tp:taxon-name> Beltrana
         </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. shares the following morphological characteristics with
            <tp:taxon-name> Reticana </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Chloronana
         </tp:taxon-name> : (1) green coloration in life, yellow when preserved; (2) crown
         moderately produced anteriorly; (3) crown-face transition distinct and foliaceous; (4)
         forewing with venation reticulated; (5) metatibia without intercalary setae between
         macrosetae in AD row; (6) style short and with apical denticles; and (7) aedeagus with
         shaft long, thin, and with apical processes. However, <tp:taxon-name> Beltrana
         </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. can easily be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name> Reticana
         </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Chloronana </tp:taxon-name> by its more robust body (
         Fig. 6A ); forewing more densely reticulated ( Fig. 1D ); male pygofer without membranous
         apical digitiform process ( Fig. 1F ); and subgenital plate fully sclerotized ( Fig. 1F, H
         ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
