<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sicrana plana Gonçalves &amp; Domahovski &amp; Mejdalani &amp; Takiya 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773849</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/442BE7C7475068F5ED616E7A5D576202</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera from South America and some taxonomic changes in Gyponini (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadellidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1363</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana plana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
7A4F2853-38B6-41C6-8EFD-DA2DDE7FB3CA
</p>
      <p>
Figs 4–5
, 
6G–J
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Male pygofer (
Fig. 4F
) with dorsal margin strongly excavated; macrosetae located on apical half, forming longitudinal row. Subgenital plate (
Fig. 4F–G
) ligulate, with tuft of filiform setae near apex on dorsal surface. Style (
Fig. 4H–I
) with apex acute, more sclerotized and curved outwards. Aedeagus (
Fig. 4J–K
) with dorsal apodeme with pair of long, claviform processes; shaft tubular with pair of long apical processes directed anteroventrally. Female sternite VII (
Fig. 5B–C
) with posterior margin with broad median lobe, rounded and emarginated medially.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name refers to its flattened body (
Fig. 6H, J
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
ECUADOR
• 
♂
; 
Ecuador
, 
Orellana
, Transect Ent. 

1 km
S of Onkonegare

, 
Reserva Etnica Waorani
, 
Onkonegare Camp
; 
00°39′10″ S
, 
76°26′00″ W
; alt. 

220 m

; fogging terre [sic! terra] firme forest; 

2 Jul. 1995

; 

T.L. Erwin 
et al
.

leg.; #1062; DNA voucher Entomologia, 
DZRJ ENT 2808
; 
EPNC
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
ECUADOR
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype but 

9 Feb. 1995

; #986; 
EPNC
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♂
; Brasil, 
Rondônia
, 
Monte Negro
, 
Reserva Legal
, 
Loteamento
; 
10°16′35″ S
, 
63°20′40″ W
; alt. 

187 m

; 
light trap
; 

3–15 Dec. 2011

; 
Amorim, Ament and Riccandi
[sic! Riccardi] leg.; 
DZUP-083603
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Total length: male 13.0– 
13.7 mm
(n =2); female 
16.8 mm
(n =1). COLORATION. Male yellow (
Fig. 6G–J
) without markings. Female with face (
Fig. 5A
) with dark band adjacent to margin of crown.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana plana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (EPNC). 
A
. Head and thorax, dorsal view. 
B
. Head, ventral view. 
C
. Head and thorax, lateral view. 
D
. Forewing. 
E
. Sternite VIII, ventral view. 
F
. Pygofer, valve, and subgenital plate, lateral view. 
G
. Subgenital plate, ventral view (outer margin at top of figure). 
H
. Style and connective, dorsal view. 
I
. Style, lateral view. 
J
. Aedeagus, lateral view. 
K
. Aedeagus, posterior view. Scale bars: A–C=1.0 mm; D =2.0 mm; E–K =0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana plana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, paratype, ♀ (EPNC). 
A
. Head, ventral view. 
B
. Posterior portion of abdomen, ventral view. 
C
. Sternite VII, ventral view. 
D
. Pygofer, second valvifer, gonoplac, and anal tube, lateral view. 
E
. First valvifer and first valvula of ovipositor, lateral view. 
F
. Apex of first valvula, lateral view. 
G
. Second valvula of ovipositor, lateral view. 
H
. Apex of second valvula, lateral view. Scale bars: A–B =1.0 mm; C–E, G =0.5 mm; F, H =0.3 mm.
</p>
      <p>HEAD AND THORAX. External morphological characters as in generic description.</p>
      <p>
MALE TERMINALIA. Sternite VIII (
Fig. 4E
) subrectangular, about 1.3 times as wide as long; lateral margins parallel, posterior margin slightly rounded. Valve subrectangular, 2.3 times as wide as long; posterior margin convex. Pygofer in lateral view (
Fig. 4F
) moderately produced posteriorly, about 1.7 times as long as maximum height, without processes; dorsal margin strongly excavated; less than 10 macrosetae forming a longitudinal row, near dorsal margin of apical half; apex tapered and rounded. Subgenital plate, in lateral view (
Fig. 4F
), produced posteriorly as far as pygofer apex; in ventral view (
Fig. 4G
), ligulate, about 3.6 times as long as wide; ventral surface covered by small setae; dorsal surface with tuft of moderately long filiform setae near apex; lateral margins divergent towards apex; apex abruptly tapered and rounded. Connective (
Fig. 4H
) with anterior portion membranous, posterior portion sclerotized; approximately one-seventh length of style; arms narrow, strongly divergent. Style in dorsal view (
Fig. 4H
) with outer lobe poorly developed; in lateral view (
Fig. 4I
), with margins parallel; ventral margin smooth; apex acute, more sclerotized and curved outwards. Aedeagus (
Fig. 4J–K
) with preatrium absent; atrium expanded posteriorly; dorsal apodeme well developed; apodemal processes claviform, extending to apex of shaft, subapical region of each process rounded and with preapical excavation dorsally; shaft elongated and tubular, curved dorsally; apex with pair of processes parallel to shaft, extending anteroventrally, half-length of shaft, each process with inner margin crenulate and apex acute.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
Habitus of type specimens, dorsal and lateral view, respectively. 
A–B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Beltrana reticulata
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (USNM). – 
C–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fulana brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (DZRJ). – 
E–F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fulana brasiliensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, paratype ♀ (DZRJ-AUCh #251). 
G–H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana plana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (EPNC). – 
I–J
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana plana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, paratype, ♀ (EPNC). Scale bars: 2.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
FEMALE TERMINALIA. Sternite VII (
Fig. 5B–C
) 2.3 times as wide as long; posterolateral angles developed and subacute; posterior margin with broad median lobe, rounded and emarginated medially. Internal sternite VIII membranous. Pygofer (
Fig. 5D
) elongate, about 1.5 times as long as maximum height; apex rounded; few macrosetae distributed near apex and ventral margin. First valvifer (
Fig. 5E
) subtriangular. First valvula of ovipositor (
Fig. 5E
) slightly curved dorsally; about seven times as long as high; slightly higher on median third; dorsal sculptured area beginning at basal third; apex (
Fig. 5F
) with dorsal and ventral sculptured areas strigate; blade apex acute. Second valvifer (
Fig. 5D
) higher than long. Second valvula of ovipositor (
Fig. 5G
) slightly higher medially; approximately 7.5 times as long as maximum height; median third with dorsal triangular protuberance; apical portion (
Fig. 5H
) with large preapical tooth; blade apex tapered and acute. Gonoplac (
Fig. 5D
) 5.4 times as long as high; dorsoapical margin long and straight; apex rounded.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
