<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sicrana Gonçalves &amp; Domahovski &amp; Mejdalani &amp; Takiya 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773847</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/83FA558858A1FE81428FFF94E8CDF913</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera from South America and some taxonomic changes in Gyponini (Insecta: Hemiptera: Cicadellidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1363</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
5D4E6996-37CB-49B3-AF47-0F247BBFF9AA
</p>
      <p>
Figs 4–5
, 
6G–J
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana plana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, by present designation and monotypy.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Large-sized, flattened leafhoppers (
Fig. 6G–J
). Head in dorsal view (
Fig. 4A
) with rugose surface, strongly produced anteriorly, anterior margin parabolic; ocellus closer to median line than to adjacent eye and closer to posterior than to anterior margin of crown; in lateral view (
Fig. 4C
), with crown- face transition distinct and strongly foliaceous, margined by two carinae. Face (
Figs 4B
, 
5A
) with frons narrow; maxillary plate not reaching clypeus apex. Pronotum (
Fig. 4A–C
) with lateral margins foliaceous, expanded laterally. Forewing (
Fig. 4D
) with appendix absent. Aedeagus (
Fig. 4J–K
) with pair of apodemal processes. Second valvula of ovipositor with apical portion (
Fig. 5G–H
) with large preapical tooth.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The generic name is feminine. 
<tp:taxon-name>Sicrana</tp:taxon-name>
, together with 
<tp:taxon-name>Beltrana</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Fulana</tp:taxon-name>
, forms a very popular expression in 
Brazil
(“Fulana, Sicrana e Beltrana’), which refers to unspecified people or people whose actual names should not be mentioned.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
HEAD AND THORAX. Head in dorsal view (
Fig. 4A
) moderately produced anteriorly, median length of crown almost as long as interocular width; transocular width three-fourths of humeral width of pronotum; crown with anterior margin parabolic; surface flat; texture rugose; ocellus medium-sized, closer to median line than to adjacent eye and closer to posterior than to anterior margin of crown; coronal suture distinct along basal two-thirds of crown. Head in lateral view (
Fig. 4C
) with crown-face transition distinct and strongly foliaceous, with two very close carinae; frons tumid. Head in ventral view (
Figs 4B
, 
5A
) approximately as wide as high; frontogenal suture strongly sinuous, reaching antennal ledge and distant from eye margin by twice maximum width of clypeus; antennal ledge carinated, strongly arched, adjacent to anterior margin of crown and not extending over frons; frons narrow, approximately two times longer than wide; epistomal suture indistinct; clypeus approximately 1.4 times as long as maximum width, lateral margins parallel, apex slightly emarginated; maxillary plate very narrow, not reaching clypeus apex; gena with ventrolateral margin slightly excavated, texture with several oblique striations parallel to ventrolateral margin. Pronotum (
Fig. 4A
) rugose, except disc and posterior third with transverse parallel striae; anterior margin almost straight; lateral margins convergent anterad, about two times as long as eye length, rounded, carinated and foliaceous, expanded laterally; posterior margin slightly excavated; in lateral view (
Fig. 4C
), pronotal surface declivous; head and pronotum in continuous slope. Mesonotum (
Fig. 4A
) as long as wide; scutellum (
Fig. 4C
) flat. Forewing (
Fig. 4D
) long and narrow, approximately 3.2 times as long as wide; venation with some additional crossveins located mainly apically; appendix absent; apex subacute. Profemur with AD, AM, and PD rows reduced and poorly defined, with exception of apical setae AD1, AM1, and PD1, respectively; AV and PV rows formed by 5–6 very short and thin setae; IC row formed by slightly arched comb of fine setae, beginning at distal half of femur and extending to AM 
1
. Protibia in cross-section semi-circular; AV row formed by short setae, slightly longer and thicker towards apex, setae of apical portion shorter than diameter of tibia; AD row without differentiated setae; PD row with three small setae and undifferentiated intercalary setae; PV row with 4–5 small setae on apical half and undifferentiated intercalary setae. Metafemur with setal formula 2:2:1. Metatibia PD, AD, and AV rows with 24–25, 12, and 16 macrosetae, respectively; metatibia AD row without intercalary setae between macrosetae. Metatarsomere I with two rows of cucullate setae, inner row formed by 5–7 setae, outer row reduced, with 0–2 median setae, apex with 5 platellae. Metatarsomere II apex with 2–3 apical platellae.
</p>
      <p>
MALE TERMINALIA. Connective (
Fig. 4H
) transversely linear. Aedeagus (
Fig. 4J–K
) with pair of apodemal processes.
</p>
      <p>
FEMALE TERMINALIA. Second valvula of ovipositor (
Fig. 5G
) slightly higher preapically; apical portion (
Fig. 5H
) with large preapical tooth.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
(
Rondônia State
) and 
Ecuador
(
Orellana Province
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
shares similar characteristics of external morphology and male terminalia with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Clinonana
Osborn, 1938
</tp:taxon-name>
, for instance: (1) large total length (&gt; 
13 mm
); (2) head distinctly narrower than pronotum; (3) crown with rugose texture; (4) transition crown-face distinct and foliaceous; (5) ocellus closer to median line than to eye and closer to posterior than to anterior margin of crown; (6) pronotum with lateral margins foliaceous, expanded laterally; (7) forewing with subacute apex; and (8) aedeagus with apodemal processes and shaft with apical processes. However, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sicrana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
can easily be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Clinonana
</tp:taxon-name>
by the following characteristics: (1) body flattened dorsoventrally (
Fig. 6H, J
); (2) crown conspicuously more produced anteriorly (
Fig. 4A
); (3) frontogenal suture strongly sinuous and not reaching the anterior margin of the crown (
Figs 4B
, 
5A
); (4) face as high as wide (
Figs 4B
, 
5A
); (5) maxillary plate not reaching the apex of the clypeus (
Figs 4B
, 
5A
); (6) pronotum with lateral margins rounded (
Fig. 4A
); (7) forewing without appendix and maculae (
Fig. 4D
); (8) metafemur with setal formula 2:2:1; and (9) male pygofer without processes (
Fig. 4F
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
