<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Odontoscelio spinosus Veenakumari &amp; Mohanraj 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4615112</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E0893A1628D4106B35FEE4FEDB7F1A</uri>
         <article-title>Review of Odontoscelio Kieffer, 1905 (Platygastroidea, Scelionidae) with the description of two new species from India</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1267</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio spinosus
Veenakumari
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank:org:act: 
909052D7-7052-45E0-85E2-C970C0CD4EF8
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3–4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>This species is very distinct because of the presence of semicircular carinae on the frons and 11 spines on mesosoma.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is named ‘spinosus’ indicative of the 11 spines present on the mesosoma.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
INDIA
• 
♀
; 
Karnataka
, 
Bengaluru
, 
Attur
; 
13°05′48″ N
, 
77°33′59″ E
; alt. 

936 m

; 

8 Nov. 2012

; YPT; 
ICAR-NBAIR P3960
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
BODY LENGTH. 
4.78 mm
, n = 1.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR (
Figs 3–4
). Body predominantly black; tegula and legs brown; radicle and A2–A4 brown, A5– A6 brownish black, remaining antennomeres black; mandible dark brown.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 3
, 
4A–C, E–G
). Densely setose, 1.26 × as wide as high, 1.38 × as high as long; IOS 0.59 × head width, subequal to eye length; OOL&gt;POL&gt;LOL in ratio of 23.8: 18.5: 7.3; OOL 2.74 × OD; eye (L: W = 71.6: 30.4) setose; frons beneath anterior ocellus with discontinuous semicircular carinae except for continuous ones above interantennal process; central keel absent; interantennal process rectangular and rugose; vertex and occiput areolate with very long setae; ocelli not raised above surface of vertex; interocellar area weakly rugose with an uneven carina between posterior ocelli; occipital carina foveate; facial striae prominent; gena longitudinally carinate, interspersed with sparse areolae; A1 with dense setae; length and width of antennomeres A1–A 
12 in
ratio of 72.3: 12.5, 10.0: 8.8, 29.1: 11.6, 15.5: 11.9, 7.3:11.1, 8.3: 11.2, 8.8: 15.2, 10.5:16.4, 9.5: 10.3, 9.8: 15.7, 11.8:14.7, 9.1: 11.9, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA (
Figs 3A–B
, 
4A–D, F
). Cervical pronotal area transversely carinate; mesoscutum (L:W = 72.3: 117.2) densely setose, anteriorly areolate, posteriorly longitudinally carinate, interspersed with sparse uneven areolae; anterolateral margin of mesoscutum extending as a short spine above tegula; pronotum laterally with a wide spine, visible when viewed dorsally; lateral pronotal area transversely carinate with an areolate patch dorsally and posteriorly; netrion foveate; mesopleuron with distinct mesopleural pit; speculum with transverse carinae; mesepimeral sulcus not foveate, femoral depression ventral to mesopleural pit with transverse carinae on posterior margin extending ¾ width of mesopleuron, carinae progressively reduced in size ventrad; anterior episternum with intricate sculpture; mesopleuron ventrally with intricate sculpture interspersed with foveae, densely setose; postacetabular sulcus indicated as a furrow; metapleuron dorsally with intricate sculpture, ventrally foveate with dense setae and with a wide spine on posterior margin; scutoscutellar sulcus foveate laterally; mesoscutellum (L:W =36.0:73.0) areolate interspersed with carinae, densely setose, medial longitudinal keel distinct; metascutellum foveate with posteromedial spine, metanotal trough foveate; lateral propodeal area laterally densely setose, remainder longitudinally carinate and with a spine on anterolateral margin; posterolateral margin of lateral propodeal area curving inwards as a spine. Fore wing (L:W = 240.9: 68.3) infuscate; hind wing (L: W = 200.0:52.40) hyaline.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio spinosus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Holotype, ♀ (ICAR-NBAIR P3960). 
A
. Habitus (dorsal view). 
B
. Habitus, showing axillular spines. 
C
. Antennae. 
D
. Frons.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA (
Fig. 3A–B
). L:W = 203.2:143.0; densely setose; T1 anteromedially smooth, longitudinally costate, space between costae weakly foveate; T2 longitudinally costate with weak foveae between costae, an additional row of foveae present posteriorly followed by a posteromedial smooth patch; T3 medially smooth, sub medially unevenly foveate followed by longitudinal rows of uneven costae, space between costae foveate; T3 sublaterally and laterally smooth with setigerous punctae; remaining tergites smooth with setigerous punctae; T1 and T2 with sparse setae laterally, T3 densely setose posterosublaterally; length and width of tergites T1–T 
6 in
ratio of 43.4: 37.4, 42.1: 52.9, 72.2: 142.6, 22.7:141.2, 14.7: 87.2, 6.8: 23.1, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
