<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pacificampa wudonghuii Sendra &amp;
                        Komerički &amp; Lips &amp; Luan &amp; Selfa &amp; Jiménez-Valverde 2021, sp.
                        nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4422583</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E40878FFCBFFB8B323FE6ED2562FAE</uri>
                  <article-title>Asian cave-adapted diplurans, with the description of two new
                        genera and four new species (Arthropoda, Hexapoda,
                        Entognatha)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Pacificampa wudonghuii Sendra </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 447EE93A-F466-4C66-827A-0751A259070F </p>
            <p> Figs 51–64 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> This species is dedicated to Professor Wu Donghui, from the Northeast Institute of
                  Geography and Agroecology (NEIGAE), Chinese Academy of Sciences, Changchun ( China
                  ), for his enthusiastic contribution and support to the knowledge of Northern
                  China soil and cave biodiversity. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <tp:material-citation>
                  <p> Holotype </p>
                  <p> CHINA • ♀ ; Liaoning Province , Benxi , Huanren , Xianren Dong ; 17 May 2019 ,
                        L. Deharveng , A. Bedos and Wu Donghui leg.; labelled
                        “CHILN19-005-holotype”; NEIGA-diplura-01. </p>
            </tp:material-citation>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> CHINA • 1 ♀ , 1 juvenile , same collection data as for
                        holotype; labelled “CHILN19-005-female paratype”; MZB ( MCNB ) 2020-1160
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 juvenile ; same collection data
                        as for preceding; labelled “CHILN19- 005-juvenile paratype”; MZB ( MCNB )
                        2020-1161 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; Liaoning
                        Province , Benxi , Huanren , Pylon cave ; 17 May 2019 ; L. Deharveng , A.
                        Bedos and Wu Donghui leg.; labelled “CHILN19-007-female paratype”; MZB (
                        MCNB ) 2020-1164 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material examined </p>
            <p> CHINA • 1 ♂, same collection data as for holotype; mounted on an aluminium stage and
                  coated with palladium-gold; Coll. AS . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> BODY. Length 6.5–6.9 mm in females; 3.9 mm in one juvenile. Epicuticle smooth under
                  optical microscope but well reticulated under high magnifications as one can see
                  irregular polygonal structures of variable sizes with scattered external glands
                  either visible or covered with secretion ( Figs 51, 53 ); body with smooth
                  clothing setae. </p>
            <p> HEAD. Antennae broken in all specimens; central antennomeres with two whorls of
                  distal barbed macrosetae and uneven short setae; in addition, with single distal
                  whorl of up to 8–12 gouge sensilla of 22–29 µm long ( Fig. 51 ) and among them one
                  or two small coniform sensilla ( 5 µm long). Proximal antennomeres with typical
                  trichobothria disposition with bacilliform sensillum ( 9–10 µm long) on third
                  antennomere in ventral position, between c–d macrosetae ( Fig. 52 ). Plain frontal
                  process with one anterior macrosetae, longer than clothing setae. Three macrosetae
                  along each side of insertion line of antennomere and x setae with length ratios of
                  a / i / p / x , 42/55/42/45, respectively, in holotype ( Fig. 54 ). Large suboval
                  labial palps, each with enlarged coniform latero-external sensillum near two gard
                  setae and eight normal setae on anterior portion, up to 150 neuroglandular setae
                  in medial and posterior positions. </p>
            <p> THORAX. Thoracic macrosetae distribution: pronotum has 1+1 ma , 1+1 la , 1+1 lp
                  macrosetae; mesonotum has 1+1 ma , 1+1 la and 2+2 lp macrosetae; and metanotum has
                  1+1 ma and 1+1 lp macrosetae. Long macrosetae with long barbs in distal
                  three-fourths; marginal setae longer than clothing setae, which are barbed from
                  distal half to three-fourths. Legs elongated, metathoracic legs reach posterior
                  border of seventh abdominal segment. Mesothoracic and metathoracic femora have one
                  dorsal macroseta each, barbed along distal three-fourths ( Fig. 55 ), absent in
                  prothoracic femora. Calcars with two or three long barbs in middle ( Fig. 56 ).
                  Prothoracic and mesothoracic tibia with one short ventral macrosetae with one
                  apical barb and two in metathoracic tibia ( Fig. 57 ). Each tarsus with two
                  separated ventral rows of thicker and longer setae among clothing setae, and a few
                  setiform sensilla ( Fig. 58 ). Three long smooth dorsal tarsal and one ventral
                  setae. Subequal elbowed claws with smooth ventral surface ridged on dorsal side
                  that can be mistaken for lateral crests under optical microscopes, between a blunt
                  unguiculus and without lateral processes ( Figs 59–60 ). </p>
            <p> ABDOMEN. Distribution of abdominal macrosetae on tergites ( Fig. 61 shows 1+1 ma on
                  III in the paratype from Grotte du Pylone, but absent in Xianren Dong Cave types;
                  1+1 ma , 1+1 la and 2+2 lp on IV–VII; 1+1 mp and 3+3 lp on VIII and 1+1 mp and 5+5
                  lp on IX abdominal; ma and la macrosetae with barbs in distal half to one third
                  and shorter than mp and lp macrosetae, which bear long barbs along distal
                  four-fifths. Urosternite I with 7+7 macrosetae ( Fig. 62 ); urosternites II to VII
                  with 4+4 macrosetae ( Fig. 63 ); urosternite VIII with 1+1 macrosetae ( Fig. 64 );
                  urosternal macrosetae of varying lengths, with one apical to twenty distal long
                  barbs. Stylus setae smooth, apical and subapical setae shorter than ventromedial
                  seta ( Fig. 63 ). </p>
            <p> Figs 51‒54. <tp:taxon-name> Pacificampa wudonghuii Sendra </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  51 . Gouge sensilla ( gs ) of antennomeres. 52 . Sensillum of the third
                  antennomeree ( sIII ). 53 . Surface of the notum with external glands ( eg ). 54 .
                  Frontal process with anterior ( a ), intermediate ( i ) and posterior ( p )
                  macrosetae of the insertion line of antennae and x setae. </p>
            <p> SECONDARY SEX CHARACTERS. Female urosternite I with subcylindrical appendages, each
                  bearing up to 40 glandular a 1 setae in apical field. Male urosternite I with
                  thick short, and subcylindrical appendages, each with large apical field of about
                  220 glandular a 1 setae ( Fig. 62 ). </p>
            <p> Figs 55‒60. <tp:taxon-name> Pacificampa wudonghuii Sendra </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  55 . Dorsal macrosetae on the metathoracic femur. 56 . Joint between tibia and
                  tarsus with calcars. 57 . Ventral macroseta on the tibia. 58 . Lateral side of the
                  tarsus. 59 . Pretarsus. 60 . Detail of the pretarsus. </p>
            <p> Figs 61‒64. <tp:taxon-name> Pacificampa wudonghuii Sendra </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  61 . Urotergites III–VIII and IX abdominal segment, left side (holotype,
                  NEIGA-diplura-01). 62 . Male first urosternite with glandular a 1 setae. 63 .
                  Fourth urosternite, right side. 64 . Male eighth urosternite. </p>
            <p> Taxonomic affinities </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Pacificampa wudonghuii </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. shares with
                        <tp:taxon-name> P. birsteini Chevrizov, 1978 </tp:taxon-name> ,
                        <tp:taxon-name> P. caesa Chevrizov, 1978 </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> P. nipponica Sendra, 2018 </tp:taxon-name> the same
                  distribution of notal macrosetae (1+1 medial anterior, 1+1 lateral anterior, and
                  1+1 lateral posterior macrosetae on pronotum; 1+1 medial anterior, 1+1 lateral
                  anterior, and 2+2 lateral posterior macrosetae on mesonotum; and 1+1 medial
                  anterior and 1+1 lateral anterior macrosetae on metanotum). An undescribed species
                  mentioned by Ferguson (1997) from northeastern China also has this setal
                  distribution. However, <tp:taxon-name> P. wudonghuii </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  differs from other species of <tp:taxon-name> Pacificampa </tp:taxon-name> in
                  having 1+1 medial anterior, 1+1 lateral anterior, and 2+2 lateral posterior
                  macrosetae on the fourth urotergite ( Fig. 61 ), a pattern distribution that
                  begins on the fifth urotergite for the other species. In addition, the larger male
                  appendages have more abundant glandular a 1 setae in <tp:taxon-name> P .
                        wudonghuii </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ( Fig. 62 ) than in the other species
                  of <tp:taxon-name> Pacificampa </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
