<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Hubeicampa melissa Sendra &amp; Komerički &amp; Lips &amp; Luan &amp; Selfa &amp; Jiménez-Valverde 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4423308</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/7BF77F2E5477112FA32A4406D87F5D88</uri>
         <article-title>Asian cave-adapted diplurans, with the description of two new genera and four new species (Arthropoda, Hexapoda, Entognatha)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Hubeicampa melissa
Sendra &amp; Lips
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E9EEC42A-21E5-43D8-B572-F4A6FD327323
</p>
      <p>
Figs 20–48
; 
Tables 3–4
; Supp. file 3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This species is dedicated to the memory of Mélissa Lagrède, a French caver and friend of Josiane Lips. Mélissa died in an accident inside a nearby cave on the very day the 
holotype
of this new species was collected. She also collected a 
paratype
in the same cave the day before she died. Noun in apposition.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <tp:material-citation>
         <p>
Holotype
</p>
         <p>
CHINA
• 
♀
; 
Hubei
, 
Banqiao
, 

Grotte du 8 
ième
Ciel Baxian Dong

; 

8 Aug. 2009

; 
Josiane Lips
leg.; labelled “4168-holotype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1162
.
</p>
      </tp:material-citation>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
CHINA
• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; labelled “4168-paratype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-0621
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
Mélissa Lagrède
leg.; 

7 Aug. 2009

; labelled “4158-paratype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1165
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Other material examined
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 specs
; same collection data as for holotype; mounted on two separate aluminium stages and coated with palladium-gold; Coll. AS
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Sichuan
, 
Beichuan
, 
Yin Keng Dong
; 

22 Aug. 2011

; 
Josiane Lips
leg.; Coll. AS
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♀♀
; 
Hubei
, 
Banqiao
, 
Tie He Cave
; 

11 Aug. 2006

; 
Josiane Lips
leg.; Coll. AS
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Length is 
9 mm
in 
holotype
, 
10.4 mm
in female 
paratype
and 
6 mm
in male 
paratype
. Epicuticle smooth under optical microscope but reticulated at higher magnification, showing irregular polygonal structures of variable sizes (
Figs 31–33
). Body with apparently smooth clothing setae that in SEM have tiny expansions (micro–barbs) more abundant on other setae (macrosetae, marginal setae, style setae, tarsal setae and calcars) (
Figs 26–29
, 
36
, 
42–45
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. In 
holotype
, one complete and intact antennae with 49 antennomeres; antennae slightly longer than body length (
Table 3
), with medial antennomeres 3 × as long as wide. Apical antennomere 4 × as long as wide, with irregular cupuliform organ containing ramiform, net-like complex with numerous perforations, occupying 1/10 of distal portion (
Figs 20–21, 23
). Distal and central antennomeres with two whorls of micro-barbed macrosetae (
Figs 26–29
); in addition, these have single distal whorl of up to 8–10 thin long gouge sensilla of 
85–95 µm
in length (
Figs 22, 24
), among them one small coniform sensillum (
10 µm
long). Proximal antennomeres with trichobothria on antennomeres 
3–5 in
a 2, 3, 1 pattern but with long flagellum (
500–800 µm
long in 
holotype
). Third antennomere with bacilliform sensillum (
25 µm
long) in ventral position (
Fig. 25
). Coniform protrusion of frontal process with one anterior and four posterior micro–barbed macrosetae. Three macrosetae along each side of insertion line of antennomere and 
x
setae with micro-barbs; ratios of length in female 
paratype
a
/ 
i
/ 
p
/ 
x
are 49/51/51/42, respectively. Suboval labial palps large, each with bacilliform latero-external sensillum near two simple
</p>
      <p>
Figs 20‒25.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hubeicampa melissa
Sendra &amp; Lips
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
20
. Apical view of the last antennomere. 
21
. Ramiform net of the olfactory chemoreceptor in the cupuliform organ. 
22
. Distal portion of a central antennomere. 
23
. Detail of the ramiform net of the olfactory chemoreceptor. 
24
. Detail of the gouge sensillum. 
25
. Ventral side of the third antennomere with its sensillum (
sIII
).
</p>
      <p>setae, in posterior position with two guard setae and up to 24 setae on anterior portion, which are followed by up to 130 neuroglandular setae on posterior portion.</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Distribution of thoracic macrosetae (
Figs 30–33
) with pronotum with 1+1 
ma
, 1+1 
la
2 (1+2 
la
2,3 in 
paratype
), 2+2 
lp
1,3 macrosetae; mesonotum with 1+1 
ma
, 1+1 
la
and 1+1 
mp
(0+0 
mp
in 
paratype
) macrosetae, and metanotum with 1+1 
ma
, 0+1 
smp
(1+1 
smp
in 
paratype
) macrosetae. All macrosetae slightly thin and micro-barbed, with a few longer and thin distal barbs; marginal setae longer than clothing setae. Legs elongated and metathoracic legs overpass end of abdomen. Tibia longer than femur or tarsus (
Table 3
). Femora III with one short dorsal macrosetae (
0.17 mm
in 
1.88 mm
femur of paratype-4158) (femora I–II with one dorsal macrosetae, less frequently without or with one submacrosetae instead). Calcar covered with thin abundant micro-barbs all over. Tibia I–III with one short completely micro-barbed ventral macroseta (in 
holotype
, prothoracic legs of tibia with three and two macrosetae). Each tibia with two ventral rows of thick micro-barbed setae, scattered around tibia thin micro-barbed setiform sensilla. Three dorsal and one ventral tarsal subapical setae with micro-barbs (
Figs 34, 36
). Subequal elbowed claws with lateral crest; basal and ventral portions of claws covered with very small, thin, spiniform formations. Laminar lateral processes of the pretarsus completely covered with what was initially thought to be dense pubescence, but under SEM high magnifications turned out to be thick micro-barbs (
Figs 34, 36–39
).
</p>
      <p>
Figs 26‒29.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hubeicampa melissa
Sendra &amp; Lips
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
26
. Detail of the setae and macrosetae on antennomeres. 
27
. Distal portion of an antenna macroseta. 
28
. Basal portion of an antenna macroseta. 
29
. Central portion of an antenna macroseta.
</p>
      <p>
Table 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hubeicampa melissa
Sendra &amp; Lips
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, length of the body, antennae and metathoracic leg, including their segments, and cerci (units in mm) as well as number of antennomeres.
</p>
      <p>
Metathoracic leg
Specimen
Body length
Antennae length
Antenno- meres
coxa
trochanter
femur
tibia
tarsus
Total leg
Holotype-4168
9.0
11.2
49
0.34
0.25
1.58
1.98
1.64
5.79
(MZB (MCNB)
2020-1162)
Paratype-4158
10.8
–
–
0.50
0.46
1.88
2.51
1.95
7.30
(MZB (MCNB)
2020-1165)
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Distribution of abdominal macrosetae on tergites (
Fig. 40
): 1+1 
post
1 on V tergite, (1 
post
1 + 2 
post
1,5 on 
paratype
); 3+3 
post
2,4,5 on VI tergite, 3+3 
post
1,4,5 (3+2 
post
4,5 in 
holotype
) on VII tergite, 4 
post
1,3,4,5 + 5 
post
1–5 (5+5 (
post
1–5 in
paratype
) on VIII tergite; and 6+6 
post
on IX abdominal segment. Short micro-barbed abdominal macrosetae with few distal barbs on urotergites V– VII; urotergite VIII and abdominal segment with similar but longer macrosetae. Urosternite I with 12+12 macrosetae (
Fig. 41
); urosternites II to VII with 5+5 macrosetae; urosternite VIII with 1+1 macrosetae; urosternal macrosetae complete covered by micro-barbs including a few distal short barbs. Stylus with apical, subapical and ventromedial setae completely covered with both micro-barbs and one apical barb (
Figs 42–43
). Cerci 1.7 × as long as body length in two presumably regenerated cerci of 
paratype
, with six primary articles (
Table 4
). Length of cerci quickly increases from proximal to distal articles, covered with long setae, and macrosetae covered with micro-barbs; each primary article with single apical whorl of shorter and thinner setae also covered with micro-barbs (
Figs 44–45
).
</p>
      <p>
SECONDARY SEX CHARACTERS. Female urosternite I with coniform appendages, each bearing up to 12 glandular 
a
1 setae in apical field (
Fig. 41
). Male urosternite I with subcylindrical enlarged appendages with large field of glandular 
a
1 sertae; without glandular 
g
1 setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
