<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Mueggejapyx brehieri Sendra &amp; Komericki 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4423328</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3E256B2496A781BC63595760318E6F41</uri>
         <article-title>Asian cave-adapted diplurans, with the description of two new genera and four new species (Arthropoda, Hexapoda, Entognatha)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
8D581345-0B2E-4E5C-918C-DBF84F3B6978
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2
, 
65–97
; 
Tables 5–6
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is dedicated to Franck Brehier, French biospeleologist, who has dedicated himself to exploring and studying many karst areas and caves in Southeast Asia.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <tp:material-citation>
         <p>
Holotype
</p>
         <p>
MYANMAR
• 
♂
; 
Shan State
, 
Ywangan
, 
Win Twin Cave
; 
21º11′51.47″ N
, 
96º32′40.34″ E
, 

16 Nov. 2018

: 
Aung Lin
leg.; labelled “♂4-holotype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1156
.
</p>
      </tp:material-citation>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MYANMAR
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; labelled “♂3-paratype” and “♀1– paratype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-0626
, 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-0627
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; labelled “♀2-paratype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1159
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Shan State
, 
Parpent Cave
1; 

2 Dec. 2015

; 
Franck Brehier
leg; collected by hand; collector’s code BUR15-FB20; labelled “♂5-paratype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-0628
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; collector’s code MY15–20.06; labelled “♂7-paratype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1158
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Shan State
, 
Kyauk Khaung
[= 
Stone Cave
]; 

30 Nov. 2015

; 
Franck Brehier
leg.; collector’s codes: BUR15–FB17, MY15–17.03; labelled “♀6-paratype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1157
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Other material examined
</p>
      <p>
MYANMAR
• 2 specs; same collection data as for holotype; mounted on two separate aluminium stages and coated with palladium-gold; Coll. 
AS
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Elongated (
Fig. 2
), length 
23 mm
in male 
holotype
(
19–26 mm
in three 
paratype
females, 
15–23 mm
in three 
paratype
males). Greatest width at urotergite VII 
2.6 mm
. Epicuticle smooth under optical microscope, with numerous micropores at higher magnifications (
Figs 72
, 
85
). Cuticle unpigmented, except for slightly sclerotized areas on dorsal head, mandible tips, femoral and tibial condyles and segments VI–X (
Fig. 2
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Antennae with 36 antennomeres; antennae less than ½ body length; first antennomere short, followed by three longer and larger antennomeres (2 
nd
to 4 
th
antennomeres with reinforced borders) (
Figs 65–68, 70
; 
Table 5
). All antennomeres with abundant setae including sM and sm setae, which appear more abundant on ventral side of 7 
th
to 16 
th
antennomeres under light microscope; trichobothria present on antennomeres 
4–6 in
a 3/5/5 pattern, in which 
a
trichobothria in distal position; 1 or 2 placoid sensilla present on latero-interior ventral side on 17 
th
and more distal antennomeres; apical antennomere bearing 16–18 placoid sensilla distributed in three irregular whorls (
Figs 65–66
). Dorsal and ventral side of head with numerous uniformly distributed sM and sm, and several M, more obvious in young specimens (♂7- 
paratype
); on dorsal side A1–3, S2,4,6, M2,3,5, I4,5, P2 and L1–5 (
Fig. 69
); on ventral side, submentum with large 1+1 M in posterior position, admentum with 4+4 M, mentum at base of labial palps with 1+1 M; external lobes of mentum with abundant sM; internal lobes with 1+1 short M. Elongated, conical labial palps almost 3 × as long as wide compared with sM and sm in addition to one
</p>
      <p>
Figs 65‒70.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
65
. Last antennomere with placoide sensilla (
ps
). 
66
. Distal antennomeres with placoide sensilla (
ps
). 
67
. Central antennomeres. 
68
. Proximal antennomeres, ventral side. 
69
. Head, dorsal side.Abbreviations: see Material and methods. 
70
. Proximal antennomeres, dorsal side.
</p>
      <p>
Table 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggenjapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, length of the body, antennae and femur, tibia and tarsus of the metathoracic leg (all units in mm except number of antennomeres). 
*
= telescoped antennomeres.
</p>
      <p>
Specimen
Body length
Antenna length
Antennomeres
Femur
Tibia
Tarsus
Cerci
♂7-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-1158)
15
4.1
36
1.1
1.0
0.9
1.4
♂3-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-0626)
16.5
5.5
36
1.6
1.6
1.3
2.0
♀6-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-1157)
19
7.2
36
1.8
1.8
1.6
2.1
♀2-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-1159)
21
–
–
1.8
1.7
1.5
2.4
♂5-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-0628)
21
6.6 *
36
1.9
1.7
1.6
2.3
♂4-holotype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-1156)
23
5.8 *
36
2.3
2.1
1.8
2.7
♀1-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-0627)
26
6.1 *
36
2.6
2.5
2.3
2.8
</p>
      <p>
long, apical seta and a few shorter setiform sensilla (
Figs 75–77
). Lacinia falciform well sclerotized, all five laminae pectinate.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Thoracic segments elongated (
Figs 71
, 
75
). Pronotum with 5+5 M and numerous uniformly distributed sM and sm; mesonotum with 5+5 M and a few sM and sm; metanotum with 2+2 M and a few sm; both prescuta have 1+1 M and scattered sM and sm; at high magnifications tiny, uniformly distributed micropores (
0.10–0.15 µm
diameter) visible on cuticle surface (
Fig. 72
). Thoracic sternites, intersternites, and presternites well defined with sm, sM, and M setae (
Figs 75, 77–79
). Pro-presternites and pro-, meso- and metasternites have strong internal Y-shaped cuticular structures (furcisternites) (
Barlet &amp; Carpentier 1962
), and only in pro-presternites prolongation of posterior branch named spine clearly visible on surface (
Denis 1949
). Pro-presternum with 1+1 short M in anterior lateral position and 1+1 sM in medial anterior; prosternum with 1+1 medial anterior M; 3+3 lateral anterior M, 1+1 medial intermediate M and 2+2 lateral posterior M; meso-poststernum with 5+5 M; meso-intersternum with 5+5 M; mesosternum with 1+1 medial anterior M, 4+4 lateral anterior M, 1 M sagittal, 1+1 medial intermediate M, 1+0 medial posterior M and 3+3 lateral posterior M; metapoststernum with 5+5 M; meta-intersternum 4+4 M; and metasternum with 1+1 medial anterior M, 3+3 lateral anterior M; 1+1 sagittal M, 1+1 medial intermediate M, 3+3 lateral posterior M (
Figs 75, 77–79
). Legs elongated, hind legs reaching 5 
th
abdominal segment. Frictional setae between trochantercoxa-femora articulations; femora-tibia-tarsus articulations with row of long M or sM setae with large sockets, plus additional 1 M in coxa, 5 M in trochanter and 7 M in femora. Tibia and tarsus with M and sM; 5 M in tibia and 2 M in tarsus. Tibia also bearing one calcar seta at ventral apex, thicker and more robust than other tibial setae, and two rows of four or five thick setae along ventral side. Pretarsus with two unequal claws and sharp medial unguiculus.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Abdominal tergites with few sm and sM. Tergite I (prescutum and scutum) without M; tergite II with 0 or 1+1 M5; tergite III with 1+1 M (medial anterior macrosetae), 0 or 1+1 M1, 1+1 M4–5; tergites IV–VI with 1+1 M (
ma
), 0 or 1+1 M1, 1+1 M2–5; tergite VIII with 1+1 M4–5; tergite IX lacking M except (M1 present in specimens from Parpent Cave 1 (
Fig. 88
). Urite X (
Figs 89
, 
92
) nearly 1.5 × as long as wide, distinctly marked carinae present with subparallel margins slightly convergent towards posterior; 2+2 intracarinal D1 and D3 macrosetae and 3+3 macrosetae (L1, L3, L5) on carinae (
Fig. 89
); ventral side with four rows of 3+3 M, 3+3 M, 2+2 M, and 2+2 M from anterior to posterior position; acropygium rounded (
Fig. 91
). Tergites I–V with blunt, slightly rounded to pointed posterolateral angles; angles on tergites VI and VII more conspicuous, lobiform projection small to more prolonged and visibly sclerotized in largest specimens; tergite IX with projections (
Fig. 88
). Sternite I (
Figs 80–85
) with multiperforated surface and rounded protrusions covered by abundant sm and lesser sM and 3+3 or 3+4 M on prescutum and 11+11 M on scutum. Median glandular organ with 12 seta-shaped sensilla (
Fig. 83
). Lateral subcoxal organs invaginated below posterior margin or evaginated showing central opening protruding over margin of first urosternite (
Figs 81–82
). Each lateral subcoxal organ with one, two, or three rows of glandular setae (GS) (
54–100 in
males, 
47–66 in
females) and one row of sensory setae (SS) (
11–24 in
males, 
13–15 in
females) occupying 0.22–0.30 (males) and 0.23–0.25 (females) of interstyle width; GS/st1 (stylus of first sternite) = 0.1–0.23 (males) and 0.18–0.28 (females), SS/st1= 0.19 (male) and 0.16–0.26 (females); row of setae with large sockets anterior to glandular setae, 
7–12 in
males and 
6–10 in
females (
Figs 80–85
). Sternites have abundant sm and strong M; sternites II–VII with 7+7 A M, 5+5 (4+4) B M and 4+4 C M; sternite VIII with 3+3 (4+4) A M, 3+3 (2+2) B M and 3+3 C M (see Material and methods for terminology); sternite IX with 1+1 M (
Figs 86–87
). Cerci strong, well developed, elongated and rectilinear, becoming curved toward apex (
Figs 89–92
), length ranging from 
2.8 mm
in largest specimen (
♀
1- 
paratype
) to 
1.4 mm
in the smallest (♂7- 
paratype
); cerci always slightly longer than urite X, heavily sclerotized with external dorsal andventral carinae projecting from dorsal and ventral acetabular articulations running almost to apex ventrally and halfway dorsally. Cerci with medial tooth; right cercus with basal notch complementary in shape to round tooth at ventral side of basal portion of left cercus. Posterior to right notch and left tooth: in right cercus short row of 5 or 6 small, round denticles in line; and in left cercus two rows of small round denticles (4+4); these rows of denticles occupying 1/8 of total length of each cercus (
Figs 89–95, 97
). Each cercus with scattered sm, sM, and M setae and several conical sensilla throughout, more abundant distally (
Figs 96–97
). Dorsal side of each cercus with 6 or 7 D macrosetae, D1, D3 and D5 largest on both cerci; ventral side with 12 V-macrosetae, V3 and V8 being largest; intracarinal region with 5–7 L macrosetae, a pair of macrosetae in L1 being largest (
Figs 91
, 
94–95
).
</p>
      <p>
Figs 71‒74.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
71
. Pronotum, mesonotum and metanotum, right side, see terminology in the text (holotype, MZB (MCNB) 2020-1156). 
72
. Detail of the surface of the mesonotum. 
73
. Detail of the latero–posterior left side of the mesonotum. 
74
. Detail of the macroseta base.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 75‒79.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
75
. Head, prothorax, mesothorax and metathorax, ventral view (paratype, MZB (MCNB) 2020-1157). 
76
. Head anterior ventral side, (ad) admentum, (el) external lobule, (lp) labial palp, and (sm) submentum. 
77
. Pro-prosternum (pr-prt) with spine (sp) and anterior portion of prosternum (pr-st). 
78
. Meso-poststernum (ms-pst), meso-intersternum (ms-ist), and mesosternum (ms-st). 
79
. Meta-poststernum (mt-pst), meta-intersternum (mt-ist), and metasternum (mt-st).
</p>
      <p>
Figs 80‒85.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
female. 
80
. First urosternite. 
81
. Lateral posterior of the first urosternite. 
82
. Detail of the lateral coxal organ with glandular setae (GS) and setiform setae (SS). 
83
. Median glandular organ (ss: setae-shaped sensilla). 
84
. Detail of the large socket setae (lss) of the lateral coxal organ. 
85
. Detail of the cuticle of the first urosternite.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 86‒91.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
86
. Eighth and ninth urosternites. 
87
. Fourth urosternite. 
88
. Eighth and ninth urotergites. 
89
. Urite X and cerci, dorsal side. 
90
. Cerci, dorsal side. 
91
. Detail of the cerci, dorsal side. Abbreviations: see Material and methods.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 92‒97.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
92
. Urite X and cerci, ventral side. 
93
. Proximal and ventral side of the cerci. 
94
. Ventral proximal portion of the left cercus. 
95
. Ventral proximal portion of the right cercus. 
96
. Conical sensillum of the cerci. 
97
. Cerci, caudal view. See Material and methods for terminology.
</p>
      <p>
Table 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggenjapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, subcoxal organs with number of glandular, sensory setae and large socket setae including body, interstylar width-length in mm and index of GS/st1 and SS/st1.
</p>
      <p>
Subcoxal organs
Specimen
Body length
Glandular setae (GS)
Sensory setae (SS)
Rows of setae Setae of length/interstylar large socket width
GS/st1
SS/st1
♂7-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-1158)
15
54
11
0.22
7
0.23
0.19
♂3-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-0626)
16.5
57
24
0.30
6
–
–
♂5-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-0628)
21
115
–
0.24
13
0.17
–
♂4-holotype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-1156)
23
100
–
0.27
12
0.22
–
♀6-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-1157)
19
47
–
0.23
6
0.21
–
♀2-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-1159)
21
60
13
0.23
5
0.28
0.26
♀1-paratype (MZB (MCNB) 2020-0627)
26
66
15
0.25
10
0.18
0.16
</p>
      <p>
Taxonomic affinities
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
is distinguished by its elongated, rectilinear, heavily sclerotized cerci curving subapically, and lacking a medial tooth but with one or two rows of basal small round denticles, its median glandular organ with seta-shaped sensilla, and short lateral subcoxal organs, each with a row of setae that have large sockets.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, was observed and collected along with 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ywangana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in Win Twin Cave (
Figs 1–4
), as well as in two nearby caves: Parpent Cave 1 and Kyauk Khaung (synonyms: Sin Lae Ye Win, Stone Cave). The latter is the second longest cave so far explored in 
Myanmar
. Kyauk Khaung Cave is over 
4790 m
long and also situated in the Ywangan karst area. Its entrance is located only 
1240 m
southeast of the entrance to Win Twin, and the cave itself extends mostly towards the northeast of the entrance. During the 2015 biological research of Kyauk Khaung, specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>Campodeidae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Japygidae</tp:taxon-name>
were found in the northernmost parts of the cave, which indicates the species is most likely distributed throughout the entire subterranean habitats of the Ywangan karst (unpublished data). The Ywangan karst covers 1050 ha, and at the moment hosts three other endemic troglobitic invertebrates: the carabid beetle 
Birmaphaenops
<tp:taxon-name>
brehieri
Deuve, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Deuve 2017
), the cave crab 
<tp:taxon-name>
Shanphusa ywarngan
Ng &amp; Whitten, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Ng &amp; Whitten 2017
), and a woodlouse 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bamaoniscus lobatus

Taiti 
et al
, 2020

</tp:taxon-name>
as well as an endemic karst-adapted gecko, the Linn-Way bent-toed gecko 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cyrtodactylus linnwayensis

Grismer 
et al
., 2017

</tp:taxon-name>
(

Grismer 
et al
. 2017

), and 17 species of bats (unpublished data). Due to its biodiversity, Ywangan karst is proposed as a karst Key Biodiversity Area and a subterranean Ramsar Site. Although cave tourism is being developed in the area, there are substantial efforts being made by the NGO sector (Fauna &amp; Flora International 
Myanmar
) to provide guidance for development of sustainable, low-impact tourism as well as cave and biodiversity conservation (unpublished data).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
