<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Anisuracampa ywangana Sendra &amp; Komericki 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4423298</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E40878FFDFFFAAB0D7FEA1D25F2C55</uri>
         <article-title>Asian cave-adapted diplurans, with the description of two new genera and four new species (Arthropoda, Hexapoda, Entognatha)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa ywangana
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
511F81B5-6CB2-4A98-AB3E-11AF72205A26
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1, 3–19
; 
Tables 1–2
; Supp. file 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This species is named after the important karst region Ywangan in 
Myanmar
, the location of Win Twin Cave (
Figs 1, 3–4
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <tp:material-citation>
         <p>
Holotype
</p>
         <p>
MYANMAR
• 
♀
; 
Shan State
, 
Ywangan
, 
Win Twin Cave
; 
21º11′51.47″ N
, 
96º32′40.34″ E
; 

16 Nov. 2018

; 
Aung Lin
leg.; labelled “holotype”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1152
.
</p>
      </tp:material-citation>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MYANMAR
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; labelled “paratype-H1”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020- 0620
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
, 
1 juvenile
; same collection data as for holotype; 

8 May 2018

; labelled “paratype-H2”, “paratype-M”, “paratype-J”; 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1153
, 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1155
, 
MZB
(
MCNB
) 
2020-1154
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Other material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MYANMAR
• 
2 specs
; same collection data as for the holotype; 

8 May 2018

; mounted on two separate aluminium stages and coated with palladium-gold; Coll. AS.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Length is 4.3–6.0 mm (n = 4) in adults and 
2.6 mm
in one juvenile (
Table 1
). The epicuticle is smooth under optical microscope but reticulated at higher magnification, showing irregular polygonal structures of variable sizes (
Fig. 11
). Body with long smooth clothing setae.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Two complete and intact antennae in 
holotype
and paratype-M with 35 antennomeres each, whereas paratype-J (juvenile) has 38 antennomeres. The antennae are similar to length of body (
Table 1
), with medial antennomeres 2× as long as wide but apical antennomeres 1½ × as long as wide. Cupuliform organ with up to 17 spheroidal olfactory chemoreceptors arranged in two uneven concentric circles; each chemoreceptor forms a complex structure of multi–perforated folds with one distinguishing crown of fringes a surrounding central column. Each of these structures is inside a polygonal cell (
Figs 5–6
). Distal and central antennomeres with three whorls of distal barbed macrosetae and 5–6 scattered whorls of smooth setae in addition to single distal whorl of up to 14 gouge sensilla of 
24–28 µm
length (
Figs 7–8
) that are more abundant on dorsal side of antennomere. Proximal antennomeres with typical trichobothria, plus small bacilliform sensillum on third antennomere in ventral position. Round protrusion of frontal process covered with one anterior macroseta and two or three posterior macrosetae (
Fig. 10
). Three macrosetae along each side of insertion line of antennomere and 
x
setae with thin distal barbs; length ratios of 
a
/ 
i
/ 
p
/ 
x
, 45/57/56/65, respectively, in paratype-H2. Labial palps large and suboval, each with bacilliform latero-external sensillum, two guard setae, up to 18 normal setae and up to 140 neuroglandular setae.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Thoracic macrosetae distribution (
Figs 9, 11
) have pronotum with 1+1 
ma
, 1+1 
la
, 2+2 
lp
2,3 macrosetae; mesonotum with 1+1 
ma
, 2+2 
la
and 4+4 
lp
1–4 macrosetae; and metanotum with 1+1 
ma
, 2+2 
la
and 3+3 
lp
1–3 macrosetae. All macrosetae long and with thin barbs along basal half to twothirds of each seta; marginal setae barbed and longer than clothing setae. Legs elongated, metathoracic legs reach end of abdomen in adults or overpass it in juvenile. Tibia always longer than femur or tarsus (
Table 1
). Each femur III with three or, less frequently, two long dorsal macrosetae with distal barbs (
0.25 mm
in 
0.62 mm
femur of paratype-H1) (femora I–II with one to three long dorsal macrosetae). Calcars covered with thin abundant barbs all over. Tibiae I–III usually with two short, completely barbed ventral macrosetae, occasionally just one. Each tibia with two rows of ventral barbed setae almost from base and scattered throughout with thin, long setiform sensilla. Three well-barbed dorsal distal tarsal setae longer than rest of tarsal setae. Subequal claws with lateral expansion in crest; basal and ventral portion of claws covered with short to long spiniform formations. Laminar pretarsus of lateral processes sharply curved with what apparently looks like thin fringes under optical microscope, but under SEM seen as narrow laminar expansions (
Figs 12–15
).
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1‒4.
Cave-adapted diplurans from Win Tin Twin Cave, Ywangan karst, Shan State, Myanmar. 
1
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa ywangana
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, with Diplopoda at 300 m from the entrance. 
2
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
at the same site. 
3
. Speleothems in the main passage of the cave. 
4
. Entrance to the cave. (Photographs: Ana Komerički).
</p>
      <p>
Table 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa ywangana
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, length of the body, antennae and metathoracic leg, including their segments, and cerci (units in mm) as well as number of antennomeres.
</p>
      <p>
Specimen
Body length
Antennae length
Antenno- meres
Segment length of the metathoracic leg coxa trochanter femur tibia tarsus
Total metathoracic length
Holotype
6.0
–
–
0.25
0.25
0.90
1.14
0.78
3.32
(MZB (MCNB)
2020-1152)
Paratype-H2
5.8
5.8
35
0.23
0.20
0.90
1.02
0.73
3.08
(MZB (MCNB)
2020-1153)
Paratype-M
4.4
4.6
35
0.22
0.20
0.57
0.85
0.60
2.44
(MZB (MCNB)
2020-1154)
Paratype-H1
4.3
–
–
0.21
0.20
0.62
0.78
0.62
2.43
(MZB (MCNB)
2020-0620)
Paratype-J
2.6
2.8
37
0.14
0.14
0.40
0.51
0.42
1.61
(MZB (MCNB)
2020-1155)
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Distribution of macrosetae on tergites with 1+1 
post
1 on I–III; 1+1 
post
1 to 3+3 
post
1–3 on IV, 4+4 
post
1–4 and 1+1 
la
on V, 5+5 
post
1–5 or 6+6 
post
1–6 and 1+1 
la
on VI–VII; 7+7 
post
on VIII; and 8+8 or 9+9 
post
macrosetae on IX abdominal segment. All tergal abdominal macrosetae long and barbed along distal half to four-fifths. Urosternite I has 7+7 macrosetae (
Figs 16–17
); while urosternites II to VII with 5+5 macrosetae; and urosternite VIII with 1+1 macrosetae; urosternal macrosetae of medium size and barbed along distal half. Stylus with short apical seta with small barbs, and each subapical seta completely covered with barbs and with short, barbed ventromedial seta (
Figs 18–19
). One intact cercus 2.4 × body length and with 14 primary articles (
Table 2
). Article length increases from proximal to distal articles; covered with long thin macrosetae, with distal barbs, and less abundant long, thin setae. Each primary article with whorl of shorter thin plumose setae at distal position.
</p>
      <p>
SECONDARY SEX CHARACTERS. Female urosternite I with enlarged subcylindrical appendages, each bearing up to 60 ventral glandular 
a
2 setae proximally and apical field of up to 28 glandular 
a
1 setae (
Figs 16–17
). Male with similar appendages with two fields of glandular setae (19 
a
2 and 27 
a
1) in one appendage of male 
paratype
. Spermatozoid fascicles small, 
0.04 mm
in diameter, and formed by undistinguishable filament of spermatozoids in spiral.
</p>
      <p>
Taxonomic affinities
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa
</tp:taxon-name>
was proposed for a soil-dwelling species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa suoxiensis
Xie &amp; Yang, 1990
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Hunan Province
in southeastern 
China
. As a plusiocampine genus, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa
</tp:taxon-name>
is characterized by the laminar pretarsus but with the lateral processes with long barbs and weakly developed lateral crests (
Figs 12–15
) (see 
Xie &amp; Yang 1991
: fig. 34). In addition to this trait, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa
</tp:taxon-name>
has two or three dorsal femoral macrosetae and 1+1 macrosetae on the eighth urosternite. All of these characters are present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ywangana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, a cave-adapted species from the Win Twin Cave in eastern 
Myanmar
.
</p>
      <p>
Table 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa ywangana
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype MZB (MCNB) 2020-1153, length of cercal articles and total length (units in mm), including number of articles of the cercus, basal article included, and division of basal article in secondary articles.
</p>
      <p>
Division- basal article
Basal article

1 
st

2 
nd

3 
rd

4 
th

5 
th

6 
th

7 
th

8 
th

9 
th

10 
th

11 
th

12 
th

13 
th

14 
th
Total cercus
Number of articles
3
1.1
0.39
0.45
0.50
0.55
0.65
0.75
0.83
0.92
0.94
1.20
1.44
1.65
1.67
1.64
14.68
15
</p>
      <p>
Therefore, these morphological similarities together with the congruent geographical distribution in Southeast Asia are considered sufficient reason to place this new species in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa
</tp:taxon-name>
. However, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ywangana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. suoxiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
in several characters besides the traits related to adaptations to cave ecosystems. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa ywangana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
has 4+4 lateral posterior macrosetae on the mesonotum (
Fig. 9
) (2+ 
2 in
<tp:taxon-name>
A. suoxiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
), 3+3 lateral posterior and 2+2 lateral anterior macrosetae on the metanotum (2+2 lateral posterior and no lateral anterior macrosetae in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. suoxiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
) and 5+5 posterior and 1+1 lateral anterior macrosetae on urotergites V–VII (4+4 posterior and no lateral anterior macrosetae in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. suoxiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
). Regarding the new species’ cave-adapted features, it has a larger body and longer appendages at least double the size of those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. suoxiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, with 30–35 antennomeres in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ywangana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(
24 in
<tp:taxon-name>
A. suoxiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
). It is impossible to compare other useful taxonomical characteristics mentioned in the description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ywangana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
with 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. suoxiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
as the former was described using SEM, whereas the latter was described under optical observations with a brief diagnosis and the 
type
material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. suoxiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is not available for study.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Figs 5‒8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa ywangana
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
5
. Apical view of last antennomere. 
6
. Olfactory chemoreceptor of the cupuliform organ. 
7
. Central antennemeres. 
8
. Lateral distal medial antenomere with gouge sensilla (gs).
</p>
   <p>
Figs 9‒11.
<tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa ywangana
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (MZB (MCNAB) 2020- 1152) 
9
. Pronotum, mesonotum, and metanotum, left side. 
10
. Frontal process. 
11
. Detail of the base of medial anterior mesonotal macroseta.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Anisuracampa ywangana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
was observed and collected walking on the Win Twin cave floor and boulders, approximately 
300 m
from the entrance, and on the wet flowstone in a vast chamber (
Figs 1–3
; Supp. file 2). The Win Twin cave is located within a large karst area referred to as Ywangan karst, which is situated in the western part of the 
Shan
plateau, approximately 
10 km
northeast of Ywangan Township and 
15 km
east of the Panlaung Pyadalin Wildlife Sanctuary. The cave has only been discovered recently and is currently under tourist development by the local community. It has not been fully surveyed and approximately only the first 
400 m
were explored during the collection of the 
type
material. The cave itself is large, with numerous chambers, and its entrance was enlarged by mining (
Fig. 4
); after approximately 
300 m
into the main passage, it opens into a vast chamber filled with speleothems (
Fig. 3
), from which it again continues further by smaller, narrow passages opening into new chambers. At the bottom of the vast chamber, the oxygen level becomes too low for further exploration during the dry season (May), while by the end of the rainy season (November) it was possible to reach two further lower chambers before the oxygen level became too low. No active water flow was observed, but sparse remains of particular organic matter are present and the air temperature recorded in 
May 2018
was 20.0°C, while the sediment temperature was 19.6°C (unpublished data).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
