<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Arcofaciella indiana Chen &amp; Yang 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4745086</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0397BE4E07DEABF29C8CE94C8EBA6A39</uri>
         <article-title>Review the bamboo-feeding genus Arcofaciella Fennah, 1956 (Hemiptera: Fulgoromorpha: Delphacidae) with description of a new species from India</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.748.1341</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Arcofaciella indiana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
7227AA9A-1341-45BA-8F20-EB841BED705D
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Arcofaciella indiana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be distinguished from the remaining species of the genus by the frons in profile (
Figs 1I
, 
2B
) not inclined anteriorly, the clypeus in profile (
Figs 1I
, 
2B
) bent at obtuse angle to frons, the presence of a median carina on the clypeus (
Fig. 2C
), and the genital styles with inner apical angle not bifurcate (
Fig. 2H–J
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This new species is named after the 
type
locality, 
India
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
INDIA
• 
♂
; 
Karnataka
, 
Mysore
; 
12°30′ N
, 
76°64′ E
; 

2 Aug. 1972

; 
C.A. Viraktamath
leg.; 
on bamboo
; 
GUGC-FDTA-19720801
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
INDIA
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
GUGC-FDTA-19720802
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length including forewing: male (
holotype
, GUGC-FDTA-19720801) 
4.3 mm
(N = 1); female (
paratype
, GUGC-FDTA-19720802) 
4.6 mm
(N = 1); forewing length: male (
holotype
) 
3.8 mm
(N = 1); female (
paratype
) 4.0 mm (N = 1).
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. General color yellowish brown to brown (
Fig. 1
). Vertex (
Fig. 1G
) grayish brown, middle area somewhat reddish orange. Frons grayish brown. Clypeus yellow brown. Rostrum yellow brown, distal part black brown. Genae yellow brown to brown. Eyes black brown, ocelli reddish brown. Antennae yellow brown, first segment with distal part and second segment with base part dark brown (
Fig. 1H–I
). Pronotum grayish brown, middle area somewhat reddish orange, lateral margin brown. Mesonotum grayish brown to brown, intercarinal area somewhat reddish orange (
Fig. 1G
). Forewings (
Fig. 2D
) semitransparent, basal half with large inclined yellowish brown stripe, apical half except area between veins ScP and MP1 yellowish brown, a small round callus near ScP-R fork and another near CuA fork piceous, veins brown with yellowish white granules, veins dashed, apex of longitudinal veins brown. Thorax with ventral and lateral areas grayish brown. Legs yellowish brown to brown, with dark brown ring markings.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD AND THORAX.Vertex (
Fig. 2A
) at midline shorter than wide at base (0.29:1), width at apex narrower than at base (0.64:1). Frons (
Fig. 2C
) 1.23 times longer in middle line than widest part, narrower at apex than at base (0.69:1). Antennae (
Fig. 2C
) with first segment longer than wide at apex (1.25:1), shorter than second segment (0.48:1). Pronotum (
Fig. 2A
) at midline slightly shorter than vertex (0.91:1), lateral carinae arched, medially concave, flexing backwards near middle at sub-right angle and nearly attaining hind margin. Mesonotum (
Fig. 2A
) 2.82 times as long as vertex and pronotum combined in middle line. Forewing (
Fig. 2D
) in middle line longer than wide at widest part (2.75:1). Spinal formula of hind tibia 5-7-5.
</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA. Anal segment (
Fig. 2E
) in lateral view small, ring-like, without anal process. Pygofer narrow with ventral margin much longer than dorsal margin in lateral view, laterodorsal angles not produced, posterior lateral margins broadly sinuate (
Fig. 2F
); in posterior view with opening longer than wide, lateral margin thick and not well defined, medioventral process absent (
Fig. 2G
). Genital styles (
Fig. 2H–J
) long, reaching basal anal segment, apical part distinctly curved inward, outer apical angle rounded and protruding slightly dorsad, inner apical angle quadrate, with inner edge angularly directed dorsally in lateral view. Aedeagus (
Fig. 2K–M
) long, tubular, with distinct phallotheca, with basal part lying between two valvular processes of phallotheca, deflecting leftward, apical part recurved downward and reaching ⅔ of phallotheca. Phallotheca almost reaching base of genital styles, apical part warping dorsad, basal part stout, with two valvular processes, in dorsal view with a large and a small round valvular processes, tapering from ½ to apex, in right view with three processes near base.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofaciella indiana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–C, G–I = holotype, ♂ (GUGC-FDTA-19720801), D–F = paratype, ♀ (GUGC-FDTA-19720802). 
A
. Male habitus, dorsal view. 
B–C
. Same, lateral view. 
D
. Female habitus, dorsal view. 
E–F
. Same, lateral view. 
G
. Head and thorax, dorsal view. 
H
. Face. 
I
. Frons, lateral view. Scale bars: A–F = 1 mm; G–I = 0.5 mm.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofaciella indiana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (GUGC-FDTA-19720801). 
A
. Head and thorax, dorsal view. 
B
. Same, lateral view. 
C
. Face. 
D
. Forewing. 
E
. Male genitalia, posterior view. 
F
. Same, lateral view. 
G
. Pygofer, posterior view. 
H
. Genital style, posterior view. 
I
. Same, posterior and lateral views. 
J
. Same, lateral view. 
K
. Aedeagus, right lateral view. 
L
. Same, left lateral view. 
M
. Same, dorsal view. Scale bars: A–C = 0.5 mm; D = 1 mm; E–M = 0.2 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host plant
</p>
      <p>Bambusoideae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
India
(
Karnataka
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa

Guo &amp; Liang, 
2005
</tp:taxon-name>
in having a similar shape of the frons, in the cylindrical antennae, in the relatively larger pronotum, in the gibbous mesonotum, strongly sloping laterally and posteriorly, and in the shape of the forewing. However, it can be distinguished from the latter by the following features: (1) frons in profile (
Figs 1I
, 
2B
) not inclined anteriorly (vs frons in profile (
Figs 3I
, 
4B
) inclined anteriorly in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa
</tp:taxon-name>
); (2) clypeus in profile (
Figs 1I
, 
2B
) bent at obtuse angle to frons, with median carina present (vs clypeus in profile (
Figs 3I
, 
4B
) bent at right angle to frons, with median carina obsolete in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa
</tp:taxon-name>
); (3) spinal formula of hind tibia 5-7-5 (vs spinal formula of hind tibia 5-8- 
5 in
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa
</tp:taxon-name>
); (4) anal segment of male (
Fig. 2E
) with lateroapical angles without spinous process (vs anal segment of male (
Fig. 4E
) with lateroapical angles produced into stout spinous process caudad in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa
</tp:taxon-name>
); (5) genital styles (
Fig. 2H–J
) without angled process medioventrally, inner apical angle not bifurcate (vs genital styles (
Fig. 4I–J
) with an angled process medioventrally, inner apical angle bifurcate in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
      <p>
This species is also similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. verrucosa

Fennah, 
1956
</tp:taxon-name>
in having a similar shape of the frons, in the cylindrical antennae, in the relatively larger pronotum, in the gibbous mesonotum, strongly sloping laterally and posteriorly, and in the shape and similar color of the forewing. However, it can be distinguished from the latter by the following features: (1) frons in profile (
Figs 1I
, 
2B
) not inclined anteriorly (vs frons in profile (
Figs 5I
, 
6B
) inclined anteriorly in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa
</tp:taxon-name>
); (2) clypeus in profile (
Figs 1I
, 
2B
) bent at obtuse angle to frons, with median carina present (vs clypeus in profile (
Figs 5I
, 
6B
) bent at right angle to frons, with median carina obsolete in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. verrucosa
</tp:taxon-name>
); (3) spinal formula of hind tibia 5-7-5 (vs spinal formula of hind tibia 5-8-5 or 5-9- 
5 in
<tp:taxon-name>
A. verrucosa
</tp:taxon-name>
); (4) genital styles (
Fig. 2H–J
) with inner apical angle not bifurcate (vs genital styles (
Fig. 6H–I
) with inner apical angle bifurcate in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
