<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Arcofaciella Fennah 1956</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4746327</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F02E5B4B6DFFFD4F65FA7AC82EF809</uri>
         <article-title>Review the bamboo-feeding genus Arcofaciella Fennah, 1956 (Hemiptera: Fulgoromorpha: Delphacidae) with description of a new species from India</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.748.1341</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofaciella
Fennah, 1956
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Arcofaciella verrucosa
Fennah, 1956
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Head including eyes (
Figs 1G
, 
2A
, 
3G
, 
4A
, 
5G
, 
6A
) as wide as or wider than pronotum. Vertex (
Figs 1G
, 
2A
, 
3G
, 
4A
, 
5G
, 
6A
) short, trapezoidal; anterior margin transverse, carinate, somewhat incised medially at areolet; posterior margin transverse; lateral margins concave. Frons (
Figs 1H
, 
2C
, 
3H
, 
4C
, 
5H
, 
6C
) at midline longer than wide at widest part, widest above level of ocelli; lateral margins convex; median carina forked at fastigium, areolet weakly depressed. Postclypeus (
Figs 2B–C
, 
4B–C
, 
6B–C
) in lateral view more or less at right angle or obtuse angle to base of frons; in ventral view lateral carinae straight, converging to labrum, median carina absent or present. Rostrum with apex reaching mesotrochanters. Antennae (
Figs 1H
, 
2C
, 
3H
, 
4C
, 
5H
, 
6C
) cylindrical, short, stout, second segment markedly longer than first segment, but both together not exceeding length of eye. Pronotum (
Figs 1G
, 
2A
, 
3G
, 
4A
, 
5G
, 
6A
) subequal or longer than vertex along midline, sloping anteriorly and laterally; anteriorly shallowly convex, posteriorly shallowly excavate; median carina distinct, lateral carinae developed only in anterior portion in line with lateral margins of vertex; disc with two pits on each side of median carina. Mesonotum (
Figs 1G
, 
2A
, 
3G
, 
4A
, 
5G
, 
6A
) strongly convex, almost gibbous, strongly sloping laterally and posteriorly, disc tricarinate with lateral carinae feeble. Mesoscutellum (
Figs 1G
, 
2A
, 
3G
, 
4A
, 
5G
, 
6A
) distinctly depressed, horizontal, median line of scutum obsolete posteriorly, but present on scutellum, with a distinct groove between scutum and scutellum. Forewings (
Figs 2D
, 
4D
, 
6D
) long, corium enfolding abdomen at region of node, costal margin sinuate, concave distad of node, apical margin shallowly undulate, forks of ScP-R and CuA distad of union of claval veins. Legs relatively short and stout, profemora shorter than procoxae (e.g., 
Figs 1F
, 
3F
, 
5C
), hind tibiae with two lateral spines (one very small at base, the other large at about one third from apex) (
Fig. 1F
) and five teeth at apex; hind tarsomere I with 7, 8 or 9 small even teeth at apex, hind tarsomere II with 5 apical teeth. Anal segment of male (
Figs 2E
, 
4E
, 
6E
) in caudal view ring-like, lateroapical angles weakly protruding caudad or not produced. Pygofer (
Figs 2G
, 
4H
, 
6G
) without medioventral process. Genital styles (
Figs 2H–J
, 
4I–J
, 
6H–I
) long. Aedeagus (
Figs 2K–M
, 
4K–L
, 
6J–K
) with phallotheca. Aedeagus tubular, apical part recurved downward. Phallotheca with valvular process, basal ⅔ quadrate.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This genus is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofacies
Muir, 1915
</tp:taxon-name>
but differs from it by: frons with lateral margins distinctly arched (
Figs 1H
, 
2C
, 
3H
, 
4C
, 
5H
, 
6C
) (vs frons with lateral margins subparallel in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofacies
</tp:taxon-name>
(

Chen 
et al.
2007

: figs 2, 11, 19, 25)); antennae short, obviously not reaching frontoclypeal suture (
Figs 1H
, 
2C
, 
3H
, 
4C
, 
5H
, 
6C
) (vs antennae long, nearly reaching or surpassing frontoclypeal suture in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofacies
</tp:taxon-name>
(

Chen 
et al.
2007

: figs 2, 11, 19, 25)); pronotum with lateral carinae not extending to hind margin (
Figs 1G
, 
2A
, 
3G
, 
4A
, 
5G
, 
6A
) (vs pronotum with lateral carinae extending to hind margin in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofacies
</tp:taxon-name>
(

Chen 
et al.
2007

: figs 1, 10, 18, 24)); spinal formula of hind leg 5-8-5 or 5-9-5 (vs spinal formula of hind leg 5-6- 
4 in
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofacies
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host plant
</p>
      <p>Bambusoideae Luerss.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Oriental region (
China
, Malay Peninsula, 
India
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key to species (males) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arcofaciella
Fennah, 1956
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Frons in profile inclined anteriorly (
Figs 3I
, 
4B
, 
5I
, 
6B
); clypeus in profile bent at right angle to frons (
Figs 3I
, 
4B
, 
5I
, 
6B
), with median carina absent (
Figs 4C
, 
6C
) ....................................................... 2

</p>
      <p>

– Frons in profile not inclined anteriorly (
Figs 1I
, 
2B
); clypeus in profile bent at obtuse angle to frons (
Figs 1I
, 
2B
), with median carina present (
Fig. 2C
) ............................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. indiana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

2. Genital styles in posterior view with an angled process medioventrally (
Fig. 4I
) ............................. ........................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. obflexa
Guo &amp; Liang, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Genital styles in posterior view without angled process medioventrally (
Fig. 6H
) ......................... 3

</p>
      <p>

3. Genital styles in posterior view with hamular process at inner apical laterally (
Fig. 6H
) .................. .................................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. verrucosa
Fennah, 1956
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Genital styles in posterior view with quadrate process at inner apical laterally ................................. ............................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. penangensis
(
Muir, 1919
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
