<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sarsinebalia ledoyeri Moreira,
                        Esquete &amp; Cunha, 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4577442</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F287D25038AA3BFDD7FDC9FE6F5B06</uri>
                  <article-title>Leptostracans (Crustacea: Phyllocarida) from mud volcanoes at the
                        Gulf of Cadiz (NE Atlantic) with description of a new species of
                        Sarsinebalia Dahl, 1985</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 6203DB5B-D428-494D-AE12-96671063F37A </p>
            <p> Figs 1 , 10–16 , Table 2 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>Rostrum length 2.4–2.5 times width. Compound eye provided with 10–20 spaced ommatidia
                  along distal half; pigment not observed; eye distal half with concave ventral
                  margin; distal third gradually compressed laterally. Antennular scale length about
                  2.2 times width. Antennule peduncle fourth article with one distal robust seta.
                  Antenna peduncle third article with 2–3 slightly plumose setae and three similar
                  spine-like setae on lateral margin. Mandibular palp second article with two setae:
                  1) proximal seta on lateral surface, setulose along distal half inferior margin,
                  about 0.5 times as long as article; 2) subdistal simple seta, longer than third
                  article. Maxilla II endopod weakly segmented, distal article 1.8 times as long as
                  proximal article; exopod 1.4 times as long as endopod proximal article. Pleonite
                  IV epimeron posterolateral corner as triangular acute process. Pleonite IV
                  posterolateral border with denticles distally acute; pleonites V–VII posterodorsal
                  border with denticles distally rounded to pointed, never acutely produced. Pleopod
                  I exopod lateral margin lacking setae. Pleopod IV protopod posterior border with
                  three serrations; posterolateral corner acutely pointed. Uropods 0.7–0.85 times as
                  long as pleonite VII+ anal somite.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>The new species is named after the French carcinologist Michel Ledoyer because of his
                  many contributions to leptostracan taxonomy.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype MOROCCO • postovigerous ♀ , TL 4.0 mm, RL 0.675 mm
                        , DCL 1.65 mm , LCL 2.15 mm , CH 1.4 mm ; Gulf of Cadiz , Gemini MV;
                        35°16.88′ N , 06°45.35′ W ; 418 m depth ; 6 Oct. 2006 ; St 64PE253_06, MV
                        crater, mud breccia ; MNCN 20.04/13706 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Allotype MOROCCO • ♂ , TL 3.9 mm , RL 0.625 mm , DCL 1.6 mm
                        , LCL 1.975 mm , CH 1.3 mm ; same locality and station as for holotype; MNCN
                        20.04/13707 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes MOROCCO • 4 postovigerous ♀♀ ; same locality and
                        station as for holotype; MNCN 20.04/13708 to 20.04/13711
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 10 preovigerous ♀♀ ; same
                        locality and station as for holotype; MNCN 20.04/13712 to 20.04/13721
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 6 ♂♂ ; same locality and station
                        as for holotype; MNCN 20.04/13722 to 20.04/13727 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 3 juveniles ; same locality and station as for
                        holotype; MNCN 20.04/13728 to 20.04/13730 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 4 postovigerous ♀♀ , 10 preovigerous ♀♀ , 5 ♂♂ , 3
                        juveniles ; same locality and station as for holotype; DBUA0002351.01
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description of female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Postovigerous ♀♀ : TL 3.625–4.0 mm, RL 0.575–0.70 mm , DCL 1.50–1.75
                  mm , LCL 1.90–2.375 mm , CH 1.325–1.50 mm ; preovigerous ♀♀ : TL 3.375–3.85 mm ,
                  RL 0.575 –0.625 mm , DCL 1.125–1.60 mm , LCL 1.625 –2.075 mm , CH 1.125–1.40 mm . </p>
            <p> CARAPACE, ROSTRUM AND EYE. Carapace roughly oval, margins convex or rounded,
                  covering laterally most of pleonites III–IV ( Fig. 10A ); LCL about 1.5–1.6 times
                  CH . Rostrum long, extending well beyond eyestalk, length 2.4–2.5 times width,
                  0.4–0.45 times DCL ( Fig. 10A, D ); tapering gradually on distal half and turning
                  downwards ( Fig. 10B ); paired ventral keels present; tip of rostrum provided with
                  terminal spine, segmented proximally. Compound eye slightly longer than high,
                  distal third becoming gradually compressed laterally ( Fig. 10C ); dorsal and
                  distal margins almost straight, ventral margin straight proximally and concave on
                  distal half ( Fig. 10B ); 10–20 spaced ommatidia, present mostly along distal
                  half; pigmentation not observed in fixed specimens; supra-orbital plate with acute
                  tip, reaching at least end of distal half of eye dorsal surface. </p>
            <p> ANTENNULE. Peduncle composed of four articles ( Fig. 11A ). First article shorter
                  than second, naked. Second article widest at midpoint, length almost 3.0 times
                  width, with (1) one plumose seta on anterior margin at mid-length, (2) cluster of
                  about 12 smooth and plumose setae arising from posterolateral distal third
                  surface, (3) cluster of about 10 short and long simple setae and one plumose seta
                  on anterodistal margin. Third article 0.5 times as long as second, wider distally,
                  with terminal cluster of about 12 simple setae on anterodistal and posterodistal
                  margins, one long simple seta on external surface and two shorter setae on inner
                  surface. Fourth article shorter than third, with (1) anterior row of 5–6 simple
                  setae, (2) one distal robust seta, (3) lateral row of 2–3 simple setae on external
                  surface, distal-most the longest, (4) one simple seta on inner surface, (5) one
                  simple seta arising from posterodistal margin, longer than article and antennular
                  scale combined. Antennular scale roughly oval, length 2.2 times width; anterior
                  margin slightly convex; anterior and terminal margins with (1) row of shorter
                  setae recurved distally and provided with blunt teeth along distal half (asb in
                  Fig. 11A ), (2) numerous simple setae of different lengths with thinner teeth,
                  setae arising from posteroterminal margin the longest (ast in Fig. 11A ); row of
                  three spaced simple setae on inner surface. Flagellum long, well-developed,
                  shorter than peduncle, with 7 articles ( 6–7 in preovigerous females), proximal
                  article as long as following three combined; each article with (1) cluster of 2–8
                  aesthetascs and (2) 2–4 simple setae on distal margin ( Fig. 11B ), distal article
                  with 5–6 setae and lacking aesthethascs. </p>
            <p> Fig. 10. <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  Postovigerous females. A . Holotype (MNCN 20.04/13706). B–D . Paratypes (MNCN
                  20.04/13708, MNCN 20.04/13709). A . Complete specimen, lateral view. B . Rostrum
                  and eye, lateral view. C . Eye and supra-orbital plate, ventral view. D . Rostrum,
                  dorsal view. A: dashed lines marking distribution of denticles on posterior
                  borders of pleonites II and III. </p>
            <p> Fig. 11. <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  Postovigerous female, paratype (MNCN 20.04/13708). A . Antennule, lateral view. B
                  . Antennule, flagellum, fifth article. C . Antenna, lateral view, outline. D .
                  Antenna, peduncle, third article, lateral view. E . Antenna, flagellum. F .
                  Antenna, peduncle, third article, distal margin plumose setae. G . Antenna,
                  flagellum, fifth article. A, C: letters in brackets refer to parts detailed in
                  other drawings with same letters; B: only one aesthethasc out of five figured. </p>
            <p> Fig. 12. <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  Postovigerous female, paratype (MNCN 20.04/13708). A . Mandible. B . Maxilla I. C
                  . Maxilla I, endites, detail. D . Maxilla II. </p>
            <p> ANTENNA. Peduncle composed of three articles ( Fig. 11C ). First article anterior
                  margin with process ending in small acute spine. Second article about as long as
                  first, anterior margin with subdistal acutely pointed process. Third article about
                  2.0 times as long as second; plumose seta arising proximally from inner surface,
                  associated to four simple short setae; medial and lateral anterior margins with
                  several rows of setae ( Fig. 11D ): (1) five sparsely plumose setae, (2) two rows
                  of simple thin spine-like setae, of 5–6 setae each (most arranged in pairs), (3)
                  five simple, thin setae, (4) terminal row of eight simple setae, increasing in
                  length distally, (5) 2–3 slightly plumose setae and three spine-like similar setae
                  along lateral margin, distal-most seta associated to 5–7 simple setae; posterior
                  margin with long, densely plumose seta ( Fig. 11F ); cluster of 8–9 plumose setae
                  along distal margin inner surface; posterodistal margin with two short simple
                  setae of different length. Flagellum well-developed, composed of 11 articles ( 12
                  in one postovigerous female) ( Fig. 11E ); each article with four terminal setae,
                  one shorter than others ( Fig. 11G ). </p>
            <p> MANDIBLE ( Fig. 12A ). Molar process well-developed, about as long as first palp
                  article, with several rows of teeth on distal third and several distal simple
                  setae; incisor process smaller, broadest basally, with row of acute teeth on
                  medial margin and acute terminal process. Mandible palp composed of three
                  articles; second article slightly longer than first, widest on proximal third; two
                  setae: one at mid-length on lateral surface, setulose on inferior margin of distal
                  half, about 0.5 times as long as article, and one subterminal simple seta, longer
                  than third article. Third article 1.3 times as long as second, with almost
                  parallel sides, slightly tapering distally; inferior margin with (1) a row of
                  plumose setae extending from ending of proximal third to distal end, first four
                  setae increasing gradually in length, (2) a row of six subdistal dentate setae,
                  (3) two terminal setae, one as long as those of (1); superior margin proximal half
                  with a row of minute setae. </p>
            <p> MAXILLA I. First endite (proximal) with rounded medial margin bearing row of plumose
                  setae ( Fig. 12B ). Second endite (distal) larger than first; inner margin with
                  several distal simple setae; medial margin with several types of setae arranged in
                  two rows: first row with (1) about 9 setae of increasing size with several teeth
                  along distal half and one large tooth on distal superior margin (tcs in Fig. 12C )
                  and (2) two pappose setae (pas in Fig. 12C ); second row with (3) about ten
                  spatulate setae (sps in Fig. 12C ) and (4) six setae with several teeth (2–4)
                  along distal superior margin, thinner than those of type (1) (tns in Fig. 12C );
                  setae of types (1), (3) and (4) with one margin provided with long, spaced setules
                  ( Fig. 12C ). Palp well-developed, about 4.0 times as long as protopod, with about
                  7–9 long setae along its entire length; setae provided with minute setules along
                  distal third and with apex recurved distally ( Fig. 12B ). </p>
            <p> MAXILLA II ( Fig. 12D ). Protopod with four endites; first (proximal) and third
                  endite the largest, fourth endite much shorter; first to third endites bearing
                  numerous plumose setae arranged in two rows; fourth endite with five longer
                  plumose setae. Endopod weakly segmented, longer than exopod, distal article 1.8
                  times as long as proximal; medial margin of both articles with one row of spaced
                  plumose setae, proximal with two additional longer setae with long setules along
                  distal half; distal article with one plumose seta, longer than endopod. Exopod 1.4
                  times as long as endopod proximal article; lateral margin with plumose setae, two
                  distal-most setae as long as exopod. </p>
            <p> THORACOPODS. Endopod longer than exopod, segmentation weak; with numerous plumose
                  setae along anterior margin arranged in two rows and one long sparsely plumose
                  seta ( Fig. 13A ); distal article expanded, in postovigerous females lacking long
                  setae, in preovigerous females with several setae shorter than exopod ( Fig. 13
                  B–C). Exopod posterior margin with 6–9 plumose setae, 1–2 distal-most the longest
                  ( Fig. 13A ). Epipod posterior margin with two plumose setae. Thoracopod VIII
                  shorter than </p>
            <p> others, with epipod comparatively reduced and lacking setae ( Fig. 13D ); exopod
                  posterior margin with about 5 plumose setae comparatively longer than those of
                  other thoracopods. </p>
            <p> PLEONITES. Pleonite I posterior border lacking denticles. Pleonites II–VII bearing
                  denticles along posterior border, at least dorsally and laterodorsally ( Fig. 10A
                  ). Pleonite II with denticles along dorsal border and extending to dorsolateral
                  border ( Fig. 14A ); denticles thin, distally acute. Pleonite III with denticles
                  along dorsal border extending well into lateral border, ending at mid-length (
                  Fig. 14B ); denticles distally pointed with more or less parallel sides (dorsal)
                  to triangular (laterodorsal). Pleonites IV–VII with posterior border fully
                  provided with denticles. Pleonite IV with dorsal and dorsolateral denticles
                  pointed to rounded becoming distally acute and triangular in shape along lateral
                  border ( Fig. 14C ); epimeron posterolateral corner forming large tooth with
                  triangular distal end, acutely pointed. Pleonites V–VII dorsal and dorsolateral
                  denticles similar in shape to those of pleonite III, distal end roughly pointed to
                  rounded but never acutely produced ( Fig. 14 D–F); some denticles on ventrolateral
                  border distally acute ( Fig. 14D ). </p>
            <p> Fig. 13. <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Female,
                  paratypes (MNCN 20.04/13708). A . Thoracopod III, showing setation. B . Thoracopod
                  V. C . Thoracopod VII. D . Thoracopod VIII. A, D: postovigerous female; B–C:
                  preovigerous female, same scale bar; B–D: only selected setae illustrated. </p>
            <p> PLEOPODS 1–4. Pleopod 1 protopod with posterior margin even ( Fig. 15A ); with one
                  short simple seta proximally on posterior margin and four distal simple setae: one
                  seta on anterior margin arising subdistally and one seta between rami, posterior
                  margin with long seta near exopod base and hardly reaching exopod distal half plus
                  one shorter subdistal seta. Exopod about 0.6 times as long as protopod; lateral
                  margin lacking ‘comb-row’; distolateral margin with one short simple seta and four
                  stout simple setaes, distal-most the longest; long plumose setae (&gt; 15) along
                  medial margin. Endopod of two articles, 1.25 times as long as exopod; proximal
                  article shorter, with appendix interna provided with three short recurved hooks;
                  lateral and medial margins of distal article each with one row of&gt; 10 plumose
                  setae, distal margin with acute process at apex and long, robust terminal seta. </p>
            <p> Fig. 14. <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  Postovigerous female, paratype (MNCN20.04/13708). A . Pleonite II, dorsal and
                  laterodorsal posterior border, denticles. B . Pleonite III, dorsal and lateral
                  posterior border, denticles. C . Pleonite IV (posterior border, denticles and
                  epimeron) and pleopod IV (protopod), lateral view. D . Pleonite V, dorsal and
                  lateral posterior border, denticles. E . Pleonite VI, dorsal and laterodorsal
                  border, denticles. F . Pleonite VII, dorsal and laterodorsal border, denticles. G
                  . Anal plates. A–B, E–F: same scale bars. </p>
            <p> PLEOPODS II–III. Similar in appearance. Protopod inner surface with 1–2 simple setae
                  on proximal third, and cluster of 2–6 long simple setae at mid-length, posterior
                  margin with cluster of three long simple setae on distal third, and two simple
                  setae near rami bases: one near appendix interna and one thicker seta close to
                  exopod ( Fig. 15 B–C); acute triangular process between rami; posterior margin
                  even. Exopod shorter than endopod; lateral margin with row of four smooth setae
                  (‘spine pairs’), each pair consisting of two setae subequal or one slightly
                  shorter (sometimes one lacking in proximal pair), with short setulose seta in
                  between; medial margin with about 10 long plumose setae; distal margin with three
                  simple setae, distal-most the longest. Endopod of two articles; proximal article
                  short, provided with appendix interna ; lateral and medial margins of distal
                  article each with one row of&gt;15 plumose setae; terminal margin with one long,
                  robust distal seta. </p>
            <p> Fig. 15. <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  Postovigerous female, paratype (MNCN20.04/13708). A . Pleopod I, lateral view. B .
                  Pleopod II, lateral view. C . Pleopod III, protopod and endopod appendix interna ,
                  inner side. D . Pleopod V, ventral view. E . Pleopod VI, ventral view. F . Right
                  uropod, ventral view. A–B, D–E: same scale bars; A–B: plumose setae not
                  illustrated; C: exopod and endopod plumose setose: setules not illustrated. </p>
            <p> PLEOPOD IV. Protopod posterior margin with three serrations ( Fig. 14C );
                  posterolateral corner acutely pointed. Rami similar to pleopods II–III. </p>
            <p> PLEOPODS V–VI. Pleopod V–VI pairs with acute triangular process between rami bases.
                  Pleopod V uniramous, length 4.3 times width, with three terminal stout simple
                  setae, proximal-most much shorter ( Fig. 15D ); approximately 12–13 simple setae
                  of different lengths along medial and terminal margins, appearing jointed at
                  mid-length. Pleopod VI uniramous, length 3.0 times width ( Fig. 15E ); with three
                  terminal simple setae, one longer than entire ramus; medial, distolateral and
                  terminal margins with about eight ‘jointed’ setae of different lengths. </p>
            <p> ANAL SOMITE, ANAL PLATES AND UROPODS. Anal somite 1.15–1.35 times as long as
                  pleonite VII ( Fig. 10A ). Anal plates with broad bases and acutely tapering
                  distally ( Fig. 14G ); medial margins convex defining a Y-shaped invagination
                  between plates; lateral margins gently sloping, lacking ‘shoulder’. Uropods
                  tapering distally, 0.7–0.85 times as long as pleonite VII+anal somite ( Fig. 10A
                  ); lateral margin with 15–18 simple setae gradually increasing in length towards
                  distal end; terminal margin with two longer robust setae, broken in all specimens
                  but distal-most at least as long as uropods ( Fig. 15F ); medial margin with one
                  row of simple setae similar to those on lateral margin but fewer and thinner plus
                  one row of long plumose setae; distomedial margin with cluster of three short
                  simple setae. </p>
            <p> Fig. 16. <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Male. A .
                  Allotype (MNCN20.04/13707). B–D . Paratype (MNCN 20.04/13722). A . Rostrum, eye
                  and carapace outline, lateral view. B . Rostrum and eye, lateral view. C .
                  Antennule, lateral view. D . Antenna, lateral view. C–D: only selected setae
                  illustrated. </p>
            <p> Table 2. Comparison of selected diagnostic characters for all known species of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia Dahl, 1985 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
            <p> Species Ommatidia Eye Eye shape Antennular Antennule Mandibular palp Mandibular
                  Maxilla II: Maxilla II: Pleonites VI–VII: Pleopod I: Pleonite IV: Source pigment
                  scale: peduncle 2 nd article: palp: 2 nd article endopod articles exopod length
                  posterodorsal exopod epimeron length/ 4 th article: setae vs proximal border,
                  denticles lateral posterior corner width distal spine seta 3 margin +
                  posterolateral border, denticles <tp:taxon-name> S. typhlops </tp:taxon-name> No
                  No Almost &gt; 2:1 1 Distal longer than Seta&gt; half Limit between Exopod
                  slightly Length about 2 Smooth Corner Sars (1896) , (G.O. Sars, rectangular,
                  proximal1; setae length of article articles hard shorter than times width; distal
                  acute +denticles Dahl (1985) 1870) longer than smooth (?)2 to distinguish; endopod
                  first third: slightly triangular, high; proximal articles subequal article
                  triangular, distally distally acute half higher rounded to slightly than distal
                  pointed <tp:taxon-name> S. biscayensis </tp:taxon-name> No No Elongated, &gt; 2:1
                  0 Distal slightly longer Seta&gt; half Limit between Exopod &lt; Triangular; 12
                  setae Corner Ledoyer Ledoyer, 1998 inferior margin than proximal; setae length of
                  article articles not half length of distally acute (proximal acute +denticles
                  (1998) distal half plumose defined endopod half)+12 triangular, convex spines
                  (distal distally acute half) <tp:taxon-name> S. kunyensis </tp:taxon-name> Yes No
                  Oval, ~ 2:1 1 Two setae at distal Both setae&gt; Limit between Exopod&gt;
                  Elongated (&gt; 2 7 spines Corner Ledoyer Ledoyer, 2000 elongated end of second
                  third, half length of articles hard endopod first times longer than (mostly along
                  acute +denticles (2000) one slightly longer; article to distinguish; article
                  wide); distally distal half) distally rounded setae smooth (?)2 articles subequal
                  rounded <tp:taxon-name> S. cristoboi </tp:taxon-name> Numerous, Yes (red- Slightly
                  longer 2.3:1 1 Distal&gt; 2 times Seta &lt;half Limit between Exopod&gt; Length 2
                  times Smooth Corner Moreira Moreira et al ., extending orange) than high; length
                  of proximal; length of article articles well- endopod first width or less, acute
                  +acute et al. 2003 for most of dorsal and setae setulose on defined; proximal
                  article parallel sides; distal spine-like (2003b) eye ventral margins distal half
                  longer than distal end bluntly rounded denticles convex <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        urgorrii </tp:taxon-name> Numerous, Yes (red, Longer than 1.8:1 1 Distal&gt;
                  2 times Seta ¼ length of Limit between Exopod&gt; Length 2 times Smooth Corner
                  ending in Moreira Moreira et al ., at least orange, high; dorsal length of
                  proximal; article articles well- endopod first width, parallel large triangular et
                  al. 2003 along distal dark) and ventral distal: setulose on defined; distal
                  article sides; distal end process, tooth- (2003b); ¾ of eye margins distal half;
                  proximal: slightly longer bluntly rounded shaped+denticles McCormack running
                  almost setulose along full than proximal triangular, et al . (2016) parallel
                  length distally rounded to slightly pointed S. pseudo- No No Oblong, length 2.5:1
                  0? Distal slightly longer Seta&gt; half Limit between Exopod &lt; Proximal ¾ with
                  7 +2 spines Corner Petryashov <tp:taxon-name> typhlops </tp:taxon-name> 1.4 times
                  than proximal; setae length of article articles well- endopod first parallel
                  sides; distal (distal half) acute +denticles (2016) Petryashov, height smooth (?)2
                  defined; proximal article third triangular, with parallel 2016 longer than distal
                  acute sides and distal third triangular, acute <tp:taxon-name> S. ledoyeri
                  </tp:taxon-name> 10–20, No (at least Slightly longer 2.2:1 1 Distal&gt; 2 times
                  Seta about half Limit between Exopod&gt; Elongated; distal Smooth Corner This work
                  sp. nov. mostly in fixed than high; length of proximal; length of article articles
                  weakly endopod first third: slightly acute +denticles along eye specimens) distal
                  third distal: smooth; defined; distal article;&lt;half triangular, distally
                  triangular, distal half becoming proximal: setulose on longer than length of
                  rounded to pointed distally acute gradually distal half proximal endopod
                  compressed laterally; ventral margin concave on distal half </p>
            <p> 1 Sars (1896) only mentions and illustrates one distal seta that is longer than
                  article; Dahl (1985) illustrates two setae, distal seta seems broken but it might
                  be longer than proximal one </p>
            <p> (cf. Sars 1896 : table IV, fig. 12). 2 Drawings included in original description
                  illustrate setae with smooth borders; description does not state whether they are
                  smooth or setulose/plumose. </p>
            <p> 3 The mandibular palp second article of <tp:taxon-name> S. kunyensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> bears two setae located at the same level; remaining species bear
                  one distal and one proximal seta. </p>
            <p> Description of male </p>
            <p> TL 3.3–3.925 mm , RL 0.525 –0.675 mm , DCL 1.275 –1.675 mm , LCL 1.6–2.05 mm , CH
                  1–1.3 mm . Carapace proportions similar to females ( Fig. 16A ), LCL about 1.5–1.6
                  times CH . Ommatidia irregularly distributed along distal half or ¾ of eye ( Fig.
                  16B ). Antennular scale proportionally longer than in females (2.2–2.45 times as
                  long as wide) ( Fig. 16C ); flagellum with up to 6–7 articles, thicker than in
                  females. Antenna peduncle third article lateral margin with similar setation as in
                  females; flagellum with many articles (&gt; 30) but not surpassing TL ( Fig. 16D
                  ). Pleopod IV protopod posterior margin with three serrations. Pleonites VI–VII
                  denticles elongated, more pointed than in females. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Known species of <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia </tp:taxon-name> can be distinguished
                  by whether or not eyes are provided with ommatidia / pigment and lateral margin of
                  pleopod I exopod is provided with setae, as well as by the eye shape, features of
                  maxilla II exopod and endopod and pleonites denticles ( Table 2 ). <tp:taxon-name>
                        Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is characterised by the
                  following combination of characters: the rostrum is about 2.4– 2.5 times as long
                  as wide, the eye is provided with ommatidia (10–20) and lacks pigment, the eye is
                  gradually compressed laterally along distal third and towards anterior margin, the
                  eye ventral margin is concave along distal half, the antennular scale is about 2.2
                  times as long as wide, the second article of the mandibular palp bears one seta on
                  lateral surface about 0.5 times as long as article and one subterminal seta longer
                  than the third article, the distal article of the endopod of the maxilla II is
                  about 1.8 times as long as the proximal article, the exopod of the maxilla II is
                  clearly longer than the proximal article of the endopod, the posterodorsal border
                  of pleonites VI–VII are provided with distally rounded to pointed denticles, the
                  protopod of pleopod IV has three serrations along the posterior border and the
                  posterolateral corner is acutely pointed, and the uropods are shorter than the
                  pleonite VII and anal somite combined. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. mainly differs
                  from <tp:taxon-name> S. typhlops </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> S. biscayensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> S. pseudotyphlops </tp:taxon-name> in having
                  eyes provided with ommatidia. Furthermore, <tp:taxon-name> S. typhlops
                  </tp:taxon-name> also differs in that the two articles of the maxilla II endopod
                  are subequal ( Sars 1896 : fig. 14), the proximal seta of the mandibular palp
                  second article is more than two thirds of the length of the article whereas in
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is only half the
                  length of the article, and the pleopod V–VI have more stout distal/distolateral
                  setae according to Sars (1896) (V: 5, VI: 5 vs 3/ 3); <tp:taxon-name> S. typhlops
                  </tp:taxon-name> also seems a larger species, reaching 9 mm in length ( Sars 1896
                  ) whereas the largest mature specimens of <tp:taxon-name> S. ledoyeri
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. only reach 4 mm . In turn, <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        biscayensis </tp:taxon-name> has elongated eyes, the fourth article of the
                  antennule peduncle lacks the distal robust seta bearing instead one long simple
                  seta similar to those along the medial margin, the pleopod I exopod is provided
                  with ‘spines’ along the lateral border (as it happens in <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        kunyensis Ledoyer, 2000 </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        pseudotyphlops </tp:taxon-name> ) and the pleopod I protopod bears a row of
                  simple, long setae along the proximal half of the posterior border instead of only
                  one shorter seta (cf. Ledoyer 1998 : fig. 2 vs Fig. 15A ); <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        pseudotyphlops </tp:taxon-name> has a comparatively longer antennular scale,
                  the proximal article of the maxilla II endopod is longer than the distal one, the
                  pleopod IV protopod has an even posterior margin and the posterodorsal denticles
                  of pleonites VI–VII are acute distally. On the other hand, <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        kunyensis </tp:taxon-name> is also provided with ommatidia but differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. ledoyeri </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. in having oval
                  elongated eyes, the two articles of the maxilla II endopod are subequal, the
                  proximal seta of the mandibular palp second article is comparatively longer and
                  the denticles along the lateral border of the pleonite IV epimeron are distally
                  rounded instead of being acute. <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from the shallow-water species, <tp:taxon-name>
                        S. cristoboi </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> S. urgorrii
                  </tp:taxon-name> , in lacking eye pigment and in the shape of the eyes, that has
                  distal and ventral margins parallel in <tp:taxon-name> S. urgorrii
                  </tp:taxon-name> and convex in <tp:taxon-name> S. cristoboi </tp:taxon-name> ; the
                  aforementioned species also bear proportionally shorter denticles along
                  posterodorsal borders of pleonites VI–VII that are always distally rounded, the
                  distal long seta of the mandibular palp second article bears short setules along
                  distal half instead of being naked, and the proximal article of the maxilla II
                  endopod is longer than the distal one in <tp:taxon-name> S. cristoboi
                  </tp:taxon-name> while the distal article is, in turn, only slightly longer in
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. urgorrii </tp:taxon-name> . Finally, the description of
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. typhlops occidentalis </tp:taxon-name> is brief but it
                  shows that the rostrum is wider basally than that of <tp:taxon-name> S. ledoyeri
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. and the furca is about as long as the pleonite VII and
                  the anal somite combined instead of the former being clearly shorter; Hessler
                  &amp; Sanders (1965) also mention that the mandible is provided with “two large
                  setae on second segment of palp” whereas in <tp:taxon-name> Sarsinebalia ledoyeri
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. the length of the proximal seta is about one third of
                  the distal one. </p>
            <p> On the other hand, <tp:taxon-name> S. typhlops </tp:taxon-name> has been previously
                  recorded in the Mediterranean at deep-sea depths ( Lo Bianco 1903 ). Ledoyer
                  (1997) also reports <tp:taxon-name> S. typhlops </tp:taxon-name> from southern
                  France in <tp:taxon-name> Posidonia </tp:taxon-name> beds at a shallow depth ( 11
                  m ); the only examined specimen corresponded to one ovigerous female but this
                  mostly differs from the description by Dahl (1985) in having eyes that are
                  provided with many ommatidia (ca 40 each), the maxilla II has an endopod with the
                  two articles clearly defined, the distal one being slightly longer than the
                  proximal, and the maxilla II exopod is clearly longer than the proximal article of
                  the endopod. In fact, this description fits better with that of <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        urgorrii </tp:taxon-name> , that is mostly present in shallow waters as
                  well; the shape of the eyes and the denticulation of pleonite IV epimeron, as
                  illustrated by Ledoyer (1997) is also very similar to that of <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        urgorrii </tp:taxon-name> (cf. Ledoyer 1997 : fig. 5 and Moreira et al .
                  2003b : figs 8f and 14g ). Therefore, previous records of <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        typhlops </tp:taxon-name> in shallow waters and into the Mediterranean might
                  correspond to other taxa and deserve further revision ( McCormack et al . 2016 ;
                  Latry &amp; Droual 2020 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Ecology </p>
            <p> This species was collected from the crater of the Gemini MV and was the most
                  abundant species in a box core sample. The sediments (mud breccia) yielded a
                  highly diverse macrofaunal assemblage (ca 50 species) characterized by the
                  presence of mega-epifauna (Pennatulacea, Hydrozoans, Crinoids), the chemosymbiotic
                  species <tp:taxon-name> Siboglinum </tp:taxon-name> spIb (as in Hilário et al.
                  2010 ), and numerous species of peracarid crustaceans. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Only known from the type locality, Gemini MV ( 418 m depth), in the Moroccan margin
                  of the Gulf of Cadiz (this study; Fig. 1 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
