<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Luciobrotula Smith &amp; Radcliffe 1913</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773703</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F287DFFF89FFEA3E4AFE5B948E5661</uri>
         <article-title>Integrative taxonomy reveals a rare and new cusk-eel species of Luciobrotula (Teleostei, Ophidiidae) from the Solomon Sea, West Pacific</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1361</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula
Smith &amp; 
Radcliffe, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Molecular phylogeny and species delimitation
</p>
      <p>
The 
COI
dataset comprised 13 aligned sequences including three newly obtained sequences from the collected specimens, three additional sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. bartschi
</tp:taxon-name>
from the South 
China
Sea and Western Australia, five sequences of 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. coheni
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Eastern Pacific, plus two outgroup sequences (
Table 1
). The length of the aligned sequences of the dataset is 618 bp. 
Figure 2
shows the phylogenetic tree inferred from the ML analysis based on the dataset. The monophyly of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula
</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly supported (bootstrap value =98%), and ingroup sequences form three clades or lineages among which two contain sequences from the two known species (
Fig. 2
). While two of our newly obtained sequences (ASIZP 0913925 and 
PNG
1082) fall into the 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. bartschi
</tp:taxon-name>
clade, the third one (
PNG
2363) appears to be a previously unknown lineage. Advanced species delimitation analyses with ABGD and bPTP based on the same 
COI
dataset reveal a congruent result with a prediction of three OTUs, corroborating the phylogenetic finding (
Fig. 2
). The delimited OTUs (or inferred species) are genetically distinct from each other. The unknown lineage is distinct from others by 37 unique nucleotide sites based on CBB analysis. The average genetic distances measured using the K2P model among them are from 0.130 to 0.138 at the 
COI
locus. Further morphological examination on the specimens indicates that the features of the sample collected from the Solomon Sea (
PNG
2363) are unique among all known 
<tp:taxon-name>
Luciobrotula
species
</tp:taxon-name>
(see below), and we validate it herein as a new species.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
