<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Deltochilum nonstriatum González-Alvarado &amp; Vaz-De 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5589709</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F48795DC50FFBCA614A6C2FB8BFDF7</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the Deltohyboma Lane, 1946 gilli species group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae: Deltochilum)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Deltochilum nonstriatum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
563D19C2-0450-4A9E-A4DC-B4AD395F25F0
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1C
, 
2C
, 
3C, G
, 
4C
, 
5C
, 
6C
, 
7C, G
, 
8C
, 
10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
jocelynae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
by having the striae I–VII inconspicuous (
Figs 1B–C
, 
4B–C
) including apically (
Fig. 5B–C
). However, it can be distinguished by presenting the largest and densest interstrial punctures (
Fig. 4C
), as well as densest punctures on the head frons (
Fig. 2C
) and on the pronotal disc (
Fig. 3C, G
); finally, by the irregular shiny points on the pronotal disc (
Fig. 3C, G
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From Latin 
non
- 'not' + 
stria
in reference to the inconspicuous elytral striae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
VENEZUELA
• 

1 
♂

; 
Bolívar
, 
km 40 Sta. [Santa] Elena
, 
Icabaru Road
; 
7°26′20″ N
, 
61°33′30″ W
; alt. 

1000 m

; 

4–6 Aug. 1986

; 
B.D. Gill
leg.; [aedeagus and endophallus extracted]; 
CMNEN
WSD00041746
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS AND COLOR. 
Holotype
male, length 
8.4 mm
, humeral width 
5.2 mm
. Dark green with red reflections dorsally (
Fig. 1C
). Black ventrally, with shiny red reflections on anterior area of metaventral process, meso- and metafemora and ventrite VI (
Fig. 6C
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 2C
). Dorsal inter-ocular distance approximately seven times width of one eye. Punctures on frons separated by less than one diameter of each puncture, almost contiguous. Punctures on head disc separated by less than one diameter of each puncture.
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM (
Fig. 3C, G
). Medial angle projected. Punctures on the disc separated by less than one diameter, almost contiguous. Shiny points on disc irregular and contiguous to punctures.
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA (
Figs 1C
, 
4C
). Carina of the ninth interstria surpassing middle of elytral length. Striae I–VIII inconspicuous including apically (
Fig. 5C
), only in some parts striae slightly visible and very narrow. Punctures of second and third interstriae on disc separated by less than one diameter. Punctures of third interstria on disc occupying about 
1
⁄ 
10
th
the distance between striae II and III. Apical tubercles on interstriae III, V–VII (
Fig. 5C
).
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Fig. 6C
). Width of expansion of ventrite I, on ventrite III, narrower than distance between clypeal teeth; expansion reaching distal margin of ventrite IV. Margins of expansion between ventrites II–IV forming an acute angle. Apex of expansion rounded. Basal area of expansion with punctures separated by less than one diameter, almost contiguous.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Apex of mesotibia on ventral-internal margin with a small spatulate expansion. Expansion of metafemur twice wider than the width of metafemur basal to expansion. Internal margin of metatibia with large tubercles, occupying almost all metatibial length.</p>
      <p>
PYGIDIUM (
Fig. 5C
). Most of the punctures separated by less than one diameter; punctures basally denser that punctures on disc; basal punctures contiguous. Discal punctures occupying approximately 
1/28
th
the width on middle of pygidium.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
FigS 7C
, 
8C
). Aedeagus as described in the 
<tp:taxon-name>
gilli
</tp:taxon-name>
species group. Medial endophallite almost straight. Sub-medial area of endophallus with scales (
Fig. 8C
, arrow).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 10.
Distribution map of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
gilli
</tp:taxon-name>
species group. Blue circle = 
<tp:taxon-name>
Deltochilum gilli
González-Alvarado &amp; Vaz-de-Mello, 2021
</tp:taxon-name>
; yellow square = 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. jocelynae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; red star = 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
nonstriatum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; green triangle = 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
quasistriatum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; white eight-point star = 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
tenuistriatum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This species is only known from the 
holotype
. The 
holotype
has an identification label from François Génier (CMNEN), in which he recognised this specimen as probably being a new species since 1998. The transcription of the label as follows: [handwritten] 
<tp:taxon-name>DELTOCHILUM</tp:taxon-name>
/? SP. NOV. / [printed] Dét. F. Génier, 199 [handwritten]8.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Known distribution
</p>
      <p>
VENEZUELA
. 
Bolívar
: km 40 Santa Elena, Icabarú Road (
Fig. 10
, red star).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
