<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Deltochilum quasistriatum González-Alvarado &amp; Vaz-De 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5590369</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/61009A92CBCEEA90963CD8387F496B8F</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the Deltohyboma Lane, 1946 gilli species group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae: Deltochilum)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Deltochilum quasistriatum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn: lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E7290E3C-1482-481C-AAAC-E0C44D7432DE
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1D
, 
2D
, 
3D
, 
4D
, 
5D
, 
6D
, 
7D
, 
8D
, 
10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
tenuistriatum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
by having striae I–VII conspicuous (
Figs 1D–E
, 
4D–E
), but III–VII successively thinner and more ill-defined and the pronotal disc with irregular shiny points contiguous with punctures (
Fig. 3D–E
). However, it can be distinguished by having the first stria wider than second, largest interstrial punctures (
Fig. 4D
) and by the pygidial punctures which are largest and densest (
Fig. 5D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From latin 
quasi
- 'almost' + 
stria
in reference to the ill-defined striae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
GUYANA
• 

1 
♂

; 
Mazaruni-Potaro District
, 
Takutu Mountains
; 
6°15′ N
, 
59°5′ W
; 

18 Dec. 1983

; 
P.D. Perkins
and 
W.E. Steiner
leg.; 
window trap
, 
mountain rainforest, near logging area
; EARTHWATCH Research Expedition; [aedeagus and endophallus extracted]; 
CMNEN
WSD00041744
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS AND COLOR. 
Holotype
male, length 
8.1 mm
, humeral width 
5.1 mm
. Dark green with red reflections on pronotum, elytra dark brown with some red reflections (
Fig. 1D
). Dark brown ventrally, with few shiny red reflections on ventrite VI and meso- and meta-legs light brown (
Fig. 6D
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 2D
). Dorsal inter-ocular distance approximately seven times width of one eye. Punctures on frons separated by less than one diameter of each puncture, almost contiguous. Punctures on head disc separated by one diameter of each puncture.
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM (
Fig. 3D
). Medial angle projected. Punctures on the disc separated by less than one diameter, almost contiguous. Shiny points on disc irregular and contiguous to punctures.
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA (
Figs 1D
, 
4D
). Carina of ninth interstria reaching middle of elytral length. Punctures on first stria subequal in size to second stria, but denser. Striae I–VII conspicuous. First stria slightly wider than second stria. Striae III–VII narrow and ill-defined, successively narrower and more ill-defined, with VII almost inconspicuous. Width third stria approximately 
1/40
th
of distance between striae II and III. Stria VIII conspicuous only laterally, discontinuous in some parts and reaching apex of carina of the ninth interstria. Punctures of second and third interstriae on disc separated by less than one diameter. Punctures of third interstria on disc occupying about 
1/10
th
of the distance between striae II and III. Apical tubercles on interstriae III, V–VII (
Fig. 5D
).
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Fig. 6D
). Width of expansion of the ventrite I, on ventrite III, subequal to distance between clypeal teeth; expansion reaching middle of ventrite IV. Margins of expansion between ventrites II–IV forming an acute angle. Apex of expansion truncate. Basal area of expansion with punctures separated by less than one diameter, almost contiguous.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Apex of mesotibia on ventral-internal margin with a small spatulate expansion. Expansion of metafemur 1.8 × wider than the width of metafemur basal to expansion. Internal margin of metatibia with large tubercles, occupying almost all metatibial length.</p>
      <p>
PYGIDIUM (
Fig. 5D
). Most of the punctures separated by less than one diameter; punctures basally denser than punctures on disc; basal punctures almost contiguous. Discal punctures occupying approximately 1/29 
th
the width on middle of pygidium.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
Figs 7D
, 
8D
). Aedeagus as described in the 
<tp:taxon-name>
gilli
</tp:taxon-name>
species group. Medial endophallite sinuate. Sub-medial area of endophallus with scales.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This species is only known from the 
holotype
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Known distribution
</p>
      <p>
Guyana
. 
Cuyuni-mazaruni
, Takutu Mountains (
Fig. 10
, green triangle).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
