<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Deltochilum gilli Gonzalez-Alvarado
                        &amp; Vaz-de-Mello 2021</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5590367</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F48795DC5FFFB4A6C9A50FFBACFE80</uri>
                  <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the Deltohyboma Lane, 1946 gilli species
                        group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae: Deltochilum)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature> The <tp:taxon-name> gilli </tp:taxon-name> species group </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> BODY ( Fig. 1 ). Medium-sized species, length 8–8.4 mm , humeral width 5.1–5.2 mm . </p>
            <p> HEAD ( Fig. 2 ). Eyes large, inter-ocular distance seven to nine times width of one
                  eye. Clypeal median emargination broadly u-shaped. Clypeal teeth separated
                  approximately by 1.5 times the basal width of a tooth. Anterior margin of the
                  clypeus, between clypeal teeth, concave and expanded posteriorly into triangular
                  shape. </p>
            <p> PRONOTUM ( Fig. 3 ). Margin between anterior and medial angle subconcave. Medial
                  angle of pronotum rounded to projected. Punctures almost with the same size, basal
                  punctures only slightly larger than discal punctures. Pronotal disc with shiny
                  points well-defined ( Fig. 3F , arrows), separated between each other and
                  separated or contiguous to punctures; or irregular ( Fig. 3G , arrows), contiguous
                  between to each other and to punctures. </p>
            <p> ELYTRA ( Fig. 4–5 ). Interstriae with shiny points mixed with the punctures.
                  Interstriae VI and VII with basal carina almost identical in size. Carina of ninth
                  interstria reaching middle of elytral length or slightly surpassing it. Striae
                  I–VIII inconspicuous including apically, only in some parts striae slightly
                  visible and very narrow or striae I–VII conspicuous and narrow, width of third
                  stria 1/30 th or 1/40 th of the distance between stria II and III. If conspicuous,
                  first stria widest and either striae III–VII subequal in width or striae III–VII
                  ill-defined, successively narrower and more ill-defined, with VII almost
                  inconspicuous, and stria VIII conspicuous apical and laterally or only laterally;
                  in both discontinuous in some parts and reaching the apex of carina of the ninth
                  interstria. Apex of elytra with tubercles on interstriae III–VII or III, V–VII (
                  Fig. 5 ). </p>
            <p> METAVENTRITE ( Fig. 6 ). With weak posterior excavation, occupying approximately the
                  metaventral basal fourth. Disc with conspicuous punctures at 8 × magnification.
                  Disc punctures at least twice smaller than punctures on anterior-lateral area of
                  metaventral process and dispersed, separated at least by three diameters of a
                  puncture. Punctures on anterior-lateral area of metaventral process separated by
                  less than one diameter. Anterior-medial area of metaventral process with few and
                  smaller punctures than anteriorlateral ones. </p>
            <p>LEGS. Ventral surface of protibia with a weak carina. Posterior edge of metafemur
                  with two margins, one dorsal and other one ventral.</p>
            <p> MALE. Protibial spur broad and foliaceus. Mesofemur modified, with slight sinuosity
                  on apical third.Apex of mesotibia wider than female and on ventral-internal margin
                  with a small or large spatulate expansion. Metatrochanter modified or not, if
                  modified with an expansion on distal third. Metafemur with steep tapering on basal
                  third, with expansion on posterior-ventral margin, before that steep tapering.
                  Internal margin of metatibia with small or large tubercles. Ventrite I expanded
                  posteriorly, expansion reaching from the middle of ventrite IV to almost the
                  distal margin of ventrite V; width of expansion on ventrite III variable, narrower
                  to wider than distance between clypeal teeth. Genitalia ( Figs 7–8 ). Paramera
                  subtriangular, with dorsal and ventral edges straight in lateral view. Apex of
                  paramera rounded in dorsal view. Paramera with short and thin apical-dorsal notch
                  ( Fig. 7 , arrows). Medial area of endophallus with one endophallite ( Fig. 8 ).
                  Basal circular shape endophallite with ring very thin and handle strongly
                  broadened medially. </p>
            <p> FEMALE ( Fig. 9 ). Protibial spur thinner than that of male and spiniform. Apex of
                  mesotibia narrower than that of male. Metatrochanter not modified. Meso- and
                  metafemur not modified. Internal margin of metatibia without tubercles.
                  Metasternal disc with posterior excavation smaller than male. Ventrite V as wide
                  as ventrite VI medially. Ventrite VI narrowed medially. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 1. Habitus of members of the <tp:taxon-name> gilli </tp:taxon-name> species group. A
            . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> Deltochilum gilli </tp:taxon-name> González- Alvarado
            &amp; Vaz-de-Mello, 2021, CNCI 379888. B . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D. jocelynae
            </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CNCI 379889. C . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . nonstriatum
            </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041746. D . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D .
                  quasistriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041744. E . Holotype of
                  <tp:taxon-name> D . tenuistriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041745. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p> Composition </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Deltochilum gilli González-Alvarado &amp; Vaz-de-Mello, 2021
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> D . jocelynae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ,
                        <tp:taxon-name> D . nonstriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , <tp:taxon-name>
                        D . quasistriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. and <tp:taxon-name> D .
                        tenuistriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 2. Head of members of the <tp:taxon-name> gilli </tp:taxon-name> species group. A .
            Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> Deltochilum gilli </tp:taxon-name> González- Alvarado &amp;
            Vaz-de-Mello, 2021, CNCI 379888. B . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D. jocelynae
            </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CNCI 379889. C . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . nonstriatum
            </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041746. D . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D .
                  quasistriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041744. E . Holotype of
                  <tp:taxon-name> D . tenuistriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041745. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> This species group is only known from few (eight) specimens and their biology is
                  poorly known. The specimens were collected above 680 m a.s.l. and the highest
                  record is 1411 m a.s.l. ( one specimen does </p>
            <p> Fig. 3. Pronotum of members of the <tp:taxon-name> gilli </tp:taxon-name> species
                  group. A . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> Deltochilum gilli </tp:taxon-name>
                  González- Alvarado &amp; Vaz-de-Mello, 2021, CNCI 379888. B . Holotype of
                        <tp:taxon-name> D. jocelynae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CNCI 379889. C .
                  Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . nonstriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN
                  WSD00041746. D . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . quasistriatum </tp:taxon-name>
                  sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041744 E . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . tenuistriatum
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041745. F . Miscrosculpture of pronotal
                  disc, Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D. jocelynae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. G .
                  Miscrosculpture pronotal disc, Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . nonstriatum
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. White arrows show the shiny points. </p>
            <p> Fig. 4. Elytra of members of the <tp:taxon-name> gilli </tp:taxon-name> species
                  group. A . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> Deltochilum gilli </tp:taxon-name>
                  González- Alvarado &amp; Vaz-de-Mello, 2021, CNCI 379888. B . Holotype of
                        <tp:taxon-name> D. jocelynae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CNCI 379889. C .
                  Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . nonstriatum </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN
                  WSD00041746. D . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . quasistriatum </tp:taxon-name>
                  sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041744. E . Holotype of <tp:taxon-name> D . tenuistriatum
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , CMNEN WSD00041745. </p>
            <p> not have altitude information). They were collected using pitfall traps baited with
                  human dung ( five specimens ), carrion ( one specimen ) as well as via window trap
                  ( one specimen ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
