<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Phanacis urhani Azmaz &amp; Katilmiş 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5076157</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B76A6C60FC9C86600440FECC996F0B3B</uri>
         <article-title>Three new species of herb gall wasps (Hymenoptera: Cynipidae) from Turkey</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1421</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Phanacis urhani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
9804711C-52E3-4E4B-989B-A8C0A912F011
</p>
      <p>
Figs 7–8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Together with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phanacis caulicola
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. hypochoeridis
(Kieffer, 1887)
</tp:taxon-name>
form a group of species in which scutellar foveae separated by a central carina; radial cell partially opened along wing margin. Most closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. caulicola
</tp:taxon-name>
, but in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. urhani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
POL 1.8 times as long as OOL and 3.6 times as long as diameter of lateral ocellus; notauli extending to half-length of scutum; median mesoscutal line absent; areolet distinct, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. caulicola
POL
</tp:taxon-name>
1.2 times as long as OOL and 3.0 times as long as diameter of lateral ocellus; notauli distinctly impressed only in posterior half, reaching pronotum but very indistinct, shallow; median mesoscutal line usually longer, reaching at least to ⅓ of scutum length; areolet absent.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>In honour of Prof. Dr Raşit Urhan who is a senior acarologist.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
TURKEY
• 
♀
; 
Ordu Province
, 
Akkuş
, 
Yolbaşı
; 
40°42′ N
, 
37°00′ E
; 

980 m

a.s.l.; ex 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cirsium vulgare
(Savi) Ten., 1835
</tp:taxon-name>
–36 (
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
); 
M. Azmaz
and 
Y. Katılmış
leg.; gall collected 

14 Mar. 2019

; adult emerged 
Jul. 2019
; 
PAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
TURKEY
• 
2 ♀♀
; 
Ordu Province
; same collection data as for holotype; 
PAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>LENGTH. 1.8–2.0 mm.</p>
      <p>COLOURATION. Head and mesosoma black, metasoma dark brown. Antennae dark brown, legs light brown to yellowish, with darker coxae. Wing veins distinct, brown.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Delicately coriaceous to alutaceous, with uniformly sparse white setae, 1.9–2.0 times as broad as long from above, 1.1 times as broad as high and slightly broader than mesosoma. Gena alutaceous, not broadened behind eye; not visible behind eye in front view. Malar space coriaceous, 0.6–0.7 times as long as height of eye, with delicate striae, radiating from clypeus and nearly reaching inner margin of eye. POL 1.8 times as long as OOL; 2.1 times as long as LOL and 3.6 times as long as diameter of lateral ocellus. Transfacial distance 1.3 times as long as height of eye; diameter of antennal torulus 2.2 times as long as distance between them and 0.7 times as long as distance between torulus and eye margin. Lower face with striae, radiating from clypeus and nearly reaching eye and antennal sockets, median elevated area slightly coriaceous with interrupted striae. Clypeus with striae, very narrow and small; with very indistinct anterior tentorial pits, epistomal sulcus and clypeo-pleurostomal line indistinct, ventral margin nearly straight. Frons, vertex and occiput delicately coriaceous to alutaceous. Postgena alutaceous, with more dense setae than on front of head.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Phanacis ciceki
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, mature gall on host plant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Picris
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(photos by Y. Katılmış).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Phanacis urhani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀. 
a
. Head in anterior view. 
b
. Mesosoma in dorsal view. 
c
. Metasoma in lateral view. 
d
. Head in dorsal view. 
e
. Scutum in dorsal view. 
f
. Scutellum in dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>ANTENNA. 13-segmented, longer than head+mesosoma; pedicel 1.5 times as long as broad; F1 1.9 times as long as pedicel and F1 1.2 times as long as F2, F2 equal F3; placodeal sensilla F2–F11.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Convex, longer than high in lateral view, with uniform very sparse white setae. Pronotum uniformly alutaceous dorsally, uniformly delicately coriaceous laterally; anterior margin with more dense setae. Submedian pronotal pits indistinct, in form of transverse impression, medially separated by a narrow carina. Scutum broader than long, 1.6 times as long as scutellum, uniformly coriaceous to alutaceous. Notauli distinctly impressed, extending to half-length of scutum; median mesoscutal line absent; parapsidal lines narrow, extending slightly above tegula level; anterior parallel lines narrow, distinct, extending to ⅓ of scutum length. Scutellum rounded with very sparse setae, as long as broad; dull rugose along sides and posteriorly, more delicately coriaceous towards centre of disk. Scutellar foveae separated by a central carina, indistinctly delimited posteriorly, with irregular longitudinal rugae. Mesopleuron uniformly reticulate; mesopleural triangle reticulate, with setae. Metapleural sulcus reaching mesopleuron above ½ of its height; axillula very narrow wrinkled, with white setae; subaxillular bar smooth, shining, narrower than height of metanotal trough; metapleuron wrinkled, rugose. Dorsellum rugose, very narrowly medially or invisible; ventral impressed area rugose. Propodeum rugose with setae, lateral propodeal carinae subparallel; central propodeal area delicately rugose, with white setae; lateral propodeal area rugose, with dense white setae; propodeal spiracle strongly elevated; nucha with some longitudinal sulci.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Phanacis urhani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀. 
a
. Mesosoma in lateral view. 
b
. Mesopleuron. 
c
. Mesosoma in posterior view. 
d
. Antenna. 
e
. Leg. 
f
. Radial cell of forewing.
</p>
      <p>FORE WING. Margin with long cilia; R1 reaching wing margin and not extending along margin (open along wing margin), radial cell partially closed, areolet distinct, Rs + M extending to half of distance between areolet and basalis. Tarsal claws narrow, without basal lobe.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Phanacis urhani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, mature gall on host plant, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cirsium vulgare
(Savi) Ten.
</tp:taxon-name>
(photos by M. Azmaz).
</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Slightly longer than high in lateral view; metasomal tergite 2 without setae anterolaterally and impunctate; only metasomal tergite 6, subsequent tergites and hypopygium with some indistinct punctures; prominent part of ventral spine of hypopygium short, with some short white setae.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Biology
</p>
      <p>
Only females are known. The adult wasps are known to induce galls on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cirsium vulgare
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
). Larvae overwinter in the gall, adults emerge next summer, in July. Another herb gall wasp, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Isocolus cirsii
Diakontschuk, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
, induces galls in flower heads of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cirsium ukranicum
Besser ex DC.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
) (
Melika 2006
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Currently known only from 
Turkey
(
Ordu
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Gall structure
</p>
      <p>
The gall is located on the stem (
Fig. 9
), in the form of an irregular swelling, 
50–80 mm
long. There are small larval cells in the typical form inside the stem. Multilocular.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
