<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Marjanus isfahanicus Zamani &amp; Chatzaki &amp; Esyunin &amp; Marusik 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4906483</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F987850367EF7B1C507919FCFF6E07</uri>
         <article-title>One new genus and nineteen new species of ground spiders (Araneae: Gnaphosidae) from Iran, with other taxonomic considerations</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.751.1381</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Marjanus isfahanicus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
9CB7FC88-C04C-4670-A98D-7A3ACC436976
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 16
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>The new species differs from the generotype by having interrupted anterior margins (vs uninterrupted), a strongly rebordered W-shaped atrium (vs inconspicuous) and round receptacles (vs tubular).</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet is an adjective and refers to 
Isfahan Province
, 
Iran
, the 
type
locality of the new species.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
♀
; 
Isfahan Province
, 
Qamsar
&amp; 
Barzok Protected Area
, 

55 km
SW of Qamsar

, 

14 km
NE of Kamoo

, 
near the road of Gargash observatory
; 
33°37′ N
, 
51°19′ E
; 

2710 m
a.s.l.

; 

19 May 2016

; 
P. Ponel
leg.; 
MHNG
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
Habitus as in 
Fig. 16A
. Total length 3.04. Carapace 1.40 long, 1.01 wide. Eye sizes and interdistance of PMEs: AME = 0.05, ALE = 0.07, PME = 0.06, PLE = 0.06, PME–PME = 0.05. Carapace and chelicerae dark brown; carapace darker at the margins, with a pattern of light patches. Chelicera with 3 promarginal teeth and 1 retromarginal tooth. Sternum, maxillae and labium light brown. Legs lighter than carapace, without annulations, tarsi lighter. Abdomen dark dorsally, light brown ventrally, without any markings. Spinnerets light gray and uniform in color. Measurements of legs: I: 3.27 (0.95, 0.63, 0.69, 0.54, 0.46), II: 3.14 (0.91, 0.52, 0.69, 0.52, 0.50), III: 2.59 (0.74, 0.37, 0.51, 0.47, 0.50), IV: 3.98 (1.08, 0.56, 0.83, 0.92, 0.59).
</p>
      <p>
Epigyne as in 
Fig. 16B–G
. Atrium with distinct and separate anterior hoods; lateral margins distinct, converging; endogyne with membranous bursae near copulatory openings; copulatory ducts thin, forming 2 screw-like, full lateral coils in mid part, straight posteriorly, with blind glandular heads, connected
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 16.
<tp:taxon-name>
Marjanus isfahanicus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (MHNG). 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B, D, F
. Epigyne, ventral view. 
C, E, G
. Epigyne, dorsal view. Scale bars: A = 0.5 mm; B = 0.2 mm; F–G = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>to ventral additional bursae with extra glandular tubes; receptacles globular, 3 times as wide as ducts, touching each other, with fertilization ducts located at their upper part.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Comments
</p>
      <p>
Based on the similarity of the epigynal conformation to that of the 
type
species, we tentatively place this species here in the absence of male specimens. However, only two of the three diagnostic elements of the females of this genus are met in this new species: the long, coiled copulatory ducts and additional anterior copulatory bursae and the receptacles being round rather than tubular. The latter character may have to be omitted from the generic diagnosis when more species are described and included in this genus.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality in 
Isfahan Province
, central 
Iran
. This is the first record of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Marjanus
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Iran
, and the second species described in this genus.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
