<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Marinarozelotes achaemenes
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D8C20D6A-0AB6-44F7-9CE1-2DFC53496DCA
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 15
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new species is mostly similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. cumensis
(Ponomarev, 1979)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. manytchensis
(Ponomarev &amp; Tsvetkov, 2006)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. malkini
(Platnick &amp; Murphy, 1984)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. mutabilis
(Simon, 1878)
</tp:taxon-name>
in that the M-shaped median ridge is at the middle to upper part of the median plate, while extending further to posterior end in the congeners. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. cumensis
</tp:taxon-name>
by its long copulatory ducts extending beyond the anterior margin (vs very short and well below the anterior margin) and from the others by the shape of atrium being wider than long (vs longer than wide).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The specific epithet is a noun in apposition, referring to the apical ancestor of the Achaemenid dynasty.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
♀
; 
Kohgiluyeh
&amp; 
Boyer-Ahmad Province
, 
Yasuj
; 
30°28′ N
, 
51°30′ E
; 

25 Jul. 1974

; 
A. Senglet
leg.; 
MHNG
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 15.
<tp:taxon-name>
Marinarozelotes achaemenes
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (MHNG). 
A–C
. Epigyne, ventral and dorsal views. 
D
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
E–F
. Chelicera, posterior and anterior views. Scale bars: A, E–F = 0.2 mm; B–C = 0.1 mm; D = 1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
Habitus as in 
Fig. 15D
. Total length 7.28. Carapace 2.42 long, 1.84 wide. Eye sizes and interdistance of PMEs: AME = 0.11, ALE = 0.13, PME = 0.15, PLE = 0.14, PME–PME = 0.05. Carapace, chelicerae, maxillae, labium and sternum light yellowish brown. Chelicera (
Fig. 15E–F
) without teeth, with a series of long, stiff anteromedian setae. Legs light yellowish and without annulations and with sparse spines. Abdomen grayish brown, with four dark gray cardiac sigilla dorsally. Spinnerets light yellowish and uniform in color. Measurements of legs: I: missing, II: 6.27 (1.76, 1.08, 1.32, 1.19, 0.92), III: 5.20 (1.41, 0.90, 0.98, 1.09, 0.82), IV: 7.98 (2.11, 1.20, 1.78, 1.89, 1.00).
</p>
      <p>
Epigyne as in 
Fig. 15A–C
. Anterior margin continuous and wide; M-shaped median ridge reaching the anterior edge of receptacles, with concave moderate grooves; copulatory ducts long, extending beyond anterior margin and folding anteriorly to form glandular outgrowths; receptacles round, almost touching each other.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality in Kohgiluyeh &amp; Boyer-Ahmad Province, southwestern 
Iran
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
