<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sphecodes uttaricus Astafurova &amp; Proshchalykin, 2020, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2020.729.1195</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/67EDAA738F4A9BB033CCEA302B5D3435</uri>
         <article-title>New and little-known bees of the genus Sphecodes Latreille, 1804 (Hymenoptera: Apoidea: Halictidae) from the Himalayas</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sphecodes uttaricus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 21
, 
22
A–E
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species is closest to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. sikkimensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. formosanus
Cockerell, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
by a combination of large body size (more than 
9 mm
), costal margin with at least nine hamuli and the presence of a lateral
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 21.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphecodes uttaricus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Holotype, ♀ (PCMS/OLBL). Habitus in lateral view and labels. Scale bar = 1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 22.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sphecodes uttaricus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Holotype, ♀ (PCMS/OLBL). 
A
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
B–C
. Head in frontal (B) and lateral view (C). 
D
. Metasoma in dorso-lateral view. 
E
. T1 in dorso-lateral view. Scale bars = 1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
preocipital carina. The new species differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. sikkimensis
</tp:taxon-name>
by having fewer hamuli (9–10 vs 12–15) and a smaller body size (
10.5 mm
vs 
12–15 mm
) and from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. formosanus
</tp:taxon-name>
it differs by having sparse and mixed punctation of T1 with coarse (15–25 μm / 0.5–3) and microscopical punctures (5 μm) (vs dense and coarse punctures separated by 0.5–1 puncture diameter).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet is named after the Indian state 
Uttar Pradesh
, the 
type
locality of this species.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
INDIA
• 
♀
; 
Uttar Pradesh
bor., 
Karnaprayag
env.; [
30°27′ N
, 
79°25′ E
]; 

770 m
a.s.l.

; 

19–21 Jul. 1994

; 
M. Valenta
leg.; 
PCMS
/ 
OLBL
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
holotype
, 
Fig. 21
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Total body length 
10.5 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 22
B–C). Black; transverse, ca 1.25 times as wide as long; lateral preoccipital carina present, well-developed; vertex elevated, distance from top of head to upper margin of lateral ocellus ca 1.5 ocellar diameter as seen in frontal view and ca two diameters as seen in dorsal view; mandibles bi-dentate; F1 0.5 times as long as wide; F2 0.7 times as long as wide; F3 1.1 times as long as wide; supraclypeal area bulging; frons and paraocular area mostly with confluent punctures; ocello-ocular area densely punctate with confluent punctures and punctures separated by at most a half puncture diameter (30–50 μm); clypeus sparser punctate with shiny, smooth interspaces equal to at most a puncture diameter; paraocular area and gena with dense plumose setae, obscuring integument.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA. Mesosoma (including legs) black; wings with strong brownish darkening and metallic violet luster; stigma and veins dark brown; hind wing with the angle between basal (
M
) and cubital (
Cu
) veins ca 70°, costal margin with nine hamuli; mesoscutum and mesoscutellum (
Fig. 22A
) densely and coarsely punctate (50–100 μm), with confluent punctures peripherally and medially with punctures separated by at most a puncture diameter; hypoepimeral area and mesepisternum coarsely reticulaterugose; propodeal triangle (metapostnotum) roughly reticulate-rugose (sculpture forming 2–3 rows of large deep cells).
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA. Metasomal T1 on disc with coarse punctures (15–25 μm) separated by 0.5–3 puncture diameters and laterally with numerous tiny punctures (ca 5 μm) between them, marginal zone sparsely and finely punctate, impunctate along posterior margin (
Fig. 22E
); remainder of terga similarly punctate, but denser and with impunctate marginal zones (
Fig. 22D
); pygidial plate dull, as wide as metabasitarsus; T1–T4 red; sterna finely tessellate to smooth with coarse shallow setal pores.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Only known from the 
holotype
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
