<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Xylothrips Lesne 1901</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4716252</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/DFD9FC3FB15FEF0D420CCFCBC00D5B9E</uri>
         <article-title>A review of the powderpost beetle genera Xylothrips Lesne, 1901 and Calophagus Lesne, 1902 (Coleoptera: Bostrichidae: Bostrichinae: Xyloperthini)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/d6aaf507-ac02-47e8-95db-47b936e625bc</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Each antennomere of antennal club with a band of golden hairs on both sides of each face; pronotum without lateral carina; punctures on elytra very fine and sparse; three pairs of marginal tubercles of declivity very reduced (
Figs 1A–B
, 
4
) ................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Calophagus pekinensis
Lesne, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Antennal club matt without sensory impression or hair bands; pronotum with ridge-like lateral carina; punctures on elytra deeper and denser; three pairs of marginal tubercles of declivity well developed (
Figs 1C–F
, 
2–3
)...............................................................................................................2

</p>
      <p>

2. Posterolateral sides of pronotum shining, glabrous without punctures; lateral callus converging into lateral margin of declivity; round tubercles on apical sutural angle of declivity. Male: frons without erect bristles in the middle or only with some bristles arranged in an arc ............................................ ......................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xylothrips flavipes
(
Illiger, 1801
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Posterolateral sides of pronotum with sparse to moderately dense punctures; lateral callus not converging into lateral margin of declivity; apical suture angle of declivity without tubercle. Male: with frontal crown formed by short but dense bristles ....... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xylothrips religiosus
(
Boisduval, 1835
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
