<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
McIntosh, 1876
</tp:taxon-name>
(emended)
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
McIntosh, 1876b: 407
</tp:taxon-name>

, pl. 73, figs 4–5.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais jeffreysi
McIntosh, 1876b: 406
</tp:taxon-name>

, pl. 72 fig. 18, pl. 73 figs 1–2 (synonymy according to 
Eliason 1962
, confirmed herein).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais heterochaeta
McIntosh, 1897b: 176
</tp:taxon-name>

, pl. 3 figs 6–10 (synonymy acc. to 
Eliason 1962
, confirmed herein).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Eusthenelais hibernica</tp:taxon-name>
–
McIntosh 1900: 425

, pl. 29 fig. 5, pl. 31 fig. 9, pl. 42 figs 9–10. 
—
Gil 2011: 937

. — 


Núñez 
et al.
2015: 233


, fig. 93.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais Jeffreysii
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

McIntosh 1900: 421

, pl. 29 fig. 4, pl. 31 fig. 7, pl. 34 fig. 13, pl. 42 figs 5–8. — 

Gil 2011: 947

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Sthenelais jeffreysi</tp:taxon-name>
–

Eliason 1962: 224

fig. 5b–h.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Parasthenelais hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Amoureux 1972: 68

, fig. 1. — 

Barnich &amp; Fiege 2003: 11

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Dorsal cirri present on segment 3. Ventral body surface and parapodial stylodes smooth. Outer elytral margin with several filiform papillae, elytral surface smooth. Neurochaetae spinigers and falcigers.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
(examined)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
:
</p>
      <p>
IRELAND
• 
syntype
; 
NE Atlantic
, 
W coast of Ireland
; depth 106 fathoms (

194 m

); “ 
Porcupine
” expedition leg.; EtOH preserved; 
BMNH 1921.5.1.620

.
</p>
      <p>
PORTUGAL
• 
syntype
; 
off Cape Sagres
; depth 45 fathoms (

82 m

); “Porcupine” expedition leg.; EtOH preserved; 
BMNH 1921.5.1.621

.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais jeffreysi
</tp:taxon-name>
:
</p>
      <p>
IRELAND
• 
holotype
; 
NE Atlantic
, 
W coast of Ireland
, station 9; 
53°16′ N
, 
12°42′ W
; depth 165 fathoms (

302 m

); 1869; “Porcupine” expedition leg.; EtOH preserved; 
BMNH 1921.5.1.616

.
</p>
      <p>
The 
syntypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais heterochaeta
</tp:taxon-name>
(type locality: 
Norway
, Osterfjorden, NE Atlantic) are probably lost.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
(examined)
</p>
      <p>
UNITED KINGDOM
• 
1 spec.
; 
NW Scotland
, Geikie Slide and Hebridean Slope; stn C05 S41 A1; 
58.38° N
, 
9.40° W
; depth 

650 m

; 

23 Jul. 2016

; sandy mud; EtOH preserved; survey code JNCC/MSS 1016S GSH; 
TUM 65469

• 

1 spec.
; same locality as for preceding; stn C11 S15 A1; 
58.45° N
, 
9.32° W
; depth 

868 m

; 

21 Jul. 2016

; coarse sandy mud; EtOH preserved; ex TUM 65481; survey code JNCC/MSS 1016S GSH; 
NMS.Z. 2020.14.4

• 

1 spec.
; same locality as for preceding; stn D03 S83 A1; 
58.29° N
, 
9.30° W
; depth 

438 m

; 

29 Jul. 2016

; sandy mud; EtOH preserved; ex TUM 65499; survey code JNCC/MSS 1016S GSH; 
NMS.Z.2020.14.1

• 

1 spec.
; same locality as for preceding; stn D11 S61 A1; 
58.40° N
, 
9.17° W
; depth 

496 m

; 

25 Jul. 2016

; sandy mud; EtOH preserved; ex TUM 65515; survey code JNCC/MSS 1016S GSH; 
NMS.Z. 2020.14.3

• 

1 spec.
; same locality as for preceding; stn F04 S90 A1; 
58.47° N
, 
8.78° W
; depth 

410 m

; 

29 Jul. 2016

; sandy mud; EtOH preserved; ex TUM 65547; survey code JNCC/MSS 1016S GSH; 
NMS.Z. 2020.14.2

• 

1 spec.
; same locality as for preceding; stn F16 S75 A1; 
58.59° N
, 
8.45° W
; depth 

450 m

; 

28 Jul. 2016

; sandy mud; EtOH preserved; ex 
TUM 65571
; survey code JNCC/MSS 1016S GSH; 
NMS.Z. 2020.14.5.
(
Fig. 8
)

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
PROSTOMIUM. Median antenna with long, smooth, tapering style; ceratophore with small auricles. Lateral antennae fused to inner side of tentaculophores, size and shape similar to dorsal tentacular cirri. Eyes indistinct (
Fig. 8A
).
</p>
      <p>
TENTACULOPHORES. Dorsal tentacular cirri long, size and shape similar to median antenna. Ventral tentacular cirri short, not reaching half the length of the dorsal ones (
Fig. 8A
).
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA. With filiform papillae on outer lateral margin and smooth surface (
Fig. 8B
).
</p>
      <p>
CIRRI. Dorsal cirri present on segment 3, size and shape similar to dorsal tentacular cirri. Ventral cirri without basal knob or long basal papillae (
Fig. 8C–D
).
</p>
      <p>
PARAPODIA. Stylodes without papillae, slender, cirriform, some slightly inflated basally. Parapodia of anterior and middle body with few stylodes present along notopodial bract, on neuropodial acicular lobe and on upper and lower parts of large, bilobed posterior neuropodial bract. Margins of neuropodial anterodorsal and anteroventral bracts smooth. Without long dorsal papillae on notopodia (
Fig. 8C–D
).
</p>
      <p>
CHAETAE. Notochaetae slender, spinous, tapering to simple capillary tip. Upper neurochaetae all slender compound spinigers. Middle neurochaetae slender compound spinigers and stout compound falcigers with short, 1–4 articled blade and bidentate tip. Lower neurochaetae slender compound falcigers with multi-articled blade and minutely bidentate tip (
Fig. 8E–G
).
</p>
      <p>
SIZE. Specimen figured: NMS.Z. 2020.14.5 (
Fig. 8
): anterior fragment, length 
45 mm
, width 
5 mm
for 98 segments. 
Syntypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
: BMNH
</tp:taxon-name>
1921.5.1.620, anterior fragment, length 
11 mm
, width 
2.5 mm
for about 28 segments; BMNH 1921.5.1.621, anterior and middle fragment, total length about 
17 mm
, width 
3.5 mm
for 31 segments (total). 
Holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais jeffreysi
: BMNH
</tp:taxon-name>
1921.5.1.616, anterior fragment, length 
18 mm
, width 
3 mm
for about 39 segments.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>The description above is emended for the terminology used in describing the parapodial bracts and stylodes and the details regarding the shape and location of the neurochaetae. The recently collected specimens of</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
McIntosh, 1876
</tp:taxon-name>
. TUM 65571. 
A
. Anterior end, left palp not figured, bent downwards. 
B
. Left elytron of segment 17. 
C
. Left parapodium of segment 19, anterior view. 
D
. Same, posterior view. 
E–G
. Neurochaetae of same, all distal part. 
E
. Upper compound spiniger. 
F
. Middle stout compound falciger. 
G
. Lower slender compound falciger. Scale bars: A=2 mm; B–D =1 mm; E–G= 100 µm.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
E. hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Geikie Slide (Northwest Scotland) were in rather good condition and proved very helpful in supplementing the diagnostic characters of the species.
</p>
      <p>
Chambers(1985)
noted that the type material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
is unidentifiable and,consequently, 
Read &amp; Fauchald (2020)
list 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais
McIntosh, 1876
</tp:taxon-name>
as a nomen dubium in WoRMS. However, especially the presence of both spinigers and bidentate falcigers as described by 
McIntosh (1876b)
is sufficient to distinguish it from other sigalionid species. The other important generic character, i.e., the presence of dorsal cirri on segment 3, was not mentioned in the original description, but later described by 
McIntosh (1900)
based on the same material (see respective remark related to generic diagnosis above). We examined the 
syntypes
, which are in rather bad condition, but we can confirm the presence of a pair of dorsal cirri on segment 
3 in
both specimens.
</p>
      <p>
In both publications (1876b, 1900) McIntosh described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais jeffreysi
</tp:taxon-name>
as different species. It is not clear why he did not realise that these are in fact synonymous, as for both species he described the two 
types
of neurochaetae and, although he did not mention the dorsal cirri in the text for 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jeffreysi
</tp:taxon-name>
, he clearly figured them in his monograph of 1900 (pl. 29 fig. 4).
</p>
      <p>
Eliason (1962)
noted that not only 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais jeffreysi
</tp:taxon-name>
, but also 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais heterochaeta
McIntosh, 1897
</tp:taxon-name>
could be possible synonyms of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
. For 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. heterochaeta
</tp:taxon-name>
again the dorsal cirri are not mentioned, but the original description of the elytral and chaetal characters leaves no doubt that this is 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
We checked the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jeffreysi
</tp:taxon-name>
and found it to be unidentifiable; moreover, the type material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. heterochaeta
</tp:taxon-name>
seems to be lost. But, as explained above, the respective original descriptions are sufficient and we confirm Eliason’s view that both 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jeffreysi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. heterochaeta
</tp:taxon-name>
are synonyms of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Compared to the other species described herein, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
presents a number of remarkable characters: The presence of a pair of dorsal cirri on segment 3 is the main differentiating character (absent in all other species). The auricles are smaller and much less obvious. The lateral antennae are of similar length to the dorsal tentacular cirri (versus distinctly shorter). The neuropodial posterior bract is large and obvious, similar to the one found in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. limicola
</tp:taxon-name>
(versus smaller and much less obvious in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. boa
</tp:taxon-name>
, or the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fimbriosthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
species).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
         <p>
Distribution and habitat
</p>
         <p>
So far only known from the NE Atlantic: recorded from off 
Norway
, along the western coasts of the British Isles and 
Ireland
, down to Southwest 
Portugal
. Occurring on muddy and sandy substrates from 
70 to 870 m
depth (see above).
</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:nomenclature/>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p>
We follow the latest subfamily designation proposed by 

Gonzalez 
et al.
(2018)

. For keys to other species currently assigned to the subfamilies 
<tp:taxon-name>Pelogeniinae</tp:taxon-name>
, Pholoinae and Pisioninae, see 
Barnich &amp; Fiege (2003)
, 

Martinez 
et al.
(2008)

and 

Meissner 
et al.
(2020)

.
</p>
            <p>
Please note: characters in the key apply to adults; in younger individuals or juveniles there is likely some variation to be observed, for example in the number of stylodes present or the degree of coverage with ventral body papillae. Elytral characters apply to anterior elytra (but not the first pair) unless otherwise stated. The distribution given for species not treated in detail herein is based on 
Barnich &amp; Fiege (2003)
, 
Wehe (2007)
and 

Núñez 
et al.
(2015)

.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
1. Median antenna indistinct or very small, without ceratophore. Outer elytral margin extended into digitiform, papillated processes ........................................................................................................ 2
</p>
            <p>
– Median antenna present, with distinct ceratophore. Outer elytral margin straight, smooth (i.e., papillae absent) or straight, papillated (papillae simple or dichotomously branched) ..................... 3
</p>
            <p>

2. Elytral marginal processes with about 20 papillae. Large papilla present on anterior side of superior margin of neuropodia (difficult to see in small individuals)................................................................ ........................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sigalion mathildae
Audouin &amp; Milne Edwards, 1832
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic, Mediterranean; nearshore)

</p>
            <p>

– Elytral marginal processes with about 10 papillae. Without papilla on neuropodia............................ ............................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sigalion squamosus
Delle Chiaje, 1830
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE and SE Atlantic, Mediterranean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
            <p>
3. Ceratophore of median antenna without auricles ............................................................................. 4
</p>
            <p>
– Ceratophore of median antenna with auricles .................................................................................. 5
</p>
            <p>

4. Outer elytral margin with irregularly dichotomously branched papillae, elytral surface smooth ...... .................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Euthalenessa oculata
(Peters, 1854)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic: south of Channel to S Africa, Mediterranean, Indian Ocean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
            <p>

– Elytral margin and surface smooth ..................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leanira hystricis
Ehlers, 1874
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE and SE Atlantic, Mediterranean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
            <p>
5. Pair of dorsal cirri present on segment 3 ......................................................................................... 6
</p>
            <p>
– Dorsal cirri absent on segment 3 ..................................................................................................... 7
</p>
            <p>

6. Neurochaetae all spinigers. Outer elytral margin with numerous filiform papillae, elytral surface smooth ..................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neoleanira tetragona
(Örsted, 1845)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Arctic, NE and SE Atlantic; offshore)

</p>
            <p>

– Neurochaetae spinigers and falcigers. Outer elytral margin with several filiform papillae, elytral surface smooth .................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
McIntosh, 1876
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic: 
Norway
, western British Isles and 
Ireland
, to SW 
Portugal
; offshore)

</p>
            <p>

7. Lateral lips of mouth with obvious labial lobes. Neurochaetae all spinigers. Elytral margin and surface smooth ..................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Labioleanira yhleni
(Malmgren, 1867)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic: south of Channel to W Africa, Mediterranean, Indian Ocean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
            <p>
– Mouth without labial lobes. Neurochaetae only falcigers or falcigers and spinigers, sometimes a few simple, spinous neurochaetae also present ...................................................................................... 8
</p>
            <p>
8. Ventral body surface and parapodial stylodes distinctly papillated ................................................. 9
</p>
            <p>
– Ventral body surface and parapodial stylodes smooth (occasionally with minute papillae in parapodia of juveniles or in anteriormost parapodia of adults)....................................................................... 10
</p>
            <p>

9. Ventral body surface densely papillated. Neuropodial posterior bracts truncate. Outer and posterior elytral margin with numerous short papillae, elytral surface covered by rounded to conical microtubercles......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fimbriosthenelais zetlandica
(McIntosh, 1876)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE and SE Atlantic, Mediterranean, Indian Ocean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
            <p>

– Ventral body surface finely papillated. Neuropodial posterior bracts bilobed. Outer elytral margin with filiform papillae, elytral surface with rounded to conical microtubercles (in anterior elytra surface completely covered, in middle and posterior elytra microtubercles confined to areas near margins) ...................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fimbriosthenelais longipinnis
(
Grube, 1869
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(E Mediterranean, Red Sea, Indo-Pacific; nearshore)

</p>
            <p>

10. Outer elytral margin with irregular extensions (anterior elytra) or notched (posterior elytra); elytral surface smooth, except for some microtubercles near anterior margin. Parapodial stylodes slender, cirriform; notopodia with few long dorsal papillae; margins of anterior neuropodial bracts smooth. Notochaetae tapering to simple capillary tip ................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais limicola
(
Ehlers, 1864
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE, NW and SE Atlantic, Mediterranean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
            <p>

– Outer elytral margin straight, with filiform papillae; elytral surface covered by conical microtubercles. Parapodial stylodes more or less club-shaped; notopodia without long dorsal papillae; margins of anterior neuropodial bracts with digitiform extensions. Notochaetae tapering to simple or minutely bidentate capillary tip ...................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais boa
(
Johnston, 1833
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic, Mediterranean, Indo-Pacific; nearshore)

</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
We follow the latest subfamily designation proposed by 

Gonzalez 
et al.
(2018)

. For keys to other species currently assigned to the subfamilies 
<tp:taxon-name>Pelogeniinae</tp:taxon-name>
, Pholoinae and Pisioninae, see 
Barnich &amp; Fiege (2003)
, 

Martinez 
et al.
(2008)

and 

Meissner 
et al.
(2020)

.
</p>
      <p>
Please note: characters in the key apply to adults; in younger individuals or juveniles there is likely some variation to be observed, for example in the number of stylodes present or the degree of coverage with ventral body papillae. Elytral characters apply to anterior elytra (but not the first pair) unless otherwise stated. The distribution given for species not treated in detail herein is based on 
Barnich &amp; Fiege (2003)
, 
Wehe (2007)
and 

Núñez 
et al.
(2015)

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>
1. Median antenna indistinct or very small, without ceratophore. Outer elytral margin extended into digitiform, papillated processes ........................................................................................................ 2
</p>
      <p>
– Median antenna present, with distinct ceratophore. Outer elytral margin straight, smooth (i.e., papillae absent) or straight, papillated (papillae simple or dichotomously branched) ..................... 3
</p>
      <p>

2. Elytral marginal processes with about 20 papillae. Large papilla present on anterior side of superior margin of neuropodia (difficult to see in small individuals)................................................................ ........................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sigalion mathildae
Audouin &amp; Milne Edwards, 1832
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic, Mediterranean; nearshore)

</p>
      <p>

– Elytral marginal processes with about 10 papillae. Without papilla on neuropodia............................ ............................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sigalion squamosus
Delle Chiaje, 1830
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE and SE Atlantic, Mediterranean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
      <p>
3. Ceratophore of median antenna without auricles ............................................................................. 4
</p>
      <p>
– Ceratophore of median antenna with auricles .................................................................................. 5
</p>
      <p>

4. Outer elytral margin with irregularly dichotomously branched papillae, elytral surface smooth ...... .................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Euthalenessa oculata
(Peters, 1854)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic: south of Channel to S Africa, Mediterranean, Indian Ocean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
      <p>

– Elytral margin and surface smooth ..................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leanira hystricis
Ehlers, 1874
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE and SE Atlantic, Mediterranean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
      <p>
5. Pair of dorsal cirri present on segment 3 ......................................................................................... 6
</p>
      <p>
– Dorsal cirri absent on segment 3 ..................................................................................................... 7
</p>
      <p>

6. Neurochaetae all spinigers. Outer elytral margin with numerous filiform papillae, elytral surface smooth ..................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neoleanira tetragona
(Örsted, 1845)
</tp:taxon-name>
(Arctic, NE and SE Atlantic; offshore)

</p>
      <p>

– Neurochaetae spinigers and falcigers. Outer elytral margin with several filiform papillae, elytral surface smooth .................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
McIntosh, 1876
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic: 
Norway
, western British Isles and 
Ireland
, to SW 
Portugal
; offshore)

</p>
      <p>

7. Lateral lips of mouth with obvious labial lobes. Neurochaetae all spinigers. Elytral margin and surface smooth ..................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Labioleanira yhleni
(Malmgren, 1867)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic: south of Channel to W Africa, Mediterranean, Indian Ocean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
      <p>
– Mouth without labial lobes. Neurochaetae only falcigers or falcigers and spinigers, sometimes a few simple, spinous neurochaetae also present ...................................................................................... 8
</p>
      <p>
8. Ventral body surface and parapodial stylodes distinctly papillated ................................................. 9
</p>
      <p>
– Ventral body surface and parapodial stylodes smooth (occasionally with minute papillae in parapodia of juveniles or in anteriormost parapodia of adults)....................................................................... 10
</p>
      <p>

9. Ventral body surface densely papillated. Neuropodial posterior bracts truncate. Outer and posterior elytral margin with numerous short papillae, elytral surface covered by rounded to conical microtubercles......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fimbriosthenelais zetlandica
(McIntosh, 1876)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE and SE Atlantic, Mediterranean, Indian Ocean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
      <p>

– Ventral body surface finely papillated. Neuropodial posterior bracts bilobed. Outer elytral margin with filiform papillae, elytral surface with rounded to conical microtubercles (in anterior elytra surface completely covered, in middle and posterior elytra microtubercles confined to areas near margins) ...................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fimbriosthenelais longipinnis
(
Grube, 1869
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(E Mediterranean, Red Sea, Indo-Pacific; nearshore)

</p>
      <p>

10. Outer elytral margin with irregular extensions (anterior elytra) or notched (posterior elytra); elytral surface smooth, except for some microtubercles near anterior margin. Parapodial stylodes slender, cirriform; notopodia with few long dorsal papillae; margins of anterior neuropodial bracts smooth. Notochaetae tapering to simple capillary tip ................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais limicola
(
Ehlers, 1864
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE, NW and SE Atlantic, Mediterranean; nearshore and offshore)

</p>
      <p>

– Outer elytral margin straight, with filiform papillae; elytral surface covered by conical microtubercles. Parapodial stylodes more or less club-shaped; notopodia without long dorsal papillae; margins of anterior neuropodial bracts with digitiform extensions. Notochaetae tapering to simple or minutely bidentate capillary tip ...................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais boa
(
Johnston, 1833
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(NE Atlantic, Mediterranean, Indo-Pacific; nearshore)

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
