<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Eusthenelais McIntosh 1876</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4650593</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B0E7DA143CD7F14BA6B4ECCF4AC4295E</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of Sthenelais Kinberg, 1856, Fimbriosthenelais Pettibone, 1971 and Eusthenelais McIntosh, 1876 (Polychaeta, Sigalionidae) in the Northeast Atlantic</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.740.1287</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais
McIntosh, 1876
</tp:taxon-name>
(emended)
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais
McIntosh, 1876b: 407
</tp:taxon-name>

(
type
species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
McIntosh, 1876
</tp:taxon-name>
). 

<tp:taxon-name>
Parasthenelais
Amoureux, 1972: 68
</tp:taxon-name>

(
type
species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
McIntosh, 1876
</tp:taxon-name>
; unjustified

</p>
      <p>name change, see remark below).</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>BODY. Elongate, with numerous segments; mid-dorsum bordered by a few pairs of small ctenidia.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>ELYTRA. Numerous, on segments 2, 4, 5, 7, continuing on alternate segments to 27, then on every segment to end of body. Dorsal tubercles on segments 3, 6, 8, continuing on alternate segments to 26.</p>
      <p>PROSTOMIUM. Rounded, fused to first segment. Median antenna inserted terminally, with stout, cylindrical ceratophore with lateral auricles and tapering style. Lateral antennae fused to inner dorsal sides of tentaculophores, without ceratophore, length equal to that of dorsal tentacular cirri. Paired palps encircled by palpal sheath emerging ventrally to tentaculophores.</p>
      <p>TENTACULOPHORES. With single aciculum, a pair of tentacular cirri, two bundles of capillary chaetae, L-shaped inner tentacular lobe with ciliated ridge and fused to palpal sheath, and dorsal tentacular crest.</p>
      <p>SEGMENT 2. With first pair of elytra, biramous parapodia and buccal cirri longer than following ventral cirri. Small ctenidia on lateral lips and medial to ventral cirri in anterior segments.</p>
      <p>SEGMENT 3. With dorsal tubercles, not fused to posterior sides of elytrophores of segment 2. Pair of dorsal cirri present.</p>
      <p>BRANCHIAE. Cirriform, absent in anteriormost segments.</p>
      <p>DORSAL CIRRI. Absent, except for segment 3.</p>
      <p>VENTRAL CIRRI. Styles without basal knob or long basal papillae.</p>
      <p>PARAPODIA. Biramous, each with up to three cup-shaped ctenidia dorsal to notopodia, noto- and neuropodial acicular lobes with accessory bracts and smooth stylodes. Notopodial acicular lobes nearly completely encircled by bract covering the basis of the notochaetae. Neuropodial acicular lobes posteriorly with large bilobed bract, anteriorly with two smaller crescent-shaped bracts.</p>
      <p>CHAETAE. Notochaetae slender, spinous, tapering to capillary tip. Neurochaetae compound falcigers and spinigers; stems of compound chaetae usually with a few rows of spines distally. Neurochaetae arranged in three groups: upper group of neurochaetae within anterodorsal bract: all slender compound spinigers. Middle group of neurochaetae within posterior bract: compound spinigers and stout compound falcigers. Lower group of neurochaetae within anteroventral bract: all slender compound falcigers.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>

Núñez 
et al.
(2015)

were the first to present an extended generic diagnosis for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
. Their diagnosis is emended herein for the terminology used in the description of the parapodial bracts and stylodes, for characters describing the tentaculophores and the location of the different neurochaetae.
</p>
      <p>
McIntosh established the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
for specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
differing from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
by the presence of compound spinigers in addition to bidentate falcigers (
McIntosh 1876b
, 
1879
, 
1900
). In the original description (
McIntosh 1876b
), he did not mention the presence of dorsal cirri on segment 3, but he refers to this character in the text and figures of his re-description of the same material (
McIntosh 1900
). The presence of dorsal cirri on segment 3 is of generic relevance and puts 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
closer to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neoleanira
Pettibone, 1970
</tp:taxon-name>
and clearly differentiates it from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fimbriosthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
, which lack any dorsal cirri. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neoleanira
</tp:taxon-name>
on the other hand differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
by the absence of any bidentate falcigers, all neurochaetae being compound spinigers (see 
Pettibone 1970
).
</p>
      <p>
We agree with 
Wehe (2007)
, 
Gil (2011)
and 
Aungtonya &amp; Eibye-Jacobsen (2014)
that the generic name 
<tp:taxon-name>
Parasthenelais
Amoureux, 1972
</tp:taxon-name>
is invalid. 
Amoureux (1972)
redescribed the species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
based on specimens collected in deep waters off the Galician coast and established a new generic name without valid reason.
</p>
      <p>
Currently, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais hibernica
</tp:taxon-name>
is the only valid representative of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais
</tp:taxon-name>
. Another species assigned to the genus, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eusthenelais abyssicola
McIntosh, 1879
</tp:taxon-name>
, was described for specimens from deep waters in the Davis Strait. However, we checked the 
holotype
(BMNH 1921.5.1.622) which is unidentifiable. The description also being insufficient, we agree with 
Hartman (1965)
and consider this to be an indeterminable sigalionid.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
