<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Electrocambala cretacea Moritz &amp; Wesener 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4985900</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/743AC20ACD162FC7C7622550F4B74973</uri>
         <article-title>Electrocambalidae fam. nov., a new family of Cambalidea from Cretaceous Burmese amber (Diplopoda, Spirostreptida)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1397</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Electrocambala cretacea
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
83055E50-E37B-4253-8C8D-F14B0A749304
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Electrocambala cretacea
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Electrocambala ornata
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
by the presence of at least two lateral ridges on the body rings (
Fig. 3C
), a prozonite without net-like ornamentation and a collum without lateral striae. Ommatidia arranged in rows (
Fig. 3E
). Male gonopods unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
ʻ 
Cretacea
ʼ in reference to the Cretaceous, the geological period to which the Burmese amber deposits are dated. Noun in apposition with a free ending.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MYANMAR
• 
♀
; 
Kachin State
, 
Hukawng Valley
, 
Mid-Cretaceous
Burmese amber inclusion; formerly in the collection of Patrick Müller (
BuB1142
); 
ZFMK-MYR7370
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
HABITUS. 55 + 3 body rings; body cylindrical, slender, up to at least 
17.9 mm
long, 
0.6 mm
in diameter. Colour brown to greyish (
Fig. 3B
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD.As wide as collum and body rings 6 onwards, wider than body rings 2–5 (
Fig. 3C
). Head and labrum with setae. 31/? ommatidia (left side obscured) arranged in 6 rows, posterior 4 rows with 6 ommatidia, row 5 (counted from posterior) with 5, anterior row with 4 ommatidia. Incisura lateralis present, closed (
Fig. 3E
). Antennae reaching to body ring 5, with 7 antennomeres, covered by setae, 6 = 4&gt; 3&gt; 5&gt; 2&gt; 1&gt; 7, with 4 sensory cones (
Fig. 3F
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Electrocambala cretacea
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (ZFMK-MYR7370). 
A
. Amber piece, photograph. 
B
. Habitus, lateral view, photograph. 
C
. Head and anterior body rings, lateral view, photograph. 
D
. Telson and posterior body rings, lateral view, photograph. 
E
. Head and anterior body rings, lateral view, drawing. 
F
. Antenna, drawing. 
G
. Midbody leg, drawing. Abbreviations: 57 = body ring 57; as = apical spine; at = antennae; av = anal valve; cl = claw; co = collum; cx = coxa; il = incisura lateralis; L = leg; la = labrum; md = mandible; om = ommatidia; ta = tarsus; te = telson.
</p>
      <p>
TRUNK. Collum slightly curved, covering posterior margin of head. Collum laterally without striae (
Fig. 3C, F
). Body rings totally fused from body ring 5 onwards, anterior four body rings with sternite free from pleuro-tergite. Metazonites from body ring 6 onwards distinctly arched and wider than prozonite (
Fig. 3C
). Body rings with several longitudinal ridges. Metazonites ventrally with at least 5 longitudinal striae, posterior margin with 1 or 2 rows of setae (
Fig. 3E
), ozopores start lateral from body ring 6.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Body ring 4 legless, from body ring 5 onwards 2 leg pairs per body ring. Midbody legs with coxa, prefemur, femur, postfemur, tibia, tarsus. Podomeres with few setae. Tarsus&gt; femur&gt; postfemur = prefemur&gt; tibia&gt; coxa. Tarsus with tarsal claw and accessory spine (only visible on well preserved legs separated from body, other legs partly decomposed). Podomeres with setae (
Fig. 3G
). 1 
st
and 2 
nd
leg pair shorter and stouter than midbody legs (
Fig. 3G
).
</p>
      <p>
POSTERIOR BODY RINGS. Preanal ring without epiproct projecting, with marginal setae. Subanal scale not projecting over anal valve. Posterior body rings and anal valves covered by fungi (
Fig. 3D
).
</p>
      <p>MALE. Unknown.</p>
      <p>
Measurements and taphonomy
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. 
17.9 mm
long, 
0.6 mm
in diameter.
</p>
      <p>
AMBER DESCRIPTION.Amber flat, oval-shaped, polished, 48.3 × 29.5 × 
7.4 mm
, yellow, reddish transparent (
Fig. 3A
).
</p>
      <p>
SYNINCLUSIONS. Same as in ZFMK-MYR7370 (
<tp:taxon-name>
Electrocambala ornata
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
).
</p>
      <p>
TAPHONOMIC FEATURES. From body ring 8 onwards body rings and anal valves partially covered by white, filamentous substance. Only right side of anterior body visible, left side obscured by leaf, several legs detached, next to body (
Fig. 3B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
