<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Disporella guada Harmelin, Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5560013</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9E3F53F91686680DFD3226BBA82372D1</uri>
         <article-title>Disporella guada sp. nov., an erect-ramose rectangulate cyclostome (Bryozoa, Stenolaemata) from the Caribbean Sea: convergent evolution in bryozoan colony morphology</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1507</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
Harmelin, Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E6E2D7BF-A429-4ABE-B91F-4D33DE70D033
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Disporella
</tp:taxon-name>
with erect, ramose colonies up to at least 
30 mm
in width and height; branches short and thick; branch axes constituting an endozone formed by proximal parts of zooids oriented parallel to branch axis, surrounded by an exozone formed by the distal parts of these zooids bent to become oriented at right angles to the axis; maculae circular to elongate in outline, comprising kenozooids. Autozooids with multiple apertural spines, the aperture often closed by a calcified diaphragm containing a central lumen. Gonozooid irregularly ramifying, the interior-walled roof rapidly concealed by a honeycomb of secondary calcification; ooeciopores at distal ends of lobes, occasionally paired, rounded quadrangular, without an ooeciostome.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From 
Guadeloupe
, the type locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
FRENCH WEST INDIES
, 
GUADELOUPE
• the largest collected spec. (
Figs 1A
, 
2A
) (kept dry, Hc 
28 mm
, Wc 
38 mm
, Bd 
5.4–6.2 mm
, Db 
2.3–3.6 mm
, Hp 320–500 µm, Nt 26, + 3 broken tips, coated for SEM); Islet “Tête-à-l’Anglais”; 
16°22.936′ N
, 
061°45.925′ W
; 

5 m

depth; 

10 Oct. 2014

; 
CB
leg.; 
MNHN-IB-2017-696
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
FRENCH WEST INDIES
, 
GUADELOUPE
• 
1 spec.
(paratype A: Hc 
20 mm
, Wc 
2.4 mm
, Nt 8; preserved in ethanol); Islet “Tête-à-l’Anglais”; 
16°22.916′ N
, 
061°35.140′ W
; 

3–5 m
depth

; 

7 Nov. 2016

; 
CB
leg.; MNHN-IB-2017-697

• 

1 spec.
(paratype B: Hc 
20 mm
, Wc 
16 mm
, Nt 5; preserved in ethanol); same collection data as for preceding; 
CB
leg; 
MNHN-IB-2017-698
(
NHMUK 2018.1.15.63
hologenophore)

• 

7 specs
; same collection data as for preceding; 
NHMUK 2021.2.25.1
, 
NHMUK 2021.3.19.1
, 
NHMUK 2012.3.19.2
, 
NHMUK 2021.6.14.1
, 
NHMUK 2021.6.14.2
, 
NHMUK 2021.6.14.3
, 
NHMUK 2021.6.14.4

.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
FRENCH WEST INDIES
, 
GUADELOUPE
• 
11 colonies
, small to medium-sized (Hc 
8-15 mm
) with varied shape (small: columnar, larger: ramified), preserved in ethanol; same collection data as for paratype A; 
MNHN-IB-2017-699–709

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Morphology
</p>
      <p>
Colony white when alive (
Fig. 1A–B
), heavily calcified, erect, up to 
30 mm
in both height and width in collected material, rapidly and irregularly ramified in all directions from a short basal trunk, branches short and thick but variably sized, roughly cylindrical or slightly flattened, with rounded tips (
Fig. 2B– C
); the largest colony (holotype) with 29 branch tips (
Fig. 2A
). Distal branch growing tips hemispherical, exposing a mixture of autozooidal and kenozooidal apertures (
Fig. 2D
); interzooecial walls with a broken medial ridge; spines lacking (
Fig. 2E
). Marginal lamina apparently absent at the base of colonies (juvenile specimens not seen). During growth, the base of the colony (
Fig. 2
C-a) can increase the diameter of its attachment surface by the downward budding of a peripheral blade apparently made of kenozooids (
Fig. 2
C-b).
</p>
      <p>
Surface of branches occupied by autozooids and kenozooids (
Figs 3B, D–E
, 
4A
). Transverse section of branches revealing an axial endozone occupying 40–50% of the area (
Fig. 3C
), formed by proximal parts of zooids growing parallel to branch axis, surrounded by an outer exozone corresponding to the distal parts of these zooids bent at right angles to the branch axis (
Fig. 2C
). Lateral walls of zooids very thick, moniliform, with pointed mural spines or pustules (
Fig. 4D–E, H
) and communication pores hourglass-shaped in vertical section (
Fig. 4G
), originating at the surface of the colony (see below). Skeletal ultrastructure granular in appearance at growing edges, lacking a layer of transverse fibres.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
Underwater photos of specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
Harmelin, Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; Guadeloupe, Islet Tête-à-l’Anglais, 5 m. 
A
. Holotype (MNHN-IB-2017-696); photo Y. Bouchon- Navaro, 10 Oct. 2014. 
B
. Another large specimen; photo C. Bouchon, 7 Nov. 2016.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
Photographs (A–B) and scanning electron micrographs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
Harmelin, Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. Holotype, specimen kept dry (MNHN-IB-2017-696). 
B
. Seven variously shaped colonies (top row, left to right: NHMUK 2021.2.25.1, 2021.3.19.2, 2018.1.15.63, 2021.3.19.1; bottom row, left to right: NHMUK 2021.6.14.1, 2021.6.14.2, 2021.6.14.3). 
C
. Longitudinal section of a specimen (NHMUK 2021.3.19.1) with two branches; 1: endozone, 2: exozone, 3: basal part with central primary attachment zone (3a) and secondary peripheral attachment zone (3b). 
D–E
. NHMUK 2021.3.19.2. 
D
. Growing tip. 
E
. Interzooecial walls at growing tip.
</p>
      <p>
Kenozooids with rounded apertures (
Fig. 4A
) smaller than those of the autozooids (25–45 µm), occasionally associated (frequently in the largest specimen) with a single pointed process rising vertically or slightly bent (
Fig. 4C
), scattered between autozooids or clustered together to form maculae on the colony surface (
Fig. 3B
). Maculae of variable shapes and sizes, from relatively small and nearly circular to large and elongated along branches (
Fig. 3A
), particularly frequent near branch bifurcations.
</p>
      <p>
Autozooids loosely arranged in quincunx or more irregularly, interspersed with kenozooids. Peristomes short, the largest (up to 500 µm) in the shape of a concave blade arising from the distal edge of the aperture, tip truncated (gouge-shaped) or pointed, with a large oblique opening reaching the colony surface; a pair of pointed processes lateral to the blade on medium-sized peristomes (
Fig. 3E
), the smallest peristomes reduced to a short, arched wall with up to 4 or 5 terminal pointed processes (
Fig. 3D
). Communication pores visible below the outer rim of apertures of both kenozooids and autozooids, and also in the peristomes of autozooids (
Fig. 4E
).
</p>
      <p>
Mural spines pointed and variously sized, or short and blunt (pustules), abundant inside tubes of autozooids and kenozooids (up to 15–18 around the circumference of kenozooidal apertures) (
Fig. 4A, E–H
), and on the outer sides of brood chambers with fewer on the inner sides.
</p>
      <p>
Calcified diaphragms present in kenozooids and in some autozooids of large (presumably old) specimens (
Fig. 4B–C
), subterminal, funnel-shaped, iris-like with a central lumen of varying size (8–25 µm), adorally curved at contact with the interzooecial walls, a clear discontinuity visible between the outer edge of the diaphragm and these walls (
Fig. 4F
); a succession of diaphragms spaced 100 to&gt;500 µm apart seen in sectioned zooids, suggesting sequential growth and resting stages.
</p>
      <p>
Brood chambers irregularly ramose with narrow lateral branches (
Fig. 5A
), sub-circular in section (
Fig.5C
), interior-walled, floor and roof formed by a thin skeletal layer, roof rapidly concealed by secondary calcification starting with a honeycomb mesh structure (
Fig. 5A–B
); outer surface of overgrowths densely dotted with large pores soon closed by a calcified diaphragm inserted below the surface, inner surface smooth or with small pustules. Ooeciopore at distal end of lobes, occasionally paired (i.e., two ooeciopores are present in the same lobe) (
Fig. 5D
), widely open, more or less quadrangular with rounded corners, the upper edge corresponding to the boundary of the brood chamber; ooeciostome lacking.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This new species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella
</tp:taxon-name>
is distinguished from all others in the genus by its erect colony-form with bifurcating branches. It was initially believed to be a species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis
Buge &amp; Tillier, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
, regarded as a cerioporine by these authors but which has an interior-walled gonozooid as noted by 
Gordon &amp; Taylor (2001)
and is therefore a rectangulate. The 
type
species of this genus, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis atlantica
Buge &amp; Tillier, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Gulf of 
Guinea
, has a semi-erect colony with claviform branches that do not bifurcate, whereas a second species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis cyanea
Gordon &amp; Taylor, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
New Zealand
, has encrusting colonies. A morphological comparison between 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis atlantica
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis cyanea
</tp:taxon-name>
is presented in 
Table 1. A
key difference between 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and the two species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis
</tp:taxon-name>
is the erect bifurcating colony-form of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, the branches comprising an axial endozone surrounded by an exozone. However, the structure of the basal part of the sectioned colony of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(
Fig. 2C
), with secondary downward growth of a peripheral blade, matches with the process of basal thickening in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis atlantica
</tp:taxon-name>
described and figured by 
Buge &amp; Tillier (1977: 6
, fig. 2). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis
</tp:taxon-name>
lacks the prominent interior-walled peristomial spines that characterize 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, although the apertural rims in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis cyanea
</tp:taxon-name>
do have short processes on one side.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
Harmelin, Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. Non-type (MNHN-IB-2017-700). 
B–C, E
. Holotype (MNHN-IB-2017-696). 
D
. Paratype (NHMUK 2021.2.25.1). 
A
. Elongated maculae. 
B
. Mixture of peristomate autozooids and kenozooids. 
C
. Part of a transverse section of a terminal branch showing the endozone, exozone and intersecting ramifications of several gonozooids (larger white cavities). 
D
. Kenozooids and autozooids with small peristomes bearing pointed processes. 
E
. Kenozooids and autozooidal peristomes of various sizes and shapes.
</p>
   <p>
Table 1.
Comparison between 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
Harmelin, Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and the two nominal species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis
Buge &amp; Tillier, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. atlantica
Buge &amp; Tillier, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. cyanea
Gordon &amp; Taylor, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   <p>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
</tp:taxon-name>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis atlantica
</tp:taxon-name>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis cyanea
</tp:taxon-name>
Colony shape
erect, irregularly ramifying with thick branches
semi-erect and claviform
adnate, thick, tendency to be moundshaped
Maculae
linear and sinuous, or irregular in outline
unclear
circular, numerous; several subcolonies
Autozooidal apertures
peristome erect, relatively short, mitrifom (single pointed end) or fimbriated (3–5 pointed processes)
no peristomes
no or a short peristome with a single pointed process in young parts of colony
Kenozooids
smaller than autozooids, sometimes with a robust spine raised from the border of apertural rim
smaller than autozooids
larger in maculae zone but with smaller aperture due to the thick subterminal rim
Mural spines
small, pointed or granular, in both autozooids small, pointed or granular, and kenozooids and on both sides of brood abundant in both autozooids and chambers kenozooids
pinhead with several spinelets forming a crown, numerous in kenozooids, absent in autozooids; granules on brood chamber walls
Diaphragms
subterminal, frequent in older parts of colonies in both autozooids and kenozooids, funnel-shaped downwardly directed with a central lumen, without pseudopores
terminal diaphragms with pseudopores closing zooids forming floor of gonozooids
unknown
Zooecial walls
moniliform, very thick
moniliform, very thick
moniliform, very thick
Communication pores
openings large, narrowing markedly at zooidal boundary
openings large, narrowing markedly at zooidal boundary
often with a tiny septum at zooidal boundary
Brood chamber
rapidly concealed by kenozooidal layer; ramose with several digitate lobes (up to 5 or 6), subcircular in outline; walls distinct; frontal wall densely dotted with circular closed pores, inner walls with pustules
ramose with several digitate lobes; walls distinct; frontal wall smooth; inner walls with pustules
not observed externally; ramose with several lobes, subcircular in outline; walls distinct, inner sides carpeted with dense granulations
Ooeciopore
lacking a collar; located at the ends of lobes, several per brood chamber
not seen
poorly visible, smaller than autozooidal apertures
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
Harmelin, Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. Paratype (NHMUK 2021.2.25.1). 
B–C, F–H
. Holotype (MNHN-IB-2017-696). 
D–E
. Paratype (NHMUK 2021.3.19.1). 
A
. Frontal view of autozooids with short peristomes interspersed with kenozooids. 
B–C
. Calcified diaphragms with a central lumen closing an autozooid (B) and a kenozooid (C). 
D–E, G
. Longitudinal sections of zooids showing the moniliform walls with mural pustules, and the communication pores. 
F
. Funnel-shaped diaphragm with a sectioned autozooid. 
H
. Mural spines and pustules surrounding a communication pore.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Habitat and colony shape
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
was found at two sites in the French West Indies characterised by the same general environmental conditions, i.e., very shallow depth (
3–5 m
) and exposure to strong wave action. Variously sized colonies of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
grow on the shadowed side of rocks together with sponges, hydroids, gorgonians, and the stylasterid 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stylaster roseus
(Pallas, 1766)
</tp:taxon-name>
, but apparently without large macrophytes. The highly robust colonies of this erect species, owing to small size and very thick trunk and branches, seem well adapted to life in a high-energy flow regime. In the largest and most profusely ramified colony collected (the holotype), the ratio of colony height (
28 mm
) to mean branch width (
3.5 mm
) is particularly low (8). This ratio contrasts with the very high values seen, for example, in large colonies of branched cheilostomes inhabiting conditions of reduced flow, such as in caves. The finding of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
only in high flow regimes where colonies are stocky raises the question of whether it is specialized for this particular habitat. Many species of cyclostomes exhibit considerable plasticity in colony form according to the microenvironment inhabited (
Harmelin 1975
, 
1976
). Therefore, it cannot be ruled out that 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is present also in other unexplored microhabitats – such as the undersides of boulders, in cavities or in deeper water – where the shape of the colonies may be different.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
Brood chambers in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella guada
Harmelin, Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. Paratype (NHMUK 2021.2.25.1). 
B–D
. Holotype (MNHN-IB-2017-696). 
A
. Brood chamber with 8 lateral branches, thinly covered by secondary calcification. 
B
. Thicker mesh of secondary calcification over a brood chamber. 
C
. Transverse section of branch intersecting six lobes of ramifying brood chambers. 
D
. Two ooeciopores (open arrowheads) at the end of a lateral branch of a brood chamber.
</p>
      <p>
Molecular phylogeny
</p>
      <p>
Previous studies on cyclostome phylogenetics have revealed several unexpected results (

Waeschenbach 
et al
. 2009

; 

Taylor 
et al
. 2011

, 2015; 
Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach 2019
), which is why the newly generated data were analysed in the broader context of cyclostome phylogeny (
Fig. 6
). Bayesian inference places 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. guada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
firmly in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Disporella
(Rectangulata)
</tp:taxon-name>
, in a strongly supported clade that also includes 
<tp:taxon-name>
Plagioecia patina
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Tubuliporina</tp:taxon-name>
) and sister taxa 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doliocoitis cyanea
(Rectangulata)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Favosipora rosea
Gordon &amp; Taylor, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Cerioporina</tp:taxon-name>
). The remainder of the phylogeny largely corresponds to previous versions, except reduced nodal support (0.89 pp) for a sister-group relationship of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Crisia
spp.
</tp:taxon-name>
and the remainder of Clade C in 

Waeschenbach 
et al
. (2009)

, and a switch in positions between 
<tp:taxon-name>
Annectocyma tubulosa
(Busk, 1875)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Heteropora
sp. 1
</tp:taxon-name>
compared to the topology presented by Taylor 
et al
. (2015) and 
Taylor &amp; Waeschenbach (2019)
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
