<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Chinoperla nigrifrons MCZ</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5578491</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F24E1821274D2685DA65666659666A19</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the genus Chinoperla Zwick, 1980 (Plecoptera: Perlidae: Perlinae) from China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla nigrifrons
(
Banks, 1939
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 6–10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ochthopetina nigrifrons
Banks, 1939: 449
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 73 (original description).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sinoperla furcomacula
Wu, 1973: 110
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 91–93 (original description).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ochthopetina nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Illies 1966: 274

(catalog).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Zwick &amp; Sivec 1980: 130

(transferred from 
Sinoperla
). — 

Zwick 1982: 168

(synopsis). — 


Sivec 
et al.
1988: 54


(provisionally possible conspecifity with 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
). — 

Sivec &amp; Zwick 1989: 14

(three theories about possible synonymy or distinctiveness with 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
– 


Sivec 
et al.
1988: 54


(transferred from 
Ochthopetina
, provisionally possible conspecifity with 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
). — 

Sivec &amp; Zwick 1989: 14

, fig. 3a, c–e (redescription of male with uneverted aedeagus and female based on 
types
). — 


Du 
et al.
1999: 62


(catalog). — 

Yang &amp; Li 2018: 36

(catalog).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Head with a heart-shaped dark brown patch and a subtriangular dark brown spot. Male tergum 9 with a trumpet-shaped median sclerite. Hemitergal processes medially indented in lateral view. Aedeagal tube with a T-shaped sclerotized dorsal marking. Aedeagal sac dorsoapically with a low membranous median lobe; ventrobasally with a large patch of spinules; ventroapically with one long and one shorter spine, or the two of equal length; apically with a long straight spine and a large membranous lobe; laterally with dense large, curved spines arranged on each side. Posterior margin of female sternum 8 slightly produced, forming a small subtriangular subgenital plate with an apical notch.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; “ 
Hainan
, 
Ta Han
” [
Hainan Province
, 
Qiongzhong Li
and 
Miao Autonomous County
, located in 
Limushan Town
]; 

23 Jun. 1935

; 
L. Gressitt
leg.; 
MCZ
Type 22693.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
1 ♀
; same locality data as for holotype; 

2 Aug. 1935

; 
L. Gressitt
leg.; 
MCZ

• 

1 ♀
; same locality data as for holotype; 

13 Jul. 1935

; 
L. Gressitt
leg.; 
MCZ

.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
(holotype and paratype of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
); “ 
Kwangtung
, 
Hainan
, 
Tung-shih
” [
Hainan Province
belonging to Guangdong at that time, 
Wuzhishan City
, 
Tongshen Town
]; alt. 

350 m

; 

27 May 1960

; 
IZCAS

• 

2 ♂♂
; 
Hainan Province
, 
Baisha Li Autonomous County
, 
Mount Yinggeling
; 
19°14′0.24″ N
, 
109°26′27.96″ E
; alt. 

430 m

; 

1 Apr. 2013

; 
Yu-Yu Wang
and 
Yun-Lan Jiang
leg.; 
HIST

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig
. 
6
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla nigrifrons
(
Banks, 1939
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂, holotype (MCZ Type 22693). 
A
. Adult habitus, dorsal view. 
B
. Head and pronotum, dorsal view. 
C
. Terminalia, dorsal view. 
D
. Cleared terminalia, dorsal view. 
E
. Cleared terminalia, lateral view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars: A = 1.0 mm; B–E = 0.5 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
ADULT HABITUS (
Figs 6A–B
, 
8C
, 
9A
). General color brown. Forewing length 7.7–8.0 mm, hindwing length 
6.7–7.1 mm
. Head brownish, with a dark brown heart-shaped spot, but specimens from Mount Yinggeling with a long brown band located on the occiput, and with a subtriangular dark brown spot in front of M-line; biocellate, ocelli about 3 diameters apart of each other, slightly closer to each other than to the compound eye; antennae brown. Pronotum trapezoidal, brown with paler lateral margin and with darker, distinct rugosities; anterior corners pointed but posterior corners obtuse. Legs generally brown, proximal part of femora mostly lighter; wings subhyaline and brownish, veins brown, Sc of forewing short, typical of the genus (
Fig. 8C
); cerci brownish.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla nigrifrons
(
Banks, 1939
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂, holotype (MCZ Type 22693). 
A
. Aedeagus, dorsal view. 
B
. Aedeagus, lateral view. 
C
. Aedeagal sac, ventral view. 
D
. Apex of aedeagal sac, oblique ventral view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 0.25 mm.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Figs 6C–E
, 
8A–B
, 
9B–E
). Sterna 3–5 with hair brushes. Dark median sclerite of tergum 9 trumpet-shaped, about half as long as the segment, heavily sclerotized, distinctly forked distally with two sharp points. Hemitergal processes slender, about 2.5× as long as basal width, distinctly narrowing subapically; medially indented in lateral view; basal callus fully covered by sensilla basiconica.
</p>
      <p>
AEDEAGUS (
Figs 7
, 
10
). Aedeagal tube partially sclerotized dorsally, forming a distinctly T-shaped marking on the 
holotype
(
Fig. 7A–B
), but marking in specimens from Mount Yinggeling indistinct, well seen only in lateral view (
Fig.10A–B
). Fully everted sac as long as the tube, curved dorsad; ventroapical and dorsoapical surface heart-shaped in specimens from Mount Yinggeling (
Fig. 10
), less definite in the 
holotype
(
Fig. 7
); dorsoapical surface with a small bulgy membranous median lobe; a single large spine about as long as ¼ aedeagus length, and a large membranous lobe medially at apex, slightly directed dorsally; ventral surface with a large basal patch of spinule, and one long and one shorter subapical spines (
Fig. 7
) but in fresh specimens from Mount Yinggeling the two of approximately equal length (
Fig. 10
); lateroapical part with dense, large and curved spines arranged on each side.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla nigrifrons
(
Banks, 1939
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–B
. ♂, holotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. furcomacula
(
Wu, 1973
) (IZCAS)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A
. Cleared terminalia, dorsal view. 
B
. Cleared terminalia, lateral view. — 
C
. ♂ from Mount Yinggeling (HIST), forewing. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 0.5 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
: 
Hainan Province
, found in three counties.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla nigrifrons
(
Banks, 1939
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ from Mount Yinggeling (HIST). 
A
. Head and pronotum, dorsal view. 
B
. Terminalia, dorsal view. 
C
. Cleared terminalia, dorsal view. 
D
. Cleared terminalia, lateral view. 
E
. Cleared terminalia, oblique lateral view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 0.5 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
We carefully compared the type specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
deposited in MCZ with the illustrations in 
Sivec &amp; Zwick (1989)
. The head pattern, direction of antennae and shape of the pronotum of the female 
paratype
collected on 
13 July 1935
are consistent with those illustrated in 
Sivec &amp; Zwick (1989
: fig. 3a, d–e). The figures of the terminalia and vagina also refer to the same female 
paratype
, because the second female 
paratype
collected on 
2 August 1935
had not been dissected, and its sternum 9 is more narrow. The figure of the male terminalia in 
Sivec &amp; Zwick (1989
: fig. 3b) shows a shallow apical notch of the median sclerite of tergum 9, and tapering and curving hemitergal processes without a straight apical half. These characters are consistent with those in the male 
paratype
, that is not conspecific with the 
holotype
and has been reassigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. changjiangensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
above (
Fig. 3B–E
). However, the small basal sclerite in the aedeagus of the 
holotype
(
Fig. 7B
) corresponds to that illustrated in 
Sivec &amp; Zwick (1989
: fig. 3c). Therefore, we believe that the half-everted aedeagus of the 
holotype
, the terminalia of the male 
paratype
(
<tp:taxon-name>
C. changjiangensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
), and the head, pronotum, sterna 7–9 and vagina of the female 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
were redescribed by 
Sivec &amp; Zwick (1989)
. Color photographs and illustrations of the male 
holotype
are provided in the present study (
Figs 6–7
). The characteristics of both female 
paratypes
agree well with the description and illustrations provided by 
Sivec &amp; Zwick (1989)
.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Chinoperla nigrifrons
(
Banks, 1939
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ from Mount Yinggeling (HIST). 
A
. Aedeagus, lateral view. 
B
. Aedeagus, dorsal view. 
C
. Aedeagus, ventral view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 0.25 mm.
</p>
      <p>
We checked the types of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
in IZCAS, but the aedeagus of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
with the 
holotype
label was difficult to fully evert due to the poor condition of the specimen. Based on the original description and redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
in the present study, we believe that the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
is conspecific with the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
, and is therefore a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Banks 1939
; 
Wu 1973
; 

Sivec 
et al.
1988

; 
Sivec &amp; Zwick 1989
). The two recently collected males from 
Hainan Province
examined in this study agree well with the type specimens in general characteristics such as head pattern, lateral aspect of the hemitergal lobes, and armatures of the aedeagus. However, these fresh specimens from Mount Yinggeling show slight differences in the head pattern and aedeagus, as they have a long brown posterior band on the head, and the two ventroapical spines of the aedeagal sac are straight and nearly equal in length. We believe this brown occipital band disappears in fully aged adults, such as the 
holotype
. Similar differences were documented in the case of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kamimuria guangxia
Li &amp; 
Wang, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neoperla lihuae
Li &amp; Murányi, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
(

Wang 
et al.
2013

; 

Li 
et al.
2014

). The differences in the aedeagal armatures can be regarded as intraspecific differences. We provide illustrations of the fully everted sac of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
holotype
and the fresh adults to allow a reliable identification for future studies (
Figs 7
, 
10
).
</p>
      <p>
Unfortunately, the 
paratype
female of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
in IZCAS is badly damaged and difficult to study. According to the original description and figures of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Wu 1973
: fig. 93), the terminalia of the 
paratype
female distinctly differ from those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. nigrifrons
</tp:taxon-name>
by the unmodified subgenital plate. 
Sivec &amp; Zwick (1989)
drew up three possibilities for the specific identity of this female; we support the third, which suggests that the 
paratype
female may not be conspecific with the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. furcomacula
</tp:taxon-name>
. Further specimens from 
Hainan
are needed to confirm the identity of the female.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
