<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora
Baird &amp; Girard, 1853
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora
Baird &amp; Girard, 1853: 104–105
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phimothyra
Cope, 1861: 566
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora grahamiae
Baird &amp; Girard, 1853
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Usually nine-plate supracephalic scaling on the head; enlarged rostral scale that intercedes between the internasals and sometimes has free edges; two nasal scales; preoculars and postoculars present; loreal scale simple or divided; smooth body scales sometimes with two apical pits; 17 rows of scales around the body on the anterior third of body and midbody; cloacal scale divided; subcaudal scales in two series; elongated head; large eyes; round pupil; long tail. Hemipenis simple with spines at the base, replaced midway by calyces that cover half the length of each organ: sulcus simple with a long basal spine. Normally from 9 to 15 maxillary teeth followed by a diastema and three enlarged teeth (9–15+ 3). Color pattern consisting of two longitudinal, dorsolateral and lateral lines on each side of the body and a pale vertebral line generally present.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Derived from the Latin ‘ 
salvator
’, which means ‘savior’, and ‘ 
adora
’, which means ‘honor’, an explicit homage to the collector of the 
type
species 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. grahamiae
, Col. J.D. Graham.
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Southern 
United States
from southern 
California
, western 
Nevada
, 
Utah
, to 
Arizona
, 
New Mexico
, to central 
Texas
; in 
Mexico
, the 
Baja California
Peninsula and 
Sonora
south to the lowlands of 
Chiapas
and 
Guatemala
excluding the Yucatán Peninsula.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The phylogenetic hypothesis and the character revision reveal that there are two groups within the genus, as previously suggested by 
Smith (1938
, 
1941
): 
<tp:taxon-name>
mexicana
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
grahamiae
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
