<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pallarica Gómez &amp; Corgosinho &amp; Rivera-Sánchez 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5104694</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0B3187C8FF8B896AFD3D364EFAF9AD5E</uri>
         <article-title>Proposal of new genera and species of the subfamily Diosaccinae (Copepoda: Harpacticoida: Miraciidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.759.1433</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pallarica
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
78F45B32-1B47-41BB-99E0-E7F8327E3333
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Bulbamphiascus
Lang, 1944: 19
</tp:taxon-name>

, pro parte.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
and only species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Bulbamphiascus cibimae
Pallares, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pallaricia cibimae
(Pallares, 1982)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
), by monotypy.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Miraciidae</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>Diosaccinae</tp:taxon-name>
. Body fusiform. Rostrum not fused to cephalothorax, triangular, elongate, with round apical margin, almost as long as first, second and third antennulary segments combined, with one subdistal sensilla at third quarter of its length, on each side. Pro- and urosomites without expansions. Genital double-somite (genital – second urosomite – and third urosomites fused) completely fused ventrally, with a dorsolateral cuticular rib marking original division between somites. Caudal rami about 1.5 times as wide as long in dorsal view; with seven setae. Female antennule eight-segmented, with aesthetasc and seta fused basally on fourth segment, and with apical acrothek on last segment. Antennulary setae typically smooth. Antenna with allobasis and abexopodal seta; exopod threesegmented, armature formula 1-1-1,3,0. Mandibular palp biramous; endopod one-segmented, larger than exopod, the latter two-segmented. Maxillule biramous; rami one-segmented. Maxilla with three endites, proximal and middle endites with two, distal endite with three elements; ENP two-segmented. Maxilliped subchelate; (syn)coxa with three, basis with two setae; ENP one-segmented, with claw and three accompanying setae. P1–P4 with three-segmented rami. Male P1 basis sexually dimorphic, with inner unipinnate spine and inner modified accessory spine. P1 EXP shorter than ENP, reaching tip of ENP2; P1 ENP1 with strong bipinnate inner seta; ENP3 2.5 times as long as ENP2, with one small inner seta, a long distal geniculate seta, and an outer spine; EXP2 with inner seta. P2–P4 EXP and ENP of approximately same lengths; P2–P4 EXP1 with inner seta; inner distal seta of P2–P4 EXP3 visibly shorter than other inner setae on same segment. P2 ENP2 with two setae, proximalmost small. Male P2 ENP sexually dimorphic, two-segmented; first segment with one inner seta; second segment with two inner setae, two elements (one medial, one apical) issuing from elongate cylindrical extension fused to segment basally, and inner subdistal element almost straight and outer subdistal element slightly thicker and longer than the former and with almost parallel margins (i.e., slightly tapering distally). P5 EXP longer than wide in female, comparatively shorter in male, with six setae in female and seven setae in male; two medial outer elements stiff short spine-like in male, slender and smooth in female.
</p>
      <p>P5 endopodal lobe with five setae in female, with two setae in male; armature of male P5 endopodal lobe strongly bipinnate.</p>
      <p>
Armature 
formula
of P1–P5 as follows:
</p>
      <p>
EXP
ENP
P1
0-1-0,2,3
1-1-1,1,1
P2
1-1-2,2,3
♀
1-2-1,2,1 / 
♂
dimorphic

P3
1-1-2,2,3
1-1-2,2,1
P4
1-1-3,2,3
1-1-1,2,1

P 
5 ♀
/ 
♂
♀
6/ 
♂
6

♀
5/ 
♂
2

</p>
      <p>Sexual dimorphism expressed in male antennule, P2 ENP, P5, P6, and in separated genital and third urosomites.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This genus is dedicated to Rosa E. Pallares for her contribution to the taxonomy of harpacticoid copepods from 
Argentina
. Gender feminine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

Apomorphies for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pallarica
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
      <p>This genus is unique by the possession of seven setae on the male P5 EXP, which is regarded here as apomorphic for the genus. The presence of an additional seta is regarded here as a character reversal.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
