<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Spinodiosaccus Gómez &amp; Corgosinho &amp;
            Rivera-Sánchez 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5104684</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0B3187C8FFBB895AFD17324AFD1DAAC0</uri>
         <article-title>Proposal of new genera and species of the subfamily Diosaccinae (Copepoda:
            Harpacticoida: Miraciidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.759.1433</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Spinodiosaccus </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: B8A6B755-8375-48B0-BC31-EBCCB4B9F9DE </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type and only species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Spinodiosaccus primus </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. , by monotypy. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis (based on <tp:taxon-name> Spinodiosaccus primus </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp.
         nov. ) </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Miraciidae</tp:taxon-name> : <tp:taxon-name>Diosaccinae</tp:taxon-name> .
         Body fusiform. Rostrum not fused to cephalothorax, elongate, almost as long as the first,
         second and third antennulary segments combined, with one subdistal sensilla on each side
         issuing at the third quarter of its length. Pro- and urosomites without extensions; with a
         flexible unsclerotized cuticle between prosome and urosome, the latter seemingly more
         evident in the male. Female genital double-somite (genital – second urosomite – and third
         urosomites fused) completely fused ventrally, with a dorsolateral cuticular rib marking
         former division between somites. Anal somite trapezoidal, without anal operculum. Caudal
         rami short, 1.6 times as wide as long in dorsal view, unornamented, with slender tube pore
         ventrally; with seven setae. Female antennule eight-segmented, with aesthetasc and seta
         fused basally on fourth segment and with apical acrothek on last segment. Male antennule
         haplocer, 11-segmented, with aesthetasc and seta fused basally on fifth segment and with
         apical acrothek on last segment. Antennulary setae typically smooth. Antenna with
         allobasis; exopod three-segmented, armature formula 1-1-1,3,0. Mandibular palp biramous;
         endopod one-segmented, exopod two-segmented. Maxillule biramous; rami one-segmented.
         Maxilla with three endites; ENP one-segmented. Maxilliped subchelate; (syn)coxa with four,
         basis with two setae; ENP one-segmented, with claw and three accompanying setae. P1–P4 with
         three-segmented rami. P1–P2 EXP shorter than endopod, P3 EXP and ENP of approximately the
         same length, P4 ENP shorter than EXP. Male P1 basis sexually dimorphic, with inner
         unipinnate spine and inner modified accessory spine. Male P2 sexually dimorphic,
         two-segmented; first segment with one inner seta; second segment with two inner, one inner
         subdistal almost straight element, and two setae (one medial, one apical) issuing from
         elongate cylindrical extension fused to segment basally, and one strong outer subdistal
         spine, the latter strongly tapering distally. P2–P4 EXP1 without, EXP2 with inner seta;
         P2–P4 ENP1 with inner seta; P2 ENP2 with two, P3–P4 ENP2 with one inner seta, inner distal
         seta of EXP3 visibly shorter than other elements of same segment. Both P5 EXP separated in
         the female, baseoendopods fused medially in the male; rami of P5 distinct in both sexes; P5
         EXP with six setae in both sexes, whip-like in the female, two medial outer elements
         transformed into short spines in the male; P5 endopodal lobe with five setae in the female,
         with two setae in the male. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Armature formula of P1–P5 as follows: </p>
      <p> EXP ENP/ENP lobe P1 0-0-0,2,3 1-1-1,1,1 P2 0-1-2,2,3 ♀ 1-2-1,2,1 / ♂ dimorphic P3
         0-1-2,2,3 1-1-2,2,1 P4 0-1-3,2,3 1-1-1,2,1 P 5 ♀ / ♂ ♀ 6 / ♂ 6 ♀ 5/ ♂ 2 </p>
      <p>Sexual dimorphism expressed in the male antennule, P1 basis, P2 ENP, P5, P6, and in the
         genital and third urosomite separated in males.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p>The prefix ‘spino’ from the Latin ‘spīna’, ‘spine’, refers to the two medial elements of
         the male P5 EXP modified into strong short spines. Gender masculine.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Apomorphies of <tp:taxon-name> Spinodiosaccus </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </p>
      <p>This new genus can easily be recognised by i) the male A1 with 11 segments resulting from
         the reexpression of the plesiomorphic condition, ii) the absence of an inner seta on the P1
         EXP2 and iii) the absence of inner armature on P2–P4 EXP1.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
