<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amorphicolinae Burckhardt &amp; Ouvrard &amp; Percy 2021, subfam. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4598611</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0C2387F6FFB2FF98FD9D8031FD6FF84C</uri>
         <article-title>An updated classification of the jumping plant-lice (Hemiptera: Psylloidea) integrating molecular and morphological evidence</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.736.1257</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3F17DEF8-6E82-4586-9AA8-ED1325E5D087
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amorphicola
Heslop-Harrison, 1961
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Adult
</p>
      <p>
Vertex separated from genae by transverse suture; genae forming conical processes; coronal suture fully developed; frons oval, almost completely covered by median ocellus; anteorbital tubercle and preocular sclerite absent. Antenna with segment 3 longer than segments 7 or 8. Thorax moderately arched dorsally; propleurites with subequal epimeron and episternum. Metatibia without genual spine, bearing 4 irregularly spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs. Forewing rhomboidal, broadly rounded apically; membrane semitransparent; costal break developed, pterostigma large; anal break close to apex of vein Cu 
1b
. Hindwing with grouped costal setae; vein M+Cu developed. Male proctiger one-segmented; in profile, tubular. Paramere complex, in profile axe or hammer-shaped with several sclerotised peg setae on the inner face.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>Amorphicolinae</tp:taxon-name>
subfam. nov.
: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amorphicola
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
A
. Habitus, in profile view. 
B
. Legs and terminalia. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Head, frontal view.
</p>
      <p>
Fifth instar immature
</p>
      <p>Body flattened, broadly oval. Antenna 7-segmented, beset with a few short club-shaped setae. Forewing pad lacking humeral lobes, bearing short marginal club-shaped setae. Margin of hindwing pad with club-shaped or capitate setae. Tarsal arolium lacking pedicel. Caudal plate with 4+4 marginal sectasetae and some moderately long club-shaped setae. Anus in ventral position; circumanal ring heart-shaped, consisting of a single row of pores, lacking additional pore fields.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult
</p>
      <p>
Head, in profile, weakly to moderately inclined at 30–45° from longitudinal body axis (
Fig. 5
A–B). Vertex subtrapezoidal, separated from genae by transverse suture; genae forming conical processes which are separated or contiguous at base; coronal suture fully developed; frons oval, almost completely covered by median ocellus; anteorbital tubercle and preocular sclerite not developed (
Fig. 5
C–D). Antenna 10-segmented, filiform, 1.0–1.5 times as long as head width, segment 3 longer than segments 7 or 8. Clypeus pear-shaped, slightly flattened, hardly visible in profile. Rostrum short, distinctly exceeding procoxae. Thorax moderately arched dorsally (
Fig. 5
A–B), slightly narrower than head; pronotum ribbon-shaped; mesopraescutum in longitudinal body axis about as long as mesoscutum; propleurites with subequal epimeron and episternum. Legs moderately long, tibiae slightly longer than femora; basitarsi not much longer than broad; metacoxa with moderately large, horn-shaped meracanthus; metatibia without genual spine, bearing 4 irregularly spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs (
Fig. 5B
). Forewing rhomboidal, broadly rounded apically (
Fig. 5A
); membrane semitransparent, covered in irregularly spaced surface spinules; costal break developed, pterostigma large; vein 
R
longer than M+Cu; anal break close to apex of vein Cu 
1b
. Hindwing almost as long as forewing, membranous; costal setae grouped; vein M+Cu developed. Male proctiger onesegmented; in profile, tubular. Male subgenital plate subglobular or elongate. Paramere complex, in profile hammer-shaped (
Fig. 5B
) with several sclerotised peg setae on the inner face. Female terminalia cuneate. Circumanal ring oval.
</p>
      <p>
Fifth instar immature
</p>
      <p>Body flattened, broadly oval. Antenna 7-segmented, beset with a few short club-shaped setae; bearing a single subapical rhinarium on each of segments 3 and 5, and 2 rhinaria on segment 7. Forewing pad lacking humeral lobes, bearing short marginal club-shaped setae. Margin of hindwing pad with clubshaped or capitate setae. Legs bearing club-shaped or capitate setae; tarsal arolium longer than claws, fan-shaped with unguitractor but lacking pedicel. Caudal plate developed, semi-circular; margin with 4+4 sectasetae and some moderately long club-shaped setae. Anus in ventral position; circumanal ring heart-shaped, consisting of a single row of pores, without additional pore fields.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="multiple">
      <p>
Included genus
</p>
      <p>
* 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amorphicola
Heslop-Harrison, 1961
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
