<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Neophyllurinae Burckhardt &amp;
                        Ouvrard &amp; Percy 2021, subfam. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4598581</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0C2387F6FFAFFF9BFDA18361FCE8F9F1</uri>
                  <article-title>An updated classification of the jumping plant-lice (Hemiptera:
                        Psylloidea) integrating molecular and morphological evidence</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.736.1257</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature/>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 2CB3C7BB-1F3C-4C9E-A8B0-F5AB5B6C537A </p>
            <p> Fig. 3 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p> Type genus </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Neophyllura Loginova, 1973 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name>Neophyllurinae</tp:taxon-name> subfam. nov. : <tp:taxon-name>
                  Neophyllura </tp:taxon-name> spp. A . <tp:taxon-name> Neophyllura arbuticola (
                  Crawford, 1914 ) </tp:taxon-name> , habitus, in profile view. B . <tp:taxon-name>
                  Neophyllura </tp:taxon-name> sp., habitus, in profile view. C–D, F .
                  <tp:taxon-name> Neophyllura arctostaphyli (Schwarz, 1904) </tp:taxon-name> . E .
                  <tp:taxon-name> Neophyllura </tp:taxon-name> sp. C, E . Head, dorsal view. D .
            Head, ventral view. F . Hind leg. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Adult </p>
            <p> Head with subtrapezoidal vertex that is separated from genae by incomplete
                  transverse suture; genae forming transverse ridges; frons oval, almost completely
                  covered by median ocellus; preocular sclerite developed, forming large tubercle.
                  Thorax strongly arched dorsally; propleurites with subequal epimeron and
                  episternum. Parapteron elongate, rectangular, much larger than tegula. Metacoxa
                  with moderately large, blunt meracanthus and inconspicuous membranous tubercle on
                  metatrochanteral cavity; metatibia without genual spine, bearing an open crown of
                  8–9 irregularly spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs.
                  Forewing membrane coriaceous, more or less rugose; costal break developed,
                  pterostigma absent or indistinct; branches of vein M relatively long; anal break
                  close to apex of vein Cu 1b . </p>
            <p> Fifth instar immature </p>
            <p>Caudal plate with additional pore fields.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Adult </p>
            <p> Head, in profile, strongly inclined at almost 90° from longitudinal body axis ( Fig.
                  3 A–B). Vertex subtrapezoidal, separated from genae by incomplete transverse
                  suture; genae forming transverse ridges; coronal suture fully developed; frons
                  oval, almost completely covered by median ocellus; preocular sclerite developed,
                  forming large tubercle ( Fig. 3C, E ). Antenna 10-segmented, filiform, about as
                  long as head width. Clypeus pear-shaped, visible in profile ( Fig. 3D ). Rostrum
                  very short, hardly exceeding procoxae. Thorax strongly arched dorsally; pronotum
                  transversely ribbon-shaped ( Fig. 3C, E ); mesopraescutum in longitudinal body
                  axis shorter than mesoscutum which is strongly bulged; propleurites with subequal
                  epimeron and episternum. Parapteron elongate, rectangular, much larger than
                  tegula. Legs relatively short, tibiae slightly longer than femora; basitarsi not
                  much longer than broad; metacoxa with moderately large, blunt meracanthus and
                  inconspicuous membranous tubercle on metatrochanteral cavity; metatibia without
                  genual spine, bearing an open crown of 8–9 irregularly spaced, sclerotised, apical
                  spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs ( Fig. 3F ). Forewing oval or rhomboidal,
                  membrane coriaceous, more or less rugose; costal break developed, pterostigma
                  absent or indistinct; vein R shorter than M+Cu or both veins subequal, branches of
                  vein M relatively long; anal break close to apex of vein Cu 1b . Hindwing almost
                  as long as forewing, membranous; costal setae grouped; vein R +M developed. Male
                  proctiger one-segmented; in profile, tubular. Male subgenital plate subglobular.
                  Paramere lamellar. Female terminalia cuneate. Circumanal ring oval. </p>
            <p> Fifth instar immature </p>
            <p>Caudal plate bearing additional pore fields. Tarsal arolium short, fan-shaped with
                  unguitractor.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="multiple">
            <p> Included genus </p>
            <p> * <tp:taxon-name> Neophyllura Loginova, 1973 </tp:taxon-name> (syn. <tp:taxon-name>
                        Arbutophila </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
