<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Kupellonura macaroni Annisaqois &amp; Wägele 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5535933</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/98B84566FBCFE32C3C0692EEB257039B</uri>
         <article-title>Morphology and Taxonomy of Isopoda Anthuroidea (Crustacea) from Sulawesi with description of six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.768.1501</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura macaroni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
1611D20A-56EF-43C8-A775-AAEC666BC7ED
</p>
      <p>
Figs 10–13
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Very slender and elongated species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura
</tp:taxon-name>
with a pair of small dorsolateral eyes, pereopod 1 carpus triangular with weak ventrodistal projection and two serrated stout spines; propodus with three prominent strong setae on mesial surface, on palm three short sensory spines; pereopods 2 and 3 of similar shape, propodus more oval, palm with 2 sensory spines, distal carpus corner projecting more than in pereopod 1; uropod exopod long-oval, lateroventral margin only weakly lobed, dorsal margin with 4–5 saw-teeth, uropod endopod as long as sympod, shorter than exopod, nearly rectangular, dorsomedial margin serrated, telson tongue-like, shape elongated oval, apex with 4 pairs of simple setae, lateral margins with 8–10 large teeth.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura macaroni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, immature adult, in dorsal and lateral view (3.2 mm) (MZB Iso 102). Abbreviations: A1 = antenna 1, A2 = antenna 2.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 11.
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura macaroni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, immature adult (MZB Iso 102). Abbreviations: Md = mandible; Mx 1 = maxilla 1; Mxp = maxilliped; P1–P4 = pereopods 1–4.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 12.
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura macaroni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, immature adult (MZB Iso 102). Abbreviations: P5– P6 = pereopods 5–6; Plp1–2 = pleopods 1–2, UEx = exopod of uropod; Tel = telson.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 13.
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura macaroni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, immature adult (MZB Iso 102). Abbreviation: Uen = endopod of uropod, two views (setae omitted in left drawing). Serrations can be difficult to see at certain view angles.
</p>
      <p>
Many species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura
</tp:taxon-name>
have weakly serrated telson margins, a stronger serration is seen in 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. serritelson
Wägele, 1981
</tp:taxon-name>
. The new species has the largest telsonic saw teeth of all known species of this genus and is therefore easily identified.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Named after noodles because of the unusually narrow and elongated body shape of this species.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
INDONESIA
• 
immature adult
(
3.2 mm
); 
Bangka Island
, 
off the jetty of Coral Eye Resort
; 
1°44′22.04″ N
, 
125°8′41.19″ E
; 

2 m
depth

; from coral rubble; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

17 Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 102.

</p>
      <p>
Paratype
INDONESIA
• manca stage (2.0 mm); 
Bangka Island
, 
off the jetty of Coral Eye Resort
; 
1°44′22.04″ N
, 
125°8′41.19″ E
; 

2 m
depth

; 
from coral rubble
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

17 Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 103

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description of immature adult
</p>
      <p>BODY. Without chromatophores, very slender, about 17 times as long as wide (rostrum to tip of telson). Head slightly as long as wide, with a pair of small dorsolateral black eyes. Pereonites dorsally smooth, as long as wide, posterior segments (4–7) slightly wider than anterior ones; length ratio of pereonites: 1&lt;2 = 3&lt;4 &lt;5&gt; 6&gt; 7. Pleonites 1–5 free, as wide as pereonites, total length of pleonites 1–5 nearly length of pereonites 6 + 7. Between pleonite 6 and telson dorsally a distinct edge. Lateroventral margins of pleonites with some feather-like setae. Telson about as long as uropods and pleotelson as a whole as long as four pleonites.</p>
      <p>ANTENNAE. Antenna 1 peduncle of three articles, first longest, articles 2 and 3 progressively shorter and slightly narrower, a conspicuous long seta on third article; flagellum shorter than first peduncle article, of four articles, with a single aesthetasc on last article. Antenna 2 peduncle with 5 articles, second article longest and widest, fifth article as long as articles 3 or 4; flagellum of 8 articles, about as long as peduncle articles 3 + 4, with several simple setae.</p>
      <p>MANDIBLE. With pointed but not sharp molar, lamina dentata with several small teeth, incisor with three cusps; palp of three articles, apically only two simple setae, second article longest. Maxilla 1 lateral endite apically with 4 curved spine-like teeth; medial endite short, a single distal seta. Maxilliped with 5 palp articles, articles 2 and 3 longest and widest, last article small and narrow, with 2 apical simple setae; endite long, surpassing palp article 2 distally, with a single distal seta.</p>
      <p>PEREOPODS. Pereopod 1 subchelate, carpus triangular with weak ventrodistal projection and two serrated stout spines; propodus with three prominent strong setae on mesial surface, on palm three short sensory spines, the distal one short, and thin serrated cuticular scales; dactylus distally with a single claw and a short spine. Pereopod 2 of similar shape, however, propodus more oval, palm with 2 sensory spines, distal one shorter, distal carpus corner projecting more than in pereopod 1, with an acute point, two stout spines on margin. Pereopod 3 roughly similar to pereopod 2. Pereopods 4–6 similar, pereopod 7 weaker. Propodi with single short sensory spine on distoventral margin, carpus trapezoidal with shorter dorsal margin.</p>
      <p>PLEOPODS. All of similar shape, pleopod 1 exopod not larger than endopod; exopods of pleopods 1 and 2 distally with more swimming setae (11) than endopods (5). Uropod exopod long-oval, lateroventral margin only weakly lobed, dorsal margin with 4–5 saw teeth-like structures, not visible from all angles; length about 2.7 times greatest width, apex with several long simple setae. Endopod as long as sympod, shorter than exopod, nearly rectangular, dorsomedial margin serrated, teeth not visible from all angles; apex with many long and slender simple setae.</p>
      <p>
TELSON. Tongue-like, shape elongated oval, length 2.6 times greatest width, apex with 4 pairs of simple setae, lateral margins with 8–10 large teeth (in 
type
specimen no perfect left-right symmetry).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
In contrast to the aforementioned species, the convexity of the ventral margin of the uropod exopod, typical for many species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura
</tp:taxon-name>
, is inconspicuous in this species. The strong teeth on the telson and the uropod serration resemble the tail fan of species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neohyssura
</tp:taxon-name>
; however, in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neohyssura
</tp:taxon-name>
the telson is elongated triangular, the spines are more voluminous and very large on the uropod exopod, furthermore, P2 is distinctly stronger than P3 and the carpus of P4–7 is longer.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
