<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pendanthura bangkaensis Annisaqois &amp; Wägele 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5535941</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CD9311844556EBF44C81650B92D4A53B</uri>
         <article-title>Morphology and Taxonomy of Isopoda Anthuroidea (Crustacea) from Sulawesi with description of six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.768.1501</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura bangkaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
465C0098-760A-4D0B-B566-5C2D8EB5ADCC
</p>
      <p>
Figs 14–17
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
with dorsally pigmented body, distinct lateral eyes with few large ommatidia, mandible palp with 1 tiny article and a long apical seta, pereopod 1 carpus triangular with protruding edge distally, propodus lower half protruding, forming a rounded corner near palm center, with 14 setae in mesial row on distal half of propodus, and 5 longer setae more proximally; pereopods 2–3 merus triangular, dorsal edge reaching nearly to propodus, uropod sympod elongate, endopod subovate, medially as long as laterally, about 0.3 sympod length, exopod twice length of endopod, long oval, margin with many short feathered setae; margins of endopod, exopod and tip of telson weakly crenulated. Telson tongue-shaped, with a pair of statocyst proximally, rounded apex bearing 3 pairs of setae, and on dorsal surface another 2 pairs of longer setae and 1 pair of short setae.
</p>
      <p>
Few species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
share with the new species the distinct projection near the center of the palm of P1 propodus. This feature also occurs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rarotonga
Kensley, 1979
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Müller (1992)
described a specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rarotonga
</tp:taxon-name>
from Bora Bora with 1 article and 2 short setae of the mandibular palp, and a pereopod 1 palm more convex in its lower half and with a sharper protrusion than in Kensley’s material (1979). Müller’s species from Bora Bora is probably not the same as 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rarotonga
</tp:taxon-name>
of 
Kensley (1979)
, which occurs on Rarotonga Island. In 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura bangkaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
from 
Sulawesi
the palm projection of the female is similar, but the mesial row of setae has more setae (14 instead of 8). Also, in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rarotonga
</tp:taxon-name>
the telson bears dorsally 4–7 pairs of setae, in the 
Sulawesi
material there are only 2 pairs of long setae and a pair of short seta dorsolaterally. A similar but larger P1 palm protrusion also occurs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. tanaiformis
Menzies &amp; Glynn, 1968
</tp:taxon-name>
, a Caribbean species. Uropod details of this species are still undescribed.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 14.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura bangkaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀, in dorsal and lateral view (3.4 mm) (MZB Iso 104). Abbreviations: A1 = antenna 1; A2 = antenna 2; Md = mandible; Mx = maxilla; Mxp = maxilliped.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 15.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura bangkaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀, holotype (MZB Iso 104). Abbreviations: P1–P7 = pereopods 1–7.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 16.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura bangkaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀, holotype (MZB Iso 104). Abbreviations: Plp 1–Plp 5 = pleopods 1–5.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species epithet refers to the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
INDONESIA
•brooding 
♀
(
3.4 mm
); 
Bangka Island
, 
off Coral Eye Resort
; 
1°44′22.04″N
, 
125°8′41.19″ E
; 

1–2 m
depth

; in coral rubble; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 104.
</tp:material-citation>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
INDONESIA
• 
2 ♀♀
(
2.8–3.4 mm
); 
Bangka Island
, 
off Coral Eye Resort
; 
1°44′22.04″ N
, 
125°8′41.19″ E
; 

1–2 m
depth

; in coral rubble; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 105
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 17.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura bangkaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀, holotype (MZB Iso 104). Abbreviations: UEx = exopod of uropod; UEn = endopod of uropod; Tel = telson.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

Description of 
holotype
</p>
      <p>BODY. About 8.1 times as long as greatest width, dorsally pigmented, small cuticular scales on body and part of appendages. Cephalothorax in dorsal view wider than long, a pronounced rounded rostrum between insertion of antennae, a pair of compound eyes with few ommatidia. Body proportions: C&lt;1&gt;2&gt;3&gt;4&gt;5&gt;6&gt;7. Pleonites 1–5 fused, together wider than long, length about as pereonite 6.</p>
      <p>ANTENNAE. Antenna 1 peduncle article 1 longest, about 2.3 times as long as wide, articles 2 and 3 progressively narrower, article 2 as long as article 3; flagellum of 2 articles, last article with 3 aesthetascs and 5 setae. Antenna 2 with very short flagellum, basal flagellar article slightly as long as wide. Mandible palp with 1 tiny article and a long apical seta. Maxilla 1 distally with 7 pointed teeth. Maxilliped palp of only 1 article, roughly rectangular, center of apex with concavity, distally with 5 simple setae and 5 medial setae on ventral palp surface, endite short, sub-triangular, apex bearing 1 seta.</p>
      <p>PEREOPODS. Pereopod 1 subchelate, basis about 1.3 times as long as greatest width, merus dorsal part trapezoidal, carpus triangular with protruding edge distally, propodus lower half protruding, forming a rounded corner near palm center, with 14 setae in mesial row on distal half of propodus, and 5 longer setae more proximally. Propodus of pereopods 2–6 distally with 1 sensory spine on palm. Pereopods 2–3 not subchelate, merus triangular, dorsal edge reaching nearly to propodus. Pereopod 2 propodus with cuticular scales laterally. Pereopods 4–6 merus nearly triangular, slightly as long as carpus. Pereopod 7 propodus as long as in pereopods 2–6.</p>
      <p>EXOPODS. Exopod of pleopod 1 operculiform, distal margin with 16 feathered setae, endopod about ½ of exopod width, margin with 9 feathered setae. Exopod of pleopods 2–5 as long as endopod. Pleopods 2–3 exopod distally with 6 feathered setae, endopod pleopod 2 with 6 feathered setae and 9 feathered setae on pleopod 3. Exopod of pleopods 4–5 with 5 feathered setae and endopod with 10 feathered setae, respectively. Uropod sympod elongate, distal margin with 3 feathered setae, endopod subovate, medially as long as laterally, about 0.3 sympod length. Exopod of uropod twice length of endopod and elongate oval, margin with 26 short feathered setae and 7 simple setae. Margins of endopod, exopod and tip of telson weakly crenulated. Telson tongue-shaped, with a pair of statocyst proximally, rounded apex bearing 3 pairs of setae, and on dorsal surface another 2 pairs of longer setae and 1 pair of short setae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This species belongs to the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
group of genera discussed by 
Poore (2001)
. Within the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Anthuridae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stygocyathura
Botosaneanu &amp; Stock, 1981
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cyathura
Norman &amp; Stebbing, 1886
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura
Menzies &amp; Glynn, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sauranthura
Poore &amp; Kensley, 1981
</tp:taxon-name>
possess a shortened pleon, shortest in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
, and they lack sensory spines distally on the carpus of P4–7. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura
Menzies &amp; Glynn, 1968
</tp:taxon-name>
is characterized by a pronounced rostrum, a maxilliped palp of only 1 rectangular article, and a very short uniarticulate mandibular palp.
</p>
      <p>
There are 10 named species that can be assigned to the genus, and there is a description of an unnamed species from 
Kalimantan
(see 
Negoescu 1997
). Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
have been found mostly in tropical seas. Most characters useful to distinguish the species can be found in the pereopod 1 propodus palm shape. The palm is generally convex, usually more so in its proximal half. The shape varies somewhat between the sexes, and males have a denser set of setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
