<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Colanthura gerungi Annisaqois &amp; Wägele 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5539423</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1A6987B821261F23FDEB6754FD00C76E</uri>
         <article-title>Morphology and Taxonomy of Isopoda Anthuroidea (Crustacea) from Sulawesi with description of six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.768.1501</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
1F397C5C-DDE1-440D-9B96-9B181CECA23D
</p>
      <p>
Figs 27–35
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
with expanded propodus of subchelate pereopod 1, palm with proximal triangular tubercle protruding at posterior margin; mesial surface beside this tubercle with row of 18 setae, propodus of subchelate pereopods 2–3 oval, 2 times long than wide, pereopod 2 with row of 5 medial sensory spines on propodus palm, six such spines on P3; uropod endopod ovate, about 0.8 times sympod length, exopod shorter and roughly triangular, margins of endopod, exopod and tip of telson weakly crenulated; telson tongue-shaped, rounded distal margin bearing 5 pairs of long setae, 2 pairs of short setae dorsomedially near apex, and 4 further pairs of dorsal setae near lateral margin.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura kensleyi
Poore, 1984
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Philippine and Sangihe Islands (north of the 
Sulawesi
area sampled for this study) shows close affinities to the material from Bangka Island described herein; both species are best distinguished through the uropod exopod, which is triangular to oval in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
,while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. kensleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
the uropod exopod has an elongate oval shape. Also, the propodus of pereopod 1 is wider in 

<tp:taxon-name>C. kensleyi</tp:taxon-name>
,

and lacks additional mesial setae distally. Three of these are present parallel to the palm of the female in our material. A redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. kensleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
is needed for further comparison (see also 
Poore 1984
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is dedicated to Dr Grevo Gerung, who sponsored and supervised the studies of the first author.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
INDONESIA
• 
♂
(
3.8 mm
); 
Bangka Island
, 
west of Coral Eye Resort
; 
1°45′20.77″ N
, 
125°7′57.28″ E
; 

1–2 m
depth

; 
in seagrass bed
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 109.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Allotype
INDONESIA
• 
♀
(
3.9 mm
); 
Bangka Island
, 
west of Coral Eye Resort
; 
1´°45′19.92″ N
, 
125°7′58.96″ E
; 

1–2 m
depth

; 
on mangrove roots
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 110.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Fig. 27.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (3.8 mm), in dorsal and lateral view (MZB Iso 109). Abbreviations: A1 = antenna 1; A2 = antenna 2; Mx = maxilla; Mxp = maxilliped.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 28.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (MZB Iso 109). Abbreviation: P1–P6 = pereopods 1–6.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 29.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (MZB Iso 109). Abbreviation: Plp1–Plp5 = pleopods 1–5.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
INDONESIA
• 
1 ♂
(
3.5 mm
), 
1 ♀
(
3.7 mm
), 
11 immature
specimens (
1.6–3.9 mm
); 
Bangka Island
; 
1°45′20.77″ N
, 
125°7′57.28″ E
; 

1–2 m
depth

; 
in seagrass bed
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 111
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 immature
specimen; 
Bangka Island
; 
1°45′19.92″ N
, 
125°7′58.96″ E
; 

1 m
depth

; 
on mangrove roots
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 112
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Bangka Island
, 
off Coral Eye Resort
; 
1°44′22.04″ N
, 
125°8′41.19″ E
; 

1–2 m
depth

; 
in coral rubble
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 113
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>BODY. Slender, about 13 times as long as greatest width, dorsally weakly pigmented, scattered small cuticular scales on body and part of appendages. Cephalothorax in dorsal view roughly as long as wide, pair of compound eyes with few but distinct ommatidia. Body proportions: C&lt;1&lt;2 = 3&gt;4&gt; 5&gt;6&gt;&gt;7. Pereonite 7 is strongly reduced, without appendages, not as long as pleonite 3 or 4. Pleonites 1–5 free, together length about as pereonite 6.</p>
      <p>
ANTENNAE. Antenna 1 with 6 flagellar articles, articles broader than long, many long aesthetascs surround flagellar segments, on last article 4 aesthetascs. Antenna 2 with short flagellum, basal flagellar article slightly as long as wide, followed by 3 minute articles. Mandible fused laterally to cephalothorax (see 
Fig. 31
), palp and molar absent. Maxilla 1 slender lanceolate, apex laterally serrated, with 11 saw-teeth. Maxilliped uniarticulate without sutures separating articles, bearing 9 simple setae, 8 of them near apex.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 30.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (MZB Iso 109). Abbreviations: UEx = exopod of uropod; UEn = endopod of uropod; Tel = telson.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 31.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, SEM-images of a male specimen. Cephalothorax in ventral and lateral view. The maxillipeds are flanked laterally by mandibles which are fused to the cephalothorax. This explains why mandibles are usually missing among dissected mouthparts of this genus. The part distally in between maxillipeds is the hypopharynx, which envelopes the maxillae and distal parts of the mandibles. Note the bulging lenses of lateral eyes.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 32.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀, allotype in dorsal and ventrolateral view (3.9 mm) (MZB Iso 110). Abbreviations: A1 = antenna 1; A2 = antenna 2; Mx = maxilla; Mxp = maxilliped.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 33.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀, allotype (MZB Iso 110). Abbreviation: P1–P6 = pereopods 1–6.
</p>
      <p>PEREOPODS. Pereopods 1–3 subchelate. Expanded propodus of pereopod 1 with proximal triangular tubercle protruding at posterior margin; mesial surface beside this tubercle with row of 18 setae and further setae on palm. Propodus of pereopods 2–3 oval, 2 times long than wide, dactylus reaching nearly to tip of carpus. Pereopod 2 with row of 5 medial sensory spines on propodus palm, six such spines on P3. Pereopods 4–6 dactylus shorter than propodus, propodus as long as wide and slightly curved, in P6 narrower than in P4 and P5, two sensory spines on palm of P4, three on P5 and P6; carpus lenght as merus, nearly rectangular and as long as wide, with 2 sensory spines on ventral margin, carpus and merus together roughly lenght of ischium.</p>
      <p>EXOPODS OF PLEOPOD. Exopod of pleopod 1 operculiform, distal margin with 13 feathered setae, endopod narrower, about ¼ of exopod width, margin with 13 feathered setae. Exopod of pleopod 2 distally with 7, endopod with 4 feathered setae. Appendix masculina surpassing tip of endopod, apex with a small hooked knob. Pleopods 3–4 endopod with 3, exopod with 6 distal feathered setae, on pleopod 5 only 5. Uropod endopod ovate, not surpassing telson. Endopod about 0.8 sympod lenght. Exopod of uropod shorter and triangular, with 12 simple setae and 8 feathered setae, most on margin. Margins of endopod, exopod and tip of telson weakly crenulated. Telson tongue-shaped, rounded distal margin bearing 5 pairs of long setae, 2 pairs of short setae dorsomedially near apex, and 4 further pairs of dorsal setae near lateral margin. Setation symmetry is imperfect.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 34.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀, allotype (MZB Iso 110). Abbreviations: UEx = exopod of uropod; UEn = endopod of uropod; Tel = telson.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 35.
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, immature specimens of different sizes (body length in mm). (MZB Iso 111) Comparison of exopods of uropods and telson setations.
</p>
      <p>
Ovigerous female
</p>
      <p>
Habitus resembling male (see 
Fig. 32
). Antenna 1 with 4-jointed flagellum; first article of flagellum short, ring-shaped, with 1 feather-like seta; second article longest, distally 2 minute articles; last article with 3 aesthetascs and 4 setae. Antenna 2 flagellum apparently uniarticulate, with whorl of distal setae. Acute mouth parts. Mandible fused laterally to cephalothorax (
Fig. 31
), without palp and without molar process. Maxilla 1 elongate, acute, distal part serrated with 10 saw-teeth. Maxilliped without sutures separating articles, apically 1 tiny and 4 longer setae. Pereopods 1–3 subchelate, propodi oval, width about two thirds of length, larger in pereopod 1, dactyli reaching to tip of carpus, carpus triangular. Propodus of pereopod 1 with mesial comb of 8 slender setae near proximal tubercle of palm, more distally three stouter mesial setae and further setae on palm. Palm of propodus of pereopod 2–3 with 5–6 sensory spines. Pereopods 4–6 dactylus shorter than propodus, propodus much as long as wide, slightly curved, with 2 (P4) or 3 (P5–6) sensory spines on palm; carpus dorsally with 1 feather like seta and ventrally 2 sensory spines. Exopod of pleopod 1 operculiform with 13 feathered setae on distal margin, endopod narrow, about ⅓ exopod width, distally with 9 feathered setae. Pleopods 2–5 endopod with 3 feathered setae and exopod with 8–5 feathered setae. Uropods not surpassing telson, exopod ovate, endopod shorter than sympod (0.6 sympod length) and smaller than exopod. Telson tongue-shaped, rounded distal margin bearing 5 pairs of long setae, 4 pairs of longer dorsal setae, and dorsally many irregularly scattered short setae.
</p>
      <p>
Immature specimens
</p>
      <p>
In all features quite similar to females. Total length 
1.6–3.9 mm
. The shape of the uropod exopod varies somewhat, but is in tendency triangular with rounded apex. The setation on the telson is not constant, with pairs of long setae on distal margin and further scattered setae dorsally (see 
Fig. 35
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This species belongs to the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
group of genera discussed by 
Poore (1984)
. The paranthurid genera 
<tp:taxon-name>
Califanthura
Schultz, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
Richardson, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cruregens
Chilton, 1882
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cruranthura
Thomson, 1946
</tp:taxon-name>
share the absence of pereopod 7, the short pereonite 7, the fusion of maxilliped basis and palp. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cruregens
</tp:taxon-name>
is blind, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cruranthura
</tp:taxon-name>
has fused pleonites 2–5 and a pereonite 7 that is short but well visible (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cruregens
</tp:taxon-name>
). Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Califanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
are very similar, and it might be that the character distinguishing 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Califanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
(pleonites not fused in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
) has not always been seen in species assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Califanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
and vice versa. Since free pleonites is the plesiomorphic state, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
might be a paraphyletic genus.
</p>
      <p>
Good illustrations of the mandible in these genera are not available. For the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
described herein, we discovered in SEM studies that the mandible is laterally fused to the cephalon and therefore it cannot be dissected with the other mouthparts (see 
Fig. 31
). This fusion might have caused the absence of illustrations of the mandible in descriptions of other species, too. The fusion of the mandible with the head capsule is a unique feature among isopods. It implies that the most active mouthpart is the movable maxilla, which probably is used as a stinging tool in these paranthurids, while mandibles and hypopharynx form a rigid sheath.
</p>
      <p>
We do not propose to place the genera with fused immobile mandible in a new family. This character evolved within the 
<tp:taxon-name>Paranthuridae</tp:taxon-name>
, and to separate some genera would leave the remaining ones in a paraphyletic group. This should always be avoided, to prevent the subjective and arbitrary creation of taxa. There are 13 described species with free pleonites that can be assigned to the genus. Unfortunately, several published species descriptions are very incomplete. Most characters useful to distinguish the species can be found in the uropod shape and setation. Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
have been found in tropical, temperate, and polar waters. Of the tropical species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura bruscai
Poore, 1984
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Mexico
and 
Costa Rica
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura pigmentata
Kensley, 1980
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Madagascar
have a broader propodus of pereopod 1 than 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Müller (1993)
reported a dorsally black 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura tenuis
</tp:taxon-name>
from Bora Bora, where the exopod of the uropod is more elongate than in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Müller’s species is probably not the same as 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. tenuis
</tp:taxon-name>
of 
Richardson (1902)
(redescribed by 
Poore 1984
), which occurs in the western Atlantic Ocean. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura nigra
Nunomura, 1975
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Japan
is also dorsally black and easily distinguished from other Indo-Pacific species. The uropod sympod is wider than in the specimens described herein. The redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. nigra
</tp:taxon-name>
by 
Poore (1984)
shows a uropod exopod with a distally straight outer margin. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura setouchiensis
Nunomura, 1993
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Japan
does not have the basal tubercle on the propodus palm of pereopod 1 that is present in most descriptions of 

<tp:taxon-name>Colanthura</tp:taxon-name>
.

<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura uncinata
Kensley, 1978
b
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
South Africa
has a small and narrow uropod exopod with very few setae. The exopod of the uropods of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. daguilarensis
Bamber, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
(a species from 
Hong Kong
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. bruscai
Poore, 1984
</tp:taxon-name>
has an outer margin that is distally slightly concave, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
the exopod is continuously oval. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gauguini
Müller, 1993
</tp:taxon-name>
from Moorea has a broad oval uropod exopod with only a few long setae on the distal half of the margin, where other species have in addition feathered setae. The Caribbean species 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. ornata
Carvacho, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
has been described with fused pleonites and might be a 
<tp:taxon-name>
Califanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
. Uropod shapes have not been published.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
