<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Smicronyx paucisquamis Haran, 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.735.1239</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/18FBF688169D1F8FCCD68AE5891D2A7B</uri>
         <article-title>The Smicronychini of southern Africa (Coleoptera, Curculionidae): Review of the tribe and description of 12 new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Smicronyx paucisquamis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1I
, 
4A
, 5H; 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Smicronyx paucisquamis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is closest to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. pseudocoecus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
. See differential diagnosis under that species for diagnostic traits.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Smicronyx paucisquamis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is named in reference to the very limited number of scales found on its elytra compared to other species in the genus.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
REPUBLIC OF SOUTH AFRICA
• 1 Ƌ; “ 
Rep. of South Africa
; 
Haenertsburg
[
Limpopo Province
]; 
23°56.361′S
29°57.037′E
; 

1380 m

, 

7.ii.2019

; 
J. Haran
leg.” / “On 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cuscuta
</tp:taxon-name>
sp.; JHAR02167” / “ 
HOLOTYPE
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Smicronyx paucisquamis
</tp:taxon-name>
; Haran 2021”; 
SAMC
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
REPUBLIC OF SOUTH AFRICA
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; ethanol coll. 
CBGP
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Mpumalanga Province
, 
God’s
window; 
24°54.396′ S
, 
30°51.650′ E
; 

6 Feb. 2019

; 
J. Haran
leg.; beating 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cuscuta
</tp:taxon-name>
sp.; JHAR02168; ethanol coll. 
CBGP
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
BODY LENGTH. 2.0– 
2.2 mm
.
</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Body integument entirely black, shiny, mostly bare of scales; vestiture of elytra consisting of white recumbent, elliptical, scales more than twice as long as wide, grouped into spots at base of interstria 3, basal ⅓ of interstriae 4–5 and middle of length of interstriae 3–5; each interstria with a series of short, recumbent, white setae.</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Rostrum as long as head + prothorax in lateral view, downcurved near base, less downcurved in apical half (
Fig. 4A
); dorsal face punctate, covered with suberect whitish setae forming four distinct series in basal ¾ and two spots near eyes, apical ⅓ glabrous; transverse furrow at base of rostrum shiny, bare of scales; head capsule glabrous; eyes flat, sub-contiguous on ventral side, space between them wider than the diameter of two ommatidia; scape of antennae slightly bisinuate, regularly widening toward apex, clavate in apical ⅓, segment 1 of funicle elongate, as long as 2 + 3, 4–7 wider than long.
</p>
      <p>PROTHORAX. Isodiametric (ratio w/l: 1), widest near middle of length, narrowed at apex, sides rounded; integument with large punctures, diameter of punctures wider than distance between punctures; scales</p>
      <p>whitish, elongate, semi-erect, not concealing the integument, mostly present at base of median line near scutellum and on sides of prothorax.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Sides moderately rounded, widest near middle of length (ratio w/l: 0.66); humeri raised; striae narrow, interstriae flat, wide, 4–5 × as wide as striae, integument shiny, slightly reticulate, apex of interstria 5 with a very moderate declivital callosity; scutellum small, covered with short whitish scales.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Underside mostly covered with overlapping white scales, more condensed on metanepisterna.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Covered with whitish, recumbent, elongate scales; femora clavate, armed with a very small ventral tooth usually concealed by scales; tibiae straight on external side, slightly bisinuate ventrally; claws equal in length.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Body of penis elongate (ratio w/l: 0.44), as long as apodemes, sides sub-parallel, slightly expanding from base to apex, converging near apex, truncate at apex, curvature in lateral view moderate and regular, tapering near apex (Fig. 5H).</p>
      <p>
Sexual dimorphism
</p>
      <p>Females are distinguished from males by their rostrum, which is slightly longer, and covered with scales only in basal ⅓ (in basal ½ in males).</p>
      <p>
Life history
</p>
      <p>
Adults were found in February on an unidentified 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cuscuta
</tp:taxon-name>
sp.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Republic of South Africa
(
Limpopo
and 
Mpumalanga
provinces).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
