<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Smicronyx similis Haran, 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">https://doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.735.1239</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2562C441C54AEDA82A38919150426D16</uri>
         <article-title>The Smicronychini of southern Africa (Coleoptera, Curculionidae): Review of the tribe and description of 12 new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Smicronyx similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1G
, 
3G
, 5F; 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Smicronyx similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is mostly similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. guineanus
Voss, 1956
</tp:taxon-name>
, a species widely distributed in tropical Africa. The two species can be distinguished by their general appearance, which is more robust in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
The second segment of the funicle is isodiametric in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
while it is distinctly longer than wide in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. guineanus
</tp:taxon-name>
, the elytra are wider in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
than in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. guineanus
</tp:taxon-name>
(ratio w/l: 0.68 and 0.58 respectively), and the integument of the prothorax of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is more coarsely punctate than in 

<tp:taxon-name>S. guineanus</tp:taxon-name>
.

The body of the penis in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is also thicker and less narrowed in the middle than in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. guineanus
</tp:taxon-name>
. In southern Africa, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is closest to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. gracilipes
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but the latter species has distinctly longer legs and rostrum and a finely punctate prothoracic integument (coarsely granulate in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. similis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name ʻsimilisʼ refers to the similar appearance of this species with 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. guineanus
</tp:taxon-name>
, which is a very widespread and abundant species in tropical Africa.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
REPUBLIC OF SOUTH AFRICA
• 1 Ƌ; “ 
S.Afr.
;N 
Cape Prov.
;Tswalu Nat. Res. 

1162m

; 
27.18S-
22.26E
” / “ 

14.2.2005

; E-Y [
Endrödy-Younga
leg.]; 3644; general [collecting] at Gosa lodge; Leg. M. Burger, 
R. Müller
” / “ 
HOLOTYPE
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Smicronyx similis
</tp:taxon-name>
; Haran 2021”; 
SANC
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
ZIMBABWE
• 
1 ♀
; 
Sebakwe
; 1903; 
D. Dods
leg.; SAM-COL-A073093; 
SAMC
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
BODY LENGTH. 
2.5 mm
.
</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Body integument black, shiny, antennae and legs reddish; vestiture of elytra with scattered, recumbent, brownish and whitish, rounded or elliptic scales, forming two ill-defined series on each interstria.</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Rostrum slightly longer than head capsule + prothorax, moderately downcurved in lateral view, slightly longer and more downcurved in 
♀
than in Ƌ, covered with scarce whitish scales dorsally (Ƌ) or scales only in basal ¼ (
♀
), shiny and slightly punctate at apex (Ƌ) or at apical ¾ (
♀
); antennae inserted slightly after middle of length (
♀
) or at apical ⅓ (Ƌ); transverse furrow at base of rostrum shiny, with two spots of whitish semi-erect scales on sides near eyes; head capsule glabrous, with slight cover of scales near transverse furrow; eyes flat, subcontiguous ventrally, distance between eyes equal to the width of 1–2 ommatidia; antennal scape slightly bisinuate at base, moderately clavate at apex, segment 1 of funicle elongate, slightly longer than 2 + 3, 4–7 wider than long.
</p>
      <p>PROTHORAX. Isodiametric (w/l ratio: 1), widest before middle, sides strongly rounded, narrowed in apical 1/4; integument densely and strongly granulate, shiny.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Sides slightly convex, widest near middle of length (w/l ratio: 0.68); humeri raised; interstriae flat, shiny, ½–⅓× as wide as striae, interstria 5 with a moderate declivital callosity near apex, followed by a slight depression; scutellum small but visible.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Underside mostly covered with non-overlapping greyish scales, twice as long as wide.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Femora clavate, armed with a small ventral tooth in middle; tibiae straight, unarmed; claws equal in length.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Body of penis elongate (w/l ratio: 0.23), 2× longer than apodemes, sides sub-parallel in basal ⅓, narrowed near middle of length, spatulate in apical ⅓, apex slightly acuminate, curvature in lateral view regular (Fig. 5F).</p>
      <p>
Life history
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Republic of South Africa
(
Northern Cape Province
), 
Zimbabwe
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
