<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Mesopolobus robiniae Lakatos &amp;
                        Laszlo 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4644005</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/222287CBFF81FFBB63CEC510ADB22EAC</uri>
                  <article-title>A new species of Mesopolobus (Hymenoptera, Pteromalidae) from black
                        locust crops</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.740.1285</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus robiniae Lakatos &amp; László </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 9650B871-3BF8-49C8-9329-43A67A3C2D5B </p>
            <p> Fig. 5 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is characterized by
                  having the following morphological characters: head with uniform reticulation,
                  antennae inserted at or above ventral edge of compound eyes, with three anelli,
                  head broader than mesoscutum, pronotal collar moderately long, marginal vein of
                  fore wing about twice as long as the stigma vein, metasoma longer than mesosoma,
                  with only slightly projecting ovipositor sheaths, body green, antennae proximally
                  testaceous with funiculus and clava infuscate, femora and tibiae testaceous, with
                  hyaline wings. <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  differs from closely resembling species by the ratios of metasoma to head plus
                  mesosoma length, of temples to eye length, of marginal to stigma vein, of pronotal
                  collar to mesoscutum length and of antennal clava to head length. Molecular
                  results: the three sequenced individuals represented one haplotype (GenBank
                  accession number: MF098549 ); based on the BI tree the new species, shows a
                  well-supported differentiation from <tp:taxon-name> M. verditer </tp:taxon-name>
                  as the closest species and from other congenerics with the maximal differentiation
                  from <tp:taxon-name> M. tibialis </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The new <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus </tp:taxon-name> species is named after the host
                  plant of its seed predator host, the black locust ( <tp:taxon-name> Robinia
                        pseudoacacia </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Holotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> ROMANIA • ♀ ; Bihor County , near Săldăbagiu de Munte ;
                        47.096354° N , 21.984963° E ; 11 Mar. 2015 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged on 1
                        Apr. 2015 ; MZBBU HYM000011 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> ROMANIA – Bihor County • 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for
                        holotype; MZBBU HYM000012 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1
                        ♀ ; near Săldăbagiu de Munte ; 47.100895° N , 21.967509° E ; 8 Mar. 2014 ;
                        T.K. Lakatos leg., emerged on 22 Apr. 2014 ; MZBBU HYM000017
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; near Săldăbagiu de Munte ;
                        47.098182° N , 21.975352° E ; 11 Mar. 2014 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged on
                        23 Apr. 2014 ; MZBBU HYM000018 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 2 ♂♂ ; near Săldăbagiu de Munte ; 47.098182° N ,
                        21.975352° E ; 8 Mar. 2014 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged on 22 Apr. 2014 ;
                        MZBBU HYM000019 , HYM000020 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation>
                        1 ♂ ; near Săldăbagiu de Munte ; 47.079446° N , 21.970817° E ; 14 Mar. 2009
                        ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged on May 2009 ; MZBBU HYM000021
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; near Săldăbagiu de Munte ;
                        47.098519° N , 21.984808° E ; 11 Mar. 2015 ; T.K. Lakatos leg., emerged on
                        Apr. 2015 ; MZBBU HYM000022 </tp:material-citation> . –
                        <tp:material-citation> Cluj County • 1 ♀ ; near Cluj-Napoca ; 46.777109° N ,
                        23.674495° E ; 17 Mar. 2015 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged on 10 Apr 2015 ;
                        MZBBU HYM000013 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same
                        collection data as for preceding; 18 Mar. 2014 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged
                        in May 2014 ; MZBBU HYM000014 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 2 ♀♀ ; near Cluj-Napoca ; 46.768086° N , 23.568935° E
                        ; 17 Mar. 2009 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged in Apr. 2009 , MZBBU HYM000015 ,
                        HYM000016 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; near
                        Cluj-Napoca ; 46.834976° N , 23.651004° E ; 22 Mar. 2014 ; T.K. Lakatos
                        leg.; emerged in May 2014 ; MZBBU HYM000024 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; near Cluj-Napoca ; 46.768086° N , 23.568935° E
                        ; 17 Mar. 2009 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged in May 2009 ; MZBBU HYM000025
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> HUNGARY • 1 ♂ ; Hajdú-Bihar County , near Debrecen ;
                        47.554773°N 21.591610°E ; 2 Mar. 2015 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged on Apr.
                        2015 ; MZBBU HYM000023 </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Other material (specimens used for the genetic analysis) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> ROMANIA • 3 ♀♀ ; Bihor County , near Săldăbagiu de Munte ;
                        47.0968° N , 21.98525° E ; 13 Mar. 2014 ; T.K. Lakatos leg.; emerged on 17
                        Apr. 2014 ; GenBank accession number: MF098549 . This specimens were fully
                        processed for the DNA extraction </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> LENGTH. 2.05 to 3.00 mm (N = 15, mean = 2.6, sd = 0.29 mm ). </p>
            <p>COLORATION. Body green, sometimes with golden reflections; metasoma bronze-black
                  distally, some of the tergites occasionally with blue or violet flecks. Coloration
                  of antennae: scape, pedicellus and anelli testaceous, sometimes last anellus
                  infuscate, all funicular segments and clava infuscate, occasionally brown. Coxae
                  concolorous with the mesosoma, femora and tibiae testaceous, the tips of the fifth
                  tarsi fuscous to black. Tegulae hyaline, usually slightly yellow posteriorly.
                  Wings hyaline; venation pale yellow.</p>
            <p>HEAD. 1.1 (range 1.02–1.18) times as broad as mesoscutum; in dorsal view 2.25
                  (2.07–2.52) times as broad as long, with temples rounded off and between one third
                  and one fourth as long as eyes; the distance between posterior ocelli (POL) 2.11
                  (1.75–2.80) times oculo-ocellar distance (OOL). Head in front view suboval with
                  the genae moderately buccate. Eyes separated about 1.59 (1.18–1.74) times their
                  length. Malar space more than half (0.68 (0.55–0.76)) the length of an eye.
                  Breadth of oral fossa 1.93 (1.69–2.36) times malar space. Clypeus strigose, its
                  anterior margin moderately emarginate. Head uniformly and moderately reticulate.
                  Antennae inserted low on head, lower edge of toruli at or hardly above level of
                  ventral edge of eyes; distance between clypeal margin and toruli 0.69 (0.54–0.8)
                  times the distance between median ocellus and toruli. Scape length 1.23 (1.09–1.4)
                  times eye length, scape almost reaching lower edge of median ocellus; combined
                  length of pedicellus and flagellum 0.87 (0.76–0.96) times breadth of head;
                  pedicellus (profile) 2.06 (0.75–2.5) times as long as broad, about as long as
                  anelli plus first funicular segment; flagellum rather weakly clavate, proximally
                  as stout as or slightly</p>
            <p> Fig. 5 (opposite page). <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus robiniae Lakatos &amp; László
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. a–b, e–f, i . ♀ (MZBBU HYM000034). c–d, g–h, j . ♂
                  (MZBBU HYM000035). k . Paratype , ♀ (MZBBU HYM000014). l . ♂ (MZBBU HYM000036). a
                  . Head, frontal view. b . Antenna. c . Head, frontal view. d . Antenna. e .
                  Mesosoma. f . Fore wing. g . Mesosoma. h . Fore wing. i . Gaster, dorsal view. j .
                  Gaster, dorsal view. k . Habitus. l . Habitus. Scale bars: a–j = 0.1 mm ; l–k =
                  0.5 mm </p>
            <p>.</p>
            <p>stouter than pedicellus; first and second anelli short, twice or slightly more than
                  twice as broad as long, third anellus longer than previous anellus and about 1.5
                  times as broad as long; funicular segments subquadrate, proximal ones sometimes
                  slightly longer than broad, distal ones occasionally very slightly transverse;
                  clava 1.9 (1.5–2.29) times as long as broad, 0.83 (0.66–1.15) as long as three
                  preceding funicular segments together; sensilla in one row on each segment, sparse
                  on funicle, more numerous on the clava.</p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. 1.52 (1.38–1.74) times as long as broad. Pronotal collar moderately long
                  medially, 0.21 (0.16–0.26) times (one sixth to one fifth) as long as mesoscutum,
                  and much longer at sides, strongly and coarsely reticulate, clearly margined.
                  Mesoscutum 1.58 (1.28–1.82) times as broad as long, rather coarsely reticulate
                  discally, more finely laterally, without piliferous punctures. Scutellum 0.9
                  (0.82–0.94) times as broad as long, moderately convex, finely reticulate, frenum
                  slightly more coarsely reticulate. Axillae finely reticulate. Dorsellum a narrow,
                  alutaceous transverse crest separated from scutellum by simple suture. Propodeum
                  medially slightly less than half (0.41 (0.36–0.48)) as long as scutellum; median
                  area 2.39 (2–3) times as broad as long, well-defined laterally, plicae distinct
                  throughout and sharp over at least their distal half; median carina distinct,
                  straight; panels of median area finely, slightly irregularly reticulate; nucha
                  transversely aciculate, separated from median area by impressed line; posterior
                  foveae, at sides of nucha, moderately deep; spiracles oval, longer than broad,
                  separated by nearly half their length from metanotum. Postspiracular sclerite
                  broad, shiny, weakly and irregularly sculptured. Mesepisternum moderately finely
                  reticulate, its upper triangular area smooth; mesepimeron rather more coarsely
                  reticulate than mesepisternum, metapleuron smooth. Legs rather short; femora
                  rather stout; mid tibiae fairly slender, 7.44 (4.88–9) times as long as their
                  maximum breadth. Fore wing rather broad; costal cell fairly broad, its upper
                  surface bare, lower surface with a complete row of hairs and some additional hairs
                  scattered over distal third to half; basal cell bare, open below; basal vein bare
                  or with one to three hairs; speculum open below, on upper surface of wing
                  extending below proximal end of the marginal vein; surface beyond speculum thickly
                  pilose; marginal vein 2.19 (2–2.47) times as long as stigmal vein; postmarginal
                  vein shorter than marginal, 0.73 (0.63–0.81) times as long as marginal.</p>
            <p>METASOMA. Ovate, 1.24 (1.16–1.33) times as long as mesosoma, 0.8 (0.66–0.96) times as
                  broad as mesosoma, 2.37 (1.91–2.96) times as long as broad; basal tergite
                  occupying from slightly more than one quarter to nearly one third of total length;
                  last tergite somewhat shorter than basal breadth, its length 1.07 (0.72–1.79)
                  times its breadth; ovipositor sheaths projecting at most very slightly; hypopygium
                  slightly reaching the middle of metasoma, ratio of hypopygium length to metasoma
                  length is 0.44 (0.35–0.54).</p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> LENGTH. 1.8 to 2.25 mm (N = 15, mean = 2.02, sd = 0.16 mm ). </p>
            <p>COLORATION. Head and mesosoma bright green; metasoma greenish dorsally with second
                  tergite (T2) and posterior half of first tergite (TI) yellow, third tergite (T3)
                  purplish; antennae bright testaceous; legs except coxae yellow, last tarsal
                  segments grey-brown.</p>
            <p>HEAD. Antenna with 3 anelli and 5 funicular segments, length of pedicel plus
                  flagellum 0.97 (0.85–1.04) times as breadth as head; scape 5.33 (4.6–6.25) times
                  as long as broad, without a boss on its anterior surface; flagellum proximally not
                  broader than pedicel, F1-F4 longer than broad, F5 subquadrate. Mouthparts
                  unmodified; no patch of modified sculpture behind malar sulcus.</p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. Pronotal collar as long as in females, about 0.21 (0.18–0.27) times
                  mesoscutal length. Middle tibiae unmodified, 7.42 (6.29–8.8) times its breadth,
                  tibial spur 1.47 (1.17–1.8) times breadth of first tarsus.</p>
            <p>METASOMA. Oblong, ovate, 0.91 (0.83–1.02) times as long as mesosoma, 2.24 (1.63–2.63)
                  times as long as broad with a yellow ventral plica; T1 with triangular depression
                  at base.</p>
            <p> Morphological comparison </p>
            <p> Females of <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. were not
                  identifiable based on Graham’s keys ( Graham 1969 ), but several morphologically
                  and morphometrically related species were found for which the differing characters
                  will be enumerated in the order that the species appear in Graham’s key. The
                  species <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. has a shorter
                  metasoma compared to head plus mesosoma in <tp:taxon-name> M. maculicornis
                  </tp:taxon-name> . The species <tp:taxon-name> M. jucundus (Walker, 1834)
                  </tp:taxon-name> has a curved stigmal vein compared to <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus robiniae </tp:taxon-name>
                  sp. nov. differs from <tp:taxon-name> M. fasciiventris </tp:taxon-name> by its
                  males having 3 anelli and 5 funicular segments while in the latter there are 2
                  anelli and 6 segments. Females of <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. differ from those of <tp:taxon-name> M. fasciiventris </tp:taxon-name> in the
                  ratios of pcl.l3/mav.l and clv.l/ hea.l (for abbreviations see Table 2 , for
                  differences Table 3 ). The head of <tp:taxon-name> M. apicalis </tp:taxon-name> in
                  dorsal view has temples nearly three quarters as long as the eyes, while
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. has its head in dorsal
                  view with temples appearing one quarter to one third as long as the eyes. The
                  metasoma of <tp:taxon-name> M. amaenus </tp:taxon-name> is less than twice as long
                  as broad and almost as long as the mesosoma, while in the case of <tp:taxon-name>
                        M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. the metasoma is not less than twice as
                  long as broad, but it is as long as the mesosoma. The species <tp:taxon-name> M.
                        longicollis </tp:taxon-name> has the pronotal collar 1/7 to 1/6 as long as
                  the mesoscutum and its metasoma is less than twice as long as broad compared to
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. The species
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. diffinis </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> M.
                        meditteraneus </tp:taxon-name> differ from <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. because the latter has longer marginal vein (1.4 to 1.6)
                  than length of the stigmal vein. </p>
            <p> The species <tp:taxon-name> M. verditer </tp:taxon-name> is not present in the keys
                  of Graham (1969) because it has a North American distribution. It differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. in the following:
                  antennal funicle segments shorter than their breadth, while in <tp:taxon-name> M.
                        robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. they are at least as long as their
                  breadth. The ratio of the stigmal vein to the last gastral tergite length is
                  1.91–2.50 in <tp:taxon-name> M. verditer </tp:taxon-name> , while in
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is between 0.08–1.15.
                        <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus sericeus </tp:taxon-name> differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. first by having 2
                  anelli and 6 funicular segments, but also in having the ratio of the stigmal vein
                  to the last gastral tergite length 1.41, while in the other species this ratio is
                  smaller (0.8–1.15). In <tp:taxon-name> M. typographi </tp:taxon-name> the median
                  area of the propodeum is 1.75–2 times as broad as long ( Graham 1969 ) while in
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is 0.82–0.94 times as
                  broad as long (N = 15). </p>
            <p> Based on von Rosen’s key ( von Rosen 1958 ), the morphological identification of
                  specimens led us to <tp:taxon-name> M. mediterraneus </tp:taxon-name> as the
                  closest species, from which females of <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs, apart from the previously mentioned longer
                  marginal than stigmal vein, in also having a longer pronotal collar and a shorter
                  metasoma than the combined length of head and mesosoma. </p>
            <p> Gahan (1932: 739) states that <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus </tp:taxon-name> (syn.
                        <tp:taxon-name> Amblymerus </tp:taxon-name> ) <tp:taxon-name> verditer (
                        Norton 1868 ) </tp:taxon-name> “…conforms very closely to the characters of
                  the genus <tp:taxon-name> Amblymerus Walker </tp:taxon-name> as represented by
                        <tp:taxon-name> Amblymerus amoenus Walker </tp:taxon-name> …” (syn.
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. amaenus </tp:taxon-name> ), when transferring the species
                  to the genus <tp:taxon-name> Amblymerus Walker, 1834 </tp:taxon-name> from the
                  genus <tp:taxon-name> Nasonia Ashmead, 1904 </tp:taxon-name> . The hosts of
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. verditer </tp:taxon-name> are usually sawflies (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> :
                        <tp:taxon-name>Diprionidae</tp:taxon-name> ) on pines ( <tp:taxon-name>
                        Pinus </tp:taxon-name> sp.) ( Noyes 2020 ). <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus
                        verditer </tp:taxon-name> is distributed in the Nearctic and Germany (
                  Thompson 1958 ). Moreover, <tp:taxon-name> M. verditer </tp:taxon-name> differs
                  from <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. in having a reticulated
                  middle area of propodeum and oblique wrinkles, as does also from <tp:taxon-name>
                        M. amaenus </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> M. longicollis ( von Rosen
                        1958 ) </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> We propose the following update to the key of <tp:taxon-name> Mesopolobus
                  </tp:taxon-name> species of Graham (1969) for females: </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>16. Either metasoma at least slightly longer than head plus mesosoma, and usually
                  more than twice as long as broad, or metasoma not longer than head plus mesosoma,
                  and at most twice as long as broad
                  ..........................................................................................................................................16A</p>
            <p> – Metasoma not longer than head plus mesosoma, their ratio is 0.94 (0.88–0.98),
                  metasoma usually more than twice, 2.37 (1.91–2.96) times as long as broad
                  ..............................................................
                  ............................................................................................
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae Lakatos &amp; László </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </p>
            <p>16A. Metasoma at least slightly longer than head plus mesosoma, usually more than
                  twice as long as</p>
            <p>broad
                  ............................................................................................................................................
                  17 – Metasoma not longer than head plus mesosoma, at most twice as long as broad
                  ....................... 27</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> The type locality for <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp.nov. is
                  Săldăbagiu de Munte, Bihor County , Romania ( 47.096354° N , 21.984963° E ). The
                  other localities are situated in the neighbouring counties: Cluj County , Romania
                  and Hajdú-Bihar County , Hungary . The species may appear in the Carpathian Basin
                  where its host plant is present, but we expect that it may also be found outside
                  of the Carpathian Basin, in Eastern Europe and maybe throughout Europe. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Biology </p>
            <p> Based on our rearing, <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. seems to
                  be an early flying parasitoid species. Individuals of the species emerged during
                  spring consequently in all study years. Our black locust seedpod samples were
                  collected mostly in March, and the emergence peak of <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. was in April, with a decrease in May. After May, we
                  rarely encountered any individuals of this parasitoid species. </p>
            <p> The host of <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. may be
                        <tp:taxon-name> Bruchophagus robiniae </tp:taxon-name> but there is no
                  information regarding the host plant of <tp:taxon-name> B. robiniae
                  </tp:taxon-name> before the introduction of black locust. Another possibility is
                  that <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. initially had another
                  host, but switched from it to <tp:taxon-name> B. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> .
                  Either possibility is plausible; before 1970 ( Zerova 1970 ) the species
                        <tp:taxon-name> B. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> was not known, and
                        <tp:taxon-name> M. robiniae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. was not described
                  until now. The parasitoid community of black locust is understudied, and the
                  available literature makes no mention of parasitoids in this community ( Farkas
                  &amp; Terpó-Pomogyi 1974 ; Perju 1998 ), with the exception of our ecological
                  study concerning the seed-predator community of black locust in Eastern Europe (
                  Lakatos et al. 2016 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
