<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Higginsarctus martini Hansen &amp; Kristensen 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5213164</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2678D5797B5CFFFDFDFFFCB3940C7062</uri>
         <article-title>A new genus and five new species of the subfamily Florarctinae (Tardigrada, Arthrotardigrada)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.762.1461</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus martini
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
0373D8D1-209D-4853-936F-CC4E5DA584CB
</p>
      <p>
Figs 12–13
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
(characters uniquely defining the taxon are written in bold)
</p>
      <p>
Characterized by 
ovoid, dome-shaped secondary clavae
. 
Bilobed antero-lateral alae with medial pointed indentations
. Bilobed medio-lateral alae with medial pointed indentations. Medio-lateral alae smaller than antero-lateral alae. 
Trilobed postero-lateral alae each with anterior pointed indentation and posterior arched indentation
. Postero-lateral alae larger than antero-lateral alae. 
Quadrilobed, round caudal ala
with 3 arched indentations, 1 medial and 2 lateral. Medial lobes of caudal ala smaller than lateral lobes. Leg sense organs I–III with similar length. Genital stoup present.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The new species is dedicated to Dr Martin Vinther Sørensen for his contributions to meiofauna research.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
FRANCE
• 
♀
; 
North Atlantic Ocean
, 
English Channel
, 
Bay of Morlaix
, 
Roscoff
; 
48°43′ N
, 
03°54′ W
; depth 

20–30 m

; 

15 Mar. 1982

; 
R.M. Kristensen
leg.; 

<tp:taxon-name>
Dentalium
</tp:taxon-name>
sand

; 
NHMD-293903
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
HABITUS. The holotypic female (
Figs 12–13
) is 159 µm long from the anterior margin of the head to the posterior margin of the body. The body is ovoid, being broadest (79 µm) at the level between the second and third pair of legs. Intersegmental folds are not recognisable.
</p>
      <p>
ALAE.Typical for the genus, eight alae, which are all clearly separated from each other, are present: frontal ala, a pair of antero-lateral alae, a pair of medio-lateral alae, a pair of postero-lateral alae and a single caudal ala (
FigS 12
, 
13A
). The antero-lateral alae each have a medial pointed indentation dividing each ala into two lobes of equal size. The medio-lateral alae which are smaller than the antero-lateral alae, each have a medial pointed indentation dividing each ala into two lobes of equal size. The posterolateral alae which are larger than both the antero-lateral and medio-lateral alae, each have an anterior pointed indentation and a posterior arched indentation defining a small medial lobe and two larger lateral lobes. The caudal ala has an overall round shape with a deep medial, arched indentation and a pair of lateral, arched indentations dividing the ala into four lobes. The medial lobes are smaller than the lateral lobes. As in all species of the new genus, the proximal halve of the lateral and caudal alae is internally supported by continuous procuticle which sends out branching processes (ramuli) into the distal halve of the alae.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 12.
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus martini
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (NHMD-293903). Ventral overview. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Drawing by Stine B. Elle.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 13.
Micrographs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus martini
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (NHMD-293903). 
A
. Overview (PhC). 
B
. Close up on the head (DIC), ventral view showing the cephalic cirri and secondary clavae. 
C
. Close up on the bucco-pharyngeal apparatus (DIC). 
D
. Close up on the caudal region (DIC), ventral view showing the gonopore, genital stoup and anus. Abbreviations: see Material and methods.
</p>
      <p>
SENSORY ORGANS. The head is not well defined from the body and a complete set of sense organs is present. All the cephalic cirri consist of an hourglass-shaped scapus, a long tubular portion and a protruding flagellum. As in most other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Florarctinae</tp:taxon-name>
the scapus of each cirrus appears somewhat outsized, enveloping the internal sensory structures rather than lining them. The internal cirri (33 µm) emerge from the frontal ala at the anterior margin of the head. The external cirri (21 µm) are inserted ventrally and the median cirrus (16 µm) mid-dorsally. Typical for the genus, the primary clava (48 µm) is slightly curved and non-flexible (
Figs 12
, 
13A
). A van der Land’s body is visible inside its base. Primary clava and lateral cirrus (28 µm) arise on the same cirrophore, and a common membrane (extended margin of cirrophore) surrounds the base of primary clava and lateral cirrus. A very large and thick cuticular ring supports the cirrophore internally. The secondary clavae are ovoid, dome-shaped papillae (6 µm × 3 µm) flanking the mouth cone. The leg I sense organ (10 µm) is an unsegmented spine with a slightly swollen base and a terminal tube. The sense organs of leg II (8 µm) and III (8 µm) are unsegmented tapering spines. The fourth leg sense organ (10 µm) is an elongate papilla with a basal van der Land’s body and a terminal pore. The cirrus E (42 µm) has a prominent cirrophorus, scapus and a long tapering flagellum.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS, DIGITS AND CLAWS. The legs consist of coxa, femur, tibia and tarsus as found in all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Florarctinae</tp:taxon-name>
. The external digits are supported by internal hook-shaped peduncles. The external claw is simple and with a calcar. The internal claw has an accessory spine, but no calcar. All the claws are of the same size, however the external claws are thicker basally and the internal claws have an almost straight portion dorsally. An internal partition is evident as a small notch in each claw, dividing the claw in a basal portion and a distal portion.
</p>
      <p>
BUCCO- PHARYNGEAL APPARATUS. The mouth cone is large with a terminal, very refractive cupola, through which the distal part of the stylets protrudes (
Figs 12
, 
13B
). The buccal tube is 40 µm long and thin (
Fig. 13C
). The stylets are 43 µm long and very thin, each with a well-developed furca. The placoids are short and thick (
Fig. 13C
).
</p>
      <p>
REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM. Consists of a single ovary in which only a single large ovum can be recognized. The ovary is 57 µm long and is attached dorsally, at the level of the second pair of legs. The gonopore consists of a rosette with six large cells (
Fig. 13D
). Posterior to the rosette, the cuticle forms what appears in LM to be a broad fold which we interpret as the genital stoup. The two cuticular seminal receptacles each consist of a spheroid vesicle and an S-shaped genital duct. The cuticle is slightly elevated at each duct opening but does not form a true papilla. The anus is a trilobed cuticular system consisting of two large lateral lobes and a smaller posterior lobe.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology and distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
