<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
B191A524-2C5F-4DBD-93BA-7DC1ADB82CC7
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus signeae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
A genus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Florarctinae</tp:taxon-name>
characterized by large, rigid and backwards bending primary clavae (shared with 

<tp:taxon-name>Ligiarctus</tp:taxon-name>
)

supported by strong internal cuticular structures at their bases. Secondary clavae occurring as papillae (dome-shaped or spherical) or as flat sacs (round, rectangular or bilobed). Frontal ala, six lateral alae and a single caudal ala present. The proximal part of the alae (except for the frontal) internally supported by procuticle which sends out branching processes (ramuli) into the distal part of the alae. External claws with calcars and with small internal notches; internal claws with accessory spines and small internal notches.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The new genus is dedicated to Dr Robert P. Higgins for his contributions to meiofauna research. 
Higgins +arctus
(latinised Greek word), meaning Higgins’s bear.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Table 1.
Differential table of major morphological characters in species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
   <p>
      <tp:taxon-name>
H. signeae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
H. shintai
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
H. lassei
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
H. martini
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
H. laurae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
H. alatus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
Secondary clava
Flat, rectangular with sligthly protruding contours
Flat, comma- shaped
Flat, oval
Ovoid, dome- shaped
Spherical
Flat, bilobed
Antero-lateral ala
Unilobed without indentation
Unilobed without indentation
Unilobed without indentation
Bilobed with medial pointed indentation
Trilobed with pair of medial pointed indentations
Unilobed without indentation
Medio-lateral ala
Unilobed without indentation
Unilobed without indentation
Bilobed with medial pointed indentation
Bilobed with medial pointed indentation
Bilobed with medial pointed indentation
Unilobed without indentation
Postero-lateral ala
Bilobed, rectangular with medial arched indentation
Bilobed with medial pointed indentation
Bilobed with medial arched indentation
Trilobed with anterior pointed indentation and posterior arched indentation
Bilobed with medial pointed indentation
Bilobed with medial arched indentation
Caudal ala
Quadrilobed, rectangular with 3 arched indentations
Quadrilobed, rectangular with 3 arched indentations
Quadrilobed, rectangular with 3 arched indentations
Quadrilobed, round with 3 arched indentations
Bilobed, round with medial pointed indentation
Bilobed, rectangular with medial arched indentation
Leg sensory organs I–III
Similar in length
Similar in length
Similar in length
Similar in length
Similar in length
Highly different in length
Genital stoup
Present
–
Present
Present
–
Present
Genital papilla
Absent
Absent
Absent
Absent
Absent
Present
Folia
Present
Absent
Absent
Absent
Present
Absent
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 1.
General features of the lateral alae of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
The procuticle sends out branches (ramuli) to the edge of the alae. Drawing by Stine B. Elle.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
shares with species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Florarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Wingstrandarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
the presence of alae, the shape of the cephalic cirri and fourth leg sense organ, the shape of the seminal receptacles, and the presence of internal hook-shaped peduncles. The very characteristic primary clavae, being large, rigid and backward bending, are shared only with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
. It is very apparent that this new genus belongs to 
<tp:taxon-name>Florarctinae</tp:taxon-name>
, perhaps being closest related to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
. However, three characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
set the genus apart from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Florarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Wingstrandarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
, namely the number of lateral alae, the branching processes of procuticle reaching the distal part of the alae, and the presence of a small internal notch both on external and internal claws.
</p>
      <p>
The term ‘caestus’(from Latin = ‘gauntlet’), originally suggested by 
Renaud-Mornant (1987)
, has been generally adopted as a term for the supporting procuticle of the alae in species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Florarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
(

Fontoura 
et al
. 2017

; 
Hansen &amp; Kristensen 2020
). While the procuticle of the alae in species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Florarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
generally forms proximal lobate processes, it is much different in species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
where the entire proximal half of the alae are supported by a procuticle which sends out branching processes into the distal part of the alae. It is therefore suggested to refer to this special configuration of the supporting structure in the alae of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
as ‘ramuli’ (plural form of ‘ramulus’ (Latin) meaning ‘a small branch’).
</p>
      <p>
The six species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
described below differ conspicuously in the morphology of the secondary clava. Further distinguishing characters include differences in alae morphology, genital features and ventral cuticular structures (
Table 1
).
</p>
      <p>
As in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Florarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Wingstrandarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
, the distal margin of the lateral and caudal alae in species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
are characterised by small or larger indentations. Although being essential to an accurate description of alae morphology of each species, previous studies have not discriminated between 
types
of indentations. Having studied numerous species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Florarctinae</tp:taxon-name>
we believe that two morphological distinct 
types
of indentations can be recognised, namely the ‘pointed’ 
type
(
Fig. 1
) and the ‘arched’ 
type
(
Fig. 1
). Consequently, the 
two types
are discriminated in the species descriptions below. We also suggest considering both 
types
in all future descriptions of species belonging to 
<tp:taxon-name>Florarctinae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
A new genital structure not observed previously in tardigrades is recognised in 4 out of 6 species. It is situated immediately posterior to the gonopore and will be referred to as the ‘genital stoup’ as it resembles the shape of the holy water holder (

Figs 
2

, 
4E
). Further investigation is needed to determine the exact function of this structure but it likely plays a role in either copulation or oviposition by facilitating the detention of spermatids/spermatozoa. The presence or absence of a genital stoup in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus shintai
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. laurae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
cannot be determined with certainty in the present study. Thus, it might be confirmed as an apomorphy of the new genus, pending a closer study of new material.
</p>
      <p>
A special kind of leaf-like structures are present on the ventral cuticle in the two species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus signeae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen et sp. nov. (
Fig. 2
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. laurae
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Figs 14
, 
16C
). Such structures have not been discussed or named previously in 
<tp:taxon-name>Florarctinae</tp:taxon-name>
although they are present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Florarctus heimi
Delamare-Deboutteville &amp; Renaud-Mornant, 1965
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

Gąsiorek 
et al
. 2021

: fig. 6), and will tentatively be referred to as ‘folia’ (plural form of ‘folium’ (Latin), meaning a thin leaf-like structure or lamella, a leaf, especially a thin leaf or plate (geometry)).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
