<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ligiarctus Renaud-Mornant 1982</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5211799</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2678D5797B56FFC5FEFEF8AF936673BA</uri>
         <article-title>A new genus and five new species of the subfamily Florarctinae (Tardigrada, Arthrotardigrada)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.762.1461</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus
Renaud-Mornant, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
(emended by 

Gomes-Júnior 
et al
. 2018

)
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type species
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus eastwardi
Renaud-Mornant, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Amended diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
A genus of 
<tp:taxon-name>Florarctinae</tp:taxon-name>
with narrow head. Wide implementation of the primary clavae occupying the lateral edge of the head. Large, rigid and backwards bending primary clavae (shared with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
) supported by strong internal cuticular structures at their bases. Frontal and caudal ala (without procuticular support) present in females. Frontal ala absent in males. Claws of external digits with internal distal notch.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus eastwardi
Renaud-Mornant, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
USA
• 
♂
, adult; 
Atlantic Ocean
: 
North Carolina
; 
34°07.3′ N
, 
75°57.7′ W
; depth 

400 m

; 1974; 
B.C. Coull
and 
R.P. Higgins
; R/V 
Eastward
; 
fine sand
; 
MNHN
AH551
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
USA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Atlantic Ocean
, 
North Carolina
; 
34°07.4′ N
, 
75°57.0′ W
; depth 

439 m

; 

16 Nov. 1983

; 
R.P. Higgins
leg. (RH 1834); R/V 
Cape Hatteras
; 
NHMD-293914
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Following the exclusion of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus alatus
</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus alatus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
) from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
, the genus diagnosis is amended to include only characters exhibited by 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus eastwardi
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
The original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus eastwardi
</tp:taxon-name>
by 
Renaud-Mornant (1982)
included only males. In the present study, we were able to obtain information on female characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus eastwardi
</tp:taxon-name>
for the first time, from the single female collected at the 
type
locality in 1983. The specimen is clearly an adult female with evident seminal receptacles and typical female gonopore consisting of a rosette of six cells. The female is 161 µm long from the anterior margin of the head to the posterior margin of the body. The body is ovoid, being broadest (81 µm) at the level between the second and third pair of legs. The primary clava is 53 µm long and slightly curved. Secondary clavae are not recognizable. A small frontal ala is evident, extending between the internal cirri. The caudal ala is disc-shaped without any procuticular support.
</p>
      <p>Comparing the female specimen to the holotypic male, strong secondary sexual dimorphism is indicated by body size, clava length and by the presence of a frontal ala in females. The male is much smaller (109 µm) than the female (161 µm), and the primary clavae proportionally much longer (52 µm).</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
