<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Higginsarctus alatus Hansen &amp; Kristensen 2021, gen. et comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5213168</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/966A6765194487ACCB9808828ACDCEB7</uri>
         <article-title>A new genus and five new species of the subfamily Florarctinae (Tardigrada, Arthrotardigrada)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.762.1461</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 17–18
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Amended diagnosis
(characters uniquely defining the taxon are written in bold)
</p>
      <p>
Characterized by 
flat, bilobed secondary clavae
. Unilobed, rectangular antero-lateral alae with weakly undulating distal margins without indentations. Unilobed, rectangular medio-lateral alae with weakly undulating distal margins without indentations. Antero-lateral alae and medio-lateral alae similar in size. Bilobed postero-lateral alae with a medial arched identation. Postero-lateral alae larger than antero-lateral alae and medio-lateral alae. 
Bilobed, rectangular caudal ala
with deep arched identation medially. Lobes of the caudal ala nearly rectangular. 
Leg sense organs I–III highly different in length
. Genital stoup present. 
Duct openings of seminal receptacles with true papillae
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
Southwestern Atlantic Ocean
, 
Potiguar Basin
, 
Rio Grande do Norte State
; 
04°37′ S
, 
36°45′ W
; depth 

150 m

; 2009; 
bioclastic and lithoclastic sand
; P. Fontoura (C. 

VII-84

).

</p>
      <p>
Paratype
BRAZIL
• 
1 spec.
; same collection data as for holotype; 
P. Fontoura
(C. 

VII-87

)

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The results of our examination of the species described as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ligiarctus alatus
</tp:taxon-name>
confirm the presence of large, rigid and backwards bending primary clavae supported by strong internal cuticular structures at their bases, proximal part of the alae internally supported by procuticle which sends out branching processes (ramuli) into the distal part of the alae, and all claws with a small internal notch. Furthermore, it is evident that this species has three pairs of lateral alae. Thus, conforming to the diagnosis of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
, the species is here transferred to the new genus as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus alatus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
In addition, our observations revealed the presence of a genital stoup (
Figs 17B
, 
18A
) and genital papillae (
Figs 17B
, 
18A
). We were also able to determine the shape of the secondary clavae (
Figs 17A
, 
18B
). As a consequence of the new information attained, the diagnosis of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Higginsarctus alatus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
is amended accordingly.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology and distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
