<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Paratranes Zimmerman 1994</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514575</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/311F2D1BFFCDFF9A0B72522FFB539DF6</uri>
         <article-title>A review of Paratranes Zimmerman, 1994, Xanthorrhoea-associated weevils of the Tranes group (Coleoptera, Curculionidae, Molytinae), with description of a new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.767.1493</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratranes
Zimmerman, 1994
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1–10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Paratranes
Zimmerman, 1994: 695
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Paratranes
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Oberprieler 1995: 306

; 

2004: 183

(classification, host associations). — 

Alonso-Zarazaga &amp; Lyal 1999: 210

(catalogue); 2014: 560 (classification, host associations). — 

Oberprieler &amp; Caldara 2012: 57

(classification, host associations). — 


Pullen 
et al
. 2014: 289


(catalogue). — 


Anderson 
et al
. 2018: 2


(classification, host associations). — 

Legalov 2018: 345

(key, catalogue, classification).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tranes monopticus
Pascoe, 1870
</tp:taxon-name>
, by monotypy.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Body slender and depressed, completely shiny black; pronotal and elytral derm nearly nude, covered with very short setae (
Fig. 1A
). Rostrum moderately long, equally long in both sexes (
Fig. 4
). Eyes dorsally well separated (
Fig. 1C
); ventrally very narrowly separated, as narrowly as procoxae (
Fig. 1B
); forehead slightly narrower than basal width of rostrum (
Fig. 1C
). Antennae inserted at about distal third of rostrum in both sexes, not sexually dimorphic (
Fig. 4
); funicles 7-segmented but segment 7 closely approximated to club and nearly continuous in outline with it, segments 1 and 2 short, 2 slightly longer or as long as apical width of scape and slightly shorter than segments 3+4 (
Fig. 5
); clubs stout and short, distinctly shorter than funicles, 4-segmented, with small conical apical segment, appearing 5-segmented due to funicle segment 7 being closely approximated to basal club segment. Pronotum distinctly narrower than elytra at humeri, with sides weakly to moderately arcuate (
Fig. 3
); surface punctate, punctures separate on disc but confluent and vague laterally (
Fig. 1D
). Elytra elongate, jointly ca 0.5–0.6× as broad as long, sides subparallel or slightly diverging apicad, subapically slightly indented (
Fig. 2A
); surface nearly flat (
Figs 3–4
). Prothorax with anterior margin laterally extended into weak ocular lobes ventrally separated by shallow emargination (
Fig. 1B
); prosternum before procoxal cavities impunctate or sparsely punctate medially; procoxal cavities confluent, with procoxae contiguous; metanepisterna without sclerolepidia. Femora distinctly sulcate beneath; meso- and metatibiae with distal setal combs continued around apex and extending to almost middle of tibia (
Fig. 2B
), metatibiae with dorso-apical corner rounded. Terminalia: tergite VII of female subtrapezoidal (
Fig. 2C
), with posterior margin subtruncate, anterior margin ca 1.5–1.9× as wide as posterior margin; tergite VIII of male subquadratic (
Fig. 2D
), with posterior margin subtruncate, of female subtrapezoidal (
Fig. 7A, C
), very long in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. monopticus
</tp:taxon-name>
, ca 0.9–1.8 × as long as width at anterior margin, posterior margin subtruncate, anterior margin ca 1.4–1.5 × as wide as posterior margin; sternite VIII of female with sclerotised parts of apical lobes slender, linear (
Fig. 7B, D
); tegmen with oval to rounded ring (
Fig. 7I–J
), manubrium distinctly shorter than parameroid lobes; penis subparallel (
Fig. 8
), dorsum strongly sclerotised at both sides, forming a broad median groove, apical margin roundly subtruncate or slightly medially emarginate, body distinctly shorter than temones (ca 2.0–3.0 ×); endophallus (
Fig. 8A–B, D–E
) membranous, long, extending below body of penis, apically with anchor-shaped symmetrical armature composed of two strongly hooked sclerites joined medially to form a common stalk (
Fig. 9A–D
); ovipositor short (
<tp:taxon-name>
P. zimmermani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
) to long (
<tp:taxon-name>
P. monopticus
</tp:taxon-name>
), ca 1.5–5.7 × as long as wide, proximal gonocoxite ca 0.8–1.4 × as long as distal gonocoxite (
Fig. 10A–B
), gonostyli subapical, broad, apically truncate, with few long setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 1.
Diagnostic external characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratranes
Zimmerman, 1994
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A
. Elytral surface and setae. 
B
. Eyes and prothorax, ventral view. 
C
. Head and base of rostrum, dorsal view. 
D
. Pronotal surface. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Paratranes
</tp:taxon-name>
is here classified in the tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Orthorhinini</tp:taxon-name>
, following 

Anderson 
et al
. (2018)

, who included the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
</tp:taxon-name>
group in this tribe based on the strongly supported relationship between 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
Schoenherr, 1843
</tp:taxon-name>
and the orthorhinine genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Vanapa
Pouillaude, 1915
</tp:taxon-name>
found by 

Shin 
et al
. (2017)

in a robust phylogenetic analysis of 522 protein-coding genes. Without considering these results, 
Legalov (2018)
recently proposed a separate tribe for the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
</tp:taxon-name>
group, Tranini (incorrectly formed as ‘Tranesini’; see 
Hsiao &amp; Oberprieler (2020))
, but his diagnosis of Tranini did not distinguish the group from 
<tp:taxon-name>Orthorhinini</tp:taxon-name>
, and it further contained characters not present in all the included genera. Pending further and more detailed analysis of the phylogenetic relationships of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
</tp:taxon-name>
group, it is premature to afford it tribal status in 
<tp:taxon-name>Molytinae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
Diagnostic external characters and terminalia of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratranes
Zimmerman, 1994
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A
. Elytral apex. 
B
. Right metatibia. 
C
. Tergite VII of female. 
D
. Tergite VIII of male. Scale bars = 0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>
The relationships of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratranes
</tp:taxon-name>
to the other genera of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
</tp:taxon-name>
group also remain uncertain for the moment. It agrees with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miltotranes
Zimmerman, 1994
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Howeotranes

Zimmerman, 
1994
</tp:taxon-name>
in lacking sclerolepidia along its metanepisternal sutures, which are present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Demyrsus
Pascoe, 1872
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Siraton
Hustache, 1934
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Oberprieler &amp; Caldara 2012
; 
Lyal 2014
; 
Hsiao &amp; Oberprieler 2020
), but how closely related it may be to the cycad-associated genera, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miltotranes
</tp:taxon-name>
, is as yet unknown. The similarity of the anchor-shaped sclerite of the endophallus in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratranes
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes lyterioides
(Pascoe, 1875)
</tp:taxon-name>
suggests a close relationship between these taxa and that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
</tp:taxon-name>
in its current concept may be nonmonophyletic. The taxonomy of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tranes
</tp:taxon-name>
is currently under investigation (unpubl. data 2020).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
