<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophiomyxidae Ljungman 1867</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5527103</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B7687F64201624BD67BFE80FA9AF96D</uri>
         <article-title>Interactive identification key to all brittle star families (Echinodermata;
            Ophiuroidea) leads to revised morphological descriptions</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.766.1483</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type genus </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Ophiomyxa Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p> Other genera </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Neoplax Bell, 1884 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiarachna Müller
            &amp; Troschel, 1842 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophioconis Lütken, 1869
         </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiostiba Matsumoto, 1915 </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> Ophiurochaeta Matsumoto, 1915 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3–4× disc diameter; covering without
         granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present.Accessory dorsal arm
         plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny
         hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section round. The
         ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given
         cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9. Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly erect,
         standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines shorter than half a segment, or
         longer than two segments ( <tp:taxon-name> Ophiarachna </tp:taxon-name> ). Tentacle scales
         present; pores visible along most of the arm; slightly longer than wide, or more than two
         times as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of
         lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of
         LAPs without constriction. Ventral position of LAP projecting ventro-proximalwards.
         Ventro-distal tip of LAP projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and
         ventral lobes; without or with a weakly developed sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire
         distal LAP edge; ventralwards increasing in size. Distance between spine articulations
         equal. Nerve and muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve opening
         approximately as large as muscle opening. </p>
      <p> DORSAL DISC. Disc pentagonal; flat (about same level as arms). Integument not obscuring
         plates. Dorsal disc with granules ( <tp:taxon-name> Ophiarachna </tp:taxon-name> ) or
         without granules; with concealed primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc
         scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; without granules/spines; length less
         than one third of the disc radius; isosceles (mirror-symmetric) triangular to pear-shaped. </p>
      <p> VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii without granules/spines,
         or with granules ( <tp:taxon-name> Ophiarachna </tp:taxon-name> ). Scales on ventral
         interradii absent. Ventral teeth single or with several tooth papillae ( <tp:taxon-name>
            Ophiarachna </tp:taxon-name> ). Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal
         scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP
         present; single row of lateral papillae; paddle-shaped. Adoral shield spine present.
         Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; about as
         long as wide. Madreporite one; with one pore. Adoral shield separated.Abradial genital
         plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the
         length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate ventral half widest;
         fragmented. Dental sockets slit-shaped and circular; less than 50% of the width or equal to
         or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as perforation with septum. Teeth
         block-like (with square tip). Teeth on DP arranged as single row. </p>
      <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral
         bridge.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
