<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophiobyrsidae Matsumoto 1915</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5527091</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B7687F6423E6274D673FEFCFEC1F8A6</uri>
         <article-title>Interactive identification key to all brittle star families (Echinodermata;
            Ophiuroidea) leads to revised morphological descriptions</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.766.1483</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type genus </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Ophiobyrsa Lyman, 1878 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p> Other genera </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Ophiobyrsella Verrill, 1899 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiophrixus
            H.L. Clark, 1911 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiosmilax Matsumoto, 1915
         </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p>ARM.Arm shape unbranched; length more than4×disc diameter;covering without
         granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm
         plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny
         hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section round. The
         ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given
         cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9. Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly erect,
         standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines between half and one segment long.
         Tentacle scales absent. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the
         arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs with constriction. Ventral position of LAP
         projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP projecting ventralwards. Arm
         spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; without sigmoidal fold; arranged over
         entire distal LAP edge; ventralwards increasing in size. Distance between spine
         articulations equal. Nerve and muscle openings separated by large, prominent ridge or
         regular stereom. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.</p>
      <p>DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms). Integument obscuring plates.
         Dorsal disc with granules; with concealed primary plates; without scales; with spines.
         Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with granules.</p>
      <p>VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii without granules/spines.
         Scales on ventral interradii absent. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae). Infradental
         papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP
         absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP present. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle
         present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; about as long as wide.
         Madreporite no data. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital
         plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the
         length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate of equal width all over;
         entire (single plate). Dental sockets circular; less than 50% of the width. At least one
         socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth spine-shaped. Teeth on DP
         arranged as covering the entire dental plate evenly.</p>
      <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae hourglass-shaped (streptospondylous); beyond segment 5 with short
         keel; without oral bridge.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
