<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Gorgonocephalidae Ljungman 1867</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5527077</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B7687F64236627DD659FD86FEC1FE44</uri>
         <article-title>Interactive identification key to all brittle star families (Echinodermata; Ophiuroidea) leads to revised morphological descriptions</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.766.1483</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Gorgonocephalus
Leach, 1815
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
Other genera
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Asteroporpa
Örstedt &amp; Lütken, 1856
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astracme
Döderlein, 1927
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astroboa
Döderlein, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrocaneum
Döderlein, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrochalcis
Koehler, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrochele
Verrill, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrochlamys
Koehler, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrocladus
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astroclon
Lyman, 1879
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrocnida
Lyman, 1872
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrocrius
Döderlein, 1927
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrocyclus
Döderlein, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrodendrum
Döderlein, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrodictyum
Döderlein, 1927
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astroglymma
Döderlein, 1927
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrogomphus
Lyman, 1869
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrogordius
Döderlein, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrohamma
Döderlein, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrohelix
Döderlein, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astroniwa
McKnight, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrophyton
Fleming, 1828
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astroplegma
Döderlein, 1927
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrosierra
Baker, 1980
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrospartus
Döderlein, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrothamnus
Matsumoto, 1915
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrothorax
Döderlein, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrothrombus
H.L. Clark, 1909
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrotoma
Lyman, 1875
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astrozona
Döderlein, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Conocladus
H.L. Clark, 1909
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiocrene
Bell, 1894
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiozeta
Koehler, 1930
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Schizostella
A.H. Clark, 1952
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
ARM
. Arm shape unbranched, or shape branched; length more than 4× disc diameter; covering with granules.Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present.Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms present (
<tp:taxon-name>
Gorgonocephalus caputmedusae
(Linnaeus, 1758))
</tp:taxon-name>
or absent in some genera. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section oval. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given crosssectional plane) 0.9–1. Arm spines flat; at proximal segments only on ventral side of arms; predominantly erect, standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines between half and one segment long. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along the arm; slightly longer than wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section round. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) only lateral. Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs without constriction. Ventral position of LAP projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP not projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation without dorsal and ventral lobes; restricted to (the ventral or central) portion of the distal edge; all similar. Distance between spine articulations ventralwards increasing. Nerve and muscle openings separated by large, prominent ridge or regular stereom. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.
</p>
      <p>
DORSAL
DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules; with concealed primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with/without granules; length more than half of the disc radius; bar-like.
</p>
      <p>
VENTRAL
DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii with granules. Scales on ventral interradii absent. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae). Infradental papillae on oral plate absent. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP present. Lateral oral papillae on OP absent.Adoral shield spine absent. Lyman’s ossicle absent. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; much wider than long. Madreporite one; with numerous pores. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit shorter than half interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate of equal width all over; fragmented. Dental sockets circular; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth spine-shaped. Teeth on DP arranged as covering the entire dental plate evenly.
</p>
      <p>
VERTEBRAE
. Vertebrae hourglass-shaped (streptospondylous); beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
