<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophiomusa
Hertz, 1927
</tp:taxon-name>
. (No other genera)
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
ARM
. Arm shape unbranched; length 3× disc diameter; covering without granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate absent or present in some species on a few proximal arm joints only (

O’Hara 
et al.
2018

). Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section round. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9. Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly parallel to arm axis (adpressed). Longest arm spines shorter than half a segment. Tentacle scales present; pores visible only on proximal arm; more than two times as long as wide; longer than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs without constriction. Ventral position of LAP not projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP not projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation without dorsal and ventral lobes; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; all similar. Distance between spine articulations equal. Nerve and muscle openings separated by large, prominent ridge or regular stereom. Nerve opening approximately as large as muscle opening.
</p>
      <p>
DORSAL
DISC. Disc pentagonal; high (above arm level). Integument not obscuring plates. Dorsal disc without granules; with obvious primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate with tubercles. Radial shield present; with tubercles, without granules/spines; length more than half of the disc radius; isosceles (mirror-symmetric) triangular to pear-shaped.
</p>
      <p>
VENTRAL
DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii without granules/spines. Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of scales on H line of an interradius fewer than 7. Ventral teeth single. Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP present. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP absent. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle absent. Oral shield covering more than one third of the length of an interradius; much longer than wide. Madreporite no data. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit shorter than half interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate dorsal half widest; entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped and circular; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip, but never spine-like). Teeth on DP arranged as single row.
</p>
      <p>
VERTEBRAE
. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
