<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophioscolecidae Lutken 1869</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5527089</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B7687F642396273D662FE80FA9AF858</uri>
         <article-title>Interactive identification key to all brittle star families (Echinodermata;
            Ophiuroidea) leads to revised morphological descriptions</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.766.1483</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type genus </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Ophioscolex Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p> Other genera </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Ophiocymbium Lyman, 1880 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiogeron
            Lyman, 1878 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiohyalus Matsumoto, 1915
         </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiohymen H.L. Clark, 1911 </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> Ophioleptoplax H.L. Clark, 1911 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name>
            Ophiologimus H.L. Clark, 1911 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiolycus Mortensen,
            1933 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiophrura H.L. Clark, 1911 </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> Ophioplexa Martynov, 2010 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophioprium
            H.L. Clark, 1915 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiorupta Martynov, 2010
         </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiosyzygus H.L. Clark, 1911 </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> Ophiuroconis Matsumoto, 1915 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3–4× disc diameter; covering without
         granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm
         plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny
         hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar, or not all similar in shape ( <tp:taxon-name>
            Ophiolycus </tp:taxon-name> ). The atypical spines are hook-shaped. Arm spine cross
         section round. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a
         given cross-sectional plane) 0.2–0.6, or 0.9–1 ( <tp:taxon-name> Ophiolycus
         </tp:taxon-name> ). Arm spines cylindrical ( <tp:taxon-name> Ophiolycus </tp:taxon-name> )
         or tapering (conical); mainly lateral; predominantly erect, standing perpendicular to arm
         axis. Longest arm spines between one and two segments long. Tentacle scales present (
            <tp:taxon-name> Ophiolycus </tp:taxon-name> ) or absent; pores visible along most of the
         arm; more than two times as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section
         oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or
         ventral edge(s) of LAPs with constriction. Ventral position of LAP projecting
         ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP projecting ventralwards. Arm spine
         articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; without sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire
         distal LAP edge; dorsalwards increasing in size. Distance between spine articulations
         dorsalwards increasing. Nerve and muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve
         opening smaller than muscle opening. </p>
      <p> DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms). Integument obscuring plates.
         Dorsal disc without granules; with concealed primary plates; with or without scales;
         without spines. However, in some species with granules and spines ( O’Hara et al. 2018 ).
         Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield absent. </p>
      <p> VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii without granules/spines.
         Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of
         scales on H line of an interradius about 14–21. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae).
         Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent.Accessory oral
         papillae on OP present. Lateral oral papillae on OP absent. Adoral shield spine present.
         Lyman’s ossicle absent. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; much wider
         than long. Madreporite one or multiple; with one pore or with numerous pores. Adoral shield
         meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital
         slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital
         papillae absent. Dental plate ventral half widest; entire (single plate). Dental sockets
         circular; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression
         or perforation without septum. Teeth spine-shaped. Teeth on DP arranged as a single row on
         half of dental plate and other half with a cluster of tooth papillae (ventral cluster), or
         a single row on ⅔ and a cluster of tooth papillae on ⅓ of dental plate ( <tp:taxon-name>
            Ophiolycus </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral
         bridge.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
