<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophiernidae O'Hara, Stohr, Hugall, Thuy &amp; Martynov 2018</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5534398</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B7687F64206624DD5D5F940FA9AFAF2</uri>
         <article-title>Interactive identification key to all brittle star families (Echinodermata; Ophiuroidea) leads to revised morphological descriptions</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.766.1483</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophiernus
Lyman, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
. (No other genera)
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
         <p>
Description
</p>
         <p>
ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3–4× disc diameter; covering without granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present.Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines not all similar in shape. The atypical spines are bristles (
Fig. 2H
). Arm spine cross section oval. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9. Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly parallel to arm axis (adpressed). Longest arm spines between half and one segment long. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; slightly longer than wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) only lateral. Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs with constriction. Ventral position of LAP not projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation without dorsal and ventral lobes or with weak lobes (

O’Hara 
et al.
2018

); arranged over entire distal LAP edge; dorsalwards increasing in size. Distance between spine articulations dorsalwards increasing. Nerve and muscle openings separated by large, prominent ridge or regular stereom. Nerve opening approximately as large as muscle opening.
</p>
         <p>DORSAL DISC. Disc pentagonal to circular; flat (about same level as arms). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules; with concealed primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; without granules/spines; length less than one third of the disc radius; isosceles (mirror-symmetric) triangular to pear-shaped.</p>
         <p>VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii with granules. Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of scales on H line of an interradius fewer than 7. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae). Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP present; single row of lateral papillae; spiniform. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; about as long as wide. Madreporite one; with one pore. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate of equal width all over; entire (single plate). Dental sockets circular; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip, but never spine-like). Teeth on DP arranged as single row.</p>
         <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
               <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophiernidae O'Hara, Stohr, Hugall, Thuy &amp; Martynov 2018</named-content>
               <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5534398</uri>
               <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B7687F64207624ED670FA08FEC1FBFB</uri>
               <article-title>Interactive identification key to all brittle star families (Echinodermata; Ophiuroidea) leads to revised morphological descriptions</article-title>
               <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.766.1483</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
         </tp:treatment-meta>
         <tp:nomenclature/>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p>
Type
genus

</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ophioleuce
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
Other genera
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ophiopallas
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiopyren
Lyman, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiostriatus
Madsen, 1983
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description
</p>
            <p>
ARM.Arm shape unbranched; length more than4×disc diameter;covering without granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar or not all similar in shape (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiopallas
</tp:taxon-name>
). The atypical spines are hook-shaped. Arm spine cross section round. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9. Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly parallel to arm axis (adpressed). Longest arm spines between half and one segment long. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; nearly as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section round. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs without constriction. Ventral position of LAP projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; without sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; larger in middle of arm. Distance between spine articulations dorsalwards increasing, or not applicable (two spine articulations) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioleuce seminudum
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
). Nerve and muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.
</p>
            <p>DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules; with concealed primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with granules; length less than one third of the disc radius; scalene (oblique) triangular.</p>
            <p>
VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii with granules. Scales on ventral interradii absent. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae). Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP absent. Adoral shield spine absent. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; much longer than wide. Madreporite multiple; with numerous pores. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae present (O 
phiopallas
) or absent. Dental plate ventral half widest; entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped; less than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth spine-shaped. Teeth on DP arranged as single row.
</p>
            <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae hourglass-shaped (streptospondylous); beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophiernidae O'Hara, Stohr, Hugall, Thuy &amp; Martynov 2018</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5534398</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B7687F64207624ED670FA08FEC1FBFB</uri>
         <article-title>Interactive identification key to all brittle star families (Echinodermata; Ophiuroidea) leads to revised morphological descriptions</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.766.1483</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophioleuce
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
Other genera
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophiopallas
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiopyren
Lyman, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiostriatus
Madsen, 1983
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
ARM.Arm shape unbranched; length more than4×disc diameter;covering without granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar or not all similar in shape (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiopallas
</tp:taxon-name>
). The atypical spines are hook-shaped. Arm spine cross section round. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9. Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly parallel to arm axis (adpressed). Longest arm spines between half and one segment long. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; nearly as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section round. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs without constriction. Ventral position of LAP projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; without sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; larger in middle of arm. Distance between spine articulations dorsalwards increasing, or not applicable (two spine articulations) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioleuce seminudum
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
). Nerve and muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.
</p>
      <p>DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules; with concealed primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with granules; length less than one third of the disc radius; scalene (oblique) triangular.</p>
      <p>
VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii with granules. Scales on ventral interradii absent. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae). Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP absent. Adoral shield spine absent. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; much longer than wide. Madreporite multiple; with numerous pores. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae present (O 
phiopallas
) or absent. Dental plate ventral half widest; entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped; less than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth spine-shaped. Teeth on DP arranged as single row.
</p>
      <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae hourglass-shaped (streptospondylous); beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
