<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Hemieuryalidae Verrill 1899</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5527111</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B7687F642056240D66DFB95FC57FC07</uri>
         <article-title>Interactive identification key to all brittle star families (Echinodermata;
            Ophiuroidea) leads to revised morphological descriptions</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.766.1483</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type genus </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Hemieuryale von Martens, 1867 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p> Other genera </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Actinozonella Stöhr, 2011 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Astrogymnotes
            H.L. Clark, 1914 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophioholcus H.L. Clark, 1915
         </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophioplocus Lyman, 1861 </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> Ophioplus Verrill, 1899 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiozonella
            Matsumoto, 1915 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Ophiozonoida H.L. Clark, 1915
         </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Quironia A.H. Clark, 1934 </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> Sigsbeia Lyman, 1878 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> ARM.Arm shape unbranched; length more than4×disc diameter;covering without
         granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm
         plate present or absent ( <tp:taxon-name> Actinozonella </tp:taxon-name> ). Ventral arm
         plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent.
         Spines all similar in shape.Arm spine cross section round or oval ( Sigbeia ). The ratio of
         thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane)
         0.9–1. Arm spines cylindrical; at proximal segments only on ventral side of arms;
         predominantly parallel to arm axis (adpressed). Longest arm spines shorter than half a
         segment ( <tp:taxon-name> Sigsbeia </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Ophiozonella
            falklandica Mortensen, 1936 </tp:taxon-name> ), or between half and one segment long (
            <tp:taxon-name> Hemieuryale </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Ophiozonella longispina
            (H.L. Clark, 1908) </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Ophioplus </tp:taxon-name> ).
         Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; nearly as long as wide;
         shorter than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) only
         lateral or arched (wrapped around the arm) ( <tp:taxon-name> Sigsbeia </tp:taxon-name> ).
         Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs without constriction. Ventral position of LAP
         projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP not projecting ventralwards. Arm
         spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; without sigmoidal fold; restricted to
         (the ventral or central) portion of the distal edge; ventralwards increasing in size.
         Distance between spine articulations not applicable (two spine articulations). Nerve and
         muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve opening smaller than muscle
         opening, or approximately as large as muscle opening ( <tp:taxon-name> Ophiozonella
         </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      <p> DORSAL DISC. Disc pentagonal to circular; high (above arm level). Integument not obscuring
         plates. Dorsal disc without granules; with obvious primary plates; with scales; without
         spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate with tubercles. Radial shield present; without
         granules/spines; length between one third and half of the disc radius, or length more than
         half of the disc radius ( <tp:taxon-name> Ophioplus </tp:taxon-name> ); isosceles
         (mirror-symmetric) triangular to pear-shaped. </p>
      <p>VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii without granules/spines.
         Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of
         scales on H line of an interradius fewer than 7. Ventral teeth single. Infradental papillae
         on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent.
         Lateral oral papillae on OP present; one lateral papilla along each side of the jaw;
         block-shaped. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering
         less than one third of interradius; much wider than long. Madreporite no data. Adoral
         shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of
         genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit shorter than half interradius. Genital papillae
         absent. Dental plate dorsal half widest; entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped
         and circular; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as
         depression or perforation without septum. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip,
         but never spine-like). Teeth on DP arranged as single row.</p>
      <p> VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae hourglass-shaped (streptospondylous) or zygospondylous (
            <tp:taxon-name> Ophiozonella longispina </tp:taxon-name> ); beyond segment 5 with short
         keel; without oral bridge. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
