<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Gompholopium quercicola Gavrilov-Zimin 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4704969</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B0E6DEF3830432D7A4A5355B05C94A94</uri>
         <article-title>New and poorly known giant scale insects (Homoptera: Coccinea: Margarodidae s. lat.) from the Oriental region with taxonomic and nomenclatural notes on the subfamily Monophlebinae</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/c8b84fd5-c191-4228-9cc9-9cbb4f8a0c68</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Gompholopium quercicola
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
9A7B1ED4-F9B1-4F36-AD5D-3AE8F0D2B144
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name was constructed from the Latin name of the host plant, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Quercus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
+ the Latin suffix ‘cola’, meaning ‘inhabitant of’.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♀
; 
Yunnan
, 

70 km
S of Jingdong

; 

25 Mar. 1957

; 
N. Borchsenius
leg.; 

on twigs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Quercus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>

; ZIN RAS, 
K 1548
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
11 dry ♀♀
; same collecting data as for holotype; ZIN RAS, 
K 1548
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult female
</p>
      <p>
Body broadly oval, up to 
4 mm
long, covered by solid wax plates (
Fig. 1
). Antennae 9-segmented, covered by flagellate setae of different sizes; some of the antennal segments bearing minute setae, which represent, probably, any kind of sensilla. Legs normally developed; trochanter with 3 sensilla on each face; claw without denticle; claw digitules short, setose. Mouthparts well developed. Thoracic spiracles with spiracularia. Abdominal spiracles numbering 7 pairs, located along abdominal margin on dorsum; each abdominal spiracle with unilocular atrium, without wax pores inside or just near spiracular atrium. Anal apparatus represented by a short tube with internal sclerotized anal ring. Fifteen round cicatrices forming semicircle on abdominal sternites. With four main 
types
of discoidal wax glands: 1) variable pores (each about 7–10 μm in diameter) with stalked centre and with 2–5 peripheral loculi, scattered on all body surface, but more numerous in marginal zone of venter; 2) usual multilocular pores (each about 10 μm in diameter), with round or oval central loculus and 10–12 peripheral loculi, grouped around anal opening on dorsum, around vaginal opening on venter and scattered in medial and submedial zone of abdominal sternites; 3) irregular multilocular pores (each about 7–10 μm in diameter), with irregular central loculus and 6–10 peripheral loculi, forming group around anal opening on dorsum, group around vaginal opening on venter and scattered in medial and submedial zone of abdominal sternites; 4) simple pores (each about 2 μm in diameter), scattered in medial zone of ventral thorax. Conical setae very numerous, with more or less lanceolate apices, scattered on all dorsum and in marginal zone of venter. Flagellate setae of different size and thickness numerous in medial and submedial zone of ventral cephalothorax, on abdominal sternites. Long hair-like setae sparsely scattered on dorsum and in marginal zone of venter among conical setae.
</p>
      <p>
Male and larval instars
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Gompholopium quercicola
</tp:taxon-name>
gen et sp. nov., paratype, dry ♀ (ZIN RAS, K 1548) on twig of host plant. Scale bar = 1 mm.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Gompholopium quercicola
</tp:taxon-name>
gen et sp. nov., holotype, adult ♀ (ZIN RAS, K 1548). Morphology. Not to scale.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>The species is probably marsupial, according to the shape of abdomen of the available very young females.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
