<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Nemastoma bidentatum sneznikensis
Novak, Komposch, Slana Novak &amp; Raspotnig
</tp:taxon-name>
ssp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
7690FA07-5D60-4545-8660-282ADED3F576
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2–3
, 
4I
, 
5I
, 
6I
, 
7I
, 
8I
, 
9I
, 
10I
, 
11I
, 
12I
, 
13H
; 
Table 11
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The subspecies name ʻ 
sneznikensis
ʼ references Mt. Snežnik, southern 
Slovenia
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Short-legged (leg II &lt;
6 mm
) species of the 
N. b.
complex, with slightly elongated-trapezoidal Ch-Apo, with row of low tubercles on Pa-Fe and with equilateral triangular glans. Rec sem of 18 balloon-like vesicles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
SLOVENIA
– 
VL54
• 
1 ♂
; 
Mt. Snežnik
; 
45.59° N
, 
14.44° E
; 

1553 m

a.s.l.; 

21 Aug. 1998

; 
Ljuba Slana Novak
and 
Tone Novak
leg.; 

deep-humus in Dinaric 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinus mugo
</tp:taxon-name>
scrub in contact with the Dinaric 

<tp:taxon-name>Fagus sylvatica</tp:taxon-name>
– 
<tp:taxon-name>Abies alba</tp:taxon-name>

treeline litter sift

; 
PMSL-Opiliones-TN 1494/1998
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
SLOVENIA
– 
VL54
• 
2 ♂♂
, 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
PMSL-Opiliones-TN 1494/1998

.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
SLOVENIA
– 
VL54
• 
3 ♂♂
, 
4 ♀♀
; 
Mt. Snežnik
; 

20 Jul. 1999

; 
L. Slana Novak
and 
T. Novak
leg. (185/1999, rev. 2009); 
PMSL

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>BODY. Length 1.81, width 1.18.</p>
      <p>
CHELICERAE. Ch basal article (without Apo) length 0.53, 2.7 times as long as wide at Ch max width at dorsal hump. Ch-Apo oval-trapezoid, wider distally, without apical pinnacle. Ch-Apo height 0.13, max width 0.13, min width 0.08 (at the base). Secretion field frontally. Distal article length 0.51, max width 0.17, movable finger length 0.22 (
Figs 4I
, 
6I
, 
9I
).
</p>
      <p>
Table 12.
Length of appendage-segments in millimeters in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nemastoma bidentatum sneznikensis
</tp:taxon-name>
ssp. nov.
from Mt. Snežnik, Slovenia: ♂ holotype (♀).
</p>
      <p>
Trochanter
Femur
Patella
Tibia
Metatarsus
Tarsus
Total length
Pedipalp
0.20 (0.15)
0.59 (0.58)
0.43 (0.48)
0.33 (0.38)
–
0.24 (0.25)
1.79 (1.84)
Leg I
0.19 (0.18)
0.73 (0.62)
0.31 (0.28)
0.52 (0.51)
0.79 (0.96)
0.74 (0.63)
3.28 (3.18)
Leg II
0.19 (0.23)
1.16 (0.95)
0.38 (0.38)
1.03 (0.93)
1.46 (1.61)
1.27 (1.24)
5.49 (5.34)
Leg III
0.18 (0.17)
0.70 (0.78)
0.29 (0.27)
0.53 (0.52)
0.86 (1.04)
0.63 (0.57)
3.19 (3.35)
Leg IV
0.17 (0.18)
1.06 (0.98)
0.33 (0.28)
0.74 (0.73)
1.42 (1.44)
1.01 (0.92)
4.73 (4.53)
</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Pa-Tr with dorsal margin slightly inclined distally. Pa-Fe slightly club-shaped (Pa-Fe min:max width ~ 1:2.6) with terminal bonce, and 7 irregular granula in distal third. Pa-Pt length:max width ~ 1:4.3. Pa-Ti slender (
Figs 5I
, 
6I
, 
10I
). Pa article lengths in 
Table 12
.
</p>
      <p>
PENIS. Pe length 1.22, base 0.46, glans 0.09, stylus 0.04 (
Figs 7I
, 
8I
).
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Pseudoarticle leg-Fe formula I−IV: 0−1−1−2. Tarsomere leg formula I−IV: 9−14−6−8. Leg article lengths in 
Table 12
.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>BODY. Length 2.11, width 1.43.</p>
      <p>
CHELICERAE. Ch basal article length 0.59, 2.7 times as long as wide at dorsal hump, with low-arched dorsal margin in front of indentation and straight ventral margin (
Fig. 13H
). Distal article length 0.66, max width 0.20, movable finger length 0.30.
</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Pa-Tr low, with roof-like broken dorsal margin, highest in the first two fifths. Pa-Fe distally with low ventral hump, Pa-Pt, Pa-Ti and Pa-Ta elongated (
Fig. 13H
). Pa article lengths in 
Table 12
.
</p>
      <p>
OVIPOSITOR. Ovipositor length 0.62, Rec sem of 18 balloon-like vesicles (
Fig. 11I
).
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Leg article lengths in 
Table 12
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Regarding external morphology, 
N. b. sneznikensis
ssp. nov. is very similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. relictum
</tp:taxon-name>
, including the habitus, the similarly shaped Pa and relatively short legs. No individuals belonging to the subspecies were found in the last decade. See remarks on taxa of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nemastoma
</tp:taxon-name>
on Mt. Snežnik under 
N. b. gruberi
ssp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Despite over 30 collections, this taxon has been recorded only in a limited area on Mt. Snežnik. Endemic to Mt. Snežnik, southern 
Slovenia
. 
Type
locality: Mt. Snežnik (
45.59° N
, 
14.44° E
, 
1553 m
a.s.l.), 
Slovenia
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Nemastoma</tp:taxon-name>
b. sneznikensis

ssp. nov. is a psychrophilous subspecies. To date it has been recorded only in a cold, well-drained, deep mull humus Dinaric 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinus mugo
</tp:taxon-name>
scrub in contact with the Dinaric 

<tp:taxon-name>Fagus sylvatica</tp:taxon-name>
– 
<tp:taxon-name>Abies alba</tp:taxon-name>

treeline on calcareous soils. Likely, it inhabits other cold habitats, like scree and stone heap edges in contact with humus accumulations, as is known for 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. relictum
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Komposch 1999
; 
Komposch &amp; Gruber 2004
), and perhaps a humus-rich shallow subterranean habitat (SSH), i.e., Milieu Souterrain Superficiel (MSS) (

Mammola 
et al.
2016

; 
Halse 2018
). Since this habitat is restricted to an area of less than 
1 km
2
on Mt. Snežnik, this subspecies is considered highly endangered. Phenology: probably eurychronous.
</p>
      <p>

Hybrids among the subspecies of 
<tp:taxon-name>Nemastoma bidentatum</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
In 
Austria
, a few localities are known where 

N. b. 
<tp:taxon-name>bidentatum</tp:taxon-name>

lives in syntopy with 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. relictum
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Gruber &amp; Martens 1968
; 
Martens 1978
; in both papers sub 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. b. relictum
</tp:taxon-name>
), and with 
N. b. sparsum
(
Komposch &amp; Gruber 2004
; 
Komposch 2009
). However, individuals of these three taxa do not interbreed and have been considered as potential species (
Gruber &amp; Martens 1968
; 
Martens 1978
; 
Komposch &amp; Gruber 2004
; 
Komposch 2009
). In 
Slovenia
, 
N. b. schmidti
ssp. nov., with its central geographic position, interbreeds with all other adjacent subspecies: 

N. b. 
<tp:taxon-name>bidentatum</tp:taxon-name>

in the North, and 
N. b. martensi
ssp. nov., 
N. b. sneznikensis
ssp. nov., 
N. b. gruberi
ssp. nov.
and 
N. b. sparsum
from the Southwest to the Northeast of the country. Besides, 
N. b. gruberi
ssp. nov.
interbreed with 
N. b. martensi
ssp. nov., and with 
N. b. sparsum
. In 
Bosnia
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. pluridentatum
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. nov.
has not been found; consequently, the genitalia have not been examined. Despite this, major differences from all the other known taxa within the 
N. b.
complex allow it to be considered a separate species. This is because interbreeding of 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. pluridentatum
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. nov.
, which might be a subalpine species, with the montane 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. kozari
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
from the same mountain is quite unlikely, given their great dissimilarity. However, data on taxa of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nemastoma
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Bosnia and Herzegovina
are nearly completely missing, allowing no further conclusions.
</p>
      <p>Although being morphologically variable, hybrids possess larger Ch-Apo than pure subspecies and are well distinguishable from these. In interbreeding subspecies, hybrids between the two subspecies frequently occur syntopically with individuals belonging to pure subspecies. Consequently, such a collection consists of either one or two pure subspecies and a series of hybrids with varying Ch-Apo shapes.</p>
      <p>
An overview of interbreeding relations among the taxa of the 
N. b.
complex is presented in 
Table 13
. In 
Slovenia
, 

N. b. 
<tp:taxon-name>bidentatum</tp:taxon-name>

and 
N. b. sparsum
do not interbreed, since the areas are several tens of kilometres distant from each other. In contrast, we have found hybrids between all the adjacent subspecies (
Fig. 3
), except 
N. b. gruberi
ssp. nov.
× 
N. b. schmidti
ssp. nov. × 
N. b. sparsum
, which is expected in the meeting area of the three taxa. Besides, data on hybridization of 
N. b. sneznikensis
ssp. nov. are too scarce to be properly evaluated in full. The zone of hybridization between 
N. b. schmidti
ssp. nov. and 
N. b. sparsum
is the widest, measuring up to 
100 km
in north-eastern 
Slovenia
, while these zones are narrow to virtually non-identifiable among the others, and hybrids are accordingly scarce. Hybrids 
N. b. gruberi
ssp. nov.
× 
N. b. schmidti
ssp. nov. were found in a zone up to 
10 km
wide, while 
N. b. martensi
ssp. nov. × 
N. b. schmidti
ssp. nov. and 
N. b. gruberi
ssp. nov.
× 
N. b. martensi
ssp. nov. are limited to zones a few kilometers wide. In 
Slovenia
, there are no hybrids between allopatric 
N. b. martensi
ssp. nov. and 
N. b. sparsum
, while these are expected in 
Croatia
.
</p>
      <p>
Hybridization patterns were not simple clines in the transition zones between two subspecies. Instead, in some cases, morphologically various hybrids between the neighboring subspecies, sharing various ratios of the hybridizing subspecies characters (cf. 
Gruber &amp; Martens 1968
; 
Martens 1978
), appeared scattered across the whole width of the transition zone. In some places in the hybridization zone, individuals of both subspecies, together with hybrids of various intermittent stages, occurred syntopically.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
