<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Troglostygnopsis kalebi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 4–7
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Troglostygnopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. CNANOp0050 

Cruz-López &amp; Francke 2017: 318

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Movable finger of chelicera with two teeth, low and wide (
Fig. 5B
). Tubercles of leg IV large and very close each other, patella with many of these tubercles (
Fig. 6B
). Penis with two pairs of MS D, MS E1 just above the level of E2.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Patronymic honoring our colleague and friend Kaleb Zárate, an enthusiastic speleologist who has helped us collecting troglomorphic arachnids during several expeditions in southeastern 
Mexico
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
• Ƌ; 
Chiapas
, 
Las Rosas
, 
Cueva del Ciprés
; 
16º18′2″ N
, 
92º19′5″ W
; 

17 Jun. 2011

; 
O. Francke
, 
J. Cruz-López
, 
R. Monjaraz-Ruedas
, 
G. Contreras
and 
K. Zárate
leg.; CNAN-T0850.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
• 1 Ƌ, 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; male is a DNA voucher CNANOp0050; CNAN-T0851

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Troglostygnopsis kalebi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, Ƌ, holotype (CNAN-T0850). 
A
. Dorsal view. 
B
. Lateral view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(based on the 
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Scutum length: 5.0, scutum width: 4.2.</p>
      <p>
BODY (
Fig. 4
). Scutum 
type
zeta ‘ζ’, with both constrictions marked, specially C1, which marks the limits between prosoma and opisthosoma. Lateral margins of the scutum projected in lateral clear areas,
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Troglostygnopsis kalebi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, Ƌ, holotype (CNAN-T0850). 
A
. Chelicera, mesal view. 
B
. Chelicera, frontal view. 
C
. Pedipalp, mesal view. 
D
. Pedipalpal femur, mesal view. 
E
. Pedipalpal tibia and tarsus, ventral view.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Troglostygnopsis kalebi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, Ƌ, holotype (CNAN-T0850). 
A
. Apical femur, patella and basal tibia IV. 
B
. Patella IV.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Troglostygnopsis kalebi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, Ƌ, holotype (CNAN-T0850), penis. 
A
. Dorsal view. 
B
. Lateral view. 
C
. Ventral view. Scale bar in C applicable to all figures.
</p>
      <p>large and rounded. Entire dorsum smooth, with few small tubercles in middle of each mesotergal area. Ocularium at the frontal margin of the prosoma, acute, without eyes.</p>
      <p>
CHELICERA (
Fig. 5
A–B). Scutum/cheliceral hand ratio: 1.29. Basichelicerite large and smooth, with few small tubercles on ventral and apical regions. Cheliceral hand slightly widened but not swollen. Fixed finger with four teeth distributed evenly throughout, central triangular-shaped. Movable finger with two teeth, one basal and one subterminal, basalmost rounded.
</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS (
Fig. 5
C–E). Measurements: 2.31/1.10/1.80/1.80/1.10.Trochanter globose, with long spiniform setiferous tubercles on ventral and dorsal faces. Femur compressed laterally, armed with dorsal and ventral row of about 10 very large spiniform setiferous tubercles. Additionally, femur with mesal apical spiniform tubercle, near patella. Patella covered with spiniform tubercles on dorsal and mesal faces. Tibia with large main armature, relative sizes of SST on mesal side 1 = 3&gt; 2, and on ectal margin 3 = 2 = 1. Also on tibia three very small tubercles between SST 1, SST 2 and SST 3 on mesal side, and four small ones between SST 1 and SST 2, one between SST2 and SST 3, and one apically. Tarsus with six major tubercles on mesal side (1&gt; 2&gt; 3&gt; 4&gt; 5&gt; 6) and six on ectal side (1&gt; 2&gt; 3&gt; 4&gt; 5).
</p>
      <p>
LEGS (
Fig. 6
). All segments long and slender, legs I–III without armature, ornate only with few disperse small tubercles. Ornamentation of femur IV formed by rounded and acuminate tubercles, which form longitudinal rows along entire femur, patella covered with many tubercles.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
Distribution of selected troglobitic genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Stygnopsidae Sørensen, 1932</tp:taxon-name>
. Squares are distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Troglostygnopsis
Šilhavý, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
: black = 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. anophthalma
Šilhavý, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
; red = 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. kalebi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Circles show distribution of 
Brujita
Cruz-López, in press, 
Toojah
Cruz-López, in press and the dubious record for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mictlana inops
(
Goodnight &amp; Goodnight, 1971
)
</tp:taxon-name>
reported by 
Goodnight &amp; Goodnight (1973)
: black = 
B. chapulapa
Cruz-López, in press; red = 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. cimutaa
Cruz-López
</tp:taxon-name>
, in press; blue = 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. inops
? Pentagons
</tp:taxon-name>
are the distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mictlana
Cruz-López &amp; Francke, 2015
</tp:taxon-name>
: black = 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. plana
(
Goodnight &amp; Goodnight, 1973
)
</tp:taxon-name>
; red = 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. inops
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
PENIS (
Fig. 7
). Pars distalis wide, spoon-shaped. Follis multifolded, apices of dorsal bilobular projection acute, stylus arises from inside. Two pairs of MS D, lateral to base of follis, one pair very small and other formed by large acute MS. Five to six pairs of acute MS C forming curved rows on lateral sides. MS A+B formed by 16–17 spatulate setae, latero-basally to pars distalis. MS E composed of two pairs, MS E1 just above level of E2.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Very similar to male, without remarkable sexual dimorphism.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
