<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Acroterius Irfan &amp; Bashir &amp; Peng
            2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4665080</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5C2F211FFFEBFFFCFD0BFBEE68B3FE6C</uri>
         <article-title>Acroterius gen. nov. (Araneae: Linyphiidae: Linyphiinae) with twelve new
            species from Yunnan, China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.743.1293</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: EEA7B37A-300B-43D9-87F3-82A380BC686D </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius brevis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. resembles <tp:taxon-name> Diplostyla
         </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria Wiehle, 1956 </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> Laetesia Simon, 1908 </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> Laperousea
            Dalmas, 1917 </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> in:
         epigyne with parmula, originates from the posterior margin of posterior median plate with a
         socket ventrally ( Fig. 8A–C ; Ivie 1969 : figs 105–108; van Helsdingen 1972 : fig. 8;
         Millidge 1988 : fig. 173; Irfan &amp; Peng 2018 : figs 5c–d, 6c–d; Irfan et al . 2019: figs
         1–2, 7, 9–10). In the male palp, the distal margin of the radix is semicircular and has
         teeth as in <tp:taxon-name> Laetesia </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Laperousea
         </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> ( Figs 6A–C , 7A–B ;
         Millidge 1988 : figs 145–146; Irfan et al . 2019: figs 4a–b, d, 5c–e, 6a–b); the embolus
         and embolic membrane arise from the dorsal side of the distal margin of the radix as in
            <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> ( Figs 6A–C , 7A–B ; Irfan et al .
         2019: figs 4a–b, d, 5c–e, 6a–b). It can be distinguished by the anterior wall of the
         epigyne which has a posterior projection on each side ( Fig. 8A–B ), but in species of
            <tp:taxon-name> Laetesia </tp:taxon-name> , the posterior arm of the anterior wall of
         the epigynal plate is long, with a copulatory opening on the posterior ventral end (
         Millidge 1988 : figs 173, 187), and the posterior projection of the anterior wall absent in
         species of <tp:taxon-name> Diplostyla </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria
         </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> ( van Helsdingen 1972
         : fig. 8; Millidge 1988 : fig. 173; Irfan &amp; Peng 2018 : figs 5c–d, 6c–d; Irfan et al .
         2019: figs 1–2, 7, 9–10). The spermathecae are situated near the base of the parmula ( Fig.
         8A–B ) in <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. , but towards the periphery
         of epigyne in species of <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name>
            Laetesia </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> (
         Millidge 1988 : figs 187–189; Tao et al . 1995 : figs 80–81; Irfan et al . 2019: figs 1–2,
         7, 9–10). The cymbium has a cymbial retrolateral lobe ( Figs 6B–D , 7B ) as in species of
            <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> (Irfan et al . 2019: figs 4b, 5b, g,
         6b), but it is absent in <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>
            Laetesia </tp:taxon-name> ( Millidge 1988 : figs 143–144; Paquin &amp; Dupérré 2003 :
         figs 1544, 1547). The distal arm of the paracymbium of <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius
         </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. has two or three projections and covers most of the proximal
         part of paracymbium ( Figs 6B–C , 7B ), the distal part of the paracymbium of all species
         of <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Laetesia
         </tp:taxon-name> is simple U- or V-shaped and doesn’t cover the proximal part ( Millidge
         1988 : figs 187–189; Paquin &amp; Dupérré 2003 : figs 1544, 1547) and there is a large,
         distal arm longer than wide, tip pendulum-shaped in species of <tp:taxon-name>
            Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> (Irfan et al . 2019: figs 4b, 5f, 6b). The distal end
         of the distal suprategular apophysis of <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius </tp:taxon-name> gen.
         nov. and <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria </tp:taxon-name> is not notched ( Figs 6B–C , 7B ; Tao
         et al . 1995 : figs 77–78) (but notched in species of <tp:taxon-name> Laetesia , Millidge
            1988 </tp:taxon-name> : fig. 146), and proximally broad with teeth, has a distal part
         strongly curved into an inversed U-shape, almost touching the distal margin of the
         paracymbium in species of <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> (Irfan et al .
         2019: figs 4b, 5b, g, 6b). The tegulum of <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius </tp:taxon-name> gen.
         nov. has a small tegular projection ventrally ( Figs 6B–C , 7B ), which is absent in
            <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria </tp:taxon-name> ( Paquin &amp; Dupérré 2003 : figs 1544,
         1547; Zhao &amp; Li 2014 : figs 47b, 49b) and <tp:taxon-name> Laetesia </tp:taxon-name> (
         Millidge 1988 : fig. 146). The embolic division of <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius
         </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. comprises a distal semicircular part of the radix with a
         serrated margin anteriorly; the embolus and embolic membrane arise from the terminal part
         of the radix ( Figs 6A–C , 7A–B ) as in species of <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia
         </tp:taxon-name> (Irfan et al . 2019: figs 4a–b, 5c–e, 6a–b); the embolus and median
         membrane arise from the lateral (inner) side of the plate in <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria
         </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Laetesia </tp:taxon-name> ( Millidge 1988 : figs 145,
         149; Zhao &amp; Li 2014 : figs 47b, 49b) whereas in <tp:taxon-name> Diplostyla
         </tp:taxon-name> the embolus arises near the base of the cymbium and extends parallel along
         the full length of cymbium ( Ivie 1969 : figs 107–108). In <tp:taxon-name> Acroterius
         </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. the proximal end of the radix has a radical apophysis ( Figs
         6A–C , 7A–B ) as in species of <tp:taxon-name> Zhezhoulinyphia </tp:taxon-name> (Irfan et
         al . 2019: figs 4a–b, 5c–e, 6a–b), but it is absent in <tp:taxon-name> Diplostyla
         </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Kaestneria </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Laetesia
         </tp:taxon-name> ( Ivie 1969 : figs 107–108; Millidge 1988 : figs 145, 149; Zhao &amp; Li
         2014 : figs 47b, 49b). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p>The generic name is an arbitrary combination of letters. Gender masculine.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Large sized, male total length 2.66–3.61; female total length 2.66–4.15.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Cephalic region slightly elevated, yellowish to dark brown; fovea, cervical and
         radial grooves distinct; sternum longer than wide, green to yellowish to dark brown with
         spine-like hairs; labium wider than long, dark brown; maxillae long, distal end broader
         with scopulae. Eye region narrow, AER recurved, PER procurved slightly wider.</p>
      <p>LEGS. All legs with annuli; patella of each leg with two spines; chaetotaxy: 2–2–2–2; Tm I
         and Tm IV present.</p>
      <p> ABDOMEN. Oval, dorsally with pattern extending down to the base of spinnerets followed by
         irregular white patches dorso-laterally, and ventrally pale, greenish to brown with or
         without irregular white patches ( Fig. 4A–B ). </p>
      <p> MALE PALP ( Figs 1 , 3 , 6 , 7 , 10–12 , 15–16 , 24 , 26 , 30–31 ). Patella shorter than
         tibia, dorsally with a long spine;tibia cone shaped, with two retrolateral trichobothria,
         with some short and long setae on all surfaces; paracymbium highly sclerotized, proximal
         part simple, somewhat rectangular, distal arm with two to three projections (characterized
         as lateral, median and ventral projections); cymbium with retrolateral lobe, covered with
         long thick spines; tegulum with small projection ventrally; distal suprategular apophysis
         long, basally covered by embolic division. Radix with distal broad semicircular serrated
         part giving rise to embolus and embolic membrane, at proximal end with small radical
         apophysis and dorsal projection of embolic plate; dorsal projection of embolic plate long,
         slightly overlapping cymbium; embolic membrane curved and approachnig distal semicircular
         part, in prolateral view; embolus stout, short with pointed end. </p>
      <p> EPIGYNE ( Figs 8 , 13 , 17 , 21A–D , 22 , 27 , 29A–D , 32 , 34B–E , 36A–D , 37 ). Anterior
         wall of epigyne wider than long; posterior margin of anterior wall with a projection on
         each side; copulatory openings situated inside the atrium between the anterior wall and
         posterior median plate, connected with long, semicircular copulatory ducts joined to the
         spermathecae. Posterior median plate posteriorly with a parmula of variable length with a
         socket ventrally. Spermathecae slender, present near the posterior median plate.
         Fertilization ducts long, present laterally on the posterior median plate, extending
         mesally. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> China ( Yunnan Province , Figs 38–39 ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
