<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Acroterius latus Irfan &amp; Bashir &amp; Peng 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4665121</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C10138D8472564D8712873AB1804658A</uri>
         <article-title>Acroterius gen. nov. (Araneae: Linyphiidae: Linyphiinae) with twelve new species from Yunnan, China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.743.1293</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
896C3469-C7F5-4931-ADBF-B423F6513F4A
</p>
      <p>
Figs 24–28
, 
38
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Figs 30A–D
, 
31A–B
) in having the distal arm of paracymbium with two projections in the male palp and the long parmula with a median incision in the epigyne (
Figs 24A–D
, 
26A–B
); it can be distinguished by: the distal suprategular apophysis short, retained below the apex of cymbium in retrolateral view (
Fig. 24B
), but long, swordshaped, protruding beyond the apex of cymbium in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Fig. 30B
). The dorsal projection of embolic plate doesn’t touch the base of cymbium in prolateral view (
Figs 24A
, 
26A
), but almost touches the base of cymbium in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Figs 30A
, 
31A
). The lateral projection of the distal arm of the paracymbium is finger-shaped, almost touches the posterior margin of the tibia (
Figs 24B, D
, 
26B
), but is tongue-shaped and away from the posterior margin of the tibia in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Figs 30B, D
, 
31B
). The posterior projection of the anterior wall of the epigynal plate is wider than long and doesn’t protrude beyond the epigastric furrow (
Fig. 27A–B
), but is longer than wide and protruding beyond the epigastric furrow in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Fig. 32A–B
). The distal part of the spermathecae is hook-shaped (
Fig. 27D
), but inverted L-shaped in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Fig. 32D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name comes from the Latin adjective ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
latus
</tp:taxon-name>
’ meaning ‘broad’, referring to the radical apophysis with a broad distal end in the male palp.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Yunnan Province
, 
Lonyang County
, 
Bawan Distr.
, 
Nankang Yakou
; 
24.83178° N
, 
98.76472° E
; alt. 

2180 m

; 

25 May 2005

; 
Charles Griswold
and 
D.H. Kavanaugh
leg.; 
HNU-CGY123
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratypes

(
3 ♀♀
)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
CHINA
– 

Yunnan Province

• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
HNU-CGY123
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Fugong County
, 

2 km
down Shibali

; 
27.16284° N
, 
98.78989° E
; alt. 

2420 m

; 

2 May 2004

; 
Guang–xu Peng
leg.; 
HNU-20040502
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Fugong County
, 
Lishadi Township
, 
Shibali
; 
27.10520° N
, 
98.77980° E
; alt. 

2530 m

; 

10 Aug. 2005

; 
Guo Tang
leg.; 
HNU-Tang–05–02
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS AND COLOUR. Total length: 3.55. Carapace 1.84 long, 1.47 wide, cephalic region slightly elevated, dark brown, with longitudinal band starting from base of posterior lateral eyes extending to base of cephalothorax followed by fovea, cervical and radial grooves distinct; clypeus 0.34 high (
Fig. 28A–B
); abdomen 1.71 long, 1.29 wide. Eye sizes and interdistances: AME 0.06, ALE 0.09, PME 0.07, PLE 0.07, AME–AME 0.07, PME–PME 0.09, AME–ALE 0.11, PME–PLE 0.13, ALE–ALE 0.51, PLE–PLE 0.55, ALE–PLE contiguous.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 24.
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (HNU-CGY123), palp. 
A
. Prolateral view. 
B
. Retrolateral view. 
C
. Dorsal view. 
D
. Ventral view.
</p>
      <p>
CHELICERAE. With six promarginal and five retromarginal teeth; distal three teeth of promargin very small (
Fig. 25B
).
</p>
      <p>LENGTH OF LEGS. I = 6.59 (1.79, 1.99, 1.67, 1.14), II = 4.88 (1.66, 1.69, 1.32, 1), III = 3.95 (1.34, 1.39, 0.76, 0.46), IV=5.98 (1.74, 1.82, 1.46, 0.96). Leg formula I–IV–II–III.</p>
      <p>
PALP (
Figs 24A–D
, 
26A–B
). Paracymbium highly sclerotized, distal arm with two projections (
Figs 24B
, 
26B
), lateral projection finger-like in ventral view and almost touches posterior margin of paracymbium in retrolateral view; ventral projection thumb-like with blunt end; distal suprategular apophysis slightly protruding above cymbium in ventral view (
Figs 24D
, 
26B
). Radical apophysis relatively large, tongueshaped, slightly curved with blunt end in ventral view (
Figs 24A–D
, 
26A–B
). Embolus stout, short with pointed end (
Figs 24A–C
, 
26A–B
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
(HNU-CGY123)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS AND COLOUR. Total length: 3.03. Carapace 1.26 long, 1.01 wide, cephalic region slightly elevated, dark brown, with a longitudinal band starting from base of posterior lateral eyes extending to base of cephalothorax; fovea, cervical and radial grooves distinct; clypeus 0.25 high (
Fig. 28C–D
);
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 25.
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (HNU-CGY123). 
A
. Chelicera, dorsal view. 
B
. Chelicera, ventral view.
</p>
      <p>abdomen 1.75 long, 1.33 wide. Eye sizes and interdistances: AME 0.07, ALE 0.09, PME 0.07, PLE 0.08, AME–AME 0.05, PME–PME 0.10, AME–ALE 0.08, PME–PLE 0.07, ALE–ALE 0.43, PLE–PLE 0.47, ALE–PLE contiguous.</p>
      <p>
CHELICERAE. In dorsal view, chelicerae with depression at proximal end slightly below reteromargin with six promarginal and seven retromarginal teeth; reteromarginal teeth gradually decreasing in length towards base of fang (
Fig. 25A–B
).
</p>
      <p>LENGTH OF LEGS. I = 4.30 (1.29, 1.48, 0.89, 0.64), II = 4.05 (1.26, 1.34, 0.86, 0.59), III = 2.27 (1.02, 1.06, 0.69, 0.52), IV = 4.39 (1.23, 1.34, 1.03, 0.79). Leg formula I–IV–II–III.</p>
      <p>
EPIGYNE. Parmula 0.45 long, 0.14 wide at base (
Fig. 27A–B
); posterior projection of anterior wall of epigynal plate margin of epigyne wider than long, not protruding beyond epigastric furrow (
Fig. 27A– B
). Spermathecae slender, distal part of spermathecae hook-shaped, slightly curved, pointing towards lateral wall of epigyne (
Fig. 27D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Yunnan Province
, 
Fig. 38
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
