<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Centris (Relicthemisia) Vivallo
                        &amp; Zanella 2021, subgen. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5103035</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6803879DFF94FF8D9430FB84D54773DE</uri>
                  <article-title>Relicthemisia, a new subgenus of the oil-collecting bee genus
                        Centris Fabricius, 1804 with notes on distribution and host plants of C.
                        xanthomelaena Moure &amp; Castro, 2001 (Hymenoptera: Apidae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.760.1435</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Relicthemisia </tp:taxon-name> subgen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 361E0AE3-2711-4089-974A-DA742A130E52 </p>
            <p> Figs 1–4 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p> Type species </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Centris xanthomelaena Moure &amp; Castro, 2001 </tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Integument dark brown to black, clypeus and labrum coriaceous with coarse and dense
                  punctation, but the clypeus with an unpunctated area as a median longitudinal band
                  on upper half ( Fig. 1A ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> Inner orbits of compound eyes converging downward ( Fig. 1A ). Mandible with four
                  apically acute teeth, the fourth tooth slightly larger than the third ( Fig. 1A ).
                  Basitibial plate elliptical, with S-like secondary plate ( Fig. 2A ). Elaiospathes
                  normally developed. </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> Clypeus, except lateral areas, and labrum yellow ( Fig. 1C ). Yellow spots on
                  paraocular and supraclypeal areas ( Fig. 1C ). Apical margin of T7 with strong
                  emargination ( Fig. 2B ). S7 without emargination on the basal border ( Fig. 2B ).
                  S8, apical projection clearly defined, larger at middle and with rounded apex (
                  Fig. 2C ). Genital capsule with long dorsoapical projection of gonocoxite, ca 2/3
                  lengths of gonostylus ( Fig. 2E ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> From Latin ‘ relictus ’ (a survivor from a previous age) plus ‘ <tp:taxon-name>
                        Hemisia </tp:taxon-name> ’ (a junior synonym of <tp:taxon-name> Centris
                  </tp:taxon-name> ) due to the antiquity and isolation of this lineage. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Centris xanthomelaena </tp:taxon-name> , the only species of the
                  new subgenus <tp:taxon-name> Relicthemisia </tp:taxon-name> , was recognized as a
                  distinct lineage with no close relationship to other species, based on
                  morphological ( Zanella 2002 ) and molecular data ( Martins &amp; Melo 2015 ).
                  Depending on the study, the phylogenetic position of this lineage was different,
                  either as sister group of <tp:taxon-name> Centris </tp:taxon-name> s. str. or
                        <tp:taxon-name> Paracentris Cameron, 1903 </tp:taxon-name> respectively.
                  Nevertheless, it was always recovered as a distinct and relatively old lineage
                  within the ‘ <tp:taxon-name> Centris </tp:taxon-name> group’. According to Martins
                  &amp; Melo (2015) , <tp:taxon-name> C. xanthomelaena </tp:taxon-name> diverged
                  from a South American clade formed by <tp:taxon-name> Paracentris </tp:taxon-name>
                  around 18 million years ago, at about the same time when the major lineages within
                  the ‘ <tp:taxon-name> Centris </tp:taxon-name> group’ diverged from each other. </p>
            <p> The hypothetical relationship of this species with <tp:taxon-name> Centris
                  </tp:taxon-name> s. str. was based on the interpretation of two morphological
                  characters: the strong emargination on the apical margin of T7 ( Fig. 2B ;
                  character 25: 0 in Zanella 2002 ) and the short and wide translucent laminar
                  projection on the dorsodistal region of the gonocoxite at the base of the long,
                  giant bristles ( Fig. 2E–F ; character 44: 1 in Zanella 2002 ), but the states
                  present in <tp:taxon-name> C. xanthomelaena </tp:taxon-name> are clearly unique
                  and cannot be homologous to those present in species of <tp:taxon-name> Centris
                  </tp:taxon-name> s. str. </p>
            <p> Despite the fact that new phylogenetic analyses using a higher number of terminals
                  of <tp:taxon-name> Centris </tp:taxon-name> s. str. and <tp:taxon-name>
                        Paracentris </tp:taxon-name> can provide new information regarding the
                  history and relatedness of the lineage of <tp:taxon-name> C. xanthomelaena
                  </tp:taxon-name> , its distinctness and old history are well supported (see
                  Martins &amp; Melo 2015 ). Besides the uniqueness of the intense yellow slightly
                  greenish pilosity covering the head, mesosoma (except the ventral surface) and on
                  the anterior half of T1 that allow to easily recognize <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        xanthomelaena </tp:taxon-name> from other species of the genus ( Fig. 1A–D
                  ), this monotypic subgenus presents a unique combination of characters of the
                  male’s genitalia that distinguishes it from the other members of the ‘
                        <tp:taxon-name> Centris </tp:taxon-name> group’: an emargination on the
                  apical margin of T7 ( Fig. 2B ); a long dorsoapical projection of gonocoxite, ca
                  2/3 lengths of gonostylus ( Fig. 2E ); the dorsomedial projections of the genital
                  capsule ( Fig. 2E ), as well as the S-like lower margin of the female’s secondary
                  basitibial plate ( Fig. 2A ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
