<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp
                        1888</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5095032</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6960BF58FF99FFD956184C0BFC52A09A</uri>
                  <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the genus Elmomorphus Sharp, 1888 I. Japanese
                        and Korean species (Coleoptera: Dryopidae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.758.1427</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp, 1888 </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 4A–C , 5A , 6A, C, E , 7A–D , 8A–B, E–F , 9A–B, D , 10A </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp, 1888: 243 </tp:taxon-name>
                  (original description, type locality). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Helichus </tp:taxon-name> “ 862 spec. ?” Lewis 1879: 12 (first
                  indication). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> – Zaitzev 1910: 19
                  (catalogue). — Kôno 1934: 125 (catalogue). — Bollow 1940: 59–62 , figs 271–276
                  (description, Japanese records). — Chûjô &amp; Satô 1964: 193 . — Delève 1968: 151
                  (differential diagnosis). — Satô 1981: 53 . — Jäch 1984: 314 (checklist). — Kodada
                  &amp; Jäch 2006: 442 (catalogue). — Hayashi &amp; Shimada 2006: 129 (Japanese
                  records, in Japanese). — Yoshioka 2007: 236 , 242, fig. 17a (Japanese records, in
                  Japanese); 2008: 224 (Japanese records, in Japanese). — Hayashi 2011: 93 . —
                  Kamezawa &amp; Nomura 2013: 29 (Japanese records, in Japanese). — Jung &amp; Bae
                  2014: 2–7 , figs 2a–c, 3–5 (description, identification key, Korean records). —
                  Kodada &amp; Jäch 2016: 606 (catalogue). — Yoshitomi &amp; Haga 2018: 341–342
                  (identification key). — Nakajima et al. 2020: 177 , 322 (diagnosis, identification
                  key, photographs of living specimens). </p>
            <p> non <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> – Devi et al . 2016:
                  371–373 (misidentification, invalid lectotype </p>
            <p>designation)].</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type locality </p>
            <p> Kobe, Hyōgo Prefecture , southern Honshu, Japan . </p>
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Syntypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> JAPAN • 1♂ ( Fig.4C );“Kobe 18.V.71 [handwritten]|Japan.G
                        Lewis1910—320.[printed]| <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis
                        </tp:taxon-name> [handwritten] | <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis
                        </tp:taxon-name> . [handwritten] | <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis
                              Sharp det. </tp:taxon-name> H. Bollow 1934 [handwritten and printed]”;
                        NHMUK </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ( Fig. 4A–B ); “
                              <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> Type D.S.
                        [David Sharp] Jokio [sic]. Japan Lewis. [handwritten] | Japan. G.Lewis
                        [printed] | Sharp Coll. 1905-313. [printed] | Type [printed, round label
                        with red frame]”; NHMUK . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Additional material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> JAPAN • 1 ♀ ; “ Shimakatsu Mie-Pref. 16.XI.1958 Coll. Shozo
                        Ishida | <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp Det. M. SATO 1971
                        </tp:taxon-name> ”; NHMW </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1
                        ♂ ; “ Nagara-River Gifu-City 26.VII.1951 Coll. Zen. Naruse ”; NHMW
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; “ Kurokawa , N-Echigo
                        2.IX.1960 Col. K. Baba ”; NHMW </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; “ Kabuchi-gawa Gifu Pref. 18.VIII.1967 M. Sato
                        leg.”; NHMW </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 10 ♂♂ , 6 ♀♀ ;
                        “ Japan , Shimane Pref. : Matsue : Yakumo 26.–30. iii.2019 M. Hayashi ”;
                        JKCB </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 5 ♂♂ , 3 ♀♀ ; “ Japan
                        , Shimane Pref. : Izumo , Nishitani 30.iii.2019 M. Hayashi ”; JKCB
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; “ NE-JAPAN Miyagi Pr. ,
                        Mts. Abukuma , 6.6. Uchikawa riv., leg. Ohmomo 1987 | <tp:taxon-name>
                              Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp </tp:taxon-name> ”; NHMW
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SOUTH KOREA • 1 ♂ , 1 spec. sex not examined; “ South Korea
                        , Jeollabuk-do , Buan-gun , Byeonsanmyeon , Junggye-ri , Jiko Falls
                        15.VI.2011 , leg. S.W.Jung ”; NHMW </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Note </p>
            <p> The original description was based on two specimens collected by G. Lewis. Both
                  specimens are still preserved in the collection of David Sharp in the NHMUK. The
                  female specimen is glued on a larger rectangular card with the following
                  handwritten text: “ <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> Type
                  D.S. Jokio. Japan Lewis.”. This style of labelling and label text is typical of
                  David Sharp’s type material. The male specimen and the dissected aedeagus are
                  glued on one card, while its detached appendages are glued on a second card,
                  pinned below the specimen. The two syntypes are conspecific. However, while the
                  type locality mentioned in the original description (“Kobé”) is written on the
                  original label of the male specimen ( Fig. 4C ), the name “Jokio” [Sharp’s
                  spelling of Tokyo ] is found on the label of the female specimen ( Fig. 4A ).
                  Since no other species is known from Honshu and since taxonomic confusion is
                  improbable, a lectotype designation is considered unnecessary (see ICZN 1999 :
                  Recommendation 74G,
                  https://www.iczn.org/the-code/declaration-44-amendment-of-article-74-7-3/). </p>
            <p> In the abstract of their most remarkable article, Devi et al . (2016: 371) wrote
                  that “A lectotype is designated for this species [ <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus
                        brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> ]”. However, the term “ lectotype ” is not used
                  anywhere else in their article, and it does not contain sufficient information to
                  ensure recognition of the specimen designated. Therefore, the requirements of the
                  International Code of Zoological Nomenclature ( ICZN 1999 : Art. 74.7) are not
                  fulfilled. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 4. <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp, 1888 </tp:taxon-name> . A–B .
            Syntype, ♀ (NHMUK). A . Specimen glued on the original card with Sharp’s handwriting. B
            . Labels. C . Syntype, ♂ (NHMUK), labels (the last label not depicted). </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> is a medium-sized (TL
                  2.59–3.51 mm ), elongated oval, dorsally moderately convex species, with the
                  highest point at the anterior third of the elytral length (lateral view). Body
                  outline discontinuous between pronotum and elytra; yellowish plastron microscales
                  cover the entire surface of the cranium, lateral portions of the pronotum and the
                  entire dorsal surface of the elytra, so most of the dorsal surface appears to be
                  matt ( Fig. 5A ). Each elytron has nine rows of large round punctures arranged in
                  shallow striae. Legs conspicuously long and robust, only moderately shorter than
                  the combined length of pronotum and elytra. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> closely resembles
                        <tp:taxon-name> E. amamiensis </tp:taxon-name> in external morphology, and
                  it can be distinguished by the following characteristics: (1) elytral sides in
                        <tp:taxon-name> E. brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> subparallel in the anterior
                  half, while in <tp:taxon-name> E. amamiensis </tp:taxon-name> they are arcuate and
                  more convergent ( Fig. 5B ), thus the outline appears to be generally broader and
                  less oval in <tp:taxon-name> E. brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> ; (2) sides of
                  pronotum usually more rounded in <tp:taxon-name> E. brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  while they are almost straight in <tp:taxon-name> E. amamiensis </tp:taxon-name> ;
                  (3) males of <tp:taxon-name> E. brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> with several longer
                  setae in a transverse row on the labrum, and with similar setae in two pairs of
                  clusters on each prosternal process and on the admedian portions of metaventrite,
                  row and clusters of setae rather inconspicuous ( Fig. 6A, C, E ); similar, longer
                  setae also near the apex of the fifth ventrite ( Fig. 7D ); in the male of
                        <tp:taxon-name> E. amamiensis </tp:taxon-name> the setal row and all setal
                  clusters are well developed, conspicuous ( Figs 6B, D, F , 7E ); (4) parameres
                  weakly curved ventrad in <tp:taxon-name> E. brevicornis </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 8B
                  ), but strongly curved in <tp:taxon-name> E. amamiensis </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 8D
                  ); (5) bursa copulatrix of the two species distally with one cluster of
                  microspines on each side ( Fig. 9D ), while in <tp:taxon-name>E.
                        amamiensis</tp:taxon-name> , besides these microspines there are several
                  additional larger sclerites ( Fig. 9E ). Except for differences in the
                  morphological characters, the two species differ by 22.7–23.9% in the partial
                  mtDNA encoding for cytochrome c oxidase subunit I. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Measurements (mm) </p>
            <p> TL: ♂♂ 2.89–3.38 (3.10 ± 0.13, n = 14), ♀♀ 3.15–3.51 (3.34 ± 0.12, n = 7); PL: ♂♂
                  0.65–0.85 (0.78 ± 0.05, n = 14), ♀♀ 0.75–0.90 (0.83 ± 0.05, n = 7); PW: ♂♂
                  1.20–1.43 (1.33 ± 0.06, n = 14), ♀♀ 1.30–1.47 (1.40 ± 0.06, n = 7); EL: ♂♂
                  2.22–2.57 (2.42 ± 0.09, n = 14), ♀♀ 2.50–2.86 (2.66 ± 0.11, n = 7); EW: ♂♂
                  1.44–1.66 (1.54 ± 0.05, n = 14), ♀♀ 1.51–1.77 (1.65 ± 0.09, n = 7); MsTL: ♂♂ 0.82–
                  0.94 (0.88 ± 0.03, n = 14), ♀♀ 0.87–0.97 (0.91 ± 0.03, n = 7); MtTL: ♂♂ 0.91–1.09
                  (1.02 ± 0.05, n = 14), ♀♀ 0.97–1.12 (1.06 ± 0.05, n = 7); PhL: 0.73–0.89 (0.83 ±
                  0.04, n = 11); PrL: 0.32–0.39 (0.37 ± 0.02, n = 11). </p>
            <p> Redescription </p>
            <p> BODY. Elongated oval, widest behind mid-length of elytra, moderately convex
                  dorsally, with the highest point at anterior third of elytral length (lateral
                  view).Colouration black, except reddish-brown mouthparts, antennal clubs, tarsi,
                  claws, trochanters, and ventral portions of femora. Tibiae and remainder of
                  femoral surface dark brown to black. Dorsal pubescence consists mainly of short,
                  thin decumbent yellowish setae arising from small punctures. Plastron microscales
                  ( Fig. 7B ) on the entire cranium, on pronotum in two lateral bands, covering ca
                  0.2 of pronotal width on each side, and on the entire surface of elytra. Ventral
                  surface with dense, thin plastron hair-like setae ( Fig. 7C ) except for
                  prosternal process and median part of metaventrite. </p>
            <p> HEAD. Dorsally entirely covered with plastron scales and with round, setiferous
                  punctures; puncture diameter ca 0.75× diameter of an eye facet, and their distance
                  varies between 0.50–1.00× of a facet diameter. Labrum transverse, with anterior
                  margin straight; anterolateral angles rounded; exposed portion microreticulate,
                  with small setiferous punctures; two types of hair-like setae present, short
                  decumbent setae on most of the surface, and several longer semi-erect setae in a
                  hardly discernible transverse row near mid-length ( Fig. 6A ), setae nearly half
                  as long as ID and more obvious in males (in older material long setae often
                  abraded). Clypeus with anterior margin straight and with a row of the fine short
                  hairs. Eyes oval, protruding and large, interfacetal setae short; ID: ♂♂ 0.38–0.43
                  mm (0.41 ± 0.02, n = 14), ♀♀ 0.42–0.48 mm (0.44 ± 0.02, n = 7); APD/ID: ♂♂
                  1.93–2.09 (2.01 ± 0.04, n = 14), ♀♀ 1.89–2.04 (1.96 ± 0.05, n = 7). Antennae
                  short, reaching slightly behind middle of eyes, 10-segmented; densely covered by
                  plastron; each club segment with a conspicuous peg-like sensillum on anterior face
                  and numerous hair-like, peg-like and branched sensilla; scape and pedicel small
                  and subequal in length, not enlarged. </p>
            <p> Fig. 5. Habitus. A . <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp, 1888
                  </tp:taxon-name> , ♂, length (anterior margin of clypeus to elytral apex): 3.7 mm
                  (JKCB). B . <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus amamiensis Nomura, 1959 </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  ♂, length (anterior margin of clypeus to elytral apex): 3.4 mm (JKCB). </p>
            <p> Fig. 6. Details of the male head and ventral portions. A, C, E . <tp:taxon-name>
                        Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp, 1888 </tp:taxon-name> (JKCB). B, D, F.
                        <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus amamiensis Nomura, 1959 </tp:taxon-name> (JKCB).
                  A–B . Head. C–D . Ventral view of the prothorax. E–F . Ventral view of the
                  metathorax. Arrows show the position of setal clusters. </p>
            <p> THORAX. Pronotum transverse, widest at base, strongly convex, PW/PL: ♂♂ 1.60–1.85
                  (1.72 ± 0.07, n = 14), ♀♀ 1.60–1.76 (1.68 ± 0.05, n = 7); plastron in lateral band
                  on each side along entire pronotal length, mesally reaching level of third elytral
                  row; disc smooth, shiny, with large round setiferous punctures, punctures nearly
                  as large as facets, separated by 0.50–1.00× of a facet diameter; punctures on
                  plastron area smaller, similar to those on head. Anterior angles strongly
                  deflexed, protruding and acute, third as long as interocular distance; pronotal
                  sides convergent anteriad, distinctly arcuate near middle, moderately explanate
                  along entire length. Hypomeron widest behind mid-length. Prosternal process wide
                  and short, lateral margins divergent and moderately arcuate; posterior margin
                  widely rounded; lateral portion raised, wide and in male with group of longer
                  setae ( Fig. 6C ) forming a hardly discernible setal cluster (these setae only
                  moderately longer than other hair-like ventral setae and often abraded); median
                  keel moderately convex, ca ⅓ as wide as width of prosternal process. Scutellum
                  longer than wide, smooth, with small, sparse punctures. Metaventral process with
                  lateral sides strongly raised, anterior margin not raised. Metaventral disc flat
                  in female, finely depressed in male; longitudinal step-like elevation along sides
                  delimits lateral area with plastron from smooth central one, surface irregularly
                  and moderately sparsely punctate and in some specimens finely irregularly
                  wrinkled; discrimen well impressed, distinct; a small, hardly discernible setal
                  cluster present in front of metakatepisternal suture in males on each side of
                  metaventral disc ( Fig. 6E ). Elytra oblong, widest behind middle; moderately
                  convex dorsally, in dorsal view with the highest point at anterior third; sides
                  subparallel in anterior half, more strongly arcuate in posterior half; EL/EW: ♂♂
                  1.53–1.69 (1.57 ± 0.04, n = 14), ♀♀ 1.53–1.66 (1.61 ± 0.04, n = 7); surface
                  entirely covered by plastron scales and with numerous minute punctures distinctly
                  smaller than a facet diameter, punctures separated by about 0.50–1.00× a facet
                  diameter. Strial punctures large and deep on elytral disc and subequal in size
                  with facet size, laterad and posteriad progressively smaller. All tibiae straight,
                  to slightly bent near mid-length; protibia ca 1.25× as long as protarsus; PrTL/PL:
                  ♂♂ 1.01–1.20 (1.10 ± 0.05, n = 14), ♀♀ 1.00–1.08 (1.05 ± 0.03, n = 7). Terminal
                  tarsomere in male foreleg ca 1.20× as long as all preceding tarsomeres combined;
                  male foreclaws strongly curved, not widened or thickened, about half of terminal
                  tarsomere length, both similar to each other ( Fig. 7A ) and similar to female
                  foreclaws. </p>
            <p> Fig. 7. A–D . <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp, 1888 </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  ♂ (JKCB). A . Foreclaws. B . Dorsal plastron scales. C . Ventral plastron scales.
                  D . Detail on ventrite 5. E . <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus amamiensis Nomura, 1959
                  </tp:taxon-name> , detail on male ventrite 5 (JKCB). </p>
            <p> ABDOMEN. All ventrites completely covered with plastron; ventrites 1–5 with a length
                  ratio about 1.00: 0.76: 0.60: 0.40: 1.26 in male, and 1.00: 0.90: 0.73: 0.60: 1.60
                  in female; intercoxal process wide, about twice as wide as long, subtriangular,
                  sides moderately arcuate; admedian keels feebly raised, reaching posterior margin
                  of ventrite. Male ventrite 5 near anterior margin declivous and then shortly
                  flattened, laterad and posteriad evenly deflexed; apex with distinct triangular
                  excision ( Fig. 7D ); several longer semi-erect setae on each side of excision in
                  hardly discernible clusters. Female ventrite 5 evenly convex and not flattened
                  anteriorly, with minute longitudinal smooth keel at apex and few longer setae
                  alongside keel; apex rounded. Sternite VIII moderately sclerotized laterally,
                  membranous medially, in males with short strut on anterior margin ( Fig. 8E ), in
                  females with strut almost as long as abdomen ( Fig. 9A ). Male sternite IX narrow,
                  with sclerotized anterior strut ( Fig. 8F ). Aedeagus: phallobase long, narrow,
                  expanded proximally ( Fig. 8A ), PhL/PrL: 2.14–2.36 (2.24 ± 0.07, n = 11);
                  parameres slightly curved ventrad along apical half, nearly straight, with apices
                  narrowly rounded ( Fig. 8B ); apex of penis slightly expanded and rounded in
                  lateral aspect, not reaching apex of parameres; ventral sclerotized fibula absent.
                  Ovipositor heavily sclerotized; right coxite ca 1.40× as long as left one;
                  paraproct ca 1.80× as long as right coxite ( Fig. 9B ). Bursa copulatrix with a
                  cluster of numerous minute spines arranged on each side of distal portions ( Fig.
                  9D ). Spermatheca tubular; accessory gland large, semi-tubular. </p>
            <p> Sexual dimorphism </p>
            <p> Females are, on average longer and broader than males. For an unambiguous
                  distinction between males and females, the apex of the fifth ventrite should be
                  examined: it is distinctly excised in males ( Fig. 7D ), while it is rounded, with
                  a short, smooth keel in females. The presence of several longer semi-erect setae
                  on the labrum, prosternal process, metaventral disc and on the apex of the fifth
                  ventrite in males is hard to observe even in well-preserved specimens, and even
                  under a high-quality microscope at a magnification of about 100×. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 8. Male terminalia. A–B, E–F . <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus brevicornis Sharp, 1888
            </tp:taxon-name> (JKCB). A . Aedeagus, ventral aspect. B . Ibidem, lateral aspect. C–D .
                  <tp:taxon-name> Elmomorphus amamiensis Nomura, 1959 </tp:taxon-name> (JKCB). C .
            Aedeagus, ventral aspect. D . Ibidem, lateral aspect. E . Sternite VIII. F . Sternite
            IX. Scale bar = 0.1 mm. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Japan : Honshu, Izu-Ôshima, Oki, Shikoku, Kyushu, Tsushima, and Tanegashima (
                  Nakajima et al. 2020 ); South Korea ( Fig. 10A ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Devi et al . (2016) erroneously recorded <tp:taxon-name> E. brevicornis
                  </tp:taxon-name> from India . Their record was published in the unreviewed “
                  Journal of Entomology and Zoology Studies ”, a so-called predatory journal (see
                  https://predatoryjournals.com/journals/). The “redescription” provided in this
                  article does not allow any conclusions to be drawn on the identity of the
                  specimens. The “Aedagues” [sic] depicted in their fig. 1c is, in fact, an
                  ovipositor! Judging from their habitus photograph (fig. 1a), these specimens,
                  beyond any doubt, do not belong to <tp:taxon-name> E. brevicornis </tp:taxon-name>
                  or any other species similar to <tp:taxon-name>E. brevicornis</tp:taxon-name> .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Immature stages </p>
            <p> The larva was described by Hayashi &amp; Kadowaki (2008) and Hayashi (2015) . It was
                  found in a river on submerged roots of <tp:taxon-name> Salix </tp:taxon-name> L.
                  and <tp:taxon-name> Carex </tp:taxon-name> L. (Hayashi pers. com.). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
