<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Smicridea (Smicridea) jeaneae Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5493208</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B76BD76D755F63F51D958302902AD677</uri>
         <article-title>The Smicridea (Smicridea) fasciatella species group (Trichoptera: Hydropsychidae) in Brazil: six new species and new distributional records</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1371</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea
(
Smicridea
) 
jeaneae

Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
B3B2E393-F3E0-4FAD-8838-32481EB11877
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3
, 

11 
–
12

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea jeaneae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
also belongs to the 
<tp:taxon-name>
albosignata
</tp:taxon-name>
complex.Among the species in this complex, it is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. bulbosa
Flint, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Suriname
based on the strong, parallel, pointed apicomesal lobes on tergum X and the short, slender apical segment of the inferior appendage with slightly acute apex. In both species the claw-shaped internal dorsolateral plates of the phallic apparatus are as long as the basal width, but in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jeaneae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
the plates are straight mesally, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. bulbosa
</tp:taxon-name>
they are curved. In addition, the phallotremal sclerite of the phallic apparatus has a hastate shape distally in dorsal view and is kidney-shaped in lateral view in the new species, but is strap-like in dorsal view and rod-like in lateral view in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. bulbosa
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea jeaneae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can also be recognized by the three stout apical spine-like setae on the basal segment of the inferior appendage, one long seta dorsally and two mediumsized setae on the mesal margin.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This new species is named in honor of Dr Jeane Marcelle Cavalcante do Nascimento (Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia, INPA – 
Brazil
) for her valuable friendship, cooperation in the field and the laboratory, and in gratitude for her help in collecting material during the doctoral studies of the first author.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Amapá
, 
Oiapoque
, 
Oiapoque River
, 
Buraco do Cristal
; 
03º48′16″ N
, 
51º51′25″ W
; 

7 Dec. 2018

; 
M. Silva
leg.; 
INPA-TRI 000116
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult male
(
Figs 11–12
)
</p>
      <p>
FOREWING LENGTH. 
6.37 mm
(n = 1).
</p>
      <p>
COLOR. General color dark brown (in alcohol) (
Fig. 11A
). Antennae yellowish brown (
Fig. 11A
). Head brown, with grayish to brown setae (
Fig. 11B–C
); dorsally with weakly pronounced median suture; with five setal warts; anteromesal wart small, rounded; anterolateral pair undivided, weakly delimited; posterolateral pair large, ovoid (
Fig. 11C
). Maxillary palp with segments 1–4 increasing gradually, about 0.8× in size toward the more apical segments, segment 5 long, about 1.2× as long as all previous segments combined (
Fig. 11B
). Thorax dark brown, covered with pale-brown setae; legs brown, with mid-leg tarsi yellowish (
Fig. 11A
). Wing venation typical for subgenus (
Fig. 11D–E
). Forewings, in alcohol, brown, with white transverse band subapically reaching base of R2+3, another arising on M1+2 and reaching base of Cu1a+b, and small white spot on apex of Cu2 (
Fig. 11D
). Sternum V with anterolateral glandular processes slightly shorter than sternum. Abdominal segments VI and VII with 2 pairs of internal glands, both pairs longer than their containing segments (
Fig. 11F
).
</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA (
Fig. 12
). Segment IX in lateral view with anterolateral margin nearly straight, strongly sclerotized (
Fig. 12A
); posterodorsal margin bearing small spicules, distributed in two subtriangular bands (
Fig. 12B
). Tergum X elongate; in lateral view, ventrolateral margin strongly sclerotized, with three medium-sized, thin setae on apical third; apex with shallow notch, ending in a slender, straight lobe (
Fig. 12A
); in dorsal view, lateral margin slightly rounded; dorsomesal setose area bearing four mediumsized, thin setae; divided apicomesally by V-shaped incision about ½ its length; apex of tergite rounded, with strong, pointed apicomesal lobe, each bearing three medium-sized, thin apical setae (
Fig. 12B
). Inferior appendages 2-segmented; basal segment long, slightly inflated distally, covered with long, thin setae, with group of stout apical spine-like setae (one very long dorsal seta and two long setae on mesal margin); apical segment short, about ⅓ as long as basal segment, slender, strongly curved medially, apex slightly acute with numerous short, thin setae on mesal margin (
Fig. 12B
). Phallic apparatus long and tubular; basal section, in lateral view, enlarged, 4× diameter of phallotheca at its narrowest point, forming an angle of about 103° with apical section; median section of phallotheca straight, without processes (
Fig. 12C
); apex enlarged, with pair of claw-shaped internal dorsolateral plates, as long as basal width, straight mesally and directed posterad; endothecal membranes without spines; phallotremal sclerite, in dorsal view, distinct, strongly sclerotized, with U-shaped proximal region and hastate distal region (
Fig. 12D–E
); in lateral view, dorsal region kidney-shaped, ventrally slender and sinuous (
Fig. 12C
). Ejaculatory duct of endophallus, in lateral view, distinct, slightly sclerotized (
Fig. 12C
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 11.
<tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea
(
Smicridea
) 
jeaneae
Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (INPA-TRI 000116). 
A
. Lateral habitus, pinned. 
B
. Head, right lateral view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Forewing, right dorsal view. 
E
. Hind wing, right dorsal view. 
F
. Abdomen, ventral view. Scale bars in mm:A, D–F = 1; B–C = 0.5.
</p>
      <p>
Bionomics
</p>
      <p>
The only male specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jeaneae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
was collected near the Oiapoque River, at a place known as “Buraco do Cristal”; this river is about 
400 m
in width. The prevalent vegetation is Dense Ombrophilous Lowland Forest. The collection site is located in the northern-most part of the Brazilian Amazon.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
(
Fig. 3
)
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
: Amazon (
Amapá
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
