<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Smicridea (Smicridea) ipiranga Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5493206</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6E659B61FFB2FFFFBE84DC01287C8EF2</uri>
         <article-title>The Smicridea (Smicridea) fasciatella species group (Trichoptera: Hydropsychidae) in Brazil: six new species and new distributional records</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1371</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea
(
Smicridea
) 
ipiranga

Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
1E07D339-6A5A-4E95-A76D-A94339AD91AC
</p>
      <p>

Figs 
3

, 
4E
, 

9 
–
10

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species can be assigned to the 
<tp:taxon-name>
fasciatella
</tp:taxon-name>
complex. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea ipiranga
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. varia
(Banks, 1913)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lacanha
Bueno-Soria &amp; Hamilton, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. catherinae
Blahnik, 1995
</tp:taxon-name>
based on the shape of the apical segment of the inferior appendage, which is slender, strongly curved medially and has a pointed apex. These four species also have a single long, stout apical spine-like seta on the internal margin of the basal segment of the inferior appendage. However, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. ipiranga
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be distinguished from its congeners by its diminutive size (on average 
3.55 mm
); the most similar species in the complex are twice its size on average: 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. catherinae
</tp:taxon-name>
(about 6.0 mm), 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lacanha
</tp:taxon-name>
(about 
7.9 mm
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. varia
</tp:taxon-name>
(about 
6.15 mm
). Additionally, the new species has the phallotremal sclerite with the distal region M-shaped in dorsal view, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. catherinae
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lacanha
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. varia
</tp:taxon-name>
, this sclerite is Y-shaped.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet is a reference to the Ipiranga Stream, located in the Reserva Florestal Adolpho Ducke, where the 
type
specimen was collected. This name is used in apposition.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Amazonas
, 
Manaus
, 
Reserva Florestal Adolpho Ducke
, 
Igarapé Ipiranga
; 
02°58′53.6″ S
, 
59°54′24.4″ W
; 

95 m
a.s.l.

; 

30 Jun.–2 Jul. 2015

; 
A.M.O. Pes
, 
G.R. Desiderio
, 
P. Barcelos-Silva
and 
W. Xavier
leg.; 
Pennsylvania trap
; 
INPA-TRI 000112
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
2 ♂♂
; same locality as for holotype; 

9 Aug. 2013

; 
A.M.O. Pes
and 
P. Barcelos-Silva
leg.; 
white sheet with an LED light
; 
INPA-TRI 000113
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
Malaise trap
; 
INPA-TRI 000114
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
5 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
Malaise trap
; 
MZUSP
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
108 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
INPA-TRI 000115
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Presidente Figueiredo
, 
AM–240, Km 13
, 
Corredeira da Dona Maroca
; 
02°02′00.1″ S
, 
59°51′45.1″ W
; 

19 Apr. 2008

; 
U.G. Neiss
leg.; 
white sheet with an LED light
; 
DZUP
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
6 ♂♂
; 
Presidente Figueiredo
, 
Balneário Sossego da Pantera
, 
Igarapé da Onça
; 
02°05′57″ S
, 
60°01′02″ W
; 

92 m
a.s.l.

; 

23 Aug. 2012

; 
A.M.O. Pes
leg.; 
white sheet with an LED light
; 
DZRJ
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult male
(
Figs 9–10
)
</p>
      <p>
FOREWING LENGTH. 
3.40–3.62 mm
(mean = 3.55, SD = 0.07, n = 6).
</p>
      <p>
COLOR. General color dark brown (in alcohol) or black (pinned) (
Fig. 9A
). Antennae yellowish brown (
Fig. 9A
). Head dark, with white setae on dorsum (
Fig. 9B–C
); dorsally with weakly-pronounced median suture; with five setal warts; anteromesal wart small, rounded; anterolateral pair undivided, weakly delimited; posterolateral pair large, ovoid (
Fig. 9C
). Maxillary palp with segments 1–4 increasing gradually about 0.8× in size toward more apical segments, segment 5 long, about 1.2× as long as all previous segments combined (
Fig. 9B
). Thorax dark brown, covered with pale brown setae; legs dark brown, with mid-leg tarsi pale yellowish (
Fig. 9A
). Wing venation typical for subgenus (
Fig. 9D–E
). Forewings, in alcohol, brown, with white transverse band subapically on pterostigma reaching base of R4+5 and small white spot on apex of Cu2 (
Fig. 9D
); pinned specimens with 2 transversal bands of white setae, one continuous band in proximal portion reaching from base of subcostal vein to apex of 1A, the other band discontinuous in distal portion reaching from pterostigma to apex of Cu1; apex of wing with fringe of white setae (
Fig. 9A
). Sternum V with anterolateral glandular processes slightly shorter than sternum. Abdominal segments VI and VII with 2 pairs of internal glands, both pairs longer than their containing segments (
Fig. 9F
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea
(
Smicridea
) 
ipiranga
Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (INPA-TRI 000112). 
A
. Lateral habitus (in alcohol). 
B
. Head, right lateral view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Forewing, right dorsal view. 
E
. Hind wing, right dorsal view. 
F
. Abdomen, ventral view. Scale bars in mm: A = 2; B–C = 0.5; D–F = 1.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea
(
Smicridea
) 
ipiranga
Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, male terminalia. – 
A–E
. Holotype (INPA-TRI 000112). 
A
. Terga IX, X and inferior appendages, lateral view. 
B
. Same, dorsal view. 
C
. Phallic apparatus, lateral view. 
D
. Apex of phallic apparatus, dorsal view. 
E
. Apex of phallic apparatus (photograph). – 
F
. Paratype (INPA-TRI 0115), apex of everted phallic apparatus (photograph), dorsal view. Scale bars in mm: A–C = 0.1; D–F = 0.05.
</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA (
Fig. 10
). Segment IX in lateral view with anterolateral margin straight, strongly sclerotized (
Fig. 10A
); posterodorsal margin bearing small spicules, distributed in two subquadrate bands (
Fig. 10B
). Tergum X elongate; in lateral view, ventrolateral margin strongly sclerotized, with small subapical lobe; apex produced and upturned (
Fig. 10A
); in dorsal view, lateral margin slightly sinuous; dorsomesal setose area bearing five medium-sized, thin setae; divided apicomesally by V-shaped incision about ¼ its length; apex of tergite rounded, with large globose lobe and about eight short, stout setae (
Fig. 10B
). Inferior appendages 2-segmented; basal segment long, slightly inflated distally, covered with long, thin setae, with one long, stout apical spine-like seta on mesal margin; apical segment short, about ⅓ as long as basal segment, slender, strongly curved medially, apex acute with numerous short, thin setae on mesal margin (
Fig. 10B
). Phallic apparatus long and tubular; basal section, in lateral view, enlarged, 2× diameter of phallotheca at its narrowest point, forming an angle of about 116° with apical section; median section of phallotheca straight, without processes (
Fig. 10C
); apex slightly enlarged, without processes or plates; endothecal membranes without spines; phallotremal sclerite, in dorsal view, distinct, strongly sclerotized, proximal region enlarged and narrowing mesally, distal region M-shaped (
Fig. 10D–E
); in lateral view, aciculate (
Fig. 10C
). Ejaculatory duct of endophallus, in lateral view, distinct, slightly sclerotized (
Fig. 10C
). When endothecal membranes are everted, phallotremal sclerite divided into two disconnected parts, one long, apicomesal, rod-like, and the other with a pair of comma-shaped sclerites, distally slightly curved (
Fig. 10F
).
</p>
      <p>
Bionomics
</p>
      <p>
The males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. ipiranga
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
were collected near streams in the central Amazon, mainly in a 2 
nd
order stream (Igarapé Ipiranga) located in the Reserva Florestal Adolpho Ducke, an area of primary Amazon rainforest of about 
100 km
2
that is under the protection of the Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas da Amazônia (INPA). The riparian vegetation along this stream is about 
2.4 m
wide and 
0.29 m
deep, with a sandy bottom, and a medium-speed water flow (
Fig 4E
). Its water is clear and acidic (pH 5.1), oxygen solubility levels are high (6.9 mgL), electrical conductivity is low (8.5 
µScm-1
), and the average temperature is 25.6°C. Specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. ipiranga
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
were also collected in medium-sized streams in the municipality of Presidente Figueiredo (Corredeira da Dona Maroca and Igarapé da Onça), 
3.5–12.5 m
in width, 
0.19–0.44 m
deep, with fast-flowing water. These streams were used for recreation (swimming and camping), with rocky bottoms characterized by black and acidic water (pH 4.2–4.8), low electrical conductivity (10.9 
µScm-1
), and a water temperature of 25ºC.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
(
Fig. 3
)
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
: Amazon (Amazonas).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
