<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Smicridea (Smicridea) caaguara Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5493204</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/51B5253E87EDB8853263AE42EEF31478</uri>
         <article-title>The Smicridea (Smicridea) fasciatella species group (Trichoptera: Hydropsychidae) in Brazil: six new species and new distributional records</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.750.1371</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea
(
Smicridea
) 
caaguara

Desiderio, Pes &amp; Hamada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
6BC132ED-63EA-4E0C-A18F-7D2A367B0C0E
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3
, 

4C 
–
D

, 

7 
–
8

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species is another member of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
albosignata
</tp:taxon-name>
complex; it is most similar to the nominal species 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. albosignata
</tp:taxon-name>
based on the enlarged, slightly bifid apex of the apical segment of the inferior appendage. However, the lateral margin of tergum X in the new species is rounded in dorsal view, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. albosignata
</tp:taxon-name>
this structure is straight. Both species also differ in the shape of the tergum X apex: in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. albosignata
</tp:taxon-name>
it is acute in dorsal view, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. caaguara
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
it is rounded. Additionally, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. albosignata
</tp:taxon-name>
has the apex of tergum X with a subtriangular apicomesal flap directed laterad in dorsal view, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. caaguara
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
this flap is absent. The new species also can be recognized by the distinct and complex phallotremal sclerite in dorsal view.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet is a reference to the indigenous people known as 
caaguaras
, first inhabitants of the São Francisco de Paula municipality, which is the 
type
locality of this species. This name is used as a noun in apposition.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Rio Grande do Sul
, 
São Francisco de Paula
, 
Floresta Nacional São Francisco de Paula
, 
Arroio Lajeado
; 
29°25′57.01″ S
, 
50°22′22.5″ W
; 

832 m
a.s.l.

; 

30 Aug.–2 Sep. 2015

; 
N. Hamada
, 
C.J. Benetti
, 
G.P. Dantas
and 
A.M.O. Pes
leg.; 
INPA-TRI 000110
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♂
; 
Rio Grande do Sul
, 
Agudo
, 
Cascata Raddatz
, 
Arroio Teotônia
; 
29°35′12.05″ S
, 
53°10′49.8″ W
; 

248 m
a.s.l.

; 

25 Aug. 2015

; 
N. Hamada
, 
C.J. Benetti
, 
G.P. Dantas
and 
A.M.O. Pes
leg.; 
INPA-TRI 000111
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult male
(
Figs 7–8
)
</p>
      <p>
FOREWING LENGTH. 4.70, 
5.92 mm
(n = 2).
</p>
      <p>
COLOR. General color dark brown (in alcohol) (
Fig. 7A
). Antennae brown (
Fig. 7A
). Head dark brown, with brown setae on dorsum (
Fig. 7B–C
); dorsally with weakly pronounced median suture; with five setal warts; anteromesal wart small, rounded; anterolateral pair undivided, weakly delimited; posterolateral pair large, ovoid (
Fig. 7C
). Maxillary palp with segments 1–4 increasing gradually about 0.8× in size toward more apical segments, segment 5 long, about 1.2× as long as all previous segments combined (
Fig. 7B
). Thorax dark brown, covered with brown setae; legs brown, with mid-leg tarsi yellowish (
Fig. 7A
). Wing venation typical for subgenus (
Fig. 7D–E
). Forewings, in alcohol, grayish to dark brown, with white transverse band subapically on pterostigma reaching base of R4+5 and small white spot on apex of Cu2 (
Fig. 7D
). Sternum V with anterolateral glandular processes slightly longer than sternum. Abdominal segments VI and VII with 2 pairs of internal glands, both pairs longer than their segments (
Fig. 7F
).
</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA (
Fig. 8
). Segment IX in lateral view with anterolateral margin nearly straight, weakly sclerotized (
Fig. 8A
); posterodorsal margin bearing small spicules, distributed in two dark, narrow parallel bands (
Fig. 8B
). Tergum X elongate; in lateral view, ventrolateral margin strongly sclerotized, with eight to 10 medium-sized, thin setae on apical third; apex produced and upturned (
Fig. 8A
); in dorsal view, lateral margin rounded; dorsomesal setose area bearing six to eight medium-sized, thin setae; divided apicomesally by V-shaped incision about ⅓ its length; apex of tergite rounded, with about three short, thin setae (
Fig. 8B
). Inferior appendages 2-segmented; basal segment long, slightly inflated distally, covered with long, thin setae, with pair of long, stout apical spine-like setae on mesal margin; apical segment short, about ½ as long as basal segment, thick, curved medially, apex enlarged and slightly bifid with numerous short, acuminate setae on mesal margin (
Fig. 8B
). Phallic apparatus long and tubular; basal section, in lateral view, enlarged, 3× diameter of phallotheca at its narrowest point, forming an angle of about 105° with apical section; median section of phallotheca straight, with dorsal periphalic cap sclerotized and flattened (
Fig. 8C
); apex enlarged, with pair of claw-shaped internal dorsolateral plates, longer than basal width, curved mesally and directed posterad; endothecal membranes without spines; phallotremal sclerite, in dorsal view, distinct, strongly sclerotized, proximal region slender, rod-like, divided distally in two subtriangular lateral flaps (
Fig. 8D–E
); in lateral view, proximal region with small middorsal lobe, distally directed downward (
Fig. 8C
). Ejaculatory duct of endophallus, in lateral view, distinct, slightly sclerotized (
Fig. 8C
).
</p>
      <p>
Bionomics
</p>
      <p>
The males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. caaguara
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
were collected near medium-sized streams, about 5.0 m wide, located in the Pampa-Atlantic Forest transition zone in the state of 
Rio Grande do Sul
. The vegetation of the collections sites varies from Grassy–Woody Steppe (Arroio Lageado – Rio dos Sinos Basin, 
Fig 4C
) to Seasonal Deciduous Forest (Arroio Teotônia – Rio Jacuí Basin, 
Fig 4D
). The streams have bedrock and fast-flowing water, with cloudy and alkaline water (pH 7.9), conductivity 25–50.4 
μScm-1
, and water temperatures of 15–16.4°C.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Smicridea
(
Smicridea
) 
caaguara
Desiderio, Pes &amp;Hamada
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (INPA-TRI 000110). 
A
. Lateral habitus. 
B
. Head, right lateral view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Forewing, right dorsal view. 
E
. Hind wing, right dorsal view. 
F
. Abdomen, ventral view. Scale bars in mm:A = 2; B–C = 0.5; D–F = 1.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
(
Fig. 3
)
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
: Atlantic Forest (
Rio Grande do Sul
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
