<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Varadia Bhosale &amp; Saadi &amp; Wade &amp;
            Thackeray &amp; Tamboli &amp; Kadam &amp; Muley &amp; Raheem 2021, gen.
            nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5047647</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/827987D3C958FF888A4F55DBF176F950</uri>
         <article-title>Varadia, a new helicarionoidean semi-slug genus from India’s Western Ghats
            (Stylommatophora: Helicarionoidea)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1413</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Varadia Bhosale &amp; Raheem </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: BB363A8F-6796-4874-BBF3-6CE1A207A3C3 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Varadia amboliensis Bhosale, Thackeray, Muley &amp; Raheem </tp:taxon-name>
         gen. et sp. nov. (here designated). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>Only known large semi-slug species from the Western Ghats having broad shell lobes
         (covering nearly all of the dorsal shell surface when fully extended) and a depressed,
         discoid shell with a large body whorl. Shell thin, glossy golden brown, with 4–4½ rapidly
         increasing whorls and barely raised spire. Extensive, largely free penial sheath enclosing
         substantial part of male genitalia. When sheath is in situ and penis in relaxed state, male
         genitalia constitute a single elongate, irregularly-shaped mass, with all of penis and
         epiphallic caecum, most of epiphallus and part of flagellum enclosed by sheath; only vas
         deferens and most of flagellum is visible outside intact sheath. Penial sheath divisible
         into thick proximal part and thin distal part, with transition between these two parts
         occurring between distal penis and epiphallic caecum. With penial sheath removed, following
         evident: region extending from penis to epiphallic caecum long and cylindrical, with
         distinctive S-shaped bend in penis and associated band of muscle running along length of
         penis; proximal ¾ of epiphallus held in long, conspicuous loop; and penial retractor muscle
         with two branches, one inserting subterminally on epiphallic caecum and one inserting on
         apex of loop of epiphallus. Inner wall of penis divisible into three regions: proximal
         penis (one major and several minor longitudinal pilasters), mid-penis (several minor
         longitudinal pilasters) and distal penis (a few minor pilasters with associated regular
         transverse ridges in interspaces). Inner wall of epiphallic caecum shows one long major
         longitudinal pilaster, a large mass of reticulate ridges proximally and several minor
         longitudinal pilasters distally. Gametolytic gland elongated and long; gametolytic sac
         3–3.5 times as long as gametolytic duct. Amatorial organ absent. Spermatophore consists of
         elongated, soft capsule and long tail-pipe, with U-shaped bend at capsule–tail-pipe
         junction and funnel-like opening at tip of tail-pipe; surface smooth apart from four ribs
         running obliquely along length of tail-pipe and short spines near end of tail-pipe.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p>The new genus is named in honour of the herpetologist Dr Varad Giri, who has made a major
         contribution to the modern study and conservation of the Indian herpetofauna;
         masculine.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
