<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Susamyia Ziegler &amp; Gilasian 2021, gen.
            nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4722980</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/895AEA68FFB7FF847F68FCB804BB30D3</uri>
         <article-title>A new genus and species of tachinid flies from Iran (Diptera, Tachinidae,
            Goniini)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"
            >http://zoobank.org/b8ae3f15-9eb5-4a7c-98fd-058a1ebe5ce9</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Susamyia Ziegler &amp; Gilasian </tp:taxon-name> gen.
      nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: D91AA3EC-2302-46C5-B269-F6B5BFD300AB </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species: <tp:taxon-name> Susamyia mira Ziegler &amp; Gilasian </tp:taxon-name> gen.
         et sp. nov. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> The first part of the genus name ‘ <tp:taxon-name> Susamyia </tp:taxon-name> ’ (Latin,
         substantive feminine) refers to the historical name of the city of Susa, pronounced
         ‘Shoush’ in modern Persian, and permanently inhabited for 6200 years. The city is located
         in the southwestern Khuzestan Province of Iran , between the Karkheh and Dez Rivers, where
         the holotype was collected. The second part of the name is the Greek word ʻmyiaʼ, which
         means ‘fly’. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> Eye bare; gena with black setulae; height of gena in lateral view about 0.2 times as long
         as vertical diameter of eye; face 1.2–1.3 times as long as frons; frons at its narrowest
         point wider than an eye, at most 1.3 times as wide as an eye viewed dorsally; upper part of
         head without black setulae behind the postocular row; facial ridge with erect setae;
         parafacial bare, moderately narrow; fronto-orbital plate with 2 proclinate orbital setae
         and usually a single reclinate upper orbital seta, if two present, then uppermost stronger;
         postpedicel not pointed dorsoapically, much longer than pedicel; arista almost bare,
         thickened in basal ⅗; first and second aristomeres short; prosternum setose; proepisternum
         bare; 3 strong basal setae of postpronotum arranged in a nearly straight line; scutum with
         4 postsutural dorsocentral setae; first postsutural supra-alar seta longer than notopleural
         setae; mesopleuron with black setulae; postmetacoxal area membranous; scutellum with 4
         pairs of marginal setae; apical setae of scutellum at most inclined at 30° to horizontal;
         lateral scutellar setae strong and as long as basal setae; katepisternum with 3 setae
         almost in a line; lower calypter not exceptionally convex at outer margin; vein R 4+5
         setose at most halfway to crossvein r-m; wing cell r4+5 open or closed at wing margin;
         section of vein M between crossveins r-m and dm-cu distinctly longer than section between
         dm-cu and bend of M; bend of M forming a right angle; vein M complete; bend of vein M flat,
         without continuation; crossvein dm-cu not exceptionally oblique; preapical anterodorsal
         seta on fore tibia shorter than preapical dorsal seta; mid tibia with a nearly complete row
         of different-sized anterodorsal setae; hind coxa bare posterodorsally; hind tibia with 2
         preapical dorsal setae; preapical posteroventral seta on hind tibia shorter than preapical
         anteroventral seta; abdomen predominantly covered with dense grey microtrichosity;
         middorsal depression of syntergite 1+2 extending back to posterior margin of that segment;
         tergites 3–4 without median discal setae. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
