<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ameroglossum genaroanum E. M. Almeida, J. M. P. Cordeiro &amp; L. P. Felix 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4697352</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8C0A87ADB160FFAB59019F24FB47FB34</uri>
         <article-title>An overview of the Brazilian inselberg genus Ameroglossum (Linderniaceae, Lamiales), with the description of seven new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.746.1313</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>urn:lsid:ipni.org:names:77216329-1</p>
      <p>Figa 2E, 5a–d</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species is morphologically similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. manoelfelixii
</tp:taxon-name>
in having young leaves with revolute margins, vegetative structures lustrous and violet trichomes on the lower lip of the corolla tube. It differs from that species in its green vegetative portions (vs tinged purple), leaf blade elliptic to ovate (vs elliptic to narrowly elliptic, sometimes trullate) and flowers orangish (vs scarlet).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific name is in honour of Prof. Genaro Viana Dornelas, a senior professor at the Universidade Federal da 
Paraíba
, who has a vast knowledge of the flora of 
Paraíba State
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Type
BRAZIL

– 
Paraíba

• 
Tacima
, 
Sítio Pão de Açúcar
; 
06°35′33″S
, 
35°27′38″W
; 

198 m
a.s.l.

; 

28 Jul. 2012

; 

E.M. Almeida
, 
E.M. Almeida
&amp; 
S.L.M. Almeida
397

; 
holotype
: EAN!; isotypes: IPA!, K!, RB!, UFP
</tp:material-citation>
!.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
BRAZIL

– 
Paraíba

• 
Serra da Raiz
, 
Zona Urbana
; 
06°41ʹ07ʺ S
, 
35°26ʹ44ʺ W
; 

341 m
a.s.l.

; 

23 May 2018

; 

L.P. Felix
, 
E.M. Almeida
&amp; 
J.M.P. Cordeiro
17,486

; 
EAN[25,542]
</tp:material-citation>
!. 
–
<tp:material-citation>
Rio Grande do Norte

• 
Santo Antônio
, 
Serra da Micaela
; 
06°18ʹ03ʺ S
, 
35°31ʹ49ʺ W
; 

295 m
a.s.l.

; 

13 Apr. 2010

; 

L.P. Felix
13041

; 
EAN[16,772]
</tp:material-citation>
! • 
<tp:material-citation>
Distrito de Lages
, 
Serrote das Lajes
; 
06°20ʹ41ʺ S
, 
35°27ʹ11ʺ W
; 

74 m
a.s.l.

; 

17 Aug. 2013

; 

J.L. Costa-Lima
1011

; 
UFP[80,126]
</tp:material-citation>
! • 
<tp:material-citation>
Estrada para Goianinha
; 
06°19ʹ15ʺ S
, 
35°27ʹ09ʺ W
; 

102 m
a.s.l.

; 

13 Apr. 2010

; 

L.P. Felix
13044

; 
EAN[13,044]
! 
Serra da Micaela
; 
06°18ʹ03ʺ S
, 
35°31ʹ49ʺ W
; 

295 m
a.s.l.

; 2008; 

P
. 
A
. 
Porto
s.n.

; 
EAN
[15972]
</tp:material-citation>
! • 
<tp:material-citation>
Serrinha
; 
06°16ʹ42ʺ S
, 
35°29ʹ58ʺ W
; 

102 m
a.s.l.

; 

16 Apr. 2003

; 

S. Pitrez et al.
365

; 
EAN[10281]
</tp:material-citation>
!.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Saxicolous chamaephyte up to 
100 cm
tall, frequently with secondary branching near the tips. Young branches green, lustrous, occasionally bicolor with wide longitudinal purplish stripes, quadrangular, sometimes with a narrow wing, glabrous; brown cinereous when mature, slightly inclined, subquadrangular. Leaves opposite decussate; leaf blade 5.8–11.7× 
2.2–4.3 cm
, green, lustrous, elliptic to ovate, bullate when young, later smooth; adaxial side glabrous; abaxial side glabrescent, principally the younger leaves, with glandular trichomes; apex acute to acuminate, flat to reflexed; margin flat to revolute, ciliate. Inflorescences simple dichasia, sometimes compound. Peduncle green, cylindrical, without wings, glabrescent, with papillose trichomes; primary peduncle 0.8–2.8 × 
0.15 cm
, secondary peduncle 0.4–1.1 × 
0.1 cm
, tertiary peduncle 0.40–0.60 × 
0.08 cm
. Pedicel 0.4–0.9 × 
0.1–0.2 cm
, green, glabrescent, with papillose trichomes, ventral side without wings. Bracts 0.20–0.70 × 
0.05–0.08 cm
, green, abaxial side glabrescent, with aciculate trichomes, adaxial side glabrescent, with papillose and aciculate trichomes, margin glabrous. Calyx green, abaxial side glabrescent, with papillose trichomes, adaxial side densely covered by papillose trichomes, margin ciliate with recurved trichomes; sepals lanceolate, dorsal one 1.1–1.8 × 
0.3–0.5 cm
, lateral ones 0.8–1.4 × 
0.2 cm
, ventral ones 0.8–1.4 × 
0.2–0.4 cm
. Corolla 
4.5–5.5 cm
long, orangish with yellow base, externally pubescent with glandular trichomes, internally glabrous; tube 
3.3–4.2 cm
long; upper lip 1.4–1.6 × 
0.8–0.9 cm
, slightly bilobate; lower lip 0.9–1.3 × 
0.4–0.5 cm
, inner perianth with filiform trichomes, violet; lobes revolute, median lobe 0.12–0.15 × 
0.08–0.10 cm
. Stamens included, sometimes with ventral pair exserted, adnate to the middle third of the corolla tube; filaments violet, dorsal ones 1.7–2.3 × 
0.7 cm
, ventral ones 1.7–2.1 × 
0.7 cm
; thecae ca 
0.2 cm
diam.; staminodium 
0.3–0.5 cm
long, adnate near the proximal third of the corolla tube, glabrescent with short, glandular trichomes. Ovary 0.6–0.8 × 
0.2–0.3 cm
; style 
3.3–4.6 cm
long, exserted. Capsule 1.2–1.5 × 
0.6–0.8 cm
, green. Seeds 0.10 × 
0.05 cm
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 5. a–d
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum genaroanum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(
Almeida et al. 397
). 
a
. Reproductive branches. 
b
. Inflorescence. 
c
. Flower. 
d
. Corolla opened, showing the stamens. 
e–h
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum intermedium
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(
Almeida &amp; Wanderley 478
). 
e
. Reproductive branches. 
f
. Inflorescence. 
g
. Flower. 
h
. Corolla opened, showing the stamens. 
i–k
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum xukuruorum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(
Felix et al. 15647
). 
i
. Reproductive branches. 
j
. Flower. 
k
. Corolla opened, showing the stamens.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
This taxon has a more northerly distribution than the other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum
</tp:taxon-name>
and occurs the lowest for this genus. It occurs on rock outcrops in the Agreste Paraibano mesoregion, in 
Paraíba State
(two populations), and in the Agreste Potiguar mesoregion in 
Rio Grande do Norte State
(four populations), 
Brazil
. Elevation between 70 and 

300 m
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum genaroanum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
occurs on rock outcrops. Flowering and fruiting between April and June.
</p>
      <p>
Population and threats
</p>
      <tp:nomenclature>
Diagnosis
Etymology
Material examined
Description
Distribution
Ecology
Population and threats
Taxonomic notes
</tp:nomenclature>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ameroglossum genaroanum E. M. Almeida, J. M. P. Cordeiro &amp; L. P. Felix 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4697352</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8C0A87ADB162FFB4597D9E27FAF9F83E</uri>
         <article-title>An overview of the Brazilian inselberg genus Ameroglossum (Linderniaceae, Lamiales), with the description of seven new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.746.1313</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>urn:lsid:ipni.org:names:77216330-1</p>
      <p>
Figs 2F
, 
5e–h
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum intermedium
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
combines characters of both 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. manoelfelixii
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. pernambucense
</tp:taxon-name>
. It can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. manoelfelixii
</tp:taxon-name>
by its puberulent branches and leaves (vs glabrousglabrescent leaves), with acicular trichomes recurved at the apex (vs papillose trichomes), and from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. pernambucense
</tp:taxon-name>
by its compound dichasial inflorescence (vs a simple dichasium) and the revolute lower lip (vs involute).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet is derived from the Latin adjectives ʻ 
inter
ʼ, ʻbetweenʼ, and ʻ 
medius
ʼ, ʻmiddleʼ, referring to the morphological characteristics of the new species that are intermediate between 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. manoelfelixii
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. pernambucense
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Type
BRAZIL

– 
Alagoas

• 
Quebrangulo
; 
09°18′17″ S
, 
36°31′13″W
; 

502 m
a.s.l.

; 

23Aug. 2012

; 

E.M.Almeida
&amp; 
A.M. Wanderley
478

; 
holotype
: EAN!; isotypes: IMA!, IPA!, K!, RB
</tp:material-citation>
!.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
BRAZIL

– 
Alagoas

• 
Quebrangulo
, 
estrada para Bom Retiro
; 
09°17ʹ56ʺ S
, 
36°30ʹ33ʺ W
; 

25 Aug. 2013

; 

L.P. Felix
&amp; 
E.M. Almeida
14,339

; 
EAN[19,860]
</tp:material-citation>
!.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Saxicolous chamaephyte up to 
150 cm
, frequently with secondary branching along the stem. Young branches green to slightly purplish, bifacial, dull, quadrangular or hexangular, often narrowly winged, pubescent, with recurved trichomes; brown cinereous when mature, slightly inclined to decumbent, subquadrangular. Leaves opposite, decussate, occasionally verticillate and then up to three leaves per node; leaf blade 5.1–14.0 × 
1.4–3.9 cm
, green, lustrous, elliptic to narrowly elliptic, rarely trullate, bullate when young, later smooth; adaxial side glabrous, abaxial side pubescent, with recurved trichomes; apex acute, rarely acuminate, flat to reflexed; margin revolute when young, later flat, ciliate. Inflorescence a compound dichasium, occasionally simple. Peduncle green or tinged purple, subcylindrical, winged, pubescent, with recurved trichomes; primary peduncle 0.7–4.0 × 
0.1–0.2 cm
, secondary peduncle 0.30– 1.80 × 
0.13–0.15 cm
, tertiary peduncle 0.30–1.20 × 
0.07–0.10 cm
. Pedicel 0.6–2.5 × 
0.1–0.2 cm
, green to slightly purplish, pubescent, with recurved trichomes; ventral side winged up to the proximal third. Bracts 0.20–0.60 × 
0.03–0.08 cm
, green, abaxial side glabrous, adaxial side glabrescent with papillose trichomes, margin ciliate with recurved trichomes. Calyx green, abaxial side glabrescent, with recurved and/or papillose trichomes, adaxial side covered by papillose trichomes, margin ciliate with recurved trichomes; sepals lanceolate, dorsal one 1.2–1.5 × 
0.3–0.5 cm
, lateral ones 1.0–1.2 × 
0.2 cm
, ventral ones 0.8–1.1 × 
0.2–0.3 cm
. Corolla 
4.5–5.6 cm
long, orangish, with proximal third yellowish, external side pubescent, trichomes glandular, rarely recurved and/or papillose; tube 
3.5–4.4 cm
long; upper lip 1.2–1.8 × 
0.6–0.8 cm
, slightly bilobate; lower lip 1.1–1.4 × 
0.35–0.50 cm
, inner perianth with white filiform trichomes; lobes revolute, median lobe 0.1 × 
0.2 cm
. Stamens occasionally with the ventral pair exserted, adnate to the median third of the corolla tube; filaments violet, dorsal ones 1.6–2.6 × 
0.8 cm
, ventral ones 1.9–2.9 × 
0.8 cm
; thecae ca 
0.2 cm
diam.; staminodium 
0.3–0.4 cm
, adnate to the median third of the corolla tube, glabrous. Ovary 0.4–0.7 × 
0.2–0.3 cm
; style 
3.6–5.6 cm
, occasionally exserted. Capsule 1.2–1.6 × 
0.6–0.8 cm
, greenish. Seeds 0.10 × 
0.05 cm
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Only two populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum intermedium
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
are currently known, both in the municipality of Quebrangulo, Agreste mesoregion of 
Alagoas State
. Elevation ca 

500 m
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>
This species occurs exclusively on granite outcrops. Flowering and fruiting recorded in August and like all other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum
species
</tp:taxon-name>
it is pollinated by hummingbirds. The surrounding vegetation was probably originally composed of deciduous forest, but this has now been replaced by natural pasture.
</p>
      <p>
Population and threats
</p>
      <p>
Only two rock outcrops separated by pasture in a single municipality in 
Alagoas State
are known to harbour this species. Approximately 
200 adult
individuals can be found in the first population, whereas the other comprises approximately 30 individuals. The main threat to these populations are farming and grazing of the site by stray animals.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Taxonomic notes
</p>
      <p>
Among the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum
</tp:taxon-name>
with quadrangular stems, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. intermedium
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
stands out by having reproductive and vegetative structures covered in trichomes, a characteristic otherwise typically observed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. pernambucense
</tp:taxon-name>
. However, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. intermedium
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
differs by having leaves that are principally opposite and decussate, inflorescences of compound dichasia and the revolute lower lip.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
