<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Tinggianthura mexicana Jarquín-Martínez &amp; García-Madrigal 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5123272</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6BEFE70843EF572AA40CF7E69683FC51</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Anthuridae (Peracarida: Isopoda) from the southern Mexican Pacific</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/666ad5f1-6ac4-4940-b05c-4b57c3063593</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tinggianthura mexicana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
0B9D9534-1B0A-4931-8929-1B0933C54C7D
</p>
      <p>
Figs 17–19
, 
20F
, 
Table 3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This species is named after 
Mexico
, the country where the second species of the genus is described.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MEXICO
• 
♀
(body length 
3.7 mm
); 
Oaxaca
, 
Huatulco
, 
El Maguey Bay
; 
15°43′59.6172″N
, 
96°9′5.5116″W
; depth 

1 m

; 

4 Jul. 2007

; 
B. Martínez-Guerrero
et al
. leg.; algae and sediment; 
UMAR-PERA 561
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
MEXICO
• 
1 ♂
(body length 
3.9 mm
); same collection data as for holotype; 
UMAR-PERA 562

• 

3 ♀♀
, 
2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
UMAR-PERA 563

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
– 

Guerrero

• 
1 ♀
; 
Ixtapa Island
, 
Coral Beach
, E-1A; 
17°40′38″ N
, 
101°39′20″ W
; depth 

1.5 m

; 

19 Sep. 2007

; 
M.S. García-Madrigal
et al
. leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR-PERA 551

• 

1 ♂
; same locality data as for preceding; depth 

6 m

; 

19 Sep. 2007

; 
M.S. García-Madrigal
et al
. leg.; algae; 
UMAR- PERA 552

• 

1 ♂
; 
Acapulco
, 
La Roqueta Island
; 
16°49′26″ N
, 
99°54′29″ W
; depth 

2 m

; 

21 Sep. 2007

; 
M.S. García-Madrigal
et al.
leg.; 
tubes of sabellariids
; 
UMAR-PERA 553

. – 

Oaxaca

• 
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Zipolite
, 
Playa del Amor
; 
15°39′35″ N
, 
96°30′33″ W
; 

3 Jul. 2007

; 
S. Rodríguez-Hernández
et al
. leg.; 
algae in tidal pool
; 
UMAR-PERA 554

• 

3 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Puerto Ángel
, 
Estacahuite Beach
; 
15°40′ N
, 
96°29′ W
; depth 

2–4 m

; 

18 May. 2005

; J. 
R
. 
Bastida-Zavala
et al
. leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR-PERA 555

• 

1 ♀
, 
2 ♂♂
; same locality data as for preceding; 

10 Sep. 2005

; 
J.R. Bastida-Zavala
et al
. leg.; 
UMAR-PERA 556

• 

3 ♀♀
, 
2 ♂♂
; 
Puerto Ángel
, 
Estacahuite Beach
; 
15°40′6″ N
, 
96°28′54″ W
; depth 

4 m

; 

25 Aug. 2006

; 
J.R. Bastida-Zavala
et al
. leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR-PERA 557

• 

3 ♀♀
; 
Puerto Ángel
, 
La Boquilla Bay
; 
15°40′59″ N
, 
96°27′54″ W
; 

3 Nov. 2007

; 
J. Medina-Elizalde
and 
E. Serrano-Figueroa
leg.; 
shallow water sand
; 
UMAR-PERA 558

• 

11 ♀♀
; 
Pochutla
, 
La Tijera Beach
; 
15°41′33″ N
, 
96°26′33″ W
; depth 

2–4 m

; 

30 Apr. 2005

; 
J.R. Bastida-Zavala
et al
. leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR-PERA 559

• 

1 ♂
; same locality data as for preceding; 

17 Sep. 2006

; 
J.R. Bastida-Zavala
et al
. leg.; 
UMAR-PERA 583

• 

1 ♀
; 
Huatulco
, 
San Agustín Bay
; 
15°41′27″ N
, 
96°14′15″ W
; 

24 Feb. 2007

; 
M.S. García-Madrigal
et al
. leg.; 
shallow water coral algae
; 
UMAR-PERA 560

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Holotype

(
♀
, UMAR-PERA 561)
</p>
      <p>
BODY (
Figs 17A
, 
20F
). Length 
3.7 mm
, 9.9 times as long as wide with a pigment line on the cephalon and pereonites 2–6; body proportion: C&lt;1&gt;2&lt;3&lt;4=5&gt;6&gt;7. Cephalon as long as wide, 0.4 times as long as pereonite 1, rostrum as long as lateral angles; eyes small, rounded. Pereonite 1 long compared to the others, pereonite 7 the shortest. Pleon sub-square, 1.4 times as long as pereonite 7; pleonites 1–5 fused with ventrolateral suture lines, distal margin of pleonite 6 emarginated. Telson linguiform, 2.3 times as long as wide with a pair of proximal statocysts; dorsal surface squamous with a row of distal and medial setae, apex with a small excavation with three pairs of setae, two short and one long.
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNULE (
Fig. 17B
). Peduncle with three articles. Article 1 and 2 with plumose sensory setae; article 2 with four long setae; article 3 with four long setae on the external margin and one on the internal distal angle; flagellum with three articles, second article 3.6 times as long as third, article 3 with three aesthetascs.
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNA (
Fig. 17C
). Peduncle with five articles. Article 2 larger compared to the others, 1.2 times as long as wide and 2.2 times as long as the third one, article 3 sub-equal to article 4, article 4 square with simple and sensory setae in the internal distal angle, last article 1.3 times as long as article 4, distal margin with a group of smooth and sensory plumose setae; flagellum with three articles, article 1 visible, distal articles smaller, difficult to distinguish with numerous setae.
</p>
      <p>
MAXILLIPED (
Fig. 17D
). Palp with two articles, first article with one proximal seta, one medial and two distal; article 2 oblique with five setae. Endite absent.
</p>
      <p>
MAXILLA (
Fig. 17E
). With six distal teeth.
</p>
      <p>
MANDIBLE (
Fig. 17F
). Symmetrical; palp with three articles, article 1 with one seta; article 2 with four long setae; article 3 reduced, 0.25 times the length of the article 1 with a robust denticulate seta; incisor with three teeth; lacinia mobilis with four denticles and molar blunt.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPOD 1 (
Fig. 18A
). Subchelate; carpus triangular, apically rounded with a cuticular ridge and seven simple setae; propodus oval, 2 times as long as wide, palm convex with a cuticular ridge and a row of eight setae; dactylus with a long seta in the ventrodistal angle; unguis longer than dactylus.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPODS 2–3 (
Fig. 18B–C
). Similar in shape and size. Carpus triangular with an apical denticle and two robust setae; propodus 1.9 times as long as wide, internal margin with 4–5 simple setae and one ventrodistally denticulate sensory spine, dorsal margin with a simple seta.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPODS 4–6 (
Fig. 18D–F
). Similar in shape and size. Merus inner margin denticulate; carpus trapezoid, ventrodistal margin with a simple sensory spine and a plumose sensory seta in the dorsal margin; propodus cylindrical, internal margin with setulated scales and two simple setae, ventrodistal angle with one denticulate sensory spine.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPOD 7 (
Fig. 18G
). Similar to pereopods 4–6, slender. Propodus 2.6 times as long as wide, ventral margin with one simple seta and setulated scales, ventrodistal angle with one denticulate sensory spine and two pectinate spines; dactylus with setulated scales on ventral and dorsal margins. Basis of all pereopods with simple and plumose sensory setae.
</p>
      <p>
PLEOPOD 1 (
Fig. 19A
). Protopod with three retinaculae and two setae on the inner margin; exopod operculiform, 2.1 times as long as wide and 2.6 times as wide as endopod, internal proximal margin
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 17.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tinggianthura mexicana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀, 3.7 mm, Oaxaca, Huatulco, El Maguey Bay (UMAR-PERA 561). 
A
. Habitus and detail of the telson (a) (the numbers indicate the pairs of setae). 
B
. Antennule. 
C
. Antenna. 
D
. Maxilliped. 
E
. Maxilla. 
F
. Mandible.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 18.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tinggianthura mexicana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀, 3.7 mm, Oaxaca, Huatulco, El Maguey Bay (UMAR-PERA 561). 
A
. Pereopod 1 and detail of the palm (a). 
B
. Pereopod 2 and detail of the sensory spine. 
C
. Pereopod 3. 
D
. Pereopod 4. 
E
. Pereopod 5. 
F
. Pereopod 6. 
G
. Pereopod 7 and detail of propodus and dactylus (g).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 19.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tinggianthura mexicana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–D
. Holotype, ♀, 3.7 mm, Oaxaca, Huatulco, El Maguey Bay (UMAR-PERA 561). 
A
. Pleopod 1. 
B
. Pleopod 2. 
C
. Uropodal endopod. 
D
. Uropodal exopod. 
E–G
. Paratype, ♂, 3.9 mm (UMAR-PERA 562). 
E
. Antennule. 
F
. Pereopod 1. 
G
. Pleopod 2.
</p>
      <p>with a simple seta, distal margin surrounded by 29 plumose setae; endopod surrounded distally by four plumose setae.</p>
      <p>
PLEOPOD 2 (
Fig. 19B
). Exopod elongated oval, 0.8 times the length of endopod; endopod and exopod surrounded distally by seven plumose setae.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL PROTOPOD (
Fig. 19C
). Rectangular, 1.6 times as long as endopod, external margin with a row of plumose setae, distoventral angle with a plumose seta.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL ENDOPOD (
Fig. 19C
). Oval, distally rounded, 1.5 times as long as wide, slightly longer than pleotelson; distal margin surrounded by simple and plumose sensory setae.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL EXOPOD (
Fig. 19D
). Oval, distally excavated, 1.8 times as long as wide, margin surrounded by 52 long setae, eight simple and 44 plumose setae; dorsal surface covered by scales and some small setae.
</p>
      <p>
Male
(dimorphic characters; based on the 
paratype
♂
, UMAR-PERA 562)
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNULE (
Fig. 19E
). Peduncle with three articles; article 1 almost twice as long as second, outer margin with plumose sensory setae; article 2 sub-square, outer margin with three long setae and sensory setae in distal margin; article 3 with three long setae in the dorsodistal angle and two on the ventral one; flagellum with four article, article 1 tiny; article 2 with a group of long aesthetascs; distal article with three aesthetascs and simple setae.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPOD 1 (
Fig. 19F
). Similar to the female; carpus triangular, rounded distally with a cuticular ridge and simple setae; palm slightly convex with a cuticular ridge and seven short marginal setae, mesial region with a row of smooth and pectinate setae.
</p>
      <p>
PLEOPOD 2 (
Fig. 19G
). Exopod elongated oval, distal margin surrounded by six plumose setae; endopod longer than exopod, 0.6 times its width, distal margin with four plumose setae; male appendix cylindrical, rounded apex, distolateral margins with setulated scales.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution and habitat
</p>
      <p>
From Ixtapa, 
Guerrero
to Huatulco, 
Oaxaca
. In coral, coral rock, algae, tubes of sabellariids and sand; intertidal to subtidal (
6 m
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tinggianthura alba
Chew, Abdul-Rahim &amp; Haji Ross, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
, described from Pulau Tinggi, 
Johor
, 
Malaysia
, is the only other species of this genus and differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. mexicana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
by having the following unique characteristics: body slightly pigmented; article three of mandibular palp with one pectinate seta; pleopod 1 with inner margin of protopod with two distal setae and exopod with inner proximal seta; and telson and uropodal exopod with scales on dorsal surface. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tinggianthura mexicana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. alba
</tp:taxon-name>
by the following characteristics: (1) the article 3 of the mandibular palp is almost a third of 1, (2) maxillipedal palp with two free segments, (3) palm of the pereopod 1 without a marginal projection, and (4) pleon as long as wide. The new species differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. alba
</tp:taxon-name>
by (1) distal setae of telson, (2) antennal flagellum, (3) lacinia mobilis, (4) molar process, and (5) palm of pereopod 1. While in 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. alba
</tp:taxon-name>
the telson has three setae on the lateral margins and eight on the dorsal surface, the antennal flagellum has two articles, lacinia mobilis with five denticles, molar process is strongly projected, and the palm of pereopod 1 has many setae. In comparison, in the new species the telson has five lateral and 10 dorsal setae, antennal flagellum with three articles, lacinia mobilis with four teeth, molar process is truncated, and palm of the pereopod 1 with eight robust setae (
Table 3
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
