<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Cortezura caeca Jarquín-Martínez
                        &amp; García-Madrigal 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5123266</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8C5D87D5BA47FFA4FD5C9596FE764DD2</uri>
                  <article-title>Six new species of Anthuridae (Peracarida: Isopoda) from the
                        southern Mexican Pacific</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://zoobank.org/666ad5f1-6ac4-4940-b05c-4b57c3063593</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Cortezura caeca </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: AE0F227A-7FA9-4897-B29F-7C32EBF9214A </p>
            <p> Figs 5–7 , 20B </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> This species is named after ‘ <tp:taxon-name> caeca </tp:taxon-name> ’ due to the
                  absence of eyes. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype MEXICO • ♀ (body length 7.1 mm ); Oaxaca ,
                        Huatulco , Jicaral Beach ; 15°42′38″ N , 96°11′49″ W ; depth 12 m ; 11 Feb.
                        2007 ; V. Hernández-Urraca and L. Estrada-Vargas leg.; coral; UMAR-PERA 534
                        . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes MEXICO • 1 ♂ (body length 8 mm ); same collection
                        data as for holotype; UMAR-PERA 535 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; UMAR-PERA
                        536 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Additional material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> MEXICO – Oaxaca • 1 ♀ ; Pochutla , La Tijera Beach ;
                        15°41′13″ N , 96°26′36″ W ; depth 8 m ; 24 Apr. 2009 ; D. Zavala-Casas leg.;
                        sand; UMAR-PERA 537 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 3 ♀♀ ,
                        1 ♂ ; Huatulco , Copalita Beach , in front of the mouth of the Copalita
                        River ; 15°47′17″ N , 96°3′5″ W ; depth 10 m ; 7 May 2007 ; E. Morales-
                        Domínguez and C. Hernández-Tlapale leg.; sediment; UMAR-PERA 538
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Holotype ( ♀ , UMAR-PERA 534) </p>
            <p> BODY ( Figs 5A , 20B ). Length 7.1 mm , about 11.8 times as long as wide with a
                  whitish color, without pigment. Body proportion:
                  C&lt;1=2&gt;3&lt;4&lt;5&gt;6&gt;7. Cephalon 1.3 times as long as wide, rostral
                  process equal to lateral lobes, eyes absent; overlapping antennas, forming a
                  flattened surface. Pleon equals to the length of the pereonite 7; pleonites 1–5
                  fused, pleonite 6 free. Telson 2.6 times as long as wide, tapering distally with
                  two proximal statocysts, mid-distal margin with a group of short setae; apex
                  broadly truncate, slightly sinuous with eight sub-marginal and eight marginal
                  setae. </p>
            <p> ANTENNULE ( Fig. 5B ). Peduncle with three articles. First article 1.2 times as long
                  as second, with four simple setae and plumose sensory setae; article 2 with four
                  long simple setae and scales in ventral margin; article 3 narrow than others with
                  a group of ventrodistal setae and a long apical seta; flagellum of three articles,
                  distal article with three aesthetascs. </p>
            <p> ANTENNA ( Fig. 5C ). Peduncle with five articles. Article 2 with scales in ventral
                  margin; articles 3 and 4 sub-equal; article 5 subrectangular, 1.2 times as long as
                  article 4; flagellum with three articles, article 1 longer than the others; distal
                  articles with numerous setae. </p>
            <p> MAXILLIPED ( Fig. 5D ). Palp with two articles. Article 1 large, 1.3 times as long
                  as wide, internal margin with four setae, external margin with one seta, distal
                  angle with two setae; distal article oblique with three distal wide setae. Endite
                  present, with fine distal setae. </p>
            <p> MAXILLA ( Fig. 5E ). With seven stout distal teeth. </p>
            <p> MANDIBLE ( Fig. 5F ). Symmetrical; palp with two articles, article 1 with a simple
                  distal seta; distal article 1.8 times as long as article 1, whit three mid-distal
                  setae and one long apical. Incisor with three teeth; lacinia mobilis with
                  approximately 13 denticles, sharp molar. </p>
            <p> PEREOPOD 1 ( Fig. 6A ). Subchelate; carpus triangular, apically rounded with a group
                  of distal simple setae; propodus ovate, palm curved, slightly medially convex with
                  a row of 11 short setae; dactylus reaching almost half the palm, internal distal
                  angle with a tooth; unguis slender, reaching the apical margin of the carpus. </p>
            <p> PEREOPODS 2–3 ( Fig. 6B–C ). Similar in shape and size. Ischium, merus and carpus
                  with numerous ventral simple setae; inner margin of merus denticulate; carpus
                  triangular, partially below the propodus with 2 robust setae on the distal margin;
                  propodus cylindrical, 2 times as long as wide, internal margin with setulated
                  scales, distoventrally one serrated sensory spine and a group of simple setae. </p>
            <p> PEREOPODS 4–7 ( Fig. 6D–G ). Similar in shape and size. Inner margin of ischium and
                  merus slightly denticulate and numerous simple setae; carpus pentagonal,
                  ventrodistal margin with a single sensory spine and a group of long setae;
                  propodus cylindrical, approximately half the width of the carpus, internal margin
                  with a group of simple setae and setulated scales, ventrodistal margin with a
                  serrate sensory spine and 1–2 pectinate spines; pereopod 7 dactylus with setulated
                  scales on the inner and outer margins. Pereopods 2–7 basis with a long simple seta
                  and plumose sensory setae; merus, carpus and propodus with scales. </p>
            <p> PLEOPOD 1 ( Fig. 7A ). Protopod with three retinaculae; exopod operculiform, 2.4
                  times as long as wide, surrounded distal and laterally by 28 plumose setae;
                  endopod almost half as wide as exopod with seven plumose setae. </p>
            <p> PLEOPOD 2 ( Fig. 7B ). Exopod surrounded distally by 11 plumose setae; endopod
                  surrounded by eight plumose setae. </p>
            <p> UROPODAL PROTOPOD ( Fig. 7C ). Rectangular, 2 times as long as basal width, outer
                  margin with plumose setae. </p>
            <p> UROPODAL ENDOPOD ( Fig. 7C ). Subtriangular, 1.5 times as long as wide, rounded
                  apex, outer and apical margin with long simple setae and plumose sensory setae. </p>
            <p> UROPODAL EXOPOD ( Fig. 7D ). Auriculiform, dorsal surface with short setae, external
                  margin with 24 simple setae and numerous plumose setae. </p>
            <p> Male (dimorphic characters; based on the paratype ♂ , UMAR-PERA 535) </p>
            <p> ANTENNULE ( Fig. 7E ). Peduncle with three articles; article 2 projected internal
                  distal angle; flagellum robust with four articles, article1 circular; article 2
                  with numerous aesthetascs; articles 3 and 4 smaller. </p>
            <p>MANDIBLE. Mandibular palp with two articles; distal article with seven long
                  setae.</p>
            <p> PEREOPOD 1 ( Fig. 7F ). Subchelate; palm concave with a strong middle tooth and
                  numerous marginal and mesial setae; distoventral angle of dactylus slightly
                  projected. </p>
            <p> PLEOPOD 2 ( Fig. 7G ). Similar to the female; exopod surrounded distally by 10
                  plumose setae; endopod surrounded by seven plumose setae; male appendix emerging
                  from the middle part of the endopod, slightly longer than ramus, apex rounded and
                  slightly bent towards the inside. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution and habitat </p>
            <p> From Puerto Ángel to Huatulco, Oaxaca . In coral, sand and sediment; subtidal ( 12 m
                  ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 5. <tp:taxon-name> Cortezura caeca </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♀, 7.1 mm,
            Oaxaca, Huatulco, Jicaral Beach (UMAR-PERA 534). A . Habitus and telson (a). B .
            Antennule. C . Antenna. D . Maxilliped. E . Maxilla. F . Mandible. </p>
      <p> Fig. 6. <tp:taxon-name> Cortezura caeca </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♀, 7.1 mm,
            Oaxaca, Huatulco, Jicaral Beach (UMAR-PERA 534). A . Pereopod 1 and detail of palm (a).
            B . Pereopod 2 and detail of the sensory spine. C . Pereopod 3 and detail of carpus. D .
            Pereopod 4. E . Pereopod 5. F . Pereopod 6. G . Pereopod 7 and detail of the sensory
            spines. </p>
      <p> Fig. 7. <tp:taxon-name> Cortezura caeca </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. A–D . Holotype, ♀, 7.1
            mm, Oaxaca, Huatulco, Jicaral Beach (UMAR- PERA 534). A . Pleopod 1. B . Pleopod 2. C .
            Uropodal endopod. D . Uropodal exopod. E–G . Paratype ♂, 8 mm (UMAR-PERA 535). E .
            Antennule. F . Pereopod 1. G . Pleopod 2. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cortezura caeca </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from the two
                  previously recorded species of this genus, <tp:taxon-name> C. penascoensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> , described from Puerto Peñasco, Sonora, and <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        confixa (Kensley, 1978) </tp:taxon-name> described from Cubagua Island,
                  Venezuela , by the following unique characteristics: distal article of the
                  mandibular palp with four medial setae and one apical, lacinia mobilis with 13
                  denticles, telson with distolateral carina, distal region with eight subapical
                  setae and eight apical. <tp:taxon-name> Cortezura caeca </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  is similar to <tp:taxon-name> C. penascoensis </tp:taxon-name> as follows: (1)
                  form of telson, (2) palm of pereopod 1, and (3) maxilla. However, in
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. caeca </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. the distal article of the
                  mandibular palp has four medial setae and one apical, lacinia mobilis with 13
                  denticles, distally tapered telson and the apex is truncated, pereopods 2–7 with
                  scales on the merus, carpus and propodus. And in <tp:taxon-name> C. penascoensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> the distal article of the mandibular palp has six medial setae
                  and one apical, lacinia mobilis presents 8 teeth, pleon with six conspicuous
                  segments. The antennular flagellum of the male of <tp:taxon-name> Cortezura caeca
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. has four articles and the palm of pereopod 1 has a
                  strong tooth projected transversally, while <tp:taxon-name> C. penascoensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> has one article on the flagellum, palm of pereopod 1 with tooth
                  projected proximally. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
