<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amakusanthura guerrerensis Jarquín-Martínez &amp; García-Madrigal 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5123264</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/1016F0DCF171470C6F11684081D8D304</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Anthuridae (Peracarida: Isopoda) from the southern Mexican Pacific</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/666ad5f1-6ac4-4940-b05c-4b57c3063593</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amakusanthura guerrerensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
B887EED9-16EB-433E-9F69-ACD26CA84B62
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2–4
, 
20A
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This species is named after 
Guerrero
, the 
Mexico State
where the 
type
material was collected.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MEXICO
• 
♀
(body length 
5 mm
); 
Guerrero
, 
Ixtapa Island
, 
Coral Beach
, E-1A; 
17°40′38″ N
, 
101°39′20″ W
; depth 

1.5 m

; 

19 Sep. 2007

; 
M.S García-Madrigal
et al
. leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR- PERA 522
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
MEXICO
• 
2 ♀♀
(ovigerous), 
4 ♀♀
, 
2 mancae
; same collection data as for holotype; 
UMAR-PERA 523
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MEXICO
– 

Guerrero

• 
4 ♀♀
, 
5 mancae
; 
Ixtapa Island
, 
Coral Beach
, E-1B; 
17°40′38″ N
, 
101°39′20″ W
; depth intertidal; 

19 Sep. 2007

; 
M.S García-Madrigal
et al
. leg.; algae; 
UMAR-PERA 524
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
7 ♀♀
, 
7 mancae
; 
Ixtapa Island
, 
Coral Beach
; 
17°40′36″ N
, 
101°39′22″ W
; depth 

6 m

; 

19 Sep. 2007

; 
M.S. García-Madrigal
et al
. leg.; 
coral
; 
UMAR-PERA 525
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
4 ♀♀
, 
1 manca
; 
Acapulco
, 
La Roqueta Island
; 
16°49′26″ N
, 
99°54′29″ W
; depth 

2 m

; 

21 Sep. 2007

; 

M.S. García-Madrigal 
et al
.

leg.; 
tubes of sabellariids
; 
UMAR-PERA 526
</tp:material-citation>
. – 
<tp:material-citation>
Oaxaca

• 
1 ♀
; 
Cozoaltepec
, 
Agua Blanca Beach
; 
15°44′2″ N
, 
96°48′32″ W
; depth intertidal; 

11 Nov. 2007

; 
I. López-Aguilar
et al
. leg.; algae; 
UMAR-PERA 527
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 ♀♀
, 
1 manca
; 
Puerto Ángel
, 
Estacahuite Beach
; 
15°40′ N
, 
96°29′ W
; depth 

0.5 m

; 

3 Jul. 2007

; J. 
Jarquín-González
et al
. leg.; coral; 
UMAR-PERA 528
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♀♀
(ovigerous), 
6 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
, 
2 mancae
; 
Pochutla
, 
La Tijera Beach
; 
15°41′33″ N
, 
96°26′33″ W
; depth 

2–4 m

; 

30 Apr. 2005

; 
J.R. Bastida-Zavala
et al
. leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR-PERA 529
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
, 
1 manca
; 
Pochutla
, 
La Tijera Beach
; 
15°41′33″ N
, 
96°26′33″ W
; depth 

3 m

; 

7 Apr. 2009

; F. 
Cortés-Carrasco
et al
. leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR-PERA 530
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
5 ♀♀
; 
Huatulco
, 
San Agustín Bay
; 
15°41′27″ N
, 
96°14′15″ W
; depth intertidal; 

24 Feb. 2007

; 
M.S. García-Madrigal
et al
. leg.; 
coral algae
; 
UMAR-PERA 531
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 ♀♀
; 
Huatulco
, 
San Agustín Bay
; 
15°41′22″ N
, 
96°14′14″ W
; depth intertidal; 

24 Oct. 2013

; 
H. Solano-García
leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR- PERA 532
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Huatulco
, 
Cacaluta Bay
; 
15°43′21″ N
, 
96°9′48″ W
; depth shallow water; 

27 Oct. 2013

; 
R
. 
Rodríguez
leg.; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Spondylus
</tp:taxon-name>
shells; 
UMAR-PERA 533
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Holotype

(
♀
, UMAR-PERA 522)
</p>
      <p>
BODY (
Figs 2A
, 
4E
, 
20A
). Length 
5 mm
, about 10 times as long as wide with a brown pigment band at the posterior margin of the pereonites 3–7 and pleonite 5; moderately setose caudal region; body proportion: C&lt;1=2=3&lt;4&gt;5&lt;6&gt;7. Subcircular cephalon as wide as long; rostral process subequal to the lateral angles. Eyes small, black. Pleonites 1–5 about 1.1 times as long as pereonite 7; pleonites 1–3 with dorsal folds; pleonites 4–5 dorsally fused; pleonite 6 with a median incision at the distal margin. Telson linguiform, medially wider, narrowing distally, rounded apex with numerous marginal setae, proximal region with a pair of statocysts.
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNULE (
Fig. 2B
). Peduncle with three articles. Articles 1 and 2 with plumose sensory setae; article 2 quadrate, 0.7 times as long as third article, external margin with three long simple setae; flagellum with three articles, subequal to the length of the third peduncular article; tiny distal article with one aesthetasc and a group of simple setae.
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNA (
Fig. 2C
). Peduncle with five articles. Article 2 rudimentary, subequal in length to articles 2 and 3 together, internal lateral margin with scales; article 4 quadrate, with a group of simple setae at the distal angles; article 5 rectangular, 1.3 times as long as the fourth. Flagellum rudimentary with four articles, 0.6 times as long as last peduncular article.
</p>
      <p>
MAXILLIPED (
Fig. 2D
). Palp with three articles. Article 1 rectangular with one simple seta; article 2 with one long medial seta and three distal setae, internal margin with setulated scales, bilobed and projected distal angle; article 3 small, oblique with five distal setae. Endite reaching half of the first article of palp.
</p>
      <p>
MAXILLA (
Fig. 2E
). Straight with seven stout distal teeth.
</p>
      <p>
MANDIBLE (
Fig. 2F
). Symmetrical; palp with three articles, first article 0.6 times as long as article 2 with a long distal seta; second article 2.5 times as long as article 3 with three distal setae; article 3 with five pectinate setae. Incisor with three teeth; lacinia mobilis with four denticles.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPOD 1 (
Fig. 3A
). Subchelate; carpus triangular, apex truncated and crenulated; propodus ovate, 1.8 times as long as wide, palm with middle projection as a step with eight robust short setae; internal distal angle of dactylus projected.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPODS 2–3 (
Fig. 3B–C
). Similar in shape and size. Carpus triangular, truncated apically with a small tooth and two long robust setae; propodus elongated oval, 2.1–2.2 times as long as wide, internal margin with a row of simple setae and setulated scales, distoventrally one slightly serrated sensory spine; proximal internal margin of the dactylus with small teeth, distal margin with a robust spine and a group of simple and plumose setae.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPODS 4–7 (
Fig. 3D–G
). Very similar in shape and size. Merus with a row of long simple setae and setules on inner margin; carpus subpentagonal, ventrodistal margin with a sensory spine and simple setae, dorsodistal margin with a plumose sensory seta; propodus sub-cylindrical, 1.8 times as long as wide in P4–6, and 2.5 times in P7; ventral margin with simple seta and setulated scales, ventrodistal margin with a denticulate sensory spine. P7 ventrodistally with two pectinate sensory spines; dactylus with setulated scales.
</p>
      <p>
PLEOPOD 1 (
Fig. 4A
). Protopod with five retinaculae; exopod operculiform, 2.3 times as wide as the endopod, external margin with a medial seta, internal margin with a proximal seta; surrounded laterally and apically by 48 plumose setae; endopod cylindrical, shorter than exopod with six plumose setae on distal margin.
</p>
      <p>
PLEOPOD 2 (
Fig. 4B
). Oval and elongated, exopod surrounded distally by 14 plumose setae; endopod shorter than exopod, surrounded by eight plumose setae.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL PROTOPOD (
Fig. 4C
). Rectangular, 1.2 times as long as endopod, inner margin with seven plumose setae, outer margin with a row of plumose setae.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL ENDOPOD (
Fig. 4C
). Apex rounded, 1.7 times as long as wide, distally and laterodistally surrounded by long simple setae.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL EXOPOD (
Fig. 4D
). Oval, distally emarginated, 1.6 times as long as wide, surrounded by 67 setae, 21 smooth and 46 plumose.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution and habitat
</p>
      <p>
From Ixtapa, 
Guerrero
to Huatulco, 
Oaxaca
. In algae, coral, coral rock, tubes of sabellariids and molluscan shells; intertidal to subtidal (
6 m
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amakusanthura guerrerensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
shares the following characteristics with 41 previously recorded species of the genus: (1) maxillipedal palp with three free articles, the internal angle of the second article projected; (2) pleon longer than wide; (3) pleonites 1–3 with dorsal suture lines and 4–5 dorsally fused. The new species differs by presenting a unique combination of characteristics: antenna with scales in the internal margin of the second article; palm of the pereopod 1 with a medial projection as a step armed with eight short setae; exopod of pleopod 1 with one proximal and medial simple seta, and 48 distal plumose setae. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amakusanthura guerrerensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. californiensis
(Schultz, 1964)
</tp:taxon-name>
, the only species recorded in the eastern Pacific, with the following characteristic: (1) more than eight setae in the distolateral part of the telson. The new species, however, differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. californiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
in the presence of a pigmented line in the pereonites 3–7 and pleonite 5, distal article of the mandibular palp with five pectinate setae, palm of the pereopod 1 with a medial projection as a step armed with eight short setae and pleonite 6 is strongly emarginated. In comparison, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. californiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
has no pigment, the distal article of the mandibular palp has four setae, palm straight, and the pleonite 6 is slightly emarginated.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
