<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Mesanthura antenniformis Jarquín-Martínez &amp; García-Madrigal 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5123268</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8C5D87D5BA42FFBBFD9D9724FC714A64</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Anthuridae (Peracarida: Isopoda) from the southern Mexican Pacific</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/666ad5f1-6ac4-4940-b05c-4b57c3063593</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Mesanthura antenniformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 8–10
, 
20C
, 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
antenniformis
</tp:taxon-name>
’ refers to the peculiar shape of the second antenna article of this species.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MEXICO
• 
♀
(ovigerous, body length 
8 mm
); 
Oaxaca
, 
Puerto Ángel
, 
Estacahuite Beach
; 
15°40′ N
, 
96°29′ W
; depth 

7 m

; 

17 Apr. 2008

; 
S. Salazar-Vallejo
et al
. leg.; dead coral; 
UMAR-PERA 542
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
MEXICO
• 
1 ♂
(body length 
4.1 mm
); same collection data as for holotype; 
UMAR-PERA 543
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
6 ♀♀
(ovigerous), 
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
UMAR-PERA 544
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MEXICO
– 

Oaxaca

• 
1 ♀
(ovigerous); 
Cozoaltepec
, 
Agua Blanca Beach
; 
15°44′2″ N
, 
96°48′32″ W
; depth shallow water; 

2 Apr. 2009

; 
J. León-Robles
leg.; fouling algae; 
UMAR-PERA 539
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
(ovigerous), 
1 ♀
; 
Puerto Ángel Dock
; 
15°39′56″ N
, 
96°29′27″ W
; depth 

3 m

; 

12 Jul. 2019

; Y. Chávez- 
López
and 
A. Pérez-Chávez
leg.; 
tubes of sabellariids
; 
UMAR-PERA 540
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
(ovigerous); 
Puerto Ángel
, 
Estacahuite Beach
; 
15°40′ N
, 
96°29′ W
; depth 

2–4 m

; 

10 Sep. 2005

; 
J.R. Bastida-Zavala
et al
. leg.; 
tubes of sabellariids
; 
UMAR-PERA 541
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
, 
2 ♂♂
, 
5 mancae
; 
Puerto Ángel
, 
Estacahuite Beach
; 
15°40′ N
, 
96°29′ W
; depth 

7 m

; 

17 Apr. 2008

; 
S. Salazar-Vallejo
et al
. leg.; rock; 
UMAR-PERA 545
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 ♀♀
, 
3 ♂♂
, 
5 mancae
; 
Puerto Ángel
, 
Estacahuite Beach
; 
15°40′ N
, 
96°29′ W
; depth 

2–4 m

; 

10 Sep. 2005

; 
J.R. Bastida-Zavala
et al
. leg.; 
coral rock
; 
UMAR-PERA 546
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Holotype

(
♀
(ovigerous), UMAR-PERA 542)
</p>
      <p>
BODY (
Figs 8A
, 
20C
). Length 
8 mm
, 7.7 times as long as wide, pigmented; cephalon almost half the length of the first pereonite; rostrum prominent and acute, sub-equal to the distal angles of the cephalon; small eyes located on the anterolateral edges of the head, not distinguishable ommatidia; body proportion: C&lt;1&gt;2&lt;3&lt;4=5&gt;6&gt;7. Pereonite 7 slightly wider than length; pleonites 1–5 fused, sub-equal to pereonite 7; telson linguiform, slightly shorter than uropodal endopod, rounded distal region, apex slightly emarginated with six pairs of setae; proximal part with one pair of statocysts.
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNULE (
Fig. 8B
). Peduncle with three articles. Article 1 rectangular, 1.3 times as long as the second and third together with plumose sensory setae; article 2 half of the 3; flagellum with three articles, sub equal to the last peduncular article, distal article with 5–6 aesthetascs and simple setae.
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNA (
Fig. 8C
). Peduncle with five articles. Second article 1.4 times as long as the subsequent peduncular articles; internal angle projected with two simple setae, distal margin with small sinuosities; article 3 partially covered by second article; last article 1.1 times as long as article 4 with simple and sensory plumose setae in the distal region; flagellum with five articles, sub-equal to the length of the last peduncle article, square article with numerous thin setae.
</p>
      <p>
MAXILLIPED (
Fig. 8D
). Palp with three articles. Article 1 rectangular, half the length of the second with a single ventrodistal seta; distal article small, oblique with six setae, proximal and distal plumose setae, a medial pectinate seta and a simple one.
</p>
      <p>
MAXILLA (
Fig. 8F
). Slender, bent apically with seven teeth.
</p>
      <p>
MANDIBLE (
Fig. 8E
). Symmetrical; palp with three articles, article 2 cylindrical, 2.2 times as long as the first with a subdistal seta; distal article with 5–6 robust marginal setae; incisor with three teeth; lacinia mobilis with five denticles and small molars.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPOD 1 (
Fig. 8G
). Subchelate; carpus triangular, apical margin rounded with four simple setae; palm slightly convex with four marginal setae, distal margin crenulated; dactylus with a spine in the distoventral angle and a group of setae.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPODS 2–3 (
Fig. 9A–B
). Similar in shape and size. Carpus triangular with three apical setae; propodus elongated, cylindrical, 2.1–2.2 times longer than wide, ventral margin slightly curved with two long setae, distoventral angle with a denticulate sensory spine; dactylus curved with one spine and a group of distal setae.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPODS 4–7 (
Fig. 9C–F
). Similar in shape and size. Carpus trapezoidal with a sensory spine at the ventrodistal margin and three simple setae, external margin with a plumose sensory seta; propodus cylindrical with a denticulate sensory spine at the distal inner angle; dactylus curved. Pereopod 7 propodus with setulated scales and two robust pectinate spines on internal angle. Propodus of all pereopods with plumose sensory setae.
</p>
      <p>
PLEOPOD 1 (
Fig. 10A
). Protopod with five retinaculae; exopod operculiform, almost two times as long as wide, sinuous distal margin, surrounded by 31 plumose setae; endopod sub-equal to the length of the exopod and 0.3 times its width, surrounded apically by 10 plumose setae.
</p>
      <p>
PLEOPOD 2 (
Fig. 10B
). Oval and elongated; exopod shorter than endopod, surrounded apically by 10 plumose setae; endopod with seven plumose setae.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL PROTOPOD (
Fig. 10C
). Uropodal protopod 2.3 times as long as endopod with plumose setae on the external margin.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL ENDOPOD (
Fig. 10C
). Oval, distally narrower, 1.6 times as long as wide, margin with simple and plumose setae.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mesanthura antenniformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (ovigerous), 8 mm, Oaxaca, Puerto Ángel, Estacahuite Beach (UMAR-PERA 542). 
A
. Habitus and detail of the telson. 
B
. Antennule. 
C
. Antenna (right). 
D
. Maxilliped. 
E
. Mandible. 
F
. Maxilla. 
G
. Pereopod 1.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mesanthura antenniformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (ovigerous), 8 mm, Oaxaca, Puerto Ángel, Estacahuite Beach (UMAR-PERA 542). 
A
. Pereopod 2 and detail of dactylus. 
B
. Pereopod 3. 
C
. Pereopod 4. 
D
. Pereopod 5. 
E
. Pereopod 6. 
F
. Pereopod 7 and detail of the sensory spines.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Mesanthura antenniformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–C
. Holotype, ♀ (ovigerous), 8 mm, Oaxaca, Puerto Ángel, Estacahuite Beach (UMAR-PERA 542). 
A
. Pleopod 1. 
B
. Pleopod 2. 
C
. Uropod. 
D–F
. Paratype, ♂, 4.1 mm (UMAR-PERA 543). 
D
. Antennule. 
E
. Pereopod 1 and detail of the palm (e). 
F
. Pleopod 2.
</p>
      <p>
UROPODAL EXOPOD (
Fig. 10C
). Sub-equal in length to the protopod, oval, distally emarginated, external margin strongly crenulated with plumose and simple setae.
</p>
      <p>
Male
(dimorphic characters; based on the 
paratype
♂
, UMAR-PERA 543)
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNULE (
Fig. 10D
). Robust; articles 1 and 2 with plumose sensory setae, article 1 rectangular, 2.4 times as long as second; article 2 and 3 sub-equal in length; flagellum with six articles, articles 2–5 with numerous aesthetascs; distal article with a group of long setae.
</p>
      <p>
PEREOPOD 1 (
Fig. 10E
). Subchelate; carpus distal part truncated with crenulated margin; palm with a step-like proximal process with robust setae, distal margin crenulated, mesial region with numerous setae.
</p>
      <p>
PLEOPOD 2 (
Fig. 10F
). Exopod shorter than endopod, surrounded apically by seven plumose setae; endopod surrounded apically by four plumose setae; male appendix cylindrical with scales in distal region.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution and habitat
</p>
      <p>
Central coast of 
Oaxaca
, from Agua Blanca to Estacahuite Beach. In coral, tubes of sabellariids, rocks and algae; intertidal to subtidal (
7 m
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Mesanthura antenniformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
differs from previously recorded species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mesanthura
</tp:taxon-name>
in the following unique characteristics: second article of antenna strongly projected and winding on the distal margin; palm of pereopod 1 straight. Between the three eastern Pacific species (
Table 1
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. antenniformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is more similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
M
. 
occidentalis
</tp:taxon-name>
, described from Point Conception, California, by the following characteristics: (1) last article of mandibular palp with five setae, (2) dorsal surface of the telson with some setae; however, differs because in that 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. antenniformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
has a dense pigmentation pattern, the palm of pereopod 1 is straight with the distal margin crenulate, propodus of pereopod 2 with setulated scales, apical part of the telson slightly emarginated and with six pair of setae, while, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. occidentalis
</tp:taxon-name>
has a slightly pigmented body in a circular pattern, palm of pereopod 1 medially projected, propodus of pereopod 2 with cuticular scales and the telson has eight pairs of setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
