<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Cerhomalus petrovitzi Frolov &amp;
                        Akhmetova 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4604244</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8D23E94B6B19FFF4FDBEFAAAC6908FED</uri>
                  <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the Afrotropical scarab beetle genus
                        Cerhomalus Quedenfeldt, 1884 (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae:
                        Orphninae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1265</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Cerhomalus petrovitzi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: A04DF237-5C78-4B76-BEDB-7453CCEAB827 </p>
            <p> Figs 3 , 5C , 6 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Differential diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cerhomalus petrovitzi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is most similar to
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. mechowi </tp:taxon-name> in having the ventral fossae on
                  the apices of the parameres completely bordered ( Figs 1F , 3G ) and the apices
                  right angled in lateral view ( Figs 1C , 3D ) but can be separated from it in
                  having the widened part of a paramere (in lateral view) about two thirds the
                  length of the paramere ( Fig. 3D ) and ventral fossa of a paramere longer and
                  narrower ( Fig. 3G ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>The new species is named after Rudolf Petrovitz (1906–1974), a German
                  coleopterist.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO • ♂ ; “MUSEE DU
                        CONGO BELGE KISANTU P. Goossens ”; MNHN . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO • 2 ♂♂ , 1 ♀ ;
                        same collection data as for holotype; RMCA </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; “MUSEE DU CONGO Belge [ Kasaï-Occidental ] (
                        Don M. Corpentier )”; MHNG </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> NIGERIA • 1 ♂ ; “ Nigeria W. Afr. / ( Staudinger coll.)
                        1914-412.”; BMNH . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male, holotype ( Fig. 3 A–B, D–G) </p>
            <p> Body length 20.1 mm . Colour uniformly brown to black. </p>
            <p> Anterior margin of frontoclypeus somewhat rectangular, slightly convex in middle,
                  bordered and slightly serrate in dorsal view ( Fig. 3A ). Frontoclypeus with a
                  keel-shaped transverse process near anterior margin; height of keel about half its
                  width. Surface of frontoclypeus almost smooth, with minute punctures. Eye
                  tubercles feebly developed. Eyes rather large: width about 1/6 distance between
                  eyes in dorsal view. Antennae 10-segmented. </p>
            <p>Pronotum widely rounded laterally, as wide as elytra. Anterior border wide. Basal
                  border narrow, keelshaped, separated from pronotal disc by deep groove with row of
                  longitudinally elongated punctures. Pronotal disc with a rounded depression
                  occupying more than half of the surface, somewhat rugose anteriorly. Most of
                  pronotum surface covered with minute punctures separated by more than 3 puncture
                  diameters. Anterolateral angles with much larger and denser punctures;
                  posteriolateral angles with same punctures but in smaller numbers.</p>
            <p> Scutellum subtriangular, narrowly rounded apically, about 1/10 length of elytra. </p>
            <p>Elytra 1.1 times longer than wide, with distinct humeral humps. Elytra widest in
                  middle, lateral margins almost parallel in basal half. First (sutural) stria
                  distinct, as groove with row of punctures. Other stria before humeral humps as
                  rows of round setiferous punctures. Striae laterad of stria 5 feebly distinct.
                  Elytral intervals covered with minute punctures, somewhat sparser than those on
                  pronotum.</p>
            <p>Macropterous.</p>
            <p>Abdominal sternite 8 medially longer than sternites 6 and 7 combined; sternite 6
                  about as long as sternite 7. Pygidium invisible from above, with slightly truncate
                  apex. Plectrum triangular with rounded apex, wider than long.</p>
            <p> Aedeagus. Ventral fossae on the apices of the parameres completely bordered, long
                  and narrow ( Fig. 3G ); apices of parameres right angled in lateral view, its
                  widened part (in lateral view) about two thirds the length of paramere ( Fig. 3D
                  ). </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> Female ( Fig. 3C ) differs from male in having a relatively smaller, convex pronotum
                  without tubercles and only with a small depression medially, frontoclypeus with
                  much smaller, low keel not bimodal apically, protibial spur, and pygidium with
                  rounded apex. Body length 21.0 mm. </p>
            <p> Variation </p>
            <p> Body length of examined male paratypes varies from 17.0 to 22.5 mm . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> The species is known from western Democratic Republic of the Congo ( Fig. 6 ). The
                  record from Nigeria is doubtful and need confirmation, therefore the specimen is
                  not included in the type series. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
