<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus acaraje Pinto-da-Rocha,
                        Machado &amp; Weygoldt 2002</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5570710</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FFCFFF84A6B3FD95FA9ADBE9</uri>
                  <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family
                        Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Charinus acaraje </tp:taxon-name> Pinto-da-Rocha, Machado &amp;
            Weygoldt, 2002 </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 7A–B , 8A–B , 43 ; Table 4 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Charinus acaraje </tp:taxon-name> Pinto-da-Rocha et al. , 2002:
                  110–113 , figs 8–12. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Charinus acaraje </tp:taxon-name> – Baptista &amp; Giupponi 2003:
                  80 . — Miranda &amp; Giupponi 2011: 66 , fig. 13. — Vasconcelos et al. 2013:
                  496–497 , fig. 12; 2014: 155, 162. — Vasconcelos &amp; Ferreira 2016: 185 . —
                  Miranda et al. 2016c: 18–29 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> This species may be separated from other <tp:taxon-name> Charinus </tp:taxon-name>
                  in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: two
                  setae, prolateral and retrolateral, on dorsal surface of chelicerae; cheliceral
                  claw with eight teeth and with complete row of setae on retrolateral surface;
                  pedipalp femur with three dorsal spines and three ventral spines; leg IV
                  distitibia sc and sf series each with six trichobothria. </p>
            <p> This species resembles C. una sp. nov., but differs in the larger size, six
                  trichobothria in the sc and sf series, and eight teeth on the cheliceral claw.
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> Noun in apposition referring to ‘ <tp:taxon-name> acarajé </tp:taxon-name> ’, a
                  famous dish in Bahia , the state in which the type locality is located (
                  Pinto-da-Rocha et al. 2002 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype BRAZIL • ♂ ; Bahia , Santa Luzia , Gruta da Pedra
                        do Sino ; 15°26′15.22″ S , 39°18′45.04″ W ; 14 Oct. 1997 ; B.S. Santos leg.;
                        MZSP 1829 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Additional material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> BRAZIL • 4 ♀♀ , 3 ♂♂ , 2 nymphae ; Bahia , Santa Luzia ,
                        Gruta do Lapão ; 15°25′44″ S , 39°20′02″ W ; 3 Nov. 2002 ; A.P.L. Giupponi
                        and R.C. Baptista leg.; new record; MNRJ 9297 </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; Bahia , Camacã , Reserva Particular do
                        Patrimônio Natural da Serra Bonita ; 15°23′02.63″ S , 39°33′46.68″ W ; 11–15
                        Jun. 2009 ; V. Dill , A. Chagas Jr , D. Pedroso , A.P.L. Giupponi , A. Kury
                        leg.; new record; MNRJ 9125 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Supplementary description </p>
            <p>Only the male was previously known. A description of the female and supplementary
                  description of the male are presented below.</p>
            <p>CARAPACE. Curved carina between ocular triads and carapace margin, closer to margin,
                  with small transverse projection medially; anterior margin rounded, with six
                  anterior setae; frontal process large, subtriangular, not visible in dorsal view.
                  Median eyes and median ocular tubercle present; median ocular tubercle shallow,
                  slightly higher than carapace surface, with pair of small setae. Lateral eyes well
                  developed, pale, small seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad; lenses
                  directed anteriorly and dorsally.</p>
            <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum rounded posteriorly and projected anteriorly into large, blunt
                  tubercle, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae, with typical setation; medial
                  platelet (tetrasternum) with single convex platelet, with pair of large setae
                  anteriorly, and several small setae posteriorly; third platelet (pentasternum)
                  with single convex platelet, smaller than medial platelet, with two setae
                  anteriorly and some setae posteriorly; metasternum with one or two anterior setae
                  in membranous region and two or three setae posteriorly.</p>
            <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
            <p> GENITALIA. Female gonopod with posterior margin of genital operculum slightly
                  convex, several setae on surface and along margin ( Fig. 7A–B ); small sclerotized
                  region at base of gonopods, not connected to each other; gonopods sucker-like with
                  large disc and small openings ( Fig. 7A–B ). Male gonopod with spine-like
                  projections over apex of fistula, LoD, and LoL2 ( Fig. 8A–B ). </p>
            <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth in retrolateral row of basal segment. Prolateral
                  surface with transverse row of six small setae, from ventral to dorsal. Three
                  setae, retrolateral, retromedial, and prolateral along dorsodistal margin, near
                  membranous region of claw. Claw with eight teeth and row of setae on retrolateral
                  surface from base to near apex (dorsal side).</p>
            <p>PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with one or two small setae encircled by round carina
                  and three setae on anterior margin. Femur with three dorsal spines in primary
                  series; two distinct setiferous tubercles proximal to first dorsal spine; three
                  ventral spines; large spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella
                  with three dorsal spines; setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, about one fourth
                  length of spine I; three ventral spines decreasing in size; setiferous tubercle
                  between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with two dorsal spines; ventral spine in
                  distal half of tibia; prominent setiferous tubercle near base of ventral spine;
                  three long setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines,
                  distal spine half length of tarsus and proximal spine one-third length of distal
                  spine. Ventral row of brush with 32–34 setae.</p>
            <p> LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles. Leg IV basitibia
                  with four pseudoarticles; trichobothrium bt situated in proximal third; distal
                  apex of basitibial pseudo-articles with dark, denticulate projection; distitibia
                  trichobothrium bc situated closer to sbf than to bf ; sf and sc series each with
                  six trichobothria; distitarsus with distinct white annulus distally on first
                  article. </p>
            <p> Measurements </p>
            <p> See Table 4 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Known from inside and outside caves in southern Bahia , Brazil . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Natural history </p>
            <p>Species with secondary sexual dimorphism, i.e., males exhibit longer pedipalps and
                  larger body size.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
