<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sarax lembeh Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536894</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F69A8B3E54A2E00BAD14D7DFC83B7224</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E44E0F80-EEA2-4319-AE0A-F87B32FD869C
</p>
      <p>
Figs 103
, 
117
; 
Table 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
in Southeast Asia and Oceania by the following combination of characters: lateral eyes very near carapace margin; one dorsal spine on pedipalp tarsus (
Fig. 117D
); leg IV basitibia with trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
The other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
with one dorsal spine on the pedipalp tibia are 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. cochinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. javensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. monodenticulatus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. palau
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, from which 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be distinguished by its smaller body size; higher number of trichobothria in the 
sc
and 
sf
series of the leg IV distitibia (six in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
compared with five in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. cochinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. palau
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
); different number of pseudo-articles on leg IV basitibia (three in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
compared with four or two in the other species); and the arrangement of spines on the pedipalp femur and patella.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition taken from the 
type
locality, Lembeh Island.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
INDONESIA
• 
♀
; 
Lembeh Island
; [
01°25′00.1″ N
, 
125°13′00.02″ E
]; 

29 Jun. 1929

; Crane, 
Field Museum Pacific Expedition 1928–1929
leg.; 
FMNH 3489485
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 117A
); frontal process triangular (
Fig. 117C
). Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed (
Fig. 117A, C
); pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, pale, small seta lateral to each lateral ocular triad.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 117B
); other sternal platelets narrow and projected, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; without anterior setae in membranous region and four setae posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sacs cover present.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum broadly sclerotized between gonopods and posteromedian margin; posterior margin slightly convex, with several setae along margin and on surface. Female gonopod plunger-like, narrower close to apex, tubiform, unsclerotized basally. Male unknown.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Retrolateral surface of basal segment without projection opposite to bifid tooth; row of setae on retrolateral surface, basally to dorsally; prolateral surface of basal segment with two parallel, transverse rows of 15 small setae, ventrally to dorsally; claw with four teeth.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxae dorsally with round carina; without small setae encircled by carina and with two or three setae on anterior margin. Femur with two distinct setiferous tubercles proximal to dorsal spine 1 (
Fig. 117E
); primary series with three dorsal spines; three ventral spines (
Fig. 117F
); setiferous tubercle proximal to ventral spine 1, between spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with four or five dorsal spines (
Fig. 117E
); setiferous tubercle distal to dorsal spine I, about one-third length of spine I; three ventral spines decreasing in length (
Fig. 117F
); setiferous tubercle between ventral spine I and distal margin. Tibia with two dorsal spines, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine; ventral spine in distal half of tibia; prominent setiferous tubercle near its base; long setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with one dorsal spine, one-fifth length of tarsus (
Fig. 117D
); ventral row of setae on cleaning organ with 26–27 setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles. Leg IV basitibia with three pseudoarticles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third; distal apex of basitibial pseudo-articles without dark, denticulate projection; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sf
and 
sc
series each with six trichobothria. Tarsus with distinct white annulus distally on first article of distitarsus.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 8
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
