<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus palikur Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536707</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D74E37D7734DE2A170D9E9D0CC0437A1</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus palikur
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
9865F856-E11E-429E-AE38-F697DB6EA076
</p>
      <p>
Figs 7C–D
, 
27
, 
31
; 
Table 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in Amazonia and northern South America by means of the following combination of characters: carapace with broad, pale yellowish marks radiating from fovea; carapace extended anteriorly (
Fig. 31A
); retrolateral spines of pedipalp trochanter distinctly smaller than prolateral spine; female gonopod cushion-like with flap of cushion curved posteriorly to anteriorly (
Fig. 7C–D
); first tarsal article of leg I as long as sum of lengths of subsequent four articles; white annulus absent from second tarsal article of legs II–IV.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus palikur
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
may be differentiated from other species by the darker coloration, larger and more numerous pedipalp spines, the proximal tarsal article of leg I elongated, and the cushion-like gonopod of the female. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus palikur
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. platnicki
</tp:taxon-name>
, but can be differentiated from the latter by the well-developed median eyes and median ocular tubercle, and the lower count of leg I tarsal articles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition referring to the Palikur (or Païkwené), one of the few indigenous tribes remaining in 
French Guiana
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
FRENCH GUIANA
• 
♂
; 
Approuague-Kaw
, 
Kaw Mountains
, 
area around Amazon Nature Lodge
; 
04°33′35″ N
, 
52°12′25.3″ W
; 

21–25 Dec. 2004

; 
J.H. Huff
leg.; 
collected from leaf litter samples in primary tropical rainforest
; 
AMCC
[
LP 3832
].

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
FRENCH GUIANA
• 
2 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Roura
, 
Cacao
, 
along trail Sentier Molokoi
; 
04°33′41.1″ N
, 
52°27′44″ W
; 

95 m
a.s.l.

; 

19 Dec. 2004

; 
J.H. Huff
leg.; 
primary tropical rainforest, under rocks and wood
; 
AMCC
[
LP 3831
]

• 

1 ♂
, 
1 juv. ♀
; 
Matoury Trail
, 
Sentier de la Mirande
; 
04°51′50.8″ N
, 
52°20′40.1″ W
; 

47 m
a.s.l.

; 

18 Dec. 2004

; 
J.H. Huff
leg.; 
primary tropical rainforest, under rocks and wood
; 
AMCC
[
LP 3833
]

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae; carapace extended anteriorly (
Fig. 31A
); frontal process triangular (
Fig. 31C
). Small granules, densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci; dark coloration, with broad, pale yellowish marks radiating from fovea; median eyes present; median ocular tubercle shallow (
Fig. 31C
); lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separared from carapace margin.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 31B
); other sternal platelets narrow and concave, with pair of setae anteriorly; pentasternum with four setae anteriorly and without seta near membranous region.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin (
Fig. 7C–D
); lateromedian region of genital operculum with pair of deep transverse sulci; gonopod cushion-like with base slightly sclerotized (
Fig. 7C–D
); flap of gonopod curved posteriorly to anteriorly (
Fig. 7C–D
). Male gonopod with apex of fistula and base of lateral lobes sclerotized.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw without row of setae; claw with six teeth; row of four setae on prolateral surface of cheliceral basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with one prominent seta dorsally encircled by round carina and with two setae on margin. Femur with three dorsal spines and three or more (up to five in large males) ventral spines (
Fig. 31E–F
); two prominent setiferous tubercles between first dorsal spine and proximal margin; spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with four dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 31E
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; three or four (in large males) ventral spines; prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and seta between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine (
Fig. 31D
); cleaning organ with 28–35 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 21 articles; tarsus I with 25–28 articles; length of first tarsal article equal to sum of lengths of subsequent three or four articles. Leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles, without sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated medially on pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 2
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from 
French Guiana
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Found under rocks and wood in tropical forest.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
