<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus apiaca Miranda &amp;
                        Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536750</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FFC6FFB3A593FC2CFAECDA9C</uri>
                  <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family
                        Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Charinus apiaca </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 259DB50B-0398-4321-81FD-60128AB7971D </p>
            <p> Figs 5A–B , 43 , 47 ; Table 4 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> This species may be separated from other <tp:taxon-name> Charinus </tp:taxon-name>
                  in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters:
                  eight setae on anterior carapace margin ( Fig. 47A ); cheliceral claw with 11–14
                  teeth; female gonopods sucker-like, sclerotized basally, and curved posteriorly (
                  Fig. 5A–B ). </p>
            <p> This species resembles other <tp:taxon-name> Charinus </tp:taxon-name> from the
                  north of the state of Rio de Janeiro , but can be differentiated by its large size
                  and the presence of an extra series of ventral spines on the pedipalp femur ( Fig.
                  47F ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> Noun in apposition referring to Apiacá, a city near the type locality. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype BRAZIL • ♀ ; Espírito Santo , Apiacá , Fazenda
                        Santa Maria ; 21°09′13.68″ S , 41°33′59.04″ W ; 12 Aug. 2003 ; R.L.C.
                        Baptista leg.; lower corridor ; MNRJ 9286 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratype BRAZIL • 1 juv. ; same locality as for holotype;
                        Jan. 1989 ; R.L.C. Baptista leg.; under rotten bark ; MNRJ 9074
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> CARAPACE. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci.
                  Median eyes well developed ( Fig. 47A, C ); median ocular tubercle weakly
                  developed; pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed,
                  pale, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated
                  from carapace margin; eight anterior setae; frontal process triangular. </p>
            <p> STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing
                  base of pedipalp coxae ( Fig. 47B ); other sternal platelets narrow and concave,
                  with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly;
                  pentasternum with ten setae anteriorly and four setae near membranous region. </p>
            <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
            <p> GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with short setae posteromedially ( Fig. 5A–B );
                  gonopod suckerlike, markedly sclerotized basally ( Fig. 5A–B ); constriction
                  present near apex, apex not broad, slightly wider than stem ( Fig. 5A–B );
                  sucker-like appendages separated from each other ( Fig. 5A–B ). Male unknown. </p>
            <p>CHELICERAE. Teeth absent on retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid
                  tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with discontinous row of setae, long patch
                  basally and another medially; claw with 11– 14 teeth; two rows of several setae on
                  prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp
                  larger than ventral cusp.</p>
            <p> PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with four (dextral) or six (sinistral) prominent
                  setae encircled by round carina and four (dextral) or three (sinistral) setae on
                  margin. Femur with six or seven dorsal spines and six ventral spines ( Fig. 47E–F
                  ); femur with one spine between dorsal spines 2 or 3; three prominent setiferous
                  tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin ( Fig. 47E ); spine between
                  ventral spine 1 and proximal margin ( Fig. 47F ); spine ventral to this extra
                  spine; spine between spines 1 and 2 and spines 2 and 3 ( Fig. 47F ). Patella with
                  six dorsal spines in primary series ( Fig. 47E ); prominent setiferous tubercle
                  distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; five ventral spines ( Fig. 47F );
                  small setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral
                  spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two
                  (dextral) or three (sinistral) dorsal spines, two larger spines subequal, third
                  spine situated near base of proximal spine ( Fig. 47D ); cleaning organ with 28–30
                  setae in ventral row. </p>
            <p> LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal
                  article shorter than subsequent article. Leg IV basitibia with four
                  pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles;
                  trichobothrium bt situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia
                  trichobothrium bc situated closer to sbf than to bf , sc and sf series each with
                  six trichobothria. </p>
            <p> Measurements </p>
            <p> See Table 4 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Known only from the type locality. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Natural history </p>
            <p> The holotype was collected inside a cave whereas the paratype was found under rotten
                  tree bark. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
