<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sarax abbatei Miranda &amp; Giupponi
                        &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, comb. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536904</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FF4BFF07A51DF93EFAA4DF8D</uri>
                  <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family
                        Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Sarax abbatei ( Delle Cave, 1986 ) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 135–136 ; Table 9 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Charinus abbatei Delle Cave, 1986: 148–150 </tp:taxon-name> , figs
                  I (1–7), II. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Charinus </tp:taxon-name> n. sp. – Messana et al. 1985: 334 . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Charinus abbatei </tp:taxon-name> – Vanni et al. 1988: 376 . —
                  Weygoldt 1994: 244 ; 2000b: 346 ; 2005: 8–10 , figs 16–18. — Harvey 2003: 4 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Based on Weygoldt (2005) , this species may be separated from other species of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Sarax </tp:taxon-name> in Africa, the Middle East and South
                  Asia by the following combination of characters: small size; female genital
                  operculum rounded posteriorly, pointed medially, with group of setae posteriorly,
                  gonopods small, cone shaped, plunger-like; bifid tooth on basal segment of
                  chelicera with ventral cusp larger than dorsal cusp; leg IV basitibia with three
                  articles. It shares this character with <tp:taxon-name> S. bengalensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. , <tp:taxon-name> S. bispinosus </tp:taxon-name> comb.
                  nov. and <tp:taxon-name> S. pakistanus </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. from which it
                  may be distinguished by the thick, plunger-like gonopods of the female genitalia
                  and by leg IV basitibia trichobothrium bc situated near sbf . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>Patronym honoring Ernesto Abbate (Delle-Cave 1986).</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype SOMALIA • ♀ ; Campione 12 , Tratto 20 , Grotta do
                        Showli Berdi ; [ 02°18′51.78″ N , 42°16′56.53″ E ]; Bardera ; 15 Mar. 1984 ;
                        Spedizione Biologica in Somalia del Centro di Studio per la Faunistica ed
                        Ecologia Tropicali del C.N.R. (Florence) leg.; MZUF 1896–167 .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Supplementary description </p>
            <p> CARAPACE. Six anterior setae ( Fig. 136A ); frontal process triangular ( Fig. 136C
                  ). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median
                  eyes reduced; median ocular tubercle very shallow with pair of setae; lateral eyes
                  reduced, situated near carapace margins, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad. </p>
            <p> STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly, short, reaching base of pedipalp coxae (
                  Fig. 136B ); with typical setation; other sternal platelets narrow and projected,
                  pair of setae situated anteriorly on plaque; pentasternum with two setae
                  posteriorly. </p>
            <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sac cover absent.</p>
            <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with short setae posteromedially; projected
                  posteromedially; gonopod plunger-like; markedly sclerotized border posterior to
                  gonopod projections. Male genitalia unknown.</p>
            <p>CHELICERAE. Retrolateral surface of basal segment without projection, opposite to
                  bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae basally to medially;
                  claw with four teeth; bifid tooth on basal segment with ventral cusp larger than
                  dorsal cusp.</p>
            <p> PEDIPALPS. Coxae without seta encircled by round carina and two setae at margin.
                  Femur with three or four dorsal spines and four ventral spines ( Fig. 136E–F );
                  three prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin;
                  ventral spine between spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal
                  spines in primary series ( Fig. 136E ); prominent tubercle distal to spine I; two
                  ventral spines ( Fig. 136F ); two small setiferous tubercles between spine I and
                  distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and
                  distal margin. Tarsus with two small dorsal spines, distal spine slightly larger
                  than proximal spine, near cleaning brush ( Fig. 136D ); cleaning brush with 29 or
                  30 setae. </p>
            <p> LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 22 articles; tarsus I with 36 articles (Delle-Cave 1986).
                  Leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles (Delle-Cave 1986); trichobothrium bt
                  situated medially on pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium bc situated closer
                  to sbf than to bf ; sc and sf series each with six trichobothria. </p>
            <p> Measurements </p>
            <p> See Table 9 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Known only from the type locality. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Natural history </p>
            <p> The holotype was collected in Showli Berd Cave, in the middle of the desert,
                  surrounded by xerophilic vegetation outside ( Messana et al. 1985 ). Another
                  arthropod described from the same cave showed no adaptation to subterranean life (
                  Taiti &amp; Ferrara 1985 ). However, <tp:taxon-name> S. abbatei </tp:taxon-name>
                  comb. nov. exhibits characters, such as reduced eyes, which suggest it may be
                  restricted to the cave. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> The holotype is a small, pale specimen, missing the first pair of legs. It was
                  originally described in the genus <tp:taxon-name> Charinus </tp:taxon-name> .
                  Delle-Cave (1986) noted that the combination of characters of <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        abbatei </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. is unusual and contemplated proposing a
                  new genus to accommodate it. Weygoldt (2005) redescribed the species. It is hereby
                  transferred to <tp:taxon-name> Sarax </tp:taxon-name> based on the phylogenetic
                  analyses of Miranda et al. (2021) . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
