<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus euclidesi Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536798</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/795D8BC1D4482FFAA373B5F0DB79BFB5</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus euclidesi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
CFBC1532-31B7-4BAF-B313-28D02A28179E
</p>
      <p>
Figs 6C–D
, 
9A–B
, 
43
, 
61–63
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: cheliceral claw with nine teeth; males with sexually dimorphic pedipalps (
Fig. 61A–D
); pedipalp coxae with three long setae on margin, and distinct seta encircled by round carina; pedipalp femur with five dorsal spines and five ventral spines (
Fig. 61A–B
); pedipalp tibia with distinct setiferous tubercle proximally and ventral spine distally; pedipalp tarsus with three dorsal spines (
Fig. 61C–D
); leg IV distitibia 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. diamantinus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but bears more spines on the pedipalp femur and patella.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Patronym honoring Euclides da 
Cunha
, one of the foremost Brazilian writers, born in the region in which this species was collected.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
Cantagalo
, 
Gruta da Pedra Santa
, 
Fazenda da Mineiração Mauá
(Euclidelândia); 
21°56′16″ S
, 
42°15′16″ W
; 

13 Nov. 2005

; 
M.S. Silva
and 
R.L. Ferreira
leg.; 
MNRJ 9099
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
2 ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9099

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Frontal process large, triangular, acute, not visible in dorsal view (
Fig. 61F
); median eyes large (
Fig. 61F
); median ocular tubercle shallow, with pair of setae, posterior to eyes; lateral eyes poorly pigmented, but with tapetum (
Fig. 61A
); small seta posterior to lateral ocular triad.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly into long tubercle (
Fig. 61E
); median and third platelet rounded, convex, with two setae medially and few small setae posteriorly; metasternum with several small setae anteriorly and three long setae posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female gonopod sucker-like, with apex of gonopods converging (
Fig. 6C–D
); posterior margin of genital operculum straight, with few setae along margin and on surface (
Fig. 6C–D
). Male gonopod with LoL2 long and fimbriate (
Fig. 9A–B
); LoD projecting posteriorly and acuminate apically (
Fig. 9A–B
).
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small retrolateral tooth on basal segment. Prolateral surface of basal segment with vertical row of seven setae. Claw with nine small teeth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae from base to mid-apex.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with one or two small setae and four or five setae on anterior margin of round carina. Femur with three distinct setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 1 (
Fig. 62A–B
); primary series with five dorsal spines and small spine between spines 3 and 4 (
Fig. 62A–B
); five ventral spines and small spine between spines 1 and 2, two small spines between spines 2 and 3, and small spine between spines 3 and 4 and 4 and 5 (
Fig. 62C–D
); large ventral spine proximal to spine 1 (
Fig. 62C–D
). Patella with five dorsal spines and small spine between spines 4 and 5 (
Fig. 62A–B
); large setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, about one-third length of spine I; five ventral spines (
Fig. 62C–D
). Tibia with two dorsal spines, basal spine two-thirds length of distal spine; ventral spine situated in distal half of tibia, with row of two setiferous tubercles near base of spine; three long setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with three dorsal spines, two distal spines subequal and one-fifth length of tarsus; proximal spine smaller, ca one-third length of other two spines, situated near large proximal spine, and with long seta at base (
Fig. 61C–D
); ventral row of cleaning brush with 27 setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; tarsal organ situated close to base of tarsal claw (
Fig. 63C, E
); rod sensilla formed by six setae in shallow groove (
Fig. 63A–B
); slit sensilla situated opposite to tarsal claw (
Fig. 63D
). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third; distal apex of basitibial pseudo-articles with dark, denticulate projection; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria; distitarsus with distinct white annulus distally on first article.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>The known specimens were collected exclusively inside caves.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
