<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sarax indochinensis Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536892</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/85F8A5B0BF2C25FBF84242C39A8157DF</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax indochinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
20DCB29C-E29F-4F43-8BB7-40B02BCF4FF6
</p>
      <p>
Figs 103
, 
112–114
; 
Table 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax brachydactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Fage 1946b: 79

(in part).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
aff. 
brachydactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 


Seiter 
et al.
2015: 545


.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
in Southeast Asia and Oceania by the following combination of characters: median and lateral eyes well developed (
Fig. 112A
); ventral sacs and ventral sac cover well developed; female gonopod finger-like with small invagination apically (
Fig. 113A
); cheliceral basal segment with small tooth adjacent to bifid tooth; secondary sexual dimorphism in males with longer pedipalp segments than females; pedipalp tarsus with two short dorsal spines; leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, distitibia 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brachydactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
, but the genital operculum is concave, with two symmetric bulges unlike that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brachydactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
, which is flat.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name is an adjective derived from Indochina, the region of Southeast Asia which included 
Cambodia
, 
Laos
, and 
Vietnam
, under French control between ca 1890–1950.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
THAILAND
• 
♀
; 
Koh Kut
[Ko Kut]; [
11°40′05.07″ N
, 
102°33′51.21″ E
]; 
B. Degerbøl
leg.; 

6 Apr. 1959

; 
ZMUC 21613
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
THAILAND
• 
3 ♀♀
, 
7 ♂♂
, 
1 juv.
; same locality as for holotype; 
B. Degerbøl
le 
g
.; 

5 Apr. 1959

; 
ZMUC 21612

.
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
1 ♀
; 
Annam
, 
Ha Tien
, 
Kien Giang Province
; 
Hang Trong Nguc
(
Da Dung mountain
); 
10°25′44.8″ N
, 
104°28′36.6″ E
; 

7 Jan. 2010

; 
H. Steiner
leg. (Northern Lao-European Cave Project 2010); 
SMF 029/10

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
CAMBODIA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Sré Umbel
[
Srae Ambel
]; [
11°07′01.82″ N
, 
103°44′43.14″ E
]; 

Feb. 1939

; 
Mission C. Dawydoff
, 
Indochine
, 1938–1939; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♂
; 
Kampong Speu
; 

Apr. 1939

; 
Mission C. Dawydoff
, 
Indochine
, 1938–1939; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
, 
2 juv.
; 
Ream
; [
10°35′02.75″ N
, 
103°38′35.34″ E
]; 

Mar. 1939

; 
Mission C. Dawydoff
, 1938–1939, Indochine; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♂
; [
11°34′37.44″ N
, 
103°07′41.04″ E
]; 

10 m
a.s.l.

; 

3 Dec. 2014

; 
J. Nigl
leg.; 
NHMW 27601

• 

1 juv.
; 
Koh Chang
; [
12°04′28.60″ N
, 
102°18′35.95″ E
]; 
under bark
; 

13 Jan. 1900

; 
Th. Mortensen
leg.; 
ZMUC 21614

.
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
1 ♂
; 
Phaurang
, 
Tour Cham
; 

May 1939

; 
Mission C. Dawydoff
, 
Indochine
1938–1939; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♂
; 
Banghoi
[Ba Ngôi], 
Indochine
; 

May 1939

; 
Mission C. Dawydoff
; 1938–1939; 
MNHN

• 

2 juv.
; 
Golf Du Siam
[
Gulf of Thailand
]; 

Nov. 1938

; 
P. Dama
, 
Mission C. Dawydoff
, Indochine, 1938– 1939; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Hang Bong Lai
; 
10°25′42″ N
, 
104°28′39″ E
; 
H. Steiner
leg.; 
SMNS 86

• 

1 ♀
; 
Hang
8; 
10°25′45″ N
, 
104°28′37.8″ E
; 
H. Steiner
leg.; 
SMNS 87

.
</p>
      <p>
NO DATA • 

4 juv.
; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
, 7 protonymphs; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
, 
1 juv.
; 
MNHN

• 

2 ♀
; 
MNHN

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 112A
); frontal process triangular (
Fig. 112C
). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed (
Fig. 112C
); pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, pale, seta lateral to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad near carapace margin; curved carina between ocular triads and carapace margin (
Fig. 112C
).
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 112B
); other sternal platelets narrow, projecting, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with four setae near membranous region.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs cover well developed.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with short setae posteromedially; pair of white bulges medially and slender setae apically (
Fig. 113A–C
); gonopod finger-like, unsclerotized basally (
Fig. 113A, C, F
); denticulate margin between gonopod and posterior margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 113E
); slit sensilla laterally on genital operculum (
Fig. 113E
). Male gonopod as wide as long, wider in distal third (
Fig. 114C
); Lol2 fimbriate with small spines apically on projections (
Fig. 114A–B, D
); PI with smooth surface and acute apex (
Fig. 114F
); dorsal lobe short, with spines on inner margin and ventrally, and apex curved outwards (
Fig. 114C, G
); LaM short, not fused medially, with smooth surface (
Fig. 114A– B
); fistula with inner spines (
Fig. 114E
).
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Retrolateral surface of basal segment with short projection, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae basally to medially; claw with five teeth; more than two rows of several setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxae without seta encircled by round carina and with three setae on margin. Femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines (
Fig. 112E–F
); two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; long spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin, two-thirds length of spine 1. Patella with four dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 112E
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I; three ventral spines (
Fig. 112F
); setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two subequal dorsal spines (
Fig. 112D
); cleaning organ with 30–32 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first and second tarsal articles equal in length. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated slightly closer to distal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated equidistant between 
bf
and s 
bf
, and 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 8
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known from 
Cambodia
, 
Thailand
and 
Vietnam
. The distribution of this species overlaps that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Weygoldtia davidovi
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Material from 
Cambodia
(Sre Unebell, Réam) in the MNHN was misidentified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. brachydactylus
</tp:taxon-name>
by 
Fage (1946)
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
