<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sarax bispinosus Miranda &amp;
                        Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, stat. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5570636</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FF41FF09A53AFCEAFB02DDCF</uri>
                  <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family
                        Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Sarax bispinosus ( Nair, 1934 ) </tp:taxon-name> , stat. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 3E–F , 4E–F , 135 , 137–140 ; Table 9 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Phrynichosarax cochinensis var. bispinosus Nair, 1934: 475
                  </tp:taxon-name> , fig. b. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Sarax cochinensis bispinosus </tp:taxon-name> – Harvey 2003: 8 .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> This species may be separated from other species of <tp:taxon-name> Sarax
                  </tp:taxon-name> in Africa, the Middle East and South Asia by the following
                  combination of characters: median eyes present; median ocular tubercle shallow (
                  Fig. 137A ); chelicera with short, acute tooth on retrolateral surface of basal
                  segment, opposite to bifid tooth; cheliceral claw with four teeth; pedipalps
                  sexually dimorphic, male pedipalps with longer segments than female pedipalps;
                  tibia of leg I with 23 articles, tarsus I with 39 articles; leg IV basitibia with
                  three pseudo-articles; distitibia trichobothrium bc situated medially and closer
                  to bf than to sbf ; sc and sf series each with five trichobothria. </p>
            <p>This species differs from its congeners in the number of articles on the tarsus of
                  leg I.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> Adjective referring to two spines on the pedipalp tarsus ( Nair 1934 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Syntypes INDIA • 2 ex. ; Kallar , 30 miles E of Trivandrum
                        , Tamil Nadu ; [ 08°42′35.41″ N , 77°07′44.77″ E ]; 2000 ft a.s.l. ; Mar.
                        1933 ; K.B. Nair leg.; [repository unspecified] [not examined]
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> many specimens; Mookunni Hill ,
                        near Trivandrum ; [ 08°32′51.76″ N , 76°59′28.26″ E ]; 842 ft a.s.l. ; K.B.
                        Nair leg.; damp places adhering to undersurface of stones and fallen timber;
                        [repository unspecified] [not examined] </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Additional material (examined) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SRI LANKA • 2 ♀♀ , 2 ♂♂ ; North Central Province ,
                        Anuradhapura District , Kodigala Mountain ; 08°06′34″ N , 80°39′24″ E ; new
                        record; 6 Feb. 2014 ; L. Prendini and P. Horsley leg.; under stones on
                        summit and rocky upper slopes, many large granitic outcrops, moderate to
                        thick leaf litter layer, dense canopy cover with sparse understorey below
                        summit; forest shorter and drier at summit; AMNH Ambly 90
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ juv.; same collection data as
                        for preceding; AMCC [ LP 12298 ] </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> CARAPACE.Six anterior setae ( Fig. 137A ); frontal process triangular, not visible
                  in dorsal view ( Fig. 137C ). Small granules densely scattered between ocular
                  triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed;
                  pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, pale, with
                  seta lateral to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad situated near carapace
                  margin; curved carina between ocular triads and carapace margin. </p>
            <p> STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing
                  base of pedipalp coxae ( Fig. 137B ); other sternal platelets narrow and
                  projected, with 6–8 setae anteriorly on plaque and 6–8 setae posteriorly;
                  pentasternum with two or three setae medially on plaque. </p>
            <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sac cover well developed.</p>
            <p> GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with short setae posteromedially; median region
                  with pair of white bulges and slender setae apically ( Fig. 138A–C ); gonopod
                  finger-like with small invagination apically ( Fig. 138A–B, E ); base of gonopods
                  unsclerotized; slit sensilla on lateral margin of genital operculum ( Fig. 138E ).
                  Male genitalia with LoL1 wrinkled ( Fig. 139A, E ); LoL2 fimbriate ( Fig. 139D );
                  LoD not projected or surpassing LaM ( Fig. 139A, C ); wth small spiny projections
                  on border of LaM ( Fig. 139A– B ); spiny projections inside fistula ( Fig. 139G );
                  short PI ( Fig. 139D ); border of fistula and base of LoL2 sclerotized. </p>
            <p>CHELICERAE. Retrolateral surface of basal segment with short, acute projection
                  opposite to bifid tooth on basal segment; retrolateral surface of claw with row of
                  setae basally to medially; claw with four teeth; two transverse rows of several
                  setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with
                  dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
            <p> PEDIPALPS. Coxae without seta encircled by round carina, two setae on margin with
                  sockets near each other. Femur with four or five dorsal spines and four or five
                  ventral spines ( Figs 3E–F , 137E–F ); two or three prominent setiferous tubercles
                  between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; short setiferous tubercle between
                  ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with five dorsal spines in primary
                  series ( Figs 4E–F , 137E–F ); two prominent setiferous tubercles distal to spine
                  I; three ventral spines decreasing in length from distal to proximal; two small
                  setiferous tubercles between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with two dorsal
                  spines, distal spine similar in length to tibia, proximal spine one-third length
                  of distal spine; ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal
                  margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, distal spine long ( Fig. 137D ), about half
                  length of tarsus, proximal spine short, emerging from base of longer spine;
                  cleaning organ with 30–32 setae in ventral row. </p>
            <p> LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 39 articles; first tarsal
                  article same length as second article; tarsal organ close to base of tarsal claw (
                  Fig. 140A–B, D ); rod sensilla in deep groove ( Fig. 140C ). Leg IV basitibia with
                  three pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles;
                  trichobothrium bt situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia
                  trichobothrium bc situated closer to bf than to s bf , sc and sf series each with
                  five trichobothria. </p>
            <p> Measurements </p>
            <p> See Table 9 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Known from India and Sri Lanka . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Natural history </p>
            <p>Specimens were collected under stones in primary forest.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> The distinctive morphology of <tp:taxon-name> S. bispinosus </tp:taxon-name>
                  justifies its elevation to the rank of species. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
