<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sarax gravelyi Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536888</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FF2FFF6BA581F9D0FAB0D9A7</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax gravelyi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
AEE16A5A-147C-4814-BF11-3CC21B1B3668
</p>
      <p>
Figs 103
, 
110–111
; 
Table 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax buxtoni
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Seiter &amp; Wolff 2014: 233–234

, 237–238, figs 1a, 2a–d, h–j, 3a–b.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species most closely resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. batuensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. rahmadii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, from which it may be separated by the following combination of characters: brownish color with red stripes on the carapace, opisthosoma, and legs; pedipalp patella with one or two ventral spines between spine I and distal margin (
Fig. 110F
); two large spines dorsally on pedipalp tarsus; leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, distitibia 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Patronym honoring Frederick H. Gravely for his contributions to arachnology.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
SINGAPORE
• 
♀
; 
Nee Soon Swamp Forest
, 
Old Upper Thomson Road
; 
01°23.445′ N
, 
103°49.077′ E
; 

46 m
a.s.l.

; 

3 Jun. 2013

; 
L. Prendini
and 
S. Loria
leg.; primary/secondary disturbed rainforest along roadside; dense canopy; sparse understorey; moderate leaf litter layer; under discarded earthen pots; 
LKC
ex 
AMCC
[
LP 11994
].
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
SINGAPORE
• 
4 ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
AMCC
[
LP 11994
]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
, 
1 juv.
; 
Bukit Timah Nature Reserve
, 
Bukit Timah
; 
01°21′16.85″ N
, 
103°46′34.95″ E
; 

163 m
a.s.l.

; 
L. Prendini
and 
S.F. Loria
leg.; 

3 Jun. 2013

; primary rainforest on slopes of Bukit Timah [highest hill in Singapore]; dense canopy and leaf litter layer; moderate to sparse understorey; forest somewhat dry; coarse, granitic sandyloam soil; under stones; 
AMCC
[
LP 11995
]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
University of Singapore
, 
University Campus
, 
Kent Ridge
; 
01°18′ N
, 
103°47′ E
; 

6 Jan. 1991

; 
M. Andersen
, 
O. Martin
and 
N. Scharff
leg.; 
secondary forest
; 
ZMUC 21592
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MALAYSIA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Johor
, 
Mount Austin
; [
01°32′41.20″ N
, 
103°46′43.94″ E
]; 1924; 
C.W. Franck
leg.; 
ZMUC 21611
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
SINGAPORE
• 
3 ♀♀
; 
Br. Timah
, Singapore; 

Mar. 1924

; 
BMNH 1324-25
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♀♀
, 
3 juv.
; 
Rifle Range Road
, 
close to Bukit Timah
; 
01°20.789′ N
, 
103°46.962′ E
; 

55 m
a.s.l.

; 

22 Jun. 2013

; 
P. Jäger
leg.; 
SMF 65287
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 110A
); frontal process triangular (
Fig. 110C
). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed (
Fig. 110A, C
); pair of setae on median tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, pale, with seta lateral to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad situated near carapace margin; curved carina between ocular triads and carapace margin.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 110B
); other sternal platelets narrow and projected, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with four setae anteriorly on plaque.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover well developed.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with short setae posteromedially (
Fig. 111A–C
); pair of white slightly bulging areas medially with slender setae apically (
Fig. 111A–C
); gonopod finger-like, unsclerotized basally (
Fig. 111A, C, E
); denticulate surface between gonopod and posterior marging of genital operculum (
Fig. 111D
); slit sensilla on lateral margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 111F
). Male unknown.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Retrolateral surface of basal segment without tooth, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae basally to medially; claw with three teeth; more than two rows of several setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxae without seta encircled by round carina and with two setae on margin. Femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines (
Fig. 110E–F
); two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; long spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin, two-thirds length of spine 1. Patella with five dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 110E
); prominent spine distal to spine I; four ventral spines; small setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin (
Fig. 110F
). Tibia with ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, distal spine long, about one-third length of tarsus and proximal spine one-third length of distal spine (
Fig. 110D
; cleaning organ with 27–29 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first and second tarsal articles equal in length. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
bf
than to s 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 8
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from 
Singapore
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Found under stones and fallen tree trunks in primary and secondary rainforest.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Three species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
occur in 
Singapore
: 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. buxtoni
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. gravelyi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. singaporae
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax buxtoni
</tp:taxon-name>
appears to be uncommon in 
Singapore
(but abundant in peninsular 
Malaysia
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. gravelyi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
occurs in some restricted forested areas of 
Singapore
, whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. singaporae
</tp:taxon-name>
is widespread in 
Singapore
.
</p>
      <p>
The specimen from Mount Austin, 
Malaysia
(ZMUC 21611), near 
Singapore
, is a female with dark coloration, perhaps due to the long time preserved in ethanol. The spines of the pedipalp tarsus are short unlike the Singaporean specimens to which the specimen is otherwise similar: the carapace has lateral carinae contacting the lateral eyes; the genital operculum is typical of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
, with prominent bulges; the gonopod is finger-like and unsclerotized basally; and the leg IV basitibia consists of four pseudo-articles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
