<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sarax pakistanus Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536908</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/0F649299649216BB067C3F307380450D</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax pakistanus
(
Weygoldt, 2005
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 135
, 
144
; 
Table 9
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus pakistanus
Weygoldt, 2005: 6–8
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 10–15.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus pakistanus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Blick &amp; Seiter 2016: 590

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
in Africa, the Middle East and South Asia by the following combination of characters: distal margin of female genital operculum with small median projection; ventral sac cover absent; female gonopod finger-like, with slender apex; sexual dimorphism in pedipalps apparently absent; pedipalp patella with large dorsal spine, not setiferous tubercle, distal to spine I, two-thirds length of spine I, two ventral spines, and one seta between spine I and distal margin (
Fig. 144E–F
); pedipalp tibia with base of two dorsal spines situated very close to each other; leg IV basitibia with three articles.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax pakistanus
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. bengalensis
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
but bears more teeth on the cheliceral claw, more spines on the pedipalp, and the eyes are not as developed, than the latter.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
An adjective referring to 
Pakistan
, the country in which the 
type
locality is situated (
Weygoldt 2005
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
PAKISTAN
• 
♂
; 
Malkandi
, 
between Kawai and Mahandri, Kaghan Valley, Mansehra District
; [
34°41′15″ N
, 
73°26′58.75″ E
]; 

1500 m
a.s.l.

; 

3 Jun. 1983

; 
C. Besuchet
and 
I. Löbl
leg.; sifting leaves and old stumps in hardwood forest; 
MHNG
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
PAKISTAN
• 
3 ♀♀
, 
2 ♂♂
; 
Khyber Pakhtunkhwa
[former North-West Frontier Province], 

ca 
1.5 km
N of Islamabad

; 
33°44.3′ N
, 
73°03′ E
; ca 

800 m
a.s.l.

; 

10 Jul. 2003

; 
S.V. Ovchinnikov
leg.; 
forest, under stones
; 
SMF 40168
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Supplementary description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle reduced (
Fig. 144A
); frontal process with rounded apex (
Fig. 144C
); one seta, not pair, posterior to median eyes; lateral eyes well developed, one seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from margin of carapace.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation (
Fig. 144B
); other sternal platelets small, rounded and convex, with pair of setae anteriorly; pentasternum with two setae anteriorly and without seta in membranous region.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Posterior margin of female genital operculum with small median projection; gonopod fingerlike, with slender apex, unsclerotized basally. Male gonopod sclerotized along entire margin of fistula and ventrally, near margin of genital operculum; lateral lobe 1 sclerotized apically; lateral lobe 2 not fimbriate.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with two patches of setae, basally and subdorsally; claw with eight teeth; row of eight setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxae with seta encircled by round carina and four setae on margin. Femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines (
Fig. 144E–F
); two setiferous tubercles between spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines and two prominent setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 3; large spine distal to spine I, two-thirds length of spine I; three ventral spines; prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with base of two dorsal spines situated very close to each other; three ventral spines distally and seta between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, distal spine long, more than half length of tarsus, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine (
Fig. 144D
); cleaning organ with 30–34 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 21 articles; tarsus I with 35 articles; first tarsal article slightly longer than second (mean length of first article: 
0.32 mm
; mean length of second article: 
0.22 mm
, n =3). Leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles, trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
bf
than to s 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series with five trichobothria; proximal-most trichobothria of 
sc
and 
sf
aligned.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 9
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
localities.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>The known specimens were collected under stones and tree stumps, and by sifting leaf litter in forest.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The specimen labeled “ 
holotype
” in the vial is male not female, as indicated in the original description by 
Weygoldt (2005)
, and the 
paratypes
are 
3 ♀♀
, 
2 ♂♂
, again contrary to the original description.
</p>
      <p>
This species was originally described in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
and is hereby transferred to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
based on the phylogenetic analyses of 

Miranda
et al.
(2021)

.
</p>
      <p>
The male gonopod of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. pakistanus
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
is completely different from all other species in the family. Detailed SEM images are needed for comparison with the genitalia of other charinids.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
