<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus imperialis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
224F52CC-D92D-4D13-83A7-BC409080E3A1
</p>
      <p>
Figs 43
, 
66–68
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: cheliceral claw with 11 teeth; pedipalp femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines, and small spine between dorsal spines 2 and 3 and spines 3 and 4 (
Fig. 66E–F
); pedipalp patella with four dorsal spines and three ventral spines (
Fig. 66E–F
); pedipalp tarsus with two dorsal spines (
Fig. 66D
); leg IV distitibia 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
The male is unknown. This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. puri
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but possesses less spines on the pedipalp.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name refers to the 
type
locality, the National Museum and former house of Brazil’s Emperor in the 19 
th
century.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
Museu Nacional
; 
22°54′20.73″ S
, 
43°13′35.50″ W
; 

18 Jan. 2018

; 
G.S. Miranda
, 
A.P.L. Giupponi
, and 
D.R. Pedroso
leg.; 
MNRJ 9358
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
2 ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
CAVAISC

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 2003; 
A.P.L. Gupponi
and 
R. Baptista
leg.; 
MNRJ 9296

• 

1 juv.
; 
Museu Nacional
, Carcinology Lab; 
MNRJ 9276

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 

Oct. 2001

; 
S.M. Ribeiro
leg.; 
MNRJ 9032

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
(examined)
</p>
      <p>
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♀
; same locality as holotype; 

Jul. 2007

; 
A. Kury
leg.; 
MNRJ 9088

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Frontal process large, subtriangular, not visible in dorsal view (
Fig. 66C
). Median eyes and median ocular tubercle present (
Fig. 66C
); median ocular tubercle shallow, slightly higher than carapace surface, with pair of small setae. Lateral eyes well developed, pale, small seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly into large, blunt tubercle, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 66B
). Medial platelet (tetrasternum) and third platelet (pentasternum) forming single convex platelet, with pair of large setae anteriorly, and several small setae posteriorly. Metasternum with two anterior setae in membranous region and longitudinal row of three setae, from anterior to posterior; four setae posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female gonopod with posterior margin of genital operculum slightly convex, several setae along margin and on surface (
Fig. 67A–C
); gonopods with small sclerotized area basally (disconnected); gonopods sucker-like with large opening (
Fig. 67A, C–D
); inner membranous region with gland openings (
Fig. 67E
); slit sense organ on lateral margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 67F
). Male unknown.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth in retrolateral row of basal segment. Prolateral surface with transverse row of more than ten small setae, from ventral to dorsal. Three setae, retrolateral, retromedial, and prolateral, on dorsodistal margin, near membranous region of claw. Claw with eleven teeth; row of setae on retrolateral surface from base to near apex (dorsal side).</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with four small setae and five setae on anterior margin of round carina. Femur with four distinct setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 1 (
Fig. 66E
); primary series with four dorsal spines, smaller spine between spines 2 and 3, and spines 3 and 4 (
Fig. 66E
); four ventral spines, small spine between spines 1 and 2, 2 and 3, and 3 and 4, the last (distal) spine half length of spine 4 (
Fig. 66F
); row of three small spines prolateral to ventral spines, first (proximal) spine near base of spine 1, second spine near base of spine 2, third spine near base of spine between spines 2 and 3; large ventral spine proximal to spine 1; small spine between this spine and articulation between trochanter and femur. Patella with four dorsal spines (
Fig. 66E
); three ventral spines decreasing in length; two or three setiferous tubercles between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with two dorsal spines, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine; ventral spine in distal half of tibia; prominent setiferous tubercle near its base; four long setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine half length of distal spine (
Fig. 66D
); ventral row of cleaning brush with 25–27 setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; tarsal organ near base of claw, with three apical projections (
Fig. 68A–B, D
); rod sensilla with seven setae in shallow groove (69A, C); two slit sensilla near tarsal claw (
Fig. 68E–F
). Leg apex with small modified claw, emerging from common base, with sensilla situated ventral to it. Lateral claws smaller than medial claw. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third; distal apex of basitibial pseudo-articles with dark, denticulate projection; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria; distitarsus with distinct white annulus distally on first article.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
Occurs underneath the National Museum of 
Rio de Janeiro
. It is unknown whether the population survived the devastating fire of 
2 September 2018
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
