<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus sooretama Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536839</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FF1BFF50A57DFE6AFD16D8E5</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus sooretama
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
8E440763-D5D2-4177-9E29-A6B533A0604A
</p>
      <p>
Figs 7E–F
, 
9C–D
, 
43
, 
75
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: males with secondary sexual dimorphism; despite the different lengths of the pedipalps of males and females, the spine counts are similar, except for the tarsus, as females appear to possess fewer spines, perhaps associated with smaller size; pedipalp tarsus with two or three dorsal spines (
Fig. 75D
).
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. brasilianus
</tp:taxon-name>
, but differs in possessing three spines on the pedipalp tarsus.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition referring to the 
type
locality, the Sooretama Biological Reserve, and the Sooretama Municipality, in which it is located.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Espírito Santo
, 
Sooretama
; 
A.P.L. Giupponi
leg.; 
MNRJ 9245
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
2 ♀♀
, 
3 ♂♂
, 
2 juv.
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9245
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♂♂
; 
Espírito Santo
, 
Estrada do Quirinão
, 
Sooretama Biological Reserve
; 
19°02′11.19″ S
, 
40°03′32.31″ W
; 

19 Apr. 2006

; 
Arachné Expedition
leg.; 
MNRJ 9244
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 75A
); frontal process triangular (
Fig. 75C
). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes well developed (
Fig. 75C
); median ocular tubercle reduced, with pair of setae; lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 75B
); other sternal platelets narrow and concave, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with four setae anteriorly and pair of setae in membranous region.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin; gonopod sucker-like, sclerotized basally, with apex slightly curved outwards (
Fig. 7E–F
). Male gonopod with apical border of fistula and lateral lobe sclerotized; LoL2 fimbriate and LoD short (
Fig. 9C–D
).
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with continous row of setae, basally to medially; claw with seven teeth; row of four setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with prominent seta encircled by round carina and three setae on margin. Femur with five dorsal spines (
one specimen
with small spine between spines 2 and 3, spines 3 and 4, and distal to spine 4) and four (some females) or five ventral spines (
Fig. 75E–F
); two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; spine between spine 1 and proximal margin; long spine between ventral spines 3 and 4. Patella with five or six (
one female
) dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 75E
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; four ventral spines (
Fig. 75F
); prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with three dorsal spines (only 
one female
with three spines, others with setiferous tubercle instead), longer spines aligned in same row (
Fig. 75D
); third spine near base of proximal spine; among longer spines, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 29–31 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article similar in length to subsequent articles. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated submedial on pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality in the Sooretama National Park, 
Brazil
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Collected under stones and fallen tree trunks.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
