<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus renneri Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536823</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FFE4FFADA56FFEE7FE9AD8DC</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus renneri
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
53281423-876C-492D-B4E3-F655A80DFFFF
</p>
      <p>
Figs 6A–B
, 
10I–J
, 
43
, 
73–74
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. acaraje
</tp:taxon-name>
, from which it may be separated by the number spines on the pedipalp; 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. renneri
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
possesses four ventral spines on the femur and five dorsal spines on the patella (
Fig. 73E–F
), whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. acaraje
</tp:taxon-name>
possesses three ventral spines on the femur and three dorsal spines on the patella. It can be separated from the other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
species
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by the widely separate sucker-like female gonopods with lateral margins projecting dorsally (
Fig. 6A–B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Patronym honoring Dr Renner L.C. Baptista for his contributions to arachnology.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Bahia
, 
Campo Formoso
, 
Lapa do Convento
; 
10°30′28.07″ S
, 
40°19′23.12″ W
; 

6 Nov. 2002

; 
A.P.L. Giupponi
and 
R. Baptista
leg.; 
MNRJ 9198
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 juv.
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9198
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Frontal process large, subtriangular, not visible in dorsal view (
Fig. 73C
). Median eyes and median ocular tubercle present; median ocular tubercle shallow, not higher than carapace surface, pair of small setae at base (
Fig. 73C
). Lateral eyes well developed, pale, small seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad (
Fig. 73A
).
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tetra-segmented, all platelets markedly sclerotized (
Fig. 73B
). Tritosternum projected anteriorly into small, blunt tubercle, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae; medial platelet (tetrasternum) and third platelet (pentasternum) forming single convex platelet, with pair of large setae anteriorly, and several small setae posteriorly; metasternum with four setae in membranous region; two or three setae, forming longitudinal row, posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with posterior margin slightly convex, and several setae along margin and on surface (
Fig. 6A–B
). Female gonopods sucker-like, sclerotized basally, with small projections from lateral margins (
Fig. 6A–B
). Male gonopod with distal margin of fistula and base of lateral lobes narrowly sclerotized; LoL2 fimbriate and short (
Fig. 74A–D
); LaM with acute projection posteriorly (
Fig. 74A–D
).
</p>
      <p>
CHELICERAE. Small tooth in retrolateral row of basal segment (
Fig. 10I–J
). Prolateral surface with transverse row of around ten small setae, from ventral to dorsal. Two setae, prolateral and retrolateral, on dorsodistal margin, near membranous region of claw. Claw with eight denticles and row of setae on retrolateral surface from base to near apex (dorsal side) (
Fig. 10I–J
); base of row with four setae, disconnected from distal row of setae (gap present between base and apex of row).
</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with small seta and three or four setae on anterior margin of round carina. Femur with two distinct setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 1; primary series with four dorsal spines (
Fig. 73E
); small spine between dorsal spines 2 and 3 on dextral pedipalp of 
holotype
; four ventral spines, with small spines between spines 1 and 2 and spines 2 and 3 (
Fig. 73F
); spine parallel to ventral spine 1, near base of spine I; spine parallel to spine 2; large ventral spine proximal to spine 1. Patella with five dorsal spines (
Fig. 73F
); large setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, about one-third length of spine I; three ventral spines decreasing in length; two or three setiferous tubercles between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with two dorsal spines, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine; ventral spine in distal half of tibia; four long setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines (also evident in juveniles) (
Fig. 73D
); proximal spine half length of distal spine; ventral row of cleaning brush with 30–32 setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles (29 or 
30 in
incomplete legs). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third, near proximal margin; distal apex of basitibial pseudo-articles with dark, denticulate projection; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria; tarsus with distinct white annulus distally on first article.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
This species inhabits a very wet cave. The 
type
specimens were only found in the aphotic zone, on cave walls, close to water. Two other caves in the vicinity, which are hotter and drier, contained no amblypygids.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
