<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus guayaquil
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
032D5F71-C742-48E8-BA93-B9488833BAD9
</p>
      <p>
Figs 34–35
; 
Table 3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in western South America by means of the following combination of characters: small size; tegument pale whitish in color; reduced median and lateral eyes (
Fig. 35A, C
); median ocular tubercle absent (
Fig. 35C
); female gonopod cushion-like; cheliceral claw with five teeth; leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition referring to the municipality in which the 
type
locality is situated.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
ECUADOR
• 
1 ♀
; 
Guayas
, 
Guayaquil
, 
Bosque Protector Cerro Blanco
; 
02°10′56.39″ S
, 
80°01′4.87″ W
; 

96 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Mar. 2011

; 
A. Chagas
, 
A. Giupponi
and 
A. Kury
leg.; 
MNRJ 9302
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratype
ECUADOR
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9301

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Ten anterior setae (
Fig. 35A
); frontal process triangular, visible in dorsal view (
Fig. 35C
). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes reduced, median ocular tubercle absent (
Fig. 35C
); pair of setae near remnants of median eyes; lateral eyes weakly developed, pale, seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad (
Fig. 35A
).
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly, with typical setation (
Fig. 35B
); other sternal platelets broad, flat, with pair of setae on each side and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with six setae anteriorly and without seta near membranous region (
Fig. 35B
).
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and smaller setae near margin; posterior margin of gonopod with pair of shallow lateral sulci; gonopod cushion-like, with retrolateral margins of fold projecting over other margin; base of gonopods unsclerotized. Male unknown.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth, slightly projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with two patches of setae, one basal, other medial; claw with five teeth; transverse row of around five setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with cusps subequal in size.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with two prominent setae encircled by round carina and two setae on margin. Femur with three dorsal and three ventral spines (
Fig. 35E–F
); two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; setiferous tubercle between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 35E
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; patella with two ventral spines in primary series; setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine (
Fig. 35D
); cleaning organ with 31 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article slightly longer than second article. Leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles, without sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
equidistant between 
sbf
and 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 3
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality. This is the first species described from continental 
Ecuador
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
Found under flat stones on the forest floor. The 
type
specimens were together under the same stone. A species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phrynus
</tp:taxon-name>
was collected in sympatry.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
