<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus cearensis Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536782</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FFFEFFBAA563FA0DFDAED884</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus cearensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
1041FC16-D0B0-4CDF-BC9E-AC5B2AA993C9
</p>
      <p>
Figs 43
, 
54–56
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: carapace with carina ventral to lateral eyes; cheliceral claw with nine teeth; leg IV basitibia with four articles.
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. potiguar
</tp:taxon-name>
, but can be differentiated by the smaller number of cheliceral teeth, with nine teeth in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. cearensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
compared with thirteen teeth in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. potiguar
</tp:taxon-name>
, and greater number of spines on the pedipalp patella in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. cearensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Adjective refering to 
Ceará
, the Brazilian state in which the 
type
locality is located.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Ceará
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ubajara
, 
Parque Nacional de Ubajara
, 
Gruta de Ubajara
</tp:taxon-name>
; [
03°50′ S
, 
40°53′59″ W
]; 

Jul. 1979

; 
Ricardo
leg.; 
IBSP 67
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♀
; same locality as for holotype; 
03°49′57.2″ S
, 
40°53′59.4″ W
; 

29–28 Jul. 2013

; 
L.S. Carvalho
and 
D.N. Lima
leg.; 
cave’s drainage flue
; 
CHNUFPI 1255
, 
AMCC
[
LP 13401
]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CHNUFPI 1252
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CHNUFPI 1254
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CHNUFPI 1253
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CHNUFPI 1251
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CHNUFPI 1250
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CHNUFPI 1256
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 54A
); frontal process triangular, visible in dorsal view (
Fig. 54C
). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci; lateral margin, ventral to lateral eyes, with small carina. Median eyes well developed (
Fig. 54C
); median ocular tubercle shallow, with pair of setae; lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 54B
); other sternal platelets narrow and concave, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with four setae anteriorly and two setae near membranous region.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin (
Fig. 55A–C
); gonopod sucker-like, unsclerotized basally (
Fig. 55A, C, F
); tubular from base to apex, with broad aperture (
Fig. 55A, F
); genital operculum with smooth surface between gonopod and distal margin (
Fig. 55D
); sensilla on lateral margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 55E
). Male unknown.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with continuous row of setae, basally to medially; claw with nine teeth; row of setae on prolateral surface of basal segment with eight setae in one row; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with four prominent setae encircled by round carina and five setae on margin (
Fig. 54A
). Femur with five dorsal spines and four or five ventral spines (
Fig. 54E–F
); spine between dorsal spines 2 or 3; two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin; small spine ventral to extra spine proximal to ventral spine 1, near articulation between femur and trochanter. Patella with five dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 54E
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; four ventral spines (
Fig. 54F
); prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and five setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine (
Fig. 54D
); cleaning organ with 25–28 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles, tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article shorter than second article; rod sensilla with five setae in shallow groove; tarsal organ situated close to base of tarsal claw (
Fig. 56A, C
). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated medially on pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
According to L.S. Carvalho (pers. com.), 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. cearensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is uncommon and only found near drainage flues in the dark zone of the cave (Gruta de Ubajara). Searches of nearby caves, such as Gruta do Morcego Branco, ca 
50 m
from the 
type
locality, as well as outside the caves, were unsuccessful in finding additional specimens, suggesting the species is restricted to Gruta de Ubajara. A schizomid, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rowlandius ubajara
Santos, Ferreira &amp; Buzatto, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
, is also endemic to the cave.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The 
holotype
possesses an extra spine between dorsal spines 3 and 4 on the femur of the sinistral pedipalp. The 
holotype
possesses four ventral spines on the pedipalp femur whereas the 
paratype
possesses five ventral spines, the last spine appearing to be a duplication of the previous spine, as both spines are similar in length and color. The basitibia of leg IV consists of three pseudo-articles on one leg and two pseudo-articles on the other, in the 
holotype
, whereas the basitibia consists of four pseudoarticles on both legs of the 
paratype
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
