<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sarax palau Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536896</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FF5BFF10A58EFE7FFEFFD8F3</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax palau
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
73538584-7F9D-4AD4-8949-A042D32298C5
</p>
      <p>
Figs 103
, 
118–119
; 
Table 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
in Southeast Asia and Oceania by the following combination of characters: pedipalp tarsus with one dorsal spine and 21 setae in ventral row of cleaning organ; leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, distitibia 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax palau
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, also with one spine on the pedipalp tarsus, but in which the spine is situated closer to proximal margin of the tarsus. Additional differences between the two species are as follows: two ventral spines on the pedipalp patella in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. palau
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
but three spines in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; three long setae between the ventral spine and distal margin of the pedipalp tibia in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. palau
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but only one seta in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; the distitibia of leg IV with four articles in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. palau
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
but three articles in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; 
sc
and 
sf
series of the distitibia each with five trichobothria in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. palau
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
but six trichobothria in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S lembeh
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition referring to 
Palau
, the country in which the 
type
locality is situated.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
PALAU
• 
♀
; 
Koror
Island
; [
07°20′40.26″ N
, 
134°29′54.15″ E
]; 

19 Nov. 1947

; 
H.S. Dybas
(Entomological Survey of Micronesia-Pacific Science Board) leg.; 
FMNH 3489487
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
PALAU
• 
1 ♂
; same locality as for holotype; 

26 Nov. 1947

; 
H.S. Dybas
(Entomological Survey of Micronesia-Pacific Science Board) leg.; 
FMNH 3489488
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 juv. ♀♀
, 1 exuvium; 
Peleliu Island
(
East Coast
); [
07°00′19.08″ N
, 
134°15′34.05″ E
]; 

4 Aug. 1945

; 
H.S. Dybas
leg.; 
FMNH 3489497
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 118A
); frontal process triangular (
Fig. 118C
). Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed (
Fig. 118A
); pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, pale, small seta on each lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad situated near lateral margin of carapace; lateral carina on lateral margin of carapace ventral to lateral eyes, with transverse line projecting from it to lateral ocular triad.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 118B
); other sternal platelets narrow and projected, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; without anterior setae in membranous region and two setae posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sacs cover present.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Posterior margin of female genital operculum slightly convex, with several setae along margin and on surface. Female gonopod plunger-like, unsclerotized basally. Male gonopod damaged, lateral lobe sclerotized, but border of fistula unsclerotized.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth on retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; prolateral surface of basal segment with transverse row of six small setae, from ventral to dorsal. Retrolateral surface of cheliceral claw with row of setae, ventrally to dorsally. Claw with four teeth.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxae dorsally with round carina; without small setae encircled by carina and with three setae on anterior margin. Femur with three or four dorsal spines (
Fig. 118E–F
); three ventral spines; setiferous tubercle proximal to ventral spine 1, between spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines (in 
one adult
paratype
spine emerges from middle of spine I) (
Fig. 118E
); setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, about one-third length of spine I; two ventral spines; setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with two dorsal spines; ventral spine in distal half of tibia. Tarsus with one dorsal spine (
Fig. 118D
); ventral row of cleaning brush with 23–25 setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; apex with small modified claw and tarsal organ ventral to it (
Fig. 118A–B
); lateral claws larger than medial claw (
Fig. 118B
); rod sensilla with four setae in deep sulcus (
Fig. 118C–D
). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third; distal apex of basitibial pseudo-articles without dark, denticulate projection; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sf
and 
sc
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 8
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
localities.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
