<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus Simon 1892</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5570595</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/91563ED77131E3B47F6D3193BC9878ED</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>Charinus</tp:taxon-name>
una

sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
B2646A6F-9AD9-47A1-A8A4-22B262034D8F
</p>
      <p>
Figs 43
, 
78–79
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: median and lateral eyes present (
Fig. 78A
); carina ventral to lateral eyes; cheliceral claw with four or five denticles and two patches of setae on retrolateral surface; secondary sexual dimorphism absent; pedipalp femur with three dorsal spines and four ventral spines (
Fig. 78E–F
); tibia of leg I with 23 articles, tarsus I with 41 articles; leg IV distitibia 
sf
and 
sc
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. acaraje
</tp:taxon-name>
, but is smaller in size, with four or five teeth on the cheliceral claw, and five trichobothria in the 
sc
and 
sf
series of the leg IV distitibia.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition referring to the 
type
locality, the Una Biological Reserve, and the Una Municipality, in which it is located.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Bahia
, 
Una
, 
Una Biological Reserve
; 
15°11′43.48″ S
, 
39°1′47.58″ W
; 

9 Jun. 2009

; 
A. Chagas
, 
Jr, A
. 
Kury, D
. 
Pedroso, A.P.L
. 
Giupponi
and 
V. Dill
leg.; 
MNRJ 9131
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9131

• 

1 ♀
; 
Mata do Lixão
; 

9 Jun. 2009

; 
A. Chagas Jr
, 
A. Kury
, 
D. Pedroso
, 
A.P.L. Giupponi
and 
V. Dill
leg.; 
MNRJ 9298

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 juv.
; 
Mata do Lixão
; 

9 Jun. 2009

; 
A. Chagas
, 
Jr, A.P.L
. 
Giupponi, D. Pedroso
and 
A. Kury
leg.; 
MNRJ 9132

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
BRAZIL
• 
1 juv.
; 
Bahia
, 
Una
, 
Una Biological Reserve
, 
Trilha do Rio Maruim II
; 
15°10′05.1″ S
, 
39°03′52.6″ W
; 

21 Aug. 2014

; 
A.A. Nogueira
leg.; 
MZSP 67527

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Curved carina between ocular triads and carapace margin, closer to margin than eyes, and with small transverse projection medially. Frontal process large, triangular, not visible in dorsal view (
Fig. 78C
). Median eyes and median ocular tubercle present (
Fig. 78A
); median ocular tubercle shallow,
</p>
      <p>slightly higher than carapace surface, with pair of small setae. Lateral eyes well developed, pale, small seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad.</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae, and rounded posteriorly (
Fig. 78B
). Medial platelet (tetrasternum) and third platelet (pentasternum) forming single convex platelet, with pair of large setae anteriorly, and several small setae posteriorly. Metasternum with two anterior setae in membranous region and two setae posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with posterior margin slightly convex and several setae along margin and on surface (
Fig. 79A–C
). Gonopods sucker-like, with large opening and small sclerotized area basally (disconnected from each other) (
Fig. 79A, C–D
); smooth surface between gonopods and posterior margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 79E
); slit sensilla on lateral margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 79F
). Male gonopod with LoL2 not fimbriate, slightly sclerotized.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth in retrolateral row of basal segment. Prolateral surface with transverse row of seven small setae, from ventral to dorsal. Claw with four or five teeth. Three setae, retrolateral, retromedial, and prolateral, on dorsodistal margin, near membranous region of claw. Retrolateral surface of claw with two small patches of setae, basally and medially.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with one or two small setae and two setae on anterior margin of round carina. Femur with three distinct setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 1 (
Fig. 78E
); primary series with three dorsal spines; four ventral spines (
Fig. 78F
); large ventral spine proximal to spine 1, between spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines (
Fig. 78E
); setiferous tubercle distal to I and about one-third length of spine I; two ventral spines decreasing in length; setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with two dorsal spines, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine; ventral spine situated in distal half of tibia; prominent setiferous tubercle near base of spine; three long setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, distal spine one-third length of tarsus, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine (
Fig. 78D
); ventral row of cleaning brush with 31–32 setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudoarticles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third; distal apex of basitibial pseudo-articles with dark, denticulate projection; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria; distitarsus with distinct white annulus distally on first article.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Found in protected and disturbed areas, in the vicinity of a dumping ground.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key to the identification of the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern Africa

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Median and lateral eyes well developed (
Fig. 81A
); pedipalp femur with five or six dorsal spines and four ventral spines (
Fig. 81
); pedipalp patella with six or seven dorsal spines and five or six ventral spines (
Fig. 81A
); pedipalp tarsus with three dorsal spines ................................................................ .......................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. madagascariensis
Fage, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 81
)

</p>
      <p>

– Median and lateral eyes reduced (
Fig. 82A
); pedipalp femur with three dorsal spines and three ventral spines (
Fig. 82E–F
); pedipalp patella with four dorsal spines and three ventral spines (
Fig. 82E–F
); pedipalp tarsus with one dorsal spine (
Fig. 82C
) .................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. susuwa
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(
Fig. 82
)

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
