<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus diamantinus Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536788</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F78806930A8BD351FF728977E2A7419F</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus diamantinus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
1AB27030-B5CC-4EA6-A499-E552B3981C38
</p>
      <p>
Figs 43
, 
57–60
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: large size; small carina ventral to lateral eyes; cheliceral claw with 8–10 teeth; pedipalp tarsus with two or three dorsal spines (
Fig. 57D
); secondary sexual dimorphism present (
Fig. 58A–B
); leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles.
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. euclidesi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, from which it may be differentiated by the smaller number of spines on the pedipalp femur and patella.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Adjective referring to the 
<tp:taxon-name>Diamantina Plateau</tp:taxon-name>
, a geological formation in the Brazilian state of 
Bahia
, where the 
type
locality is located.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Bahia
, 
Gruna Lava Pé
(Igatu020), 
povoado Igatu
, 
Andaraí
; 
12°53′54.61″ S
, 
41°19′21.19″ W
; 

10 Mar. 2012

; 
MNRJ
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♀
; 
Bahia
, 
Andaraí
; 
Giupponi
and 
Baptista
leg.; 
MNRJ 9299

• 

1 ♂
; 
Gruna Lava Pé
(
Igatu
020), 
povoado Igatu
, 
Andaraí
; 
A.P.L. Giupponi
, 
G.S. Miranda
, 
M.E. Bichuette
and 
J.E. Gallão.
leg.; 
MNRJ 9189

• 

1 ♂
, 
1 juv.
; 
Bahia
, 
Povoado Igatu
, 
Andaraí
, 
Gruna Parede Vermelha
(Igatu 010); 

11 Mar. 2012

; 
A.P.L. Giupponi
, 
G.S. Miranda
, 
M.E. Bichuette
and 
J.E. Gallão
leg.; 
MNRJ 9190

• 

1 ♂
; 
Bahia
, 
Gruta do Lapão
, 
Lençóis
; 

9 Mar. 2012

; 
MNRJ 9288

• 

1 ex.
[without gonopod], 
1 juv.
; 
Bahia
, 
Igatu
; 
MNRJ 9203

• 

2 ♂♂
; 
Bahia
, 
Igatu
; 
MNRJ 9300

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Weak carina ventral to lateral eyes, closer to carapace margin than to lateral eyes; frontal process large, subtriangular, not visible in dorsal view (
Fig. 57C
). Median eyes and median ocular tubercle present (
Fig. 57C
); median ocular tubercle shallow, slightly higher than carapace surface, with pair of small setae. Lateral eyes well developed, pale, small seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad (
Fig. 57A
).
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly into small, blunt tubercle, barely surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 57B
); medial platelet (tetrasternum) and third platelet (pentasternum) forming single convex platelet, with pair of large setae anteriorly, and several small setae posteriorly; metasternum with anterior seta in membranous region; two or three setae forming longitudinal row posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum slightly convex, with several setae along margin and on surface; base of sucker-like gonopods sclerotized; small claws projecting from distal border. Male gonopod with thin sclerotized region in distal border of fistula and at base of lateral lobes; LoL2 fimbriate (
Fig. 59A– B
); LaM elongated, reaching LoD (
Fig. 59A–B
); LoD covered with denticulate projections (
Fig. 59C
).
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth in retrolateral row of basal segment; prolateral surface with transverse row of ca ten small setae, from dorsal to ventral; three setae, retrolateral, retromedial, and prolateral, on dorsodistal margin, near membranous region of claw; claw with 8–10 teeth and row of setae on retrolateral surface from base to near apex (dorsal side).</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with five or six small setae and three or four setae on anterior margin. Femur with three distinct setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 1 (
Fig. 57E
); primary series with four dorsal spines and smaller spine between spines 1 and 2, and (in some specimens) between spines 2 or 3 (
Fig. 57E
); small spine, similar in size to spine 4 (suggesting a duplication) may also be present between spines 3 and 4 (present on sinistral pedipalp of adult female (MNRJ 9299), 
two adult
males (MNRJ 9190 and MNRJ 9300), juvenile (MNRJ 9288), and, as smaller spine, on both pedipalps of adult male (MNRJ 9189; 
Fig. 57E
); four ventral spines, with small spine between spines 1 and 2 and between spines 2 or 3 (
Fig. 57F
); spine parallel to ventral spine 1, near base; large ventral spine proximal to spine 1. Patella with three dorsal spines (
Fig. 57E
); large setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, about one-third length of spine I; three ventral spines decreasing in size (
Fig. 57F
); two or three setiferous tubercles between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with two dorsal spines, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine; two or three ventral spines, longest spine in distal half and other(s) medially on tibia. Tarsus with three dorsal spines (also present in juveniles) (
Fig. 57D
); ventral row of cleaning brush with 24–27 setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles (up to 36 on regenerated legs), tarsus I with 41 articles (up to 57 on regenerated legs); leg apex with small modified claw, emerging from common base, with sensilla ventral to it (
Fig. 60A–B
); lateral claws smaller than medial claw (
Fig. 60A–C
); rod sensilla with six setae in shallow groove (
Fig. 60D
). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third; distal apex of pseudo-articles with dark, denticulate projection; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria; distitarsus with marked white annulus distally on first article.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Occurs in several caves in the 
<tp:taxon-name>Diamantina Plateau</tp:taxon-name>
, in the Brazilian state of 
Bahia
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Known only from caves. This is a large species with secondary sexual dimorphism, i.e., the pedipalps are larger in males than females.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
