<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Phantolabis glacialis Pilipenko 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4723715</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A94E87D8FFCD92563543FBE87834AE55</uri>
         <article-title>The genus Phantolabis (Diptera: Limoniidae) new to the Palearctic: description of a new species and re-definition of the genus</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/c7a36863-f039-4c0a-bb6b-d55e8262046a</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Phantolabis glacialis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
9E18EC1A-B53A-49E2-989E-1612582E6860
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. lacustris
</tp:taxon-name>
by wing venation, structure of male genitalia and ovipositor. Wings entirely brownish, crossvein 
r-m
connecting to 
Rs
near wing midlength, apex of 
R3
bent to costal margin, apical part of vein 
CuP
strongly curving toward wing margin, 

A 
1

straight, noticeably thickened basally. Gonocoxites massive, with large ventromesal protrusion basally and ventral protrusion apically; lobe of gonostylus well developed, apically with 4–5 small teeth on inner surface; clasper of gonostylus small, situated at base of lobe of gonostylus, plate-like, each with thin apical process; aedeagus relatively thin, long and straight, apically bent upward and divided into two short rods.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific Latin epithet ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
glacialis
</tp:taxon-name>
’ refers to the discovery of this species on ice.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
RUSSIA
• 
♂
; 
Primorsky Krai
, 
Khasan district
, 
Narva River
; 
43°04′18.7″ N
, 
131°22′20.3″ E
; 

25 m

a.s.l; 

30 Mar. 2001

; 
E.A. Makarchenko
leg.; 
ZISP
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
RUSSIA
• 
5 ♂♂
, 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
ZISP
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
6 ♂♂
, 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
ZMUM
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
RUSSIA
• 
1 ♂
; 
Primorsky Krai
, 
Khasan district
, 
Narva River
; 
43°04′18.7″ N
, 
131°22′20.3″ E
; 

25 m

a.s.l; 

27 Mar. 2005

; 
E.A. Makarchenko
leg.; 
ZMUM
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
JSOC
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Sikhote-Alin Reserve
, 
Kabaniy Klyuch River
; 
44°53′31.0″ N
, 
135°28′20.0″ E
; 

580 m
a.s.l.

; 

24 Mar.–7 Apr. 2015

; 
D.E. Shcherbakov
leg.; 
Malaise trap
; 
VPMC
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Type locality
</p>
      <p>
RUSSIA
: 
Primorsky Krai
, Khasan district.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Figs 1–2
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 3.5–4.0 mm, wing length 4.5–5.0 mm, length of antennae 
0.8–0.9 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 1A
–С). Greyish brown; rostrum short, greyish brown, mouth parts yellow; palpi yellow, with 3 oval segments. Antenna yellowish brown. Scape short, widening distally, pedicel oval. Flagellum 9–10-segmented. Basal flagellar segments subcylindrical, more apical ones shorter, ovoid. Distal flagellomere (
Fig. 1C
) elongate, formed by fused 4–5 distal segments. Verticils short, yellow, approximately half as long as respective segments. Segments covered with short, yellow pubescence.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Fig. 1A–B
). Dark brown with grey pruinose. Pronotum yellowish brown. Mesonotal prescutum dark brown with grey pruinose, longitudinal stripes broad, indistinct, prescutal pits black, tuberculate pits indistinct. Scutal lobes and scutellum same color as prescutum. Mediotergite brownish grey pruinose. Pleuron brownish grey. Meron not separated by a suture from katepimeron, both midleg and hindleg coxae widely separated.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS (
Fig. 1E
). Coxae and trochanters light brown, femora light brown, tibiae brown without spurs, tarsomeres yellowish brown. Legs covered with very short, semi-erect brown setae. Mid tarsus with shortened first and second segments, third tarsomere short with rounded outgrowth on outer lateral side. Tarsal claws inserted subapically, claw simple, without additional spines, arolium absent.
</p>
      <p>
WINGS (
Fig. 1D
). Wide, brownish, sometimes darkened along 
CuA
, veins brownish, almost without macrotrichia. Macrotrichia on wing membrane absent. Venation: arculus absent; 
Sc
short, ending about level with midlength of 
Rs
, stigma indistinct, but costal margin after 
Sc
thickened, 
sc-r
indistinct (if present then close to 
Sc
tip); origin of 
Rs
approximately level with apex of 

A 
1

; 

R 
1

long, apex of 

R 
3

bent to costal margin; bases of cells 

r 
1

and 

r 
3

at same level. Veins 
r-m
and 
m-cu
shifted to mid-wing, 
r-m
connecting to 
Rs
(not to 

R 
4+5

as usual) closer to its middle. Discal cell very long and open due to absence of 
m-m
. Apical part of 
CuP
strongly bent toward wing margin, 

A 
1

straight, noticeably thickened basally; anal angle wide, posterior margin widely rounded. Haltere with knob yellowish white.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Fig. 1A
). Generally light brown, grey pruinose, covered with rather long, erect, yellow setae; tergites brownish yellow, grey pruinose, lateral and medial stripes missing, posterior margins of tergites greyish. Sternites yellowish grey.
</p>
      <p>
HYPOPYGIUM (
Fig. 2A–H
). Dark brown, grey pruinose. Tergite IX transverse with shallow U-shaped notch. Gonocoxites massive, covered with spike-shaped setae directed laterally, with large ventromesal protrusions basally and ventral protrusions at apex (
Fig. 2D
). One pair of terminal gonostyli well developed, lobes of gonostyli (
Fig. 2G–H
), each shaped as triangular-rounded plate, apically with 4–5 small teeth on inner surface. Claspers of gonostyli strongly reduced, poorly visible, each situated at base of adjacent lobe of gonostylus, shaped as small plate, tightly attached to the gonostylus with thin process directed inward. Distal portion of interbase (
Fig. 2E–F
) simple, appearing as slender rod gradually narrowing to acute point, basal portions of interbases merge together medially to form separate crescent-shaped plate above aedeagus, referred to here as interbasal plate (ip). Lateral apodeme of paramere poorly developed. Lateral processes of aedeagal sheath absent. Aedeagus relatively thin, long and straight, protruding beyond apices of interbases and reaching approximately to midlength of gonocoxites, apically bent upward and divided into two short rods.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Phantolabis glacialis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂, Khasan district, Narva River (ZMUM). 
A
. General view, the left wing is broken. 
B
. Head and thorax. 
C
. Apex of the antenna. 
D
. Wing. 
E
. Legs. Scale bars: A–B, D = 1.0 mm; C = 0.5 mm; E = 5 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Phantolabis glacialis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂, Khasan district, Narva River (ZMUM). Terminalia. 
A
. General dorsal view. 
B
. Lateral view. 
C
. Ventral view. 
D
. Left gonostylus. 
E
. Aedeagal complex, dorsal view. 
F
. Aedeagal complex, lateral view. 
G
. Lobe of gonostylus, lateral view. 
H
. Lobe of gonostylus, dorsal view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
Fig. 3A–F
)
</p>
      <p>Similar to male. Antenna short, with 10 segments.</p>
      <p>
Female terminalia (
Fig. 3B–F
) with tergites VIII, IX and X and sternite VIII brown, cerci and hypovalvae brownish yellow. Tergite VIII narrow in lateral aspect, tergite IX triangular, and tergite X relatively small. Cercus elongate, nearly parallel-sided, bent upwards at approximately ⅔ of its length, bluntapexed. Hypovalve long and straight, nearly parallel-sided, setae on dorsal margin long and distinct (
Fig. 3E
). Tips of hypovalvae reach approximately to ⅔ of cercus length. Two pigmented spermathecae (
Fig. 3F
).
</p>
      <p>
Elevation
</p>
      <p>
Specimens were collected at altitudes from approximately 
25 to 600 m
a.s.l.
</p>
      <p>
Period of activity
</p>
      <p>Adults fly in March–April.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Russia
: 
Primorsky Krai
(
Fig. 5
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
