<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Oryctopterus varuna Hiremath &amp;
                        Prathapan 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4746277</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AA2487F3FFB069457F249DE0FD280213</uri>
                  <article-title>Two new species of the genus Oryctopterus (Orthoptera:
                        Stenopelmatidae: Oryctopinae) from India, with some notes on
                        biology</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.748.1349</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 9E74ACC6-86D2-4A93-812A-5997835415D3 </p>
            <p> Figs 1–39 , 49–52 , 70 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. can be
                  differentiated from <tp:taxon-name> Ot. lagenipes </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 48 )
                  from Sri Lanka , by the following characters: (1) clypeus weakly narrowed
                  ventrally in <tp:taxon-name> Ot. varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , more strongly
                  narrowed ventrally in <tp:taxon-name> Ot. lagenipes </tp:taxon-name> , (2) first
                  foretarsomere about 1.4 times as long as the rest combined in <tp:taxon-name> Ot.
                        varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , 2.4 times as long as the rest combined in
                        <tp:taxon-name> Ot. lagenipes </tp:taxon-name> , (3) hindwings fully
                  developed in <tp:taxon-name> Ot. lagenipes </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 48 ) (much
                  reduced in <tp:taxon-name> Ot. varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. : Figs 1–2 , 10–12
                  ). <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. can be
                  differentiated from <tp:taxon-name> Ot. yeshwanthi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. based
                  on the structure of the mandible, pronotum and female genitalia, as mentioned
                  under the latter species. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The new species is named after Varuna, the god of rains in Indian mythology. The
                  name is a noun in apposition. This cricket was observed coming out to open areas
                  such as campus roads following rains, hence the name. In the regional dialect,
                        <tp:taxon-name> Ot. varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is called ‘ Mannunni ’,
                  meaning ‘child of soil’. Also nicknamed ‘ Thanni-Pillai ’, meaning ‘baby of
                  water’, alluding to its emergence following rains. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype INDIA • ♂ ; Kerala , College of Agriculture ,
                        Vellayani ; 18 Mar. 2021 ; Kumar A. leg.; “HOLOTYPE; <tp:taxon-name>
                              Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ; des. Hiremath &amp;
                        Prathapan, 2021”; NBAIR . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes INDIA • 1 ♀ * ; same collection data as for
                        holotype; 3 Sep. 2019 ; S.R. Hiremath leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; Kerala , Vellayani ; 10 Jul. 2007 ; K.D.
                        Prathapan leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ;
                        same collection data as for preceding; 23 Jul. 2015 ; Ashwathi leg.; NBAIR
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for
                        holotype; 7 Jun. 2018 ; Mithra Mohan leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 3 ♀♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; Student
                        leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same
                        collection data as for holotype; 20 Aug. 2019 ; Student leg.; NBAIR
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ * ; same collection data as
                        for holotype; 8 Sep. 2019 ; S.R. Hiremath leg.; NBAIR
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for
                        holotype; 23 Oct. 2019 ; S.R. Hiremath leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; 3 Mar.
                        2020 ; Amritha Hari leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; 21 Mar.
                        2020 ; S.R. Hiremath leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; 10 Jan.
                        2021 ; Pradeep D leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for holotype; 21 Mar.
                        2021 ; Pradeep D leg.; NBAIR </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; 6 Nov.
                        2019 ; Gouripriya leg.; UASB </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; 10 Jan.
                        2020 ; S.R. Hiremath leg.; UASB . ( * Presence of mature eggs confirmed
                        through dissection) </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> INDIA • 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for holotype; 2019;
                        Student collection leg. (lost after the specimen was studied and
                        illustrated: Fig. 10 ) </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male ( Figs 1–17 ) </p>
            <p> COLORATION. General color chestnut brown; abdominal tergites, tegmina darker than
                  head, thorax and sternites. Vertex and frons demarcated by M-shaped dark marking;
                  a U-shaped dark stripe extends vertically over vertex ( Figs 5–6 ), a single
                  vertical stripe arises from each eye and a third pair of vertical stripes arise
                  from the gena. Some of this stripes may be indistinct. Clypeus straw brown in
                  distal half, concolorous with frons in proximal half. Labrum concolorous with
                  frons. Tegmina chestnut brown. Abdominal tergites dark brown. </p>
            <p>HEAD. Vertex strongly convex. Distance between eyes 1.41 times distance between
                  antennal sockets. M-shaped dark marking demarcating vertex, frons depressed. Frons
                  moderately convex between antennal sockets, gradually turning flat and gently
                  depressed ventrally; without wrinkles, except few beneath eye. Eyes with mesal
                  margin concave near antennal socket, lateral margin strongly rounded. Antenna
                  extends well beyond apex of tegmina. Clypeus more or less as long as labrum,
                  trapezoidal, narrowed ventrally, a little wider than long, with a vertical sulcus
                  originating from middle of anterior margin, indistinct in proximal half. Mandibles
                  exceed length of labrum.</p>
            <p> THORAX. Pronotum 1.76 times wider than long, anteriorly 0.95 times wider than
                  posteriorly ( Fig. 6 ). Lateral margin evenly curved; anterolateral margin convex,
                  forming somewhat obtuse angle with anterior margin. Posterior margin apparently
                  bisinuate. Pronotal anteapical transverse impression merged with anterolateral
                  depressions on either side. Oblique sulcus originating from postero-lateral corner
                  of pronotum shallow. Tegmina not covering supragenital plate and 1–5 preceding
                  tergites. Costa 3-branched, subcosta (Sc) unbranched, reaches between apical ¼ and
                  apex; RA 3 or 4-branched, RS + M 1 unbranched or 2-branched, 2 MA 1 unbranched or
                  2-branched ( Figs 10–12 ). Hindwings much shorter than tegmina ( Figs 10–12 ).
                  Prosternite wider than long, converging posteriorly, posterior margin emarginate
                  medially, with two pairs of ventral cervical sclerites; lateral cervical sclerites
                  acutely narrowed distally, oblique; prosternite distally with raised setose
                  portion medially. Metathoracic basisternum with posterior margin emarginate
                  medially. </p>
            <p> Figs 1–4. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂. 1 .
                  Holotype (NBAIR), dorsal habitus. 2–4 . Paratypes (NBAIR). 2 . Dorsal habitus. 3 .
                  Ventral habitus. 4 . Lateral view. Scale bars = 10 mm. </p>
            <p> Figs 5–9. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Paratype, ♂
                  (NBAIR). 5 . Head, frontal view. 6 . Head and pronotum, dorsal view. 7–9 . Apex of
                  abdomen. 7 . Dorsal view. 8 . Ventral view. 9 . Lateral view.Scale bars = 5 mm. </p>
            <p> Figs 10–12. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂. 10 .
                  Lost specimen. 11 . Holotype (NBAIR). 12 . Paratype (NBAIR). Abbreviations: see
                  Material and methods. Scale bars = 5 mm. </p>
            <p> Figs 13–17. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Paratype,
                  ♂ (NBAIR). 13 . Supragenital plate and cerci. 14 . Subgenital plate, dorsal view.
                  15 . Subgenital plate, ventral view. 16 . Genital hook and associated structures,
                  ventral view. 17 . Genital hook. Scale bars = 1 mm. </p>
            <p>HIND LEGS. Coxa depressed ventrally. Dorsolateral and dorsomesal margins of metatibia
                  with a row of 3–6 sharp denticles.</p>
            <p> ABDOMEN ( Figs 7–9 ). Supragenital plate triangular with inverted Y-shaped sulcus
                  medially, apex rounded ( Figs 1–2 , 7 ). Subgenital plate with convex posterior
                  margin ( Figs 14–15 ). Subgenital plate constricted in distal third, apex rounded;
                  with a pair of long apodemes proximally ( Figs 14–15 ). </p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Figs 13–14 ). Genital hooks long, pointed, gently curved, with 6 setae
                  on apex. </p>
            <p>MEASUREMENTS (mm) (n = 3). Body length: 27.50–37.68, head width: 7.55–7.89, pronotal
                  length: 4.42– 4.73, pronotal width: 8.08–8.30, forefemur: 8.94–9.11, foretibia:
                  9.88–10.98, foretarsi: I. 3.39–4.31, II. 0.54–1.46, III. 1.39–1.46, IV. 1.08–1.16,
                  midfemur: 7.76–8.11, midtibia: 8.30–9.01, midtarsi: I. 1.85– 3.08, II. 1.08–1.16,
                  III. 1.16–1.39, IV. 1.31–2.31, hindfemur: 13.17–13.35, hindtibia: 13.47–14.81,
                  hindtarsi: I. 2.46–4.54, II. 1.46–1.62, III. 1.54–1.85, IV. 1.54–2.70.
                  Proportionate length of forefemur: foretibia: foretarsi: midfemur: midtibia:
                  midtarsi: hindfemur: hindtibia: hindtarsi as follows: 1.00: 1.09– 1.23: 0.72–0.92:
                  0.87–0.89: 0.92–0.98: 0.59–0.89: 1.46–1.48: 1.49–1.66: 0.77–1.19. Proportionate
                  length of tarsomeres I–IV: foreleg – 1.00: 0.16–0.34: 0.32–0.41: 0.25–0.34; midleg
                  – 1.00: 0.38–0.58: 0.45–0.66: 0.70–0.75; hindleg – 1.00: 0.36–0.59: 0.39–0.63:
                  0.59–0.63.</p>
            <p> Female ( Figs 18–39 , 49–52 ) </p>
            <p> COLORATION. General color chestnut brown; abdomen darker than head and thorax; legs
                  lighter than thorax. Vertex and frons demarcated by M-shaped dark marking; a
                  U-shaped dark stripe extends vertically over vertex ( Fig. 21 ), a single vertical
                  stripe arise from each eye and a third pair of vertical stripes arise from the
                  gena. The stripes may be obliterated in some specimens. Clypeus straw brown,
                  distinctly lighter than frons. Labrum proximally concolorous with clypeus,
                  gradually turning darker towards distal area. Thoracic sternites lighter than
                  tergites. </p>
            <p>HEAD. Vertex strongly convex. Distance between eyes 1.27–1.40 times distance between
                  antennal sockets. Frons moderately convex between antennal sockets, gradually
                  turning flat to depressed ventrally; minutely wrinkled in ventral half. Eyes with
                  mesal margin concave near antennal socket, lateral margin strongly rounded.
                  Antenna just crosses anteapical sulcus of pronotum. Clypeus a little shorter than
                  labrum, trapezoidal, narrowed ventrally, a little over twice wider than long, with
                  a vertical sulcus originating from middle of anterior margin, depressed on either
                  side of vertical sulcus. Mandibles exceed length of labrum.</p>
            <p> THORAX. Pronotum 1.67–1.79 times wider than long, anteriorly 1.12–1.26 times wider
                  than posteriorly ( Fig. 22 ). Lateral margin evenly curved; anterolateral margin
                  convex, forming somewhat obtuse angle with anterior margin. Posterior margin
                  concave medially. Pronotal anteapical transverse impression merged with
                  anterolateral depressions on either side. Oblique sulcus originating from
                  postero-lateral corner of pronotum not discernible. Prosternite wider than long,
                  converging posteriorly, posterior margin emarginate medially, with two pairs of
                  ventral cervical sclerites; lateral cervical sclerites acutely narrowed distally,
                  oblique; prosternite distally with raised setose portion medially. Metathoracic
                  basisternum with posterior margin emarginate medially. </p>
            <p> Figs 18–21. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Paratype,
                  ♀ (NBAIR). 18 . Dorsal habitus. 19 . Ventral habitus. 20 . Lateral habitus. 20 .
                  Head, frontal view. Scale bars = 5 mm. </p>
            <p> Figs 22–25. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Paratype,
                  ♀ (NBAIR). 22 . Head and pronotum, dorsal view. 23–25 . Apex of abdomen in
                  preserved specimen. 23 . Dorsal view. 24 . Lateral view. 25 . Ventral view. Scale
                  bars = 5 mm. </p>
            <p> Figs 26–28. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Apex of
                  male abdomen in freshly killed specimen (NBAIR). 26 . Dorsal view. 27 . Ventral
                  view. 28 . Lateral view. Scale bars: 26–27 = 5 mm; 28 = 1 mm. </p>
            <p> Figs 29–31. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Paratype,
                  ♀ (NBAIR). 29 . Supragenital plate and cerci, dorsal view (macerated specimen,
                  through transmitted light). 30 . Supragenital plate, cerci and alimentary canal,
                  dorsal view (macerated specimen). 31 . Supragenital plate, cerci and alimentary
                  canal, ventral view (macerated specimen). Scale bars = 1 mm. </p>
            <p>HIND LEGS. Coxa depressed ventrally. Dorsolateral and dorsomesal margins of metatibia
                  with a row of five small denticles, proximal one or two hardly noticeable.</p>
            <p> ABDOMEN ( Figs 23–28 ). Supragenital plate almost semicircular ( Figs 23 , 26 ,
                  29–31 ). Subgenital plate with arcuate posterior margin ( Figs 25 , 27 ). </p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Figs 32–36 ). Ovipositor with dorsal valve broader and slightly longer
                  than ventral one. Base of ventral valve with two pairs of obliquely placed rod
                  shaped sclerites, inner one shorter than outer. Vagina longer than dorsal valve,
                  conical with lateral sides each bearing an elongate, rectangular, unsclerotized
                  vaginal plate at middle. Spermathecal duct elongate, narrow tube with spindle
                  shaped bulb near middle, entering vagina dorsally at middle. Median oviduct merged
                  with ventral wall of vagina. Spermatheca spherical, with smooth integument.
                  Spermathecal gland tubular, narrower and distinctly longer than spermathecal duct.
                  Spermathecal gland with two spindle shaped bulbs near basal third and slightly
                  elongate, spindle shaped bulb at apex ( Fig. 36 ). Sternite VIII transverse with
                  apical margin broadly rounded and weakly projected at middle, integument
                  concentrated with elongate red-brown setae ( Fig. 34 ). </p>
            <p>MEASUREMENTS (mm) (n = 4). Body length: 26.02–37.64, head width: 8.62–12.57, pronotal
                  length: 5.13–7.29, pronotal width: 8.57–13.05, forefemur: 7.71–10.13, foretibia:
                  9.95–13.77, foretarsi: I. 4.42– 6.05, II. 1.01–1.78, III. 0.86–1.49, IV.
                  0.67–1.01, midfemur: 6.63–9.23, midtibia: 7.44–11.24, midtarsi: I. 2.59–3.60, II.
                  0.82–1.34, III. 0.96–1.25, IV. 1.63–2.30, hindfemur: 10.23–14.20, hindtibia:
                  9.53–13.62, hindtarsi: I. 3.17–5.38, II. 1.20–1.68, III. 1.20–1.68, IV. 1.92–2.88.
                  Proportionate length of forefemur: foretibia: foretarsi: midfemur: midtibia:
                  midtarsi: hindfemur: hindtibia: hindtarsi as follows: 1.00: 1.16–1.36: 0.89–1.09:
                  0.70–0.91: 0.94–1.11: 0.76–0.84: 1.27–1.40: 1.15–1.34: 0.97–1.05. Proportionate
                  length of tarsomeres I–IV: foreleg – 1.00: 0.23–0.29: 0.19–0.25: 0.15–0.17; midleg
                  – 1.00: 0.32–0.39: 0.29–0.37: 0.47–0.68; hindleg – 1.00: 0.27–0.45: 0.27–0.41:
                  0.43–0.65.</p>
            <p> Sexual dimorphism </p>
            <p> Male ( 27.50–37.68 mm ) apparently subequal in length to the female ( 26.02–37.64 mm
                  ), with fully developed wings, female apterous and stouter. Claws of forelegs well
                  developed in male, absent in female. Spines on metatibia well developed and sharp
                  in male, much reduced or hardly discernible in the female. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. and <tp:taxon-name>
                        Ot. lagenipes </tp:taxon-name> were geographically isolated multiple times
                  in the Quarternary and most recently during the separation of Sri Lanka from south
                  India , around 7500 years ago with the Holocene rises in sea level ( Gunatilaka
                  2000 ). Poorly developed hind wings indicate that <tp:taxon-name> Ot. varuna
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. could be flightless, despite being alate. Wing venation
                  varies considerably, in the branching pattern, shape of veins and cross veins (
                  Figs 10–12 ). Béthoux (2012) showed that in king crickets, raspy crickets and
                  weta, wing venation vary greatly within species and several species delimited
                  based on wing venation are synonyms. Ross (2012) , who studied cockroaches, proved
                  that forewings of a cockroach species vary considerably; even the left and right
                  wings on the same specimen are slightly different. According to Ross (2012) ,
                  since forewings in cockroaches are not used for active flight, the positions of
                  the veins, which are important for the aerodynamics and flexing of the wings, vary
                  greatly. The intraspecific variation in the wing venation in <tp:taxon-name>
                        Oryctopterus </tp:taxon-name> , could be the outcome of a flightless,
                  subterranean mode of life. </p>
            <p> Figs 32–36. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , female
                  genitalia. Paratype (NBAIR). 32 . Dorsal view. 33 . Dorsal view (valves
                  separated). 34 . Ventral view. 35 . Ventral view (without sternite VIII). 36 .
                  Spermatheca Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 1 mm. </p>
            <p> Figs 37–39. Ovary, ovarioles and egg of <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. Paratype, ♀ (NBAIR). 37 . Ovary. 38 . Ovariole. 39 .
                  Egg. Scale bars: 37–38 = 1 mm; 39 = 0.1 mm. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is only known from
                  the Vellayani campus of the Kerala Agricultural University ( 8°25′46.3″ N ,
                  76°59′07.8″ E , 39 m elevation). Description of this new species underscores the
                  importance of biodiversity conservation in periurban areas, as reckless
                  development is taking its toll on all life forms in every imaginable habitat,
                  throughout India and elsewhere. </p>
            <p> Notes on biology </p>
            <p> Female reproductive system </p>
            <p> Ovaries were paired and each ovary ( Fig. 37 ) consists of more than 10 panoistic
                  ovarioles, each ovariole containing about six eggs ( Fig. 38 ). A total of about
                  175– 200 eggs were present inside the ovaries of an individual. Mature eggs are
                  lemon-shaped ( Fig. 39 ). Fully developed eggs in the ovary indicate that the
                  dissected as well as the other examined specimens, which are morphologically
                  identical, are probably all adults. </p>
            <p> Habitat </p>
            <p> Vellayani campus of the Kerala Agricultural University is the sole known habitat of
                  the new species. The total area of the campus is about 2.52 km 2 . This is a
                  highly populated residential area and the open lands are under cultivation with
                  various agricultural crops. Chemical fertilizers and pesticides are used to raise
                  the crops. The campus has a network of roads connecting academic and residential
                  buildings and other facilities. The soil type is red loam and the average annual
                  rainfall is 1577 mm . </p>
            <p> Seasonality </p>
            <p> Most females were seen walking on the open campus roads during or after a downpour,
                  both during day and night. One individual was caught around midday on 8 September
                  2019 , when it was bright and sunny. Emergence of females of <tp:taxon-name> Ot.
                        varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. coincides with the south-west monsoon rains
                  during June to September. However, males are extremely rare and two individuals
                  were collected following summer rains during the peak summer of March 2021 . </p>
            <p> Food habits as indicated by the gut contents ( Figs 40–47 ) </p>
            <p> Examination of the gut contents of three of the specimens revealed the presence of
                  mandibles of mandibulate soldiers ( Figs 40–41 ) and workers ( Fig. 42 ) of the
                  termite <tp:taxon-name> Odontotermes sp. </tp:taxon-name> (Blattaria,
                        <tp:taxon-name>Termitidae</tp:taxon-name> ); and the body parts, including
                  head ( Fig. 43 ), thorax ( Figs 44–45 ), and abdomen of ants (probably
                        <tp:taxon-name> Pheidole sp. </tp:taxon-name> ,
                        <tp:taxon-name>Hymenoptera</tp:taxon-name> ,
                        <tp:taxon-name>Formicidae</tp:taxon-name> ). Interestingly, a piece of the
                  stem of a plant ( 0.58 mm × 0.43 mm ) ( Fig. 46 ) and sand particles ( 0.24–0.62
                  mm diameter) ( Fig. 47 ) were also observed inside the gut. </p>
            <p> Behavior </p>
            <p> The new species is a ‘heel-walker’ ( Fig. 49 , Supp. file 3). They walk on the
                  distal tip of tibiae with the foretarsi always held raised, while the mid- and
                  hind tarsi are in close proximity to the ground, yet not touching it while
                  walking. However, when not moving, all the tarsi may touch the ground. While
                  walking, the long maxillary palpi are held forward and constantly touch the
                  objects in the foreground in tandem. South African Jerusalem Crickets are known to
                  hop and climb vegetation ( Weissman &amp; Bazelet 2013 ) while some of the New
                  World species exhibit drumming (abdomen striking against the substrate) ( Weissman
                  2001a ). However, no such behaviors were observed in <tp:taxon-name> O. varuna
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. When a female was held above the ground level on a flat
                  substrate, it rather tumbled down instead of hopping. It also failed to climb up
                  sticks on which it was placed. A male was observed flapping wings and performing
                  short jumps of about 0.3 m . </p>
            <p> Defense </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. displayed intricate
                  defensive postures when intimidated. Confronted from the front, the cricket sprang
                  into a pouncing posture, raised its forelegs and waved in mid-air, the mandibles
                  opened widely, as if ready to bite ( Fig. 50 , Supp. file 1). When approached from
                  the anterolateral side, it raised the front leg on that side to defend. However,
                  when the animal was poked on the thorax, in addition to the forelegs, the abdomen
                  also was raised, to startle the attacker ( Fig. 51 ). When an individual is pinned
                  down with the index finger firmly pressed on the thorax, the whole body was flexed
                  and all legs were raised and started kicking to fend off the assailant. They
                  inflicted painful bites when handled. Weissman (2001a) reported that New World
                  Stenopelmatine, when confronted, frequently flip on their back, with mandibles
                  agape, or can rear up. </p>
            <p> Figs 40–47. Gut contents of <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. 40–41 . Mandibles of <tp:taxon-name> Odontotermes sp. </tp:taxon-name>
                  soldier. 42 . Mandible of <tp:taxon-name> Odontotermes sp. </tp:taxon-name>
                  worker. 43 . Head of <tp:taxon-name> Pheidole sp. </tp:taxon-name> 44–45 . Thorax
                  of <tp:taxon-name> Pheidole sp. </tp:taxon-name> dorsal and lateral views. 46 .
                  Piece of stem. 47 . Pebbles. Scale bars: 40–42, 46–47 = 0.1 mm; 43–45 = 0.5 mm. </p>
            <p> Figs 48–52. <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus species. </tp:taxon-name> 48 .
                        <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus lagenipes (Karny, 1935) </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  allotype, ♂, from Colombo, Sri Lanka ( Karny 1937 : pl. 7 fig. 2; available from
                        <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name> species file). 49–52 .
                        <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. 49 . Walking
                  posture. 50 . Defending a frontal attack. 51 . Abdomen and fore-legs raised when
                  poked on thorax. 52 . Initiation of digging. Images not to scale. </p>
            <p> Burrowing </p>
            <p> Burrowing was observed by releasing an adult female into a 23.50 cm high, 21.50 cm
                  wide polypropylene tub filled with loose soil up to ⅔ the height of the tub.
                  Mainly head and legs are used in burrowing. To begin with, the forelegs were
                  firmly held against the ground to anchor the body, then the head was bent down,
                  moving forward and backward to dig up the soil, with the mandibles acting like a
                  shovel ( Fig. 52 , Supp. file 2). The dug-up soil was then pushed backwards and
                  sideways with hindlegs and midlegs respectively. In the laboratory, it made a
                  burrow that was vertical initially but turned oblique, then horizontal and nearly
                  parallel to the surface. Observed behavior suggests that the
                        <tp:taxon-name>Oryctopinae</tp:taxon-name> are subterranean, inhabiting
                  underground burrows. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
