<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Oryctopterus Karny 1937</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4746275</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AA2487F3FFB169527F1E9D4AFE3604D2</uri>
         <article-title>Two new species of the genus Oryctopterus (Orthoptera: Stenopelmatidae:
            Oryctopinae) from India, with some notes on biology</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.748.1349</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus Karny, 1937 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus Karny, 1937: 39–41 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus </tp:taxon-name> – Gorochov 2001: 6 , 20, 23–24, 26. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopus lagenipes Karny, 1935 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> Male alate, female apterous. Chestnut brown, smooth, shiny. Pronotal margins, legs and
         abdomen with bristle-like setae. Vertex broad, convex, merged with frons. Eyes small,
         acutely narrowed ventrally. A pair of lateral fenestra-like transparent portions present
         between eyes above level of antennal sockets, a similar median fenestra-like portion
         present a little below level of antennal sockets on vertex. Maxillary palps with four
         palpomeres: first small, nearly twice as long as broad; all others elongate, subequal, not
         distinctly thickened. Pronotum strongly convex; lateral and posterior margins narrowly
         bordered and explanate, anterior margin thickened, neither explanate nor narrowly
         bordered.Anterior margin distinctly emarginate, forming obtuse angle. Pronotum with deep
         anteapical transverse impression. Median longitudinal sulcus narrow, running between
         anterior and posterior margins, dividing pronotum into left and right halves. Oblique
         sulcus arises from anterolateral depression on either side, almost reaching near middle of
         posterior margin. Pronotum on either side with a weak, oblique sulcus originating from
         posterolateral corner, reaching oblique sulcus originating from anterolateral corner
         (hardly discernible in <tp:taxon-name> Ot. varuna </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ). Prosternite
         broader than long, converging posteriorly, unspined. Mesothoracic basisternum
         longitudinally sulcate along middle, deeply emarginate posteriorly, convexly raised on
         either side of middle. Metathoracic basisternum wider than long. All legs with coxa,
         trochanter, femur unarmed. Foretibia thinner than forefemur, distinctly narrowed distally
         resembling a bottle, apex of tibia with two pairs of prominent spines on each side, with
         ventral one on either side longer than dorsal; all tarsomeres unarmed dorsally; first
         tarsomere longer than rest combined, claw well developed in male, absent in female. Middle
         tibia thick, convex dorsally, with eight spines arranged in a row around apex: two lateral,
         one apical, five mesal. Hind tibia with six prominent spines arranged around apex: three
         lateral, one apical, two mesal, mesal ones larger than rest; dorsolateral and dorsomesal
         margins of metatibia with row of three to six denticles, prominent in male, distinctly
         smaller in female. First protarsomere thin, nearly rounded, 1.4–2.4 times as long as rest
         combined. Cerci hardly exceeding apex of ovipositor valves, basally with bulb-like
         sensillae at mesal side. Supragenital plate nearly as long as broad. Subgenital plate
         broader than long. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus </tp:taxon-name> can be differentiated from <tp:taxon-name>
            Oryctopus </tp:taxon-name> by the following characters: (1) males fully winged ( Figs
         1–2 , 10–12 ) (males are apterous in <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopus </tp:taxon-name> ), (2)
         anterior margin of pronotum emarginate forming obtuse angle (only slightly emarginate in
            <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopus </tp:taxon-name> ), (3) anteapical transverse groove on
         pronotum deeply impressed (weak in <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopus </tp:taxon-name> ), (4)
         foretibia distally narrowed, bottleshaped (foretibia distally not narrowed in
            <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopus </tp:taxon-name> ), (5) hind tibia with 3–6 small denticles on
         lateral and mesal margins of dorsal surface (denticles absent on lateral and mesal margins
         of dorsal surface of hind tibia in <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopus </tp:taxon-name> ). Shishodia
         et al . (2010) , in their checklist of Indian <tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name> ,
         wrongly stated that Johns (1997) synonymized <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus </tp:taxon-name>
         with <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopus </tp:taxon-name> . <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopus sordellii
         </tp:taxon-name> from Sri Lanka probably belongs to <tp:taxon-name> Oryctopterus
         </tp:taxon-name> , as the original description states that the foretibia are apically
         narrowed (“ Tibiae anticae apice magis angustatae ”) and the pronotum has a deep anteapical
         impression (“ Pronotum, excepto sulco subito post marginum anticum transverse impress ”) (
         Griffini 1914 ). Moreover, in the original description, it is specified that the holotype
         is a male that has rudimentary wings (“ rudimenta perminima elytrarum et alarum aegre
         conspicienda ”), indicating that it could be a subadult. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
