<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Troporhaconotus jacobsoni Belokobylskij &amp; Zaldívar-Riverón 2021, gen. et comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651615</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5703360337AA51E359AEB997A028A5B9</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Troporhaconotus jacobsoni
(
Szépligeti, 1908
)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 58–59
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudospathius jacobsoni
Szépligeti, 1908: 222
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Spathiohormius filicornis
Enderlein, 1912: 22
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudospathius jacobsoni
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Nixon 1943: 437

(as probably 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
). — 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1386

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus jacobsoni
</tp:taxon-name>
– Belokobylskij 2001: 133. — Belokobylskij 
et al.
2004: 89. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius filicornis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1385

. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus filicornis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Belokobylskij 1996a: 158

; 

1998b: 69

; 2001: 135 (as synonym).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
INDONESIA
• 
♀
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudospathius jacobsoni
Szépligeti, 1908
</tp:taxon-name>
; “ 
E. Jacobson
, Semarang, 
Java
, 1905”, “Holotypus ♀, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudospathius jaconsoni
Szepl. 1908
</tp:taxon-name>
”, “Hym. Typ. No 1620. Mus. Budapest”, “ 
Pseudospath Jacobsoni
” [handwriting by Szépligeti]; 
HNHM
.

</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
SRI LANKA
• 
1 ♀
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Spathiohormius filicornis
Enderlein, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
; “Ceylon, Paradna, W. Horn”, “Holotypus”, “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Spathiohormius filicornis
Enderl.
</tp:taxon-name>
♀, type, Dr. Enderlein det. 1912”, “Type”, “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus filicornis
(End.)
</tp:taxon-name>
, det. 

Belokobylskij
, 1992

”, “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus jacobsoni
(Sz.)
</tp:taxon-name>
, det. 
Belokobylskij
, 2001”; 
SDEI
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 58.
<tp:taxon-name>
Troporhaconotus jacobsoni
(
Szépligeti, 1908
)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
, ♀, holotype, HNHM. 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head, front view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Head, lateral view. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Fore tibia. 
G
. Hind coxa and femur, lateral view. 
H
. Hind tibia, lateral view. 
I
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
J
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
K
. Propodeum and first metasomal tergite, dorsal view.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 59.
<tp:taxon-name>
Troporhaconotus jacobsoni
(
Szépligeti, 1908
)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
, ♀, holotype, HNMN. 
A
. Fore wing. 
B
. Hind wing. 
C
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
D
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 7.0– 
7.5 mm
; fore wing length 
4.2–4.4 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Width 1.4–1.5 times its median length, 1.2–1.3 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye about 2.0 times as long as temple. Ocelli medium-sized, arranged in triangle with base 1.1–1.2 times its side; POL 0.7–1.0 times OD, 0.5–0.7 times OOL. Eye distinctly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.15 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.30–0.35 times height of eye, about 0.8 times basal width of mandible. Face width 0.9 times eye height and 1.2–1.3 times height of face and clypeus combined. Upper margin of clypeus situated distinctly higher than lower level of eyes. Width of hypoclypeal depression 0.7–0.9 times distance from depression to eye, 0.35–0.40 times width of face. Vertex weakly convex. Head below eyes (front view) distinctly and almost linearly narrowed. Antennae slender, weakly setiform, more then 35-segmented (apical segments missing). Scapus 1.6–1.7 times as long as its maximum width, about 4.0 times length of pedicel. First flagellar segment 4.8–5.0 times as long as its apical width, almost as long as second segment. Submedian segments 3.3–3.5 times as long as wide.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.4–2.6 times its height. Pronotal carina high and situated on or weakly behind middle of pronotum (dorsal view). Mesoscutum (dorsal view) 1.1 times as long as wide. Notauli rather deep in anterior 0.3, shallow on remaining part, rather wide, densely and distinctly crenulate with additional small and very dense granulation almost entirely. Median lobe of mesoscutum distinctly convex anteriorly. Prescutellar depression with three distinct carinae, finely rugulose to smooth on remaining parts, distinctly oblique from middle to both sides along its posterior margin, medially 0.2–0.3 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum distinctly convex, its maximum width 1.2 times median length. Subalar depression rather densely and distinctly crenulate, below fused with anterior margin of sternaulus. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) entirely distinctly and more or less densely crenulate. Propodeum weakly and almost linearly sloping backward (lateral view). Metapleural flange posteriorly with rather dense white setae.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 4.7–4.8 times its maximum width. Pterostigma 5.5 times as long as wide. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.1 times as long as pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell 3.7 times as long as wide. Radial vein (r) arising almost from middle of pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming very obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 3.1–3.3 times as long as first abscissa (r), about 0.5 times as long as the straight third abscissa (SR1), 1.5–1.7 times as long as second radiomedial vein (r-m). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell not widened distally, 3.4–3.5 times as long as wide, 0.8–0.9 times as long as the rather narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) distinctly sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) 4.8–5.0 times as long as second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M), 0.6–0.7 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) strongly curved in apical half. Medial (basal) cell sparsely setose. Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal (1-M) vein 0.2–0.3 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Brachial (subdiscal) cell closed weakly before recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla present but short; posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) absent. Hind wing 6.5–6.7 times as long as wide. Recurrent vein (m-cu) weakly curved, strongly oblique towards base of wing.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa 1.5–1.6 times as long as wide (with tubercle), 0.75 times as long as propodeum, with very dense white setae around tubercle. Hind femur about 3.0 times as long as wide. Hind tarsus 0.9 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus with lower keel and with dense long setosity along keel. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.40–0.45 times as long as basitarsus, about as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length 1.2–1.3 times as long as head and mesosoma combined, with sixth visible tergites, remaining segments not protruding behind sixth tergite. First tergite long, distinctly, almost linearly and evenly widened from base to apex; its maximum width 1.6–1.8 times minimum basal width; length 2.4–2.6 times its apical width, 1.3–1.4 times length of propodeum. Apical area of second tergite 0.5–0.6 times as long as remaining part of tergite. Median length of second tergite (with area) 1.2 times its basal width, about 2.0 times median length of third tergite. Sixth tergite strongly enlarged, weakly curved on posterior margin, without median emargination posteriorly and postero-ventral lobes. Sixth tergite 1.7–1.8 times as long as fifth tergite (till subbasal transverse furrow) and 1.8–2.0 times as long as fourth tergites. Ovipositor sheath 0.6–0.8 times as long as metasoma, 1.0–1.3 times as long as mesosoma, 0.5–0.7 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex densely granulate; frons densely granulate in posterior third, densely rugose in anterior two thirds; face densely granulate, transverse striate additionally on narrow median area; temple granulate-coriaceous in upper half and finely reticulate to almost smooth in lower half. Mesoscutum and scutellum very densely granulate; mesopleuron and metapleuron densely and small areolate-coriaceous, metapleuron coarsely rugose in posterior third. Propodeum densely granulatereticulate in anterior 0.5 (medially) or 0.7 (laterally), distinctly rugose, with distinct median (in basal half) and two lateral (almost complete) strong carinae. Hind coxa and femur densely granulate-reticulate. First tergite with distinctly separate and almost parallel dorsal carinae, with coarse and complete lateral carinae; coarsely striate with very dense and fine transverse striation or reticulation between striae, only granulate-reticulate basally on short area and laterally in basal half. Second–fifth tergites entirely distinctly striate with very dense and fine transverse striation or reticulation between striae. Sixth tergites in semi-round coarse striation, with additional small and dense reticulation in its basal half. Second–sixth tergites laterally distinctly striate with additional very dense reticulation. Vertex medially widely glabrous, with rather dense, long and semi-erect white setae arranged along posterior margin and laterally. Mesonotum glabrous on wide median areas on all lobes, with sparse, short semi-erect white setae arranged widely along notauli and in single line marginally. Mesopleuron mostly glabrous, with narrow line of long, rather dense and white setae along posterior margin. Hind tibia in inner ventral half with dense yellow setae, dorsally with rather sparse numerous long pale setae, these setae 0.7–1.0 times as long as maximum width of tibia. Laterotergites mainly glabrous.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Body black, head around eyes rather narrowly posteriorly and widely below and anteriorly red, sometimes third–sixth metasomal tergites apically reddish.Antenna light reddish brown or reddish brown basally, evenly darkened toward apex. Palps reddish brown or dark brown, becoming pale apically. Fore and middle legs reddish brown or light reddish brown, coxae paler, trochanters and trochantelli, base of tibiae and tarsi (except dark fifth segments) yellow. In hind leg, coxa and femur black, trochanters, trochantellus and most part of tibia yellowish brown or light reddish brown, tibia yellow basally and distinctly infuscate subasally and apically; tarsus yellow, fifth segment mainly almost black. Ovipositor sheath black, brown basally. Fore wing distinctly and widely maculate, hyaline in basal third, in rather narrow transverse stripes below base of pterostigma, in anterior half of radial (marginal) cell and in apical margin of wing. Pterostigma dark brown, yellow in basal third.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Indonesia
, 
Sri Lanka
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
