<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
Viereck, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
Viereck, 1911: 185
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Spathiohormius
Enderlein, 1912: 21
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
         <p>
(
type
species 
<tp:taxon-name>
Spathiohormius ornatulus
Enderlein, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
, by original designation).
</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Nixon 1943: 423

. — 

Granger 1949: 153

. — 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1384

. — 

Belokobylskij 1996a: 178

. — 

Belokobylskij &amp; Ku 2001: 37

. — 

van Achterberg 2003: 283

— Belokobylskij 
et al.
2004: 81. — 

Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto 2006: 735

; 

2009: 402

. — 

Belokobylskij &amp; Villemant 2015: 113

. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

. — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 165


.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Spathiohormius
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1384

(as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius pictipennis
Viereck, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(
Figs 28–37
)
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head usually not depressed, high, rather transverse. Vertex entirely very densely granulate. Ocelli arranged in obtuse triangle. Frons weakly concave, without median keel, usually with very fine longitudinal furrow. Eyes often with very short and sparse setae. Occipital carina dorsally complete, obliterate below and not joining ventrally with hypostomal carina. Malar suture absent. Clypeal suture rather distinct and complete. Hypoclypeal depression medium size, round. Palps rather short; maxillary palps 6-segmented, its sixth (apical) segment longer than fifth segment; labial palps short, 4-segmented, its third segment not shortened. Scapus wide, rather short, without apical lobe and basal constriction, its ventral margin (lateral view) shorter than dorsal margin. First flagellar segment subcylindrical, very weakly curved, almost as long as or weakly longer second segment. Apical segment pointed apically and without spine.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed dorso-ventral and relatively short. Neck of prothorax short. Pronotum dorsally distinctly convex, with fine and submedially situated pronotal carina; pronope absent. Propleural dorsoposterior flange long and narrow. Mesonotum relatively highly and roundly elevated above pronotum, mostly densely and distinctly granulate-coriaceous. Median lobe of mesonotum with very shallow median longitudinal furrow, without anterolateral corners. Notauli incomplete, deep in anterior half and absent or almost absent in posterior half. Tegula short, widened distally, weakly convex along its posterior margin. Prescutellar depression short, distinctly curved, with several carinae. Lateral longitudinal wing-like flanges on the level of prescutellar depression narrow and low. Scutellum more or less distinctly convex, often with lateral carinae. Metanotum with short, wide and pointed apically median tooth (lateral view). Sternaulus (precoxal sulcus) very shallow, narrow, long, running along anterior 0.5–0.6 of lower part of mesopleuron, more or less straight. Prepectal carina distinct and complete, rather wide below. Postpectal carina absent. Metapleural flange rather long, narrow, rounded apically. Propodeum without areas; lateral tubercles present, but low; propodeal bridge absent. Propodeal spiracles small and round.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Pterostigma of fore wing rather narrow and long. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Both radiomedial veins (2-SR, r-m) present. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell long and rather wide. Recurrent vein (m-cu) postfurcal or rarely subinterstitial. Discoidal (discal) cell petiolate anteriorly, petiole (1-SR) long or short. Nervulus (cu-a) almost interstitial or postfurcal, rarely weakly antefurcal, oblique towards base of wing. Brachial (subdiscal) cell weakly narrowed apically, gently curvedly closed apically usually before recurrent vein (m-cu), without antero-posterior corner. Parallel vein (CU1a) always interstitial. Transverse anal veins (2A, a) absent. Hind wing with three hamuli. Radial vein (SR) arising from costal vein (2-SC+R) far separating from basal vein (1r-m). Radial (marginal) cell without transverse vein (r). Medial (basal) cell weakly widened towards apex from base. Nervellus (cu-a) present. Submedial (subbasal) cell short; first abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.5–0.6 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent (m-cu) vein long, curved, strongly oblique towards base of wing.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore and middle tibiae with distinct thickened spines arranged in narrow stripe. All tibiae thick. Middle tarsal segments long. Hind coxa short, wide, subrounded, without basoventral corner, often without basoventral tubercle or sometimes present but small. Inner spur of hind tibia simple, 0.3 times as long as hind basitarsus. Hind femur wide, without distinct dorsal protuberance. Hind basitarsus 0.6 times as long as second-fifth segments combined. Claws short and simple.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. First tergite semi-petiolate, long, rather narrow, very densely and very small areolatepunctate. Acrosternite of first tergite weakly elongate, about 0.35–0.40 times as long as first tergite, its apical margin situated about on or weakly behind level of spiracles. Dorsope of first tergite shallow and rather small; present wide basolateral processes; spiracular tubercles often absent, spiracles situated almost in basal 0.3 of tergite; dorsal carinae absent, but present distinct and complete lateral carinae. Second tergite without basal and often without apical areas delineated by furrows. Second suture usually shallow or very shallow, rather narrow or sometimes wide, complete and evenly curved. Third tergite without transverse depression or furrow. Second and third tergites mainly very densely and very small areolate-punctate. Second to sixth tergites with distinctly separated laterotergites. Six–seven dorsally visible tergites. Fifth tergite weakly enlarged, slightly longer than previous tergite (measured from transverse subbasal furrow), not covered following apical segments. Setae on fourth–sixth tergites widely distributed laterally and almost in single submedian line medially.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
characterise by having the following combination of diagnostic morphological features: acrosternite of first metasomal segment distinctly (but not strongly) elongate; first tergite usually long and narrow; sculpture of vertex and mesoscutum densely and sometimes finely granulate-areolate; first– third metasomal tergites mainly or entirely densely areolate-reticulate; hind coxa without basoventral corner and tubercle; all tibiae (especially posterior) thickened; propodeum without any delineated areas, parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing mostly interstitial, recurrent vein (m-cu) always postfurcal, and metasoma with more than five dorsally visible tergites with usually enlarged fifth tergite.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Composition
</p>
      <p>
This genus currently consists of two subgenera, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lenticularia
van Achterberg, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
s. str.
The following species belong to the nominative subgenus: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
(
Platyspathius
) 
bisignatus
(Walker, 1860) (OR)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
clymene
Nixon, 1943
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
dice
Nixon, 1943
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
europaeus
van Achterberg, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
(PA); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
hospitus
Belokobylskij &amp; Ku, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
(PA); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
ornatulus
(
Enderlein, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>
P. dinoderi
Gahan, 1925
</tp:taxon-name>
) (PA, OR, PC); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
picardi
Belokobylskij &amp; Villemant, 2015
</tp:taxon-name>
(PA); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
pictipennis
Viereck, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
pyrene
Nixon, 1943
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
ruiliensis
Chao, 1978
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
thyone
Nixon, 1943
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
turneri
Nixon, 1943
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P.
(
P.
) 
venezuelicus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(NT).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Hosts
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dinoderus brevis
Horn, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. minutus
(Fabricius, 1775)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. ocellaris
Stephens, 1830
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sinoxylon anale
Lesne, 1897
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. senegalense
Karsch, 1881
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Bostrichidae</tp:taxon-name>
) (

Yu 
et al.
2016

); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anobium punctatum
(DeGeer, 1774)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Anobiidae</tp:taxon-name>
) (
Belokobylskij &amp; Villemant, 2015
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Afrotropical, Neotropical, Oceanic, 
Oriental
and Palaearctic regions.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
