<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus basoareolus
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 10–11
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus basoareolus
Belokobylskij, 2001: 102
</tp:taxon-name>
.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus basoareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Yu 
et al.
2016

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
♀
; Province 
Gia Lai
- 
Con Tum
, 
Buon Luoi
, 

20 km
N of Kannack

; 

17–20 Nov. 1988

; 
A. Sharkov
leg.; 
ZISP
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 

8–16 Nov. 1988

• 

1 ♀
; Province 
Ha Son Binh
, 
Ky Son
, 
Cao Phong
; 

25 Oct. 1990

, 
S. Belokobylskij
leg.; 
forest
; 
ZISP

.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus basoareolus
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
, ♀, holotype, ZISP. 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head, front view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Apical segments of antenna. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
G
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
H
. Propodeum and first to third metasomal tergites, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 11.
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus basoareolus
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
, ♀, holotype, ZISP. 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
C
. Metasoma and ovipositor, lateral view.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
MALAYSIA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Sarawak
, 3 div. 
Hillpadi, NB
–2–2; 

22 Sep. 1974

; 
D. Munroe
leg.; 
CNCI

• 

1 ♀
; 
Sarawak
, 
Santubang
; 

3–4 Jan. 1978

; 
B. Bendell
leg.; 
CNCI

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
2.5–2.7 mm
; fore wing length 2.0– 
2.3 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width 1.4–1.5 times its median length, 1.1–1.2 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 2.0–2.5 times length of temple. Ocelli small, arranged in almost equilateral triangle; POL 1.2–1.3 times OD, 0.35 times OOL. Eye glabrous, 1.1–1.2 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.40–0.45 times height of eye, almost equal to basal width of mandible. Face width 1.1–1.2 times height of eye and 1.3–1.4 times height of face and clypeus combined. Malar suture present, complete but weak. Upper margin of clypeus situated slightly upper than lower border of eyes or on same level. Hypoclypeal depression subround, its width 0.7–0.8 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.3–0.4 times width of face. Occipital carina not fused ventrally with hypostomal carina being shortly obliterated upper base of mandible. Vertex distinctly convex. Head below eyes weakly and weakly-roundly narrowed (front view). Antennae rather slender, filiform, 25–26-segmented, 1.3–1.4 times as long as body. Length of scapus 1.5–1.7 times its maximum width. First flagellar segment 4.7–5.0 times as long as its apical width, 0.80–0.95 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 4.3–4.5 times as long as wide, 0.8–0.9 times as long as first segment, 0.8 times as long as apical segment.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 1.8–2.0 times its height. Pronotal carina distinct, distances from carina to anterior and posterior margins of pronotum subequal. Notauli entirely deep, complete, sparsely crenulate. Median lobe of mesoscutum without median furrow. Prescutellar depression rather deep, weakly and roundly widened postero-laterally, with distinct median carina, smooth, 0.3 times as long as weakly convex scutellum. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) rather shallow, crenulate, weakly sinuate, running along entire lower part of mesopleuron. Prepectal carina distinct, rather wide ventrally but without widened lobes opposite fore coxae. Subalar depression deep, narrow, crenulate. Metanotum with short and acuminate posteriorly tooth (lateral view).</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing length 3.5–3.6 times its maximum width. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.3–1.4 times as long as pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming distinct obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 3.3–3.7 times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.5–0.6 times as long as the straight third abscissa (SR1), 1.5–2.2 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell weakly widened distally, its length 3.0–3.5 times maximum width, 1.4–1.6 times length of narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1- SR+M) weakly sinuate. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) weakly curved to anal vein (2-1A) in distal half. Nervulus (cu-a) postfurcal, distance between nervulus (cu-a) and basal (1-M) vein almost equal to nervulus (cu-a) length. Brachial (subdiscal) cell strongly and almost linearly closed distinctly before level of recurrent vein; posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) indistinct. Hind wing 5.8–6.2 times as long as wide. First costal abscissa 0.4–0.5 times as long as second abscissa. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) about 0.4 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) fine and strongly desclerotised.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa with rather distinct basoventral tubercle, 1.4–1.6 times as long as its wide (with tubercle). Hind femur with dorsal protuberance, its length 3.5–3.8 times maximum width. Hind tarsus 1.10–1.15 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus about 0.7 times combined length of second–fifth</p>
      <p>segments. Second tarsal segment 0.40–0.45 times as long as basitarsus, 1.2–1.3 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length slightly longer than head and mesosoma combined. First tergite distinctly, evenly and linearly widened towards subapex. Maximum width of first tergite almost 2 times its basal width, its length 1.3–1.4 times apical width, about 1.4 times length of propodeum. Median length of second tergite 0.8–0.9 times its basal width, 1.8–2.0 times length of third tergite; basal area medially 0.2 times as long as remaining part of second tergite (with apical area); apical area medially 0.6 times as long as remaining part of tergite (with basal area). Fifth tergite moderately large, with weakly and regularly rounded posterior margin, without median emargination and postero-ventral lobes. Fifth tergite 1.2–1.3 times as long as fourth tergite, 1.5–1.6 times as long as third tergite. Ovipositor sheath 0.4–0.6 times as long as metasoma, 0.6–0.8 times as long as mesosoma, about 0.3 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex and frons finely and densely granulate; face very finely granulate, smooth medially; temple smooth or very finely coriaceous along occipital carina. Mesonotum entirely densely and finely coriaceous, with two convergent medio-posteriorly striae and without rugosity between them. Scutellum finely granulate. Mesopleuron coriaceous, granulate posteriorly. Metapleuron densely granulate, rugose posteriorly. Propodeum with median carina along its entire length; basolateral areas distinctly delineated, densely granulate or coriaceous; remainder of propodeum rugulose, with distinct, at least medially, transverse median carina, areola more or less distinctly delineated. Hind coxa granulate in upper half, smooth in lower half. Hind femur mainly coriaceous, almost smooth below. First metasomal tergite with dorsal carinae fused in basal 0.2 of tergite, then united carina following to apex of tergite. First and second tergites striate, second tergite smooth basally, finely or very finely rugulose in apical area. Third and fourth tergites in its basal 0.7 striate with rugulosity between striae, smooth in apical ⅓. Fifth tergite striate in basal its 0.2–0.3, rugulose-coriaceous medially, almost smooth in apical ⅓, but sometimes tergite here finely or very finely transversely striate-coriaceous. Second–fourth tergites laterally coriaceous-striate (especially below) or only coriaceous with granulation partly. Vertex with rather long and very sparse semi-erect setae directed forward. Mesoscutum with rather dense, semierect, white setae arranged along notauli and marginally. Hind tibia dorsally with semi-erect and rather sparse white setae; length of these setae 1.2–1.5 times maximum width of hind tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Body dark reddish brown and partly reddish brown; pronotum and metasoma dorsally partly light reddish brown, sometimes metasoma entirely medially light reddish brown. Antenna brown to almost black, two basal segments brownish yellow. Palps pale yellow. Legs brownish yellow or yellow; hind coxae sometimes darker basally or entirely. Ovipositor sheath dark brown, yellow or pale brown basally. Wings almost hyaline. Pterostigma brown or pale brown, yellow in basal quarter.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Vietnam
, 
Malaysia
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
