<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Mimipodoryctes Belokobylskij
            2000</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651680</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD3D5F55FDA3E49E3F433B7D</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
            Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Mimipodoryctes Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Mimipodoryctes Belokobylskij, 2000: 348 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Mimipodoryctes </tp:taxon-name> – Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto 2006: 704 ;
         2009: 305 . — Yu et al. 2016 . — Jasso-Martínez et al. 2019: 165 . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Mimipodoryctes robustus Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name> (=
            <tp:taxon-name> Rhyssalus rubriceps Cameron, 1909 </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description ( Figs 24–25 ) </p>
      <p>HEAD. Head not depressed, transverse. Ocelli arranged in weakly obtuse triangle. Frons not
         concave, without median keel or furrow. Eyes glabrous. Occipital carina complete dorsally,
         joined below with hypostomal carina above base of mandible. Malar suture indistinct.
         Clypeal suture complete, deep laterally and shallow upper. Hypoclypeal depression
         medium-sized and subround. Postgenal bridge narrow. Palps long; maxillary palps
         6-segmented, its sixth segment about as long as fifth segment; labial palps 4-segmented,
         its third segment not shortened. Scapus of antenna rather wide and long, without apical
         lobe and basal constriction; its ventral margin (lateral view) not longer than dorsal
         margin. First flagellar segment subcylindrical, almost straight, longer than second
         segment. Apical segment acuminate apically, without spine.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed and rather long. Neck of prothorax rather short. Pronotum
         dorsally almost flat, with distinct submedian pronotal carina; pronope absent. Propleural
         dorsoposterior lobe rather long and wide. Mesonotum highly, gently and roundly elevated
         above pronotum; entirely distinctly rugose-granulate and entirely cover by dense setae.
         Median lobe of mesonotum without median longitudinal furrow and anterolateral corners.
         Notauli entirely rather deep, complete, densely and distinctly crenulate. Tegula widened
         distally, weakly convex along its posterior margin. Prescutellar depression long, rather
         deep, with several carinae. Lateral longitudinal wing-like flanges on level of prescutellar
         depression rather high. Scuto-scutellar suture distinct and complete. Scutellum weakly
         convex, with distinct lateral carinae at least in basal half. Metanotum with short, but
         distinct and subpointed median tooth or sometimes without it. Mesopleural pit deep, round,
         connected with mesopleural suture. Sternaulus (precoxal sulcus) rather deep, narrow, long,
         weakly curved, almost smooth. Prepectal carina distinct and complete, weakly widened below
         opposite fore coxae. Postpectal carina absent. Metapleural flange long, narrow and rounded
         apically, covered by very dense white setae. Propodeum with basolateral areas distinctly
         delineated by carinae, without areola; lateral tubercles small; propodeal bridge absent.
         Propodeal spiracles small and round.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Pterostigma of fore wing wide. Radial vein (r) arising almost from middle of
         pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Both radiomedial veins (2-SR, r-m)
         present. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell rather short and wide. Recurrent vein (m-cu)
         postfurcal or sometimes almost interstitial. Discoidal (discal) cell petiolate anteriorly,
         petiole (1-SR) rather long; basal (1-M) and recurrent (m-cu) veins subparallel. Nervulus
         (cu-a) postfurcal. Brachial (subdiscal) cell rather strongly, obliquely and linearly closed
         apically distinctly behind recurrent vein (m-cu). Parallel vein (CU1a) not interstitial,
         arising almost from or slightly before or behind middle of brachial vein (CU1b). Transverse
         anal veins (2A, a) absent. Hind wing with three hamuli. Radial vein (SR) arising from
         costal vein (2-SC+R) distinctly far from basal vein (1r-m). Radial (marginal) cell
         subparallel in basal half and very weakly roundly narrowed toward apex, without additional
         transverse vein (r). Medial (basal) cell distinctly widened towards apex, 0.45–0.50 times
         as long as hind wing. Nervellus (cu-a) present. Submedial (subbasal) cell medium sized.
         First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.6–0.9 times as long as second abscissa (1-M).
         Recurrent vein (m-cu) rather short, antefurcal, strongly oblique towards base of wing,
         weakly sclerotised.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore and middle tibiae with rather dense short and thick spines arranged in narrow
         stripe. Middle tarsal segments rather short. Hind coxa rather short and wide, with distinct
         basoventral corner and tubercle. All femora with more or less distinct dorsal
         protuberances. Hind femur wide. Inner spur of hind tibia almost entirely shortly setose,
         about 0.3 times as long as hind basitarsus. Hind basitarsus 0.7–0.9 times as long as
         second–fifth segments combined. Claws short, thick and simple.</p>
      <p> METASOMA. Metasoma with six (female) or seven (male) visible, coarsely sclerotised and
         sculptured tergites. First metasomal tergite not petiolate, wide, immovably fused with
         second tergite in female, not fused in male (see laterally). Acrosternite of first segment
         about 0.2 times as long as first tergite, its apical margin placed distinctly before
         spiracles. Dorsope of first tergite small but distinct; usually present short and rather
         wide basolateral lobes; spiracular tubercles indistinct, spiracles situated in basal third
         of tergite; dorsal carinae usually complete. Second suture distinct and deep. Second
         tergite with short or sometimes very short (almost indistinct) semi-oval basal area, with
         narrow apical area delineated anteriorly by fine furrow and different type of sculpture.
         Third tergite without transverse depression or furrow. Second–sixth tergites with separate
         laterotergites. Sixth tergite of female rather large, often with median emargination on
         posterior margin, longer than previous tergite, covered the following segments. Hypopygium
         small, obtuse medioposteriorly. Ovipositor shorter or longer than metasoma. Apical part of
         ovipositor with single or two small dorsal nodes and serrate ventrally. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Mimipodoryctes Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name> is morphologically
         similar to <tp:taxon-name> Ipodoryctes Granger, 1949 </tp:taxon-name> but differs from the
         latter genus by having immovably fused first and second metasomal tergites in females. This
         genus differs from <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name> , also
         having immovably fused first and second metasomal tergites, by parallel vein (CU1a) of fore
         wing not interstitial (vs interstitial), first and second tergites of male not fused
         immovably (vs fused in male), mesopleuron entirely densely pubescent (vs not entirely and
         sparsely setose), first abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) of hind wing long (vs short),
         laterotergites entirely coved by long and dense setae (vs almost glabrous) and vertex and
         mesoscutum striate or rugose-granulate (vs usually granulate). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Composition </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Mimipodoryctes korotyaevi (Belokobylskij, 1996) (OR) </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> M. peregrinus (Belokobylskij, 1994) (OR) </tp:taxon-name> ;
            <tp:taxon-name> M. rokkoensis Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2006 </tp:taxon-name> (PA);
            <tp:taxon-name> M. rubriceps ( Cameron, 1909 ) (OR, AU) </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p> Hosts </p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Australasian, Oriental and Palaearctic regions. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> Only one species of <tp:taxon-name> Mimipodoryctes </tp:taxon-name> was included in
         molecular phylogenetic study by Jasso-Martínez et al . (2019) , whereas no specimens of
            <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus </tp:taxon-name> were examined. However, some morphological
         characters of these two genera suggest their close relationship. </p>
      <p> A key to all described species <tp:taxon-name> Mimipodoryctes </tp:taxon-name> was
         published by Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto (2009: 306) . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
