<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Rhacontsira Belokobylskij 1998</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651728</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27ADFD5F94FD9AE79F3F533AAD</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
Belokobylskij, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
Belokobylskij, 1998b: 2
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
</tp:taxon-name>
– Belokobylskij 
et al.
2004: 89. — 

Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto 2006: 739

; 

2009: 453

. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

. — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 165


.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ontsira heterospiloides
Belokobylskij, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(
Figs 49–57
)
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head transverse, not depressed. Ocelli arranged in obtuse triangle with base usually larger than their sides, but rarely in almostequilateral triangle. Frons not concave. Eyes glabrous. Occipital carina complete, lower often fused with hypostomal carina upper base of mandible. Malar suture usually absent, but sometimes present and and shallow or very shallow. Clypeal suture distinct and almost completre. Clypeus with distinct flange along lower margin. Hypoclypeal depression rather small, oval or round. Postgenal bridge present but very narrow. Palps rather long; maxillary palps 6-segmented, labial palps 4-segmented. Scapus of antenna rather thick and short, without apical lobe and basal constriction. Pedicel relatively enlarged. Flagellum slender; first flagellar segment sometimes shorter than second segment, but usually subequal or weakly longer than it.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Neck of prothorax short; pronotal keel usually distinct, but not connected with anterior margin of mesoscutum; dorsoposterior propleural lobe distinct. Mesonotum usually highly and almost vertically elevated above pronotum. Median lobe of mesoscutum without anterolateral corners and usually without medial longitudinal furrow. Notauli complete, sculptured, deep entirely or sometimes in anterior half only. Prescutellar depression relatively long, sculptured or smooth, with median carina. Scutellum weakly convex, without lateral carinae. Metanotum with short and pointed or obtuse median tooth (lateral view). Mesopleural pit distinct. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) shallow, usually long, almost straight or sunuate, mostly crenulate. Prepectal carina distinct and complete. Propodeum with basolateral areas and usually with areola deliniated by distinct carinae; lateral tubercles and propodeal bridge absent. Propodeal spiracles small and round.</p>
      <p>WINGS.Pterostigma of fore wing rather wide. Radial vein (r) arising from or behind middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Both radiomedial veins (2-SR, r-m) present. Recurrent vein (mcu) antefurcal, rarely almost interstitial. Nervulus (cu-a) postfurcal. Discoidal (discal) cell petiolate, petiole (1-SR) short. Parallel vein (CU1a) not interstitial, arising from anterior third or almost middle of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell. Brachial (subdiscal) cell narrow, closed distally behind recurrent vein (m-cu). Transverse anal veins (2A, a) absent. Longitudinal anal vein (2-1A) with short abscissa behind brachial vein (CU1b). In hind wing, radial (marginal) cell almost parallel-sided, without additional transverse vein (r). Medial (basal) cell rather narrow or wide distally, 0.4–0.5 times as long as wing. Submedial (subbasal) cell short; first abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.5–0.7 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) present, but usually finely sclerotised.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore and middle tibiae with numerous and small relatively dispersed spines. Hind coxa with distinct basoventral corner and tubercle. All femora with lower dorsal protuberances. Hind femur widened. Hind basitarsus 0.6–0.8 times as long as second–fifth segments combined.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma with at least six visible tergites, following tergites shortly protruding behind sixth one. First tergite usually rather short and wide; dorsope distinct; present small and narrow basolateral lobes; spiracular tubercles indistinct or small, spiracles placed in basal third of tergite. Acrosternite of first segment about 0.20–0.25 times as long as first tergite, its apical margin situated distinctly before spiracles. Second suture distinct and straight. Second tergite with almost straight, shallow of rather deep transverse furrow in apical third separating apical sublenticular area. Second–sixth tergites with separate laterotergites. Sometimes fourth or fifth segment at least weakly largened. Ovipositor shorter or longer than metasoma.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
</tp:taxon-name>
is morphologically similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotinus
</tp:taxon-name>
, but differs from it by having the recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing antefurcal to the first radiomedial vein (2-SR) (vs always postfurcal); the parallel vein (CU1a) not interstitial and arising from the middle or anterior third of the vein (3-CU1) closed brachial (subdiscal) cell distally (vs predominantly interstitial); metasoma behind third tergite mainly or entirely smooth (vs posterior tergites often sculptured at least basally); the first flagellar segment of antenna shorter, almost equal or weakly longer than second segment (vs always longer than second segment).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Composition
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira haeselbarthi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. heterospiloides
(Belokobylskij, 1988) (PA)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. insulicola
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
(PA); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. mozambiquensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. nana
Belokobylskij, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. sculpturator
Belokobylskij, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. toamasina
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. toyota
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
(PA); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. variegata
Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
(AU); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. yamagishii
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
(PA).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Hosts
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Afrotropical, Australasian 
Oriental
and Palaearctic regions.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Vertex entirely finely coriaceous (
Fig. 56C
). Apical segments of antenna white, contrastingly lighter than previous segments (
Figs 56A, E
). Second metasomal tergite with very short and smooth basal area (
Fig. 57B
). Body length 5.0 mm. 
Madagascar
....................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. toamasina
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Vertex at least partly striate, rarely mainly smooth, never coriaceous (
Figs 49C
, 
51B
, 
52C, G
, 
54C
). Apical segments of antenna dark, same colour as previous segments (
Figs 51F
, 
52F
, 
54E
). Second metasomal tergite without distinct basal area (
Figs 50C
, 
51H
, 
53B
, 
55B
) ....................................... 2

</p>
      <p>

2. Head (dorsal view) less distinctly and convex-roundly narrowed behind eyes (
Figs 49C
, 
51B
). Temple long, transverse diameter of eye 1.5–1.6 times as long as temple (
Figs 49C
, 
51B
). First flagellar segment 0.80–0.85 times as long as second segment (
Figs 49D
, 
51E
) .............................. 3

</p>
      <p>

– Head (dorsal view) rather strongly and weakly-roundly narrowed behind eyes (
Figs 52C, G
, 
54C
). Temple short, transverse diameter of eye 1.8–2.2 times as long as temple (
Figs 52C, G
, 
54C
). First flagellar segment almost as long as or only a little shorter than second segment (
Figs 52E
, 
54D
) .... ........................................................................................................................................................... 4

</p>
      <p>

3. Malar space 0.3 times height of eye and 0.5–0.6 times basal width of mandible (
Fig. 49B
). Pronotal carina situated submedially on pronotum (dorsal view) (
Fig. 49E
). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) of fore wing 0.80–0.85 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR) (
Fig. 50A
). Hind femur 3.2 times as long as wide (
Fig. 49G
). Ovipositor sheath 2.0 times as long as mesosoma and 0.75 times as long as fore wing (
Fig. 49A
). Body length 
2.1–2.2 mm
. Eastern Palaearctic: 
Japan
, 
Russia
............................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. heterospiloides
(Belokobylskij, 1988)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Malar space 0.45 times height of eye and 0.9 times basal width of mandible (
Fig. 51D
). Pronotal carina situated on pronotum more closely to mesoscutum (dorsal view). Second radial abscissa (3- SR) of fore wing 1.1 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR) (
Fig. 51I
). Hind femur 3.7 times as long as wide. Ovipositor sheath 1.3 times as long as mesosoma and 0.55 times as long as fore wing (
Fig. 51A
). Body length 
1.8 mm
. Afrotropics: 
South Africa
............. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. haeselbarthi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

4. Frons entirely distinctly and densely striate (
Figs 52B, C, G
). Mesosoma 1.4–1.6 times as long as high (
Fig. 52H
). Metapleural flange posteriorly with very dense pubescence (
Fig. 52H
). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell 1.2–1.4 times as long as brachial (subdiscal) cell. Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 0.7–0.9 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR) (
Figs 52K
, 
53A
). First tergite shorter or almost as long as its apical width (
Fig. 53B
). Areola of propodeum almost indistinct (
Fig. 52I
) ........................................................................................................................................... 5

</p>
      <p>

– Frons at least partly or almost entirely rugulose-reticulate with punctation or granulation, often medially or laterally smooth (
Figs 54B–C, F
). Mesosoma 1.7–1.9 times as long as high (
Fig. 54G
). Metapleural flange posteriorly with sparce pubescence (
Fig. 54G
). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell 1.4–1.8 times as long as brachial (subdiscal) cell. Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 0.9–1.2 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR) (
Fig. 55A
). First tergite 1.1–1.5 times as long as its apical width (
Fig. 55B
). Areola of propodeum distinctly delineated (
Fig. 54F
) ..................... 6

</p>
      <p>

5. First flagellar segment thick, 3.8–4.3 times as long as its apical width and not longer than second segment. Ocelli arranged in almost equilateral triangle. Frons entirely distinctly and densely oblique striae (Figs.). First metasomal tergite almost as long as its maximum width. Body length 1.5–3.0 mm. Eastern Palaearctic: 
Japan
................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. insulicola
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– First flagellar segment slender, 5.2 times as long as its apical width and 1.1 times as long as second segment (
Fig. 52E
). Ocelli arranged in triangle with base 1.3 times its sides (
Fig. 52C
). Frons rugose-granulate and with curved longitudinal carinae laterally (
Fig. 52C
). First metasomal tergite 0.8 times as long as its maximum width (
Fig. 53B
). Body length 
3.3–3.6 mm
. Afrotropics: 
Mozambique
........................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. mozambiquensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
6. Frons mostly smooth, only narrowly anteriorly with fine sculpture. Prescutellar depression smooth or almost smooth. Hind femur 3.6–4.0 times as long as its width .................................................... 7
</p>
      <p>

– Frons entirely or at least laterally and widely anteriorly densely striate or rugulose-reticulate with punctation (
Figs 54B, C
). Prescutellar depression distinctly sculptured (
Fig. 54F
). Hind femur 3.2– 3.6 times as long as its width (
Fig. 54H
) .......................................................................................... 8

</p>
      <p>

7. Ovipositor sheath shorter, as long as metasoma, 1.3 times as long as mesosoma, 0.5 times as long as fore wing. Length of first metasomal tergite of female 1.5 times its apical width. Body length 
1.7 mm
. 
Vietnam
....................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. nana
Belokobylskij, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Ovipositor sheath longer, 1.3–1.5 times as long as metasoma, twice longer than mesosoma, 0.80– 0.85 times as long as fore wing. Length of first metasomal tergite of female 1.2–1.3 times its apical width. Body length 1.6–2.0 mm. 
Japan
..................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. yamagishii
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

8. Body entirely or mainly brownish yellow (
Fig. 54A
). Fore wing hyaline (
Fig. 55A
). Antenna 18–20-segmented (
Fig. 54A
). Body length 
1.7 mm
. 
Vietnam
..................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Body entirely or mainly black, partly with reddish tint, rarely head below and mesonotum partly lightly reddish brown. Fore wing infuscate. Antenna 22–23-segmented. Body length 
2.1–2.9 mm
....................................................................................................................................... 9

</p>
      <p>

9. Temple almost entirely rugulose-reticulate. Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing arising almost from middle of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell. Pterostigma entirely dark brown. Body length 
2.9 mm
. 
Vietnam
..................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. sculpturator
Belokobylskij, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Temple entirely smooth. Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing arising distinctly before middle of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell. Pterostigma brown, yellow or pale brown basally and sometimes apically ............................................................................................................................................ 10
</p>
      <p>

10. Vertex mainly finely striate-coriaceous, only coriaceous laterally, almost smooth in small anterolateral areas. Frоns without longitudinal median саrinа. First flagellar segment 4.6 times as long as its apical width. Prоnоtаl keel distinct. Mesopleuron behind deep posterior part of sternaulus till middle coxa with shallow, narrow and longitudinally striate furrow. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell 2.6 times as long as maximum width. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.3 times as long as basitarsus. Body length 
2.4 mm
. 
Japan
............................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. toyota
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Vertex finely transverse striate in anterior 0.5–0.7, smooth posteriorly. Frоns with longitudinal median саrinа. First flagellar segment 5.0–5.5 times as long as its apical width. Prоnоtаl keel vеrу finе. Mesopleuron behind deep posterior part of sternaulus without furrow. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell 3.5 times as long as maximum width. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.45–0.50 times as long as basitarsus. Body length 
2.1–2.8 mm
. 
Australia
........................................................ ............................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. variegata
Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
