<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Arhaconotus Belokobylskij
            2000</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651646</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD745F1DFD9EE1143E913AAD</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
            Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus Belokobylskij, 2000: 345 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus </tp:taxon-name> – Belokobylskij 2001: 157.— Belokobylskij et
         al. 2004: 22. — Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto 2009: 59 . — Tang et al. 2010: 63 . — Yu et al.
         2016 . — Jasso-Martínez et al. 2019: 165 . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus papuanus Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name> , by original
         designation. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description ( Figs 3–4 ) </p>
      <p>HEAD. Head not depressed, high, transverse. Ocelli arranged almost in equilateral triangle.
         Frons not concave, without median keel or furrow. Eyes glabrous. Occipital carina complete
         dorsally, joined ventrally below with hypostomal carina. Malar suture fine. Clypeal suture
         distinct and complete. Clypeus with short ventral flange. Hypoclypeal depression
         medium-sized, round. Postgenal bridge narrow. Palps long; maxillary palps 6-segmented, its
         fifth segment longest, 1.4 times as long as sixth (apical) segment; labial palps
         4-segmented, its third segment not shortened. Scapus wide and short, without apical lobe
         and basal constriction; its ventral margin (lateral view) not longer than dorsal margin.
         First flagellar segment subcylindrical, almost straight, weakly longer than second
         segment.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed and relatively long. Neck of prothorax short. Pronotum
         dorsally almost flat, with distinct submedian pronotal carina. Pronope absent. Propleural
         dorsoposterior flange rather short and not wide. Mesonotum high, gently and roundly
         elevated above pronotum, mainly smooth. Median lobe of mesonotum with median longitudinal
         furrow in posterior half, without anterolateral corner. Notauli entirely deep and complete.
         Tegula short, widened distally, weakly convex along its posterior margin. Prescutellar
         depression deep, long, with several carinae. Lateral longitudinal winglike flanges situated
         on level of prescutellar depression low. Scuto-scutellar suture rather distinct and
         complete. Scutellum weakly convex, without lateral carinae. Metanotum with short, but
         distinct and pointed median tooth posteriorly. Mesopleural pit deep, subround, connected
         with mesopleural suture. Sternaulus (precoxal sulcus) rather deep, not wide, long, running
         along whole length of lower part of mesopleuron, almost straight, smooth. Prepectal carina
         distinct and complete, high below opposite coxae, laterally following up till subalar
         furrow. Postpectal carina absent. Metapleural flange rather long, wide, round apically.
         Propodeum with distinctly delineated by carinae basolateral areas and areola; lateral
         tubercles and propodeal bridge absent. Propodeal spiracles small and round.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Pterostigma of fore wing wide. Radial vein (r) arising almost from middle of
         pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Both radiomedial veins (2-SR, r-m)
         present. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell long and narrow. Recurrent vein (m-cu)
         weakly postfurcal. Discoidal (discal) cell petiolate anteriorly, petiole (1-SR) rather
         long. Nervulus (cu-a) postfurcal. Brachial (subdiscal) cell gently and almost linearly
         closed apically before recurrent vein (m-cu). Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial. Transverse
         anal veins (2A, a) absent. Hind wing with three hamuli. First abscissa of costal vein
         (C+SC+R) 0.4 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). Radial vein (SR) arising from
         costal vein (2-SC+R) not far separating from basal vein (1r-m). Radial (marginal) cell
         subparallel-sided, without transverse vein (r). Medial (basal) cell distinctly widened
         towards apex, about 9.0 times as long as its wide, 0.45 times as long as hind wing.
         Nervellus (cu-a) present. Submedial (subbasal) cell short. First abscissa of mediocubital
         vein (M+CU) 0.5–0.6 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) short,
         antefurcal, strongly oblique towards base of wing, unclerotised.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore and middle tibiae with dense short and thick spines arranged almost in single
         row. Fore tarsus 1.5 times as long as fore tibia. Middle tarsal segments rather short. Hind
         coxa rather long and wide, with distinct basoventral corner and tubercle. All femora with
         more or less distinct dorsal protuberances. Hind tibia with spine with single row of dense
         white setae in inner distal margin. Hind femur wide. Inner spur of hind tibia rather long,
         glabrous, but with row of setae on basal half, 0.2 times as long as hind basitarsus; outer
         spur short, about 0.5 times as long as inner spur. Hind basitarsus about 0.9 times as long
         as second–fifth segments combined. Claws short and simple.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Widened from base till end of fore tergite, then rather evenly narrowed to apex,
         with six visible tergites, but seventh tergite also weakly protruding behind sixth tergite.
         First metasomal tergite not petiolate, wide, immovably fused with second tergite in both
         sexes. Acrosternite of first segment about 0.2 times as long as first tergite, its apical
         margin placed distinctly before spiracles. Dorsope of first tergite small but distinct;
         present short and wide basolateral lobes; spiracular tubercles indistinct, spiracles placed
         in basal third of tergite; dorsal carinae complete and parallel. Second suture deep,
         regularly curved, without lateral bends. Second tergite with short semi-oval basal area,
         with long lenticular apical area delineated by deep concave furrow. Third tergite without
         transverse depression or furrow. Second–sixth tergites with separate laterotergites. Sixth
         tergite of female not enlarged, without transformations, not or only weakly longer than
         previous tergite, not entirely covered following apical segments. Hypopygium small, pointed
         medioposteriorly. Ovipositor almost as long as metasoma. Apical part of ovipositor with two
         small dorsal nodes and serrate ventrally.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> This genus is very similar to <tp:taxon-name> Bathycentor Saussure, 1892 </tp:taxon-name>
         but differs from it mainly immovably fused first and second metasomal tergites in both
         sexes (vs not fused), the interstitial position of parallel vein (CU1a) in fore wing (vs
         not interstitial) and postfurcal position of recurrent vein (m-cu) (vs antefurcal). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Composition </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus hainanensis Tang &amp; Chen, 2010 </tp:taxon-name> (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> A. ishigakiensis Belokobylskij, 2001 </tp:taxon-name> (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> A. papuanus Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name> (AU); <tp:taxon-name>
            A. vietnamicus Belokobylskij, 2001 </tp:taxon-name> (OR). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p> Hosts </p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Australasian and Oriental regions. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remark </p>
      <p> A key to all described species of <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus </tp:taxon-name> was
         published by Tang et al. (2010: 67) . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
