<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ipodoryctes (Afroipodoryctes) saintphilippensis Belokobylskij &amp; Zaldívar-Riverón 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651674</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/DAEAAF433EE6C4FE0A985186DAD157A2</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
(
Afroipodoryctes
) 
saintphilippensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D1CDBBD2-2E82-402B-88E5-4CFBAC361C70
</p>
      <p>
Figs 20–21
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Named from Saint Philippe locality in 
Reunion Island
, where all 
type
material was collected.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
REUNION
• 
♀
; “La Reunion, ML 207 

350 m

, Saint Philippe”, “Mare Longue, 

13/19.IX.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “forêt primaire, piege Malaise, au sol site 1”; 
MNHM
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
REUNION
• 
1 ♀
; “La Reunion, ML 19 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

20/26.II.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “ 
forêt primaire
, 
piege Malaise
, suspendu site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 33 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

10/16.III.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “ 
forêt primaire
, 
piege Malaise
, suspendu site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 53 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

03/09.IV.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “ 
forêt primaire
, 
piege Malaise
, suspendu site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 90 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

16/22.V.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “ 
forêt primaire
, 
piege Malaise
, suspendu site 1”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 157 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 2/ 

8.VIII.2001

, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “ 
forêt primaire
, 
piege Malaise
, suspendu site 2”; 
IB-UNAM

• 

2 ♂♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 178 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

20/26.VIII.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “ 
forêt primaire
, 
piege Malaise
, suspendu site 1”; 
MNHM
, 
IB-UNAM

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 214 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

19/25.IX.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “forêt primaire, piege Malaise, suspendu site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 221 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

25.IX/01

.X.2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “forêt primaire, piege Malaise, au sol site 2”; 
ZISP

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 245 

320 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

13/19.X.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “plantation ONF, piege Malaise, au sol site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 248 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

19/25.X.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “forêt primaire, piege Malaise, suspendu site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♀
[without metasoma]; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 255 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

25/31.X.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “forêt primaire, piege Malaise, suspendu site 1”, “RUS43 [= Jo929]”; 
MNHM

• 

2 ♂♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, ML 297 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

30.XI/06

.XII.2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “forêt primaire, piege Malaise, suspendu site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♀
“ 
La Reunion
, ML 266 

320 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

31.X/06

.XI.2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “plantation ONF, piege Malaise, suspendu site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♀
“ 
La Reunion
, ML 287 

320 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

18/24.XI.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “plantation ONF, piege Malaise, au sol site 1”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♀
“ 
La Reunion
, ML 308 

320 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

06/12.XII.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “plantation ONF, piege Malaise, au sol site 2”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♀
“ 
La Reunion
, ML 329 

320 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

24/30.XII.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “plantation ONF, piege Malaise, au sol site 2”; 
ZISP

• 

1 ♀
“ 
La Reunion
, ML 312 

350 m

, 
Saint Philippe
”, “ 
Mare Longue
, 

12/18.XII.

2001, 
Attie Marc
leg”, “forêt primaire, piege Malaise, au sol site 1”; 
MNHM

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
La Reunion
, 
Saint-Denis
, 
Colorado
650 m

”, “vegetation secondaire, 

22. iii.2003

, Delvare G.”, “forêt primaire, piege Malaise, suspendu site 1”; 
MNHM

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 20.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
(
Afroipodoryctes
) 
saintphilippensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀, holotype, MNHM. 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head and mesoscutum, dorsal view. 
C
. Head, front view. 
D
. Head and basal segments of antenna, lateral view. 
E
. Apical segments of antenna. 
F
. Mesosoma and first metasomal tergite, dorsal view. 
G
. Head and mesosoma, lateral view. 
H
. Hind coxa and femur. 
I
. Hind tibia.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 21.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
(
Afroipodoryctes
) 
saintphilippensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♀, holotype, MNHM. 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
C
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
2.1–3.2 mm
; fore wing length 
1.9–2.7 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width 1.5–1.6 times its median length, about 1.1 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) distinctly and roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 1.8–2.2 times as long as temple. Ocelli small, arranged in almost equilateral triangle; POL 1.2–1.3 times OD, 0.4–0.5 times OOL. Eye weakly emarginated opposite antennal socket, 1.2 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.25–0.30 times height of eye, 0.7–0.8 times basal width of mandible. Face width 0.9 times eye height and 1.4–1.5 times height of face and clypeus combined. Upper margin of clypeus situated weakly higher than lower level of eyes. Width of hypoclypeal depression 0.9–1.0 times distance from depression to eye, 0.4 times width of face. Vertex convex. Head below eyes (front view) strongly and weakly-roundly narrowed. Antennae slender, almost filiform, 22–29-segmented, 1.2–1.3 times as long as body. Scapus 1.5–1.6 times as long as its maximum width, about 2.0 times length of pedicel. First flagellar segment 4.5–5.3 times as long as its apical width, about 1.1 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 4.7– 5.3 times as long as its width, 0.7–0.8 times as long as first segment, about 0.9 times as long as apical segment.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.2–2.4 times its height. Pronotal carina high, situated submedially. Mesoscutum (dorsal view) 0.9 times as long as wide. Notauli distinct and rather deep in anterior half, fine and shallow in posterior half, rather narrow, densely crenulate with granulation partly. Median lobe of mesoscutum distinctly convex anteriorly. Prescutellar depression shallow, with 3–5 carinae, finely granulatereticulate, weakly curved along posterior margin, 0.4 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum almost as long as its maximum width. Subalar depression weakly and shortly crenulate. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) entirely smooth, with subround distinct pit posteriorly. Prepectal carina below without low lobes opposite fore coxae. Propodeum weakly arcuately sloping backward (lateral view). Metapleural flange posteriorly with very sparse long setae.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 3.6–3.8 times its maximum width. Pterostigma 3.8–4.0 times as long as wide. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.3–1.4 times as long as pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell 3.6–3.8 times as long as wide. Radial vein (r) arising weakly before middle of pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming obtuse corner with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 3.3–3.8 times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.6 times as long as the straight third abscissa (SR1), 1.4–1.5 times as long as second radiomedial vein (r-m). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell long, not widened distally, 3.2–3.3 times as long as wide, 1.4–1.5 times as long as the narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1- SR+M) weakly sinuate. Second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M) short. Recurrent vein (m-cu) 3.5–4.0 times as long as second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M), 0.6 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) almost straight. Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal (1-M) vein almost equal to nervulus (cu-a) length. Parallel vein (CU1a) not interstitial, arising from anterior 0.2–0.3 of vein closed brachial (subdiscal) cell distally. Brachial (subdiscal) cell closed weakly behind recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla present but short; posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) very short. Hind wing 4.8–5.6 times as long as wide. Recurrent vein (m-cu) curved, oblique towards base of wing, antefurcal.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa about 2.0 times as long as wide, 0.8–0.9 times as long as propodeum. Hind femur 2.8–3.0 times as long as wide. Hind tarsus 0.90–0.95 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus without keel, with dense and distinct pale setosity. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.4 times as long as basitarsus, as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length 1.1 times as long as head and mesosoma combined, with sixth visible tergites, remaining segments weakly protruding behind sixth tergite. First tergite distinctly, evenly and weakly convexly widened from base to apex. Maximum width of tergite 2.2–2.4 times its minimum basal width; length 1.15–1.20 times its apical width, 1.1 times length of propodeum. Basal area of second tergite weakly delineated by shallow furrow, 0.30–0.35 times as long as remaining part of tergite; apical area 0.6–0.7 times as long as remaining part of tergite. Median length of second tergite (with areas) 0.6 times its basal width, 1.4–1.5 times median length of third tergite. Second suture distinctly sinuate. Sixth tergite not enlarged, almost straight in posterior margin, without median emargination and posteroventral lobes. Sixth tergite 0.7–0.8 times as long as fifth tergite; fifth tergite 1.1–1.3 times as long as fourth tergites. Ovipositor sheath 0.5–0.6 times as long as metasoma, 0.70–0.85 times as long as mesosoma, 0.30–0.35 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Head mostly smooth, only face partly punctate. Prothorax mostly smooth, its sides partly finely rugose. Mesoscutum and scutellum entirely densely granulate; mesoscutum rugose but without striae in its medioposterior third. Mesopleuron almost entirely smooth. Metapleuron very finely rugulose in anterior half, distinctly rugose-reticulate in posterior half. Propodeum mainly smooth, with large smooth or partly finely reticulate basolateral areas; areola short and wide, finely rugulose, 1.0–1.2 times as long as its maximum width; median carina 1.2–1.3 times as long as anterior fork of areola. Hind legs mainly smooth. First tergite mainly rugulose-reticulate and partly with sparse longitudinal and weakly curved striae, smooth on small medio-apical area. Second tergite interruptedly rugose-striate with smooth basal and apical areas, distinctly crenulate on furrows and suture. Remaining tergites smooth, but fourth tergite distinctly crenulate on subbasal transverse furrow. Third–sixth tergites laterally entirely smooth. Vertex mainly glabrous, with sparse, short and semi-erect pale setae posteriorly and laterally. Mesonotum almost completely in short semi-erect yellow setae. Mesopleuron mostly glabrous. Hind tibia dorsally with rather dense, long and short semi-erect white setae, its length about 0.4–0.6 times as long as maximum width of tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head dark reddish brown to black. Metasoma mostly reddish brown with darks sports ventrally and on mesopleuron. Metasoma reddish brown to light reddish brown. Antenna dark reddish brown, 6–7 basal segments reddish brown. Palps yellow. Legs yellow with brownish tint. Ovipositor sheath dark</p>
      <p>brown to black. Fore wing distinctly and almost evenly infuscate. Pterostigma mainly brown and partly pale or yellow and partly brownish.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
1.7–3.1 mm
; fore wing length 
1.5–2.3 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Antenna 19–26-segmented.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind femur wide, 2.6–2.8 times as long as maximum width.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma slender, 1.1–1.2 times as long as head and mesosoma combined. First tergite long and narrow, its length 1.4–1.6 times maximum width of tergite, which is 1.8–2.0 times its minimum basal width. Basal area of second tergite 0.2–0.4 times as long as remaining part of tergite; apical area short, 0.3–0.5 times as long as remaining part of tergite; areas sometimes indistinctly delineated. Median length of second tergite (with areas) 1.0–1.1 times its basal width, 1.5–1.8 times median length of third tergite. Third–fifth tergites rugose-striate in basal 0.5–0.3.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Rarely body paler. Pterostigma sometimes mostly brown, pale basally and apically. Metasoma sometimes light brown or light reddish brown. Otherwise similar to female.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species distinctly differs from the remaining two described species of the subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Afroipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
[
I.
<tp:taxon-name>
(
A
.) 
insignis
Granger
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
A
.) 
reunionus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
] by having the mesoscutum entirely densely and distinctly granulate and almost entirely covered by short pale setae (vs smooth and mainly glabrous).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Réunion
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
