<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Neorhaconotus Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp;
            Austin 2004</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651684</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD325F5FFE0DE3303B1B3B52</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
            Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Neorhaconotus Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004
      </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Neorhaconotus Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004: 65 </tp:taxon-name>
         . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Neorhaconotus </tp:taxon-name> – Belokobylskij 2005: 205. — Belokobylskij
         &amp; Austin 2013: 341 . — Yu et al. 2016 . — Jasso-Martínez et al. 2019: 165 . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Neorhaconotus rieki Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004
         </tp:taxon-name> , by original designation (Belokobylskij et al. 2004). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description ( Figs 26–27 ) </p>
      <p>HEAD. Head transverse. Ocellar arranged in obtuse triangle with base 1.2 times its sides.
         Frons slightly concave, without median keel, but with distinct curved carina along eyes.
         Oblique furrow between eye and antennal socket absent. Eye glabrous or with sparse and very
         short setae, with shallow or very shallow emargination opposite antennal sockets. Distance
         between antennal sockets wide. Malar suture absent. Clypeal suture distinct and complete.
         Hypoclypeal depression weakly oval. Postgenal bridge narrow. Occipital carina strong and
         complete, fused below with hypostomal carina upper base of mandible. Maxillary palps
         6-segmented; labial palps 4-segmented, third labial segment long. Scapus of antenna long
         and wide, not flattened laterally, without apical lobe and basal constriction; length of
         scapus 1.7–2.0 times its maximum width. First flagellar segment straight, almost as long as
         second segment.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed dorso-ventrally. Neck of prothorax long, almost flat
         dorsally, with distinct pronotal keel, with long smooth anterior lobe which is marginated
         subapically. Postero-dorsal propleural lobe distinct and wide. Mesonotum subvertical or
         obliquely curving and distinctly elevated above pronotum. Median lobe of mesoscutum without
         anterolateral corners. Notauli complete, entirely shallow or sometimes deeper in anterior
         half and distinctly shallow in posterior half. Prescutellar depression long, rugulose, with
         five-seven distinct carinae. Metanotum with distinct, obtuse or pointed median tooth
         (lateral view). Subalar depression shallow, wide and coarsely sculptured. Mesopleural pit
         present, elongate and deep. Sternaulus (precoxal sulcus) deep, long, almost straight,
         weakly or distinctly sculptured. Prepectal carina strong. Prepectus with or without lateral
         carinae. Postpectal carina absent. Metapleural flange long, narrow and densely pubescent at
         least partly. Propodeum with long areola and basolateral areas distinctly delineated by
         carinae; with more or less distinct tubercles or without them; propodeal bridge absent</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore tibia with several slender spines arranged in single row. Hind coxa with
         distinct basoventral corner and tubercle. Fore and middle femora with weak medio-dorsal
         protuberances, virtually missing on hind femur. Hind femur rather thick, 3.0–3.8 times as
         long as wide. Inner hind tibial spur 0.25–0.35 times as long as basitarsus. Hind basitarsus
         0.6–0.7 times as long as second–fifth segments combined.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing usually large, but sometimes micropterous. Radial vein (r) arising almost
         from middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Both radiomedial veins
         (2RS, r-m) present. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell long or median sized. Discoidal
         (discal) cell petiolate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) postfurcal. Nervulus (cu-a) distinctly
         postfurcal. Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial. Brachial (first subdiscal) cell closed
         apically before recurrent vein (m-cu). Both transverse anal veins (2A, a) absent.
         Mediocubital vein (M+CU) entirely sclerotised. Hind wing with three hamuli. Second costal
         abscissa (SC+R) and nervulus (cu-a) present. Medial (basal) cell closed anteriorly,
         distinctly widened distally, its length 6.5–7.0 times maximum width. Radial vein (RS)
         unsclerotised, without additional transverse vein (r). Submedial (subbasal) cell long;
         first mediocubital abscissa (M+CU) 0.85–1.0 times as long as second abscissa (1M).
         Recurrent vein (m-cu) present, oblique, curvedly directed to base of wing.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma with five dorsally visible tergites. First tergite short and wide, with
         small dorsope; its spiracular tubercles small and situated in basal quarter of tergite;
         dorsal carinae fine and subparallel. Acrosternite of first segment short, 0.15–0.20 times
         as long as first tergite. First and second tergites movably connected, not fused. Second
         suture deep, wide and sometimes weakly curved laterally. Second tergite without any furrows
         or defined areas, shorter than third tergite. Third tergite with deep and weakly curved
         transverse crenulate furrows in basal 0.3–0.5. Second to fifth tergites with separate
         laterotergites. Fifth tergite slightly enlarged, 1.2–1.6 times as long as fourth tergite,
         almost concealing the succeeding tergites. Fourth to sixth tergites with transverse
         subapical rows of long sparse erect setae. Ovipositor slightly longer or shorter than
         metasoma; apex of its dorsal valve with two distinct and widely separated nodes, apex of
         ventral valve serrate.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Neorhaconotus </tp:taxon-name> is similar to <tp:taxon-name> Rhaconotus
         </tp:taxon-name> , but differs from the latter genus by having the submedial (subbasal)
         cell of the hind wing large (vs distinctly short) and first mediocubital abscissa (M+CU)
         0.85–1.0 times as long as second abscissa (1M) (vs 0.3–0.5 times), the propodeum with
         elongate areola distinctly delineated by high carinae (vs without areola), the posterior
         metasomal tergites (started from fourth) mostly smooth (vs mostly sculptures at least
         basally), and tergites behind fifth one are shortly projecting (vs almost never projected).
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Composition </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Neorhaconotus cardaleae Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004
         </tp:taxon-name> (AU); <tp:taxon-name> N. julieae Belokobylskij &amp; Austin, 2013
         </tp:taxon-name> (AU); <tp:taxon-name> N. pappi Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004
         </tp:taxon-name> (AU); <tp:taxon-name> N. rieki Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004
         </tp:taxon-name> (AU). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p> Hosts </p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p>Australasian region.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> A key to the described macropterous species of <tp:taxon-name> Neorhaconotus
         </tp:taxon-name> was published by Belokobylskij et al. (2004: 66). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
