<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Rhacontsira haeselbarthi
                        Belokobylskij &amp; Zaldívar-Riverón 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651732</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27ADF55F9CFDE6E3313BCF3CBA</uri>
                  <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
                        Braconidae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Rhacontsira haeselbarthi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: D2A46876-0B35-4BDE-B49F-FB7927B69864 </p>
            <p> Fig. 51 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> Named after Dr E. Haeselbarth, well-known German hymenopterist and collector of the
                  holotype specimen. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype REPUBLIC OF SOUTH AFRICA • ♀ ; “ Entabeni Forest ,
                        Soutpansberg, Tvl. [Transvaal], 4–5000’, 3.– 7.6.[19]64, E. Haeselbarth ”;
                        SSMG . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 1.8 mm ; fore wing length 1.7 mm . </p>
            <p>HEAD. Width 1.4 times its median length, 1.2 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind
                  eyes (dorsal view) roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 1.6 times as long
                  as temple (dorsal view). Ocelli small, arranged in triangle with base 1.2 times
                  its sides. POL 1.5 times OD, 0.5 times OOL. Eye glabrous, very weakly emarginated
                  opposite antennal sockets, 1.25 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.45 times
                  height of eye and 0.9 times basal width of mandible. Face width 1.1 times height
                  of eye and 1.3 times height of face and clypeus combined. Clypeal suture distinct
                  and complete. Hypoclypeal depression round, its width almost equal to distance
                  from edge of depression to eye, 0.4 times width of face. Occipital carina complete
                  dorsally, fused below with hypostomal carina above base of mandible. Hypostomal
                  flange distinct. Vertex distinctly convex. Head below eyes distinctly and roundly
                  narrowed (front view). Antennae slender, filiform, 19-segmented, 1.3 times as long
                  as body. Scapus 1.8 times as long as maximum width. First flagellar segment 4.5
                  times as long as its apical width, 0.85 times as long as second segment.
                  Penultimate segment 4.0 times as long as width, as long as first flagellar and
                  apical segments; the latter distinctly pointed.</p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed. Length almost twice its height. Pronotum with
                  distinct pronotal carina situated more closely to mesoscutum, but not fused with
                  it. Mesoscutum highly and almost perpendicularly raising above pronotum (lateral
                  view), almost as long as maximum width. Median lobe of mesoscutum not protruding
                  forward. Notauli deep anteriorly, shallow posteriorly, narrow, crenulategranulate.
                  Prescutellar depression rather deep and long, weakly curved postero-laterally,
                  with distinct median carina, finely rugulose, about 0.5 times as long as weakly
                  convex scutellum. Subalar depression shallow, wide, rugose-granulate. Sternaulus
                  (precoxal furrow) distinct, rather deep, finely crenulategranulate, connected with
                  prepectal carina anteriorly, running along entire length of lower part of
                  mesopleuron, weakly curved medially. Metanotum without dorsal tooth (lateral
                  view). Metapleural lobe short, widened, rounded apically, with sparse
                  pubescence.</p>
            <p>WING. Fore wing 3.2 times as long as its maximum width. Pterostigma 4.5 times as long
                  as wide. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.3 times as long as pterostigma. Radial vein (r)
                  arising almost from middle of pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming
                  obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 2.4 times
                  first abscissa (r), 0.4 times the straight third abscissa (SR1), 1.1 times first
                  radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell not narrowed
                  distally, about 3.0 times as long as maximum width, 1.4 times as long as the
                  narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) weakly sinuate.
                  Recurrent vein (m-cu) about 4.0 times as long as second medial abscissa, 0.6 times
                  as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) almost
                  straight. Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal (1-M) vein almost equal to
                  nervulus (cu-a) length. Hind wing 5.6 times as long as wide. First costal abscissa
                  (C+SC+R) 0.6 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). First abscissa of
                  mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.7 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent
                  vein (mcu) weakly curved, strongly oblique, strongly antefurcal.</p>
            <p> Fig. 51. <tp:taxon-name> Rhacontsira haeselbarthi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♀,
                  holotype, SSMG. A . Habitus, lateral view. B . Head and mesoscutum, front view. C
                  . Mesosoma, dorsal view. D . Head, front view. E . Basal segments of antenna. F .
                  Apical segments of antenna. G . Head and mesosoma, lateral view. H . Metasoma,
                  dorsal view. I . Wings. </p>
            <p>LEGS. Hind coxa 1.6 times as long as wide (with basoventral tubercle). Hind femur 3.7
                  times as long as wide. Hind tarsus 0.9 times as long as hind tibia. Hind
                  basitarsus 0.75 times as long as second– fifth segments combined; second tarsal
                  segment 0.4 times as long as basitarsus, almost as long as fifth segment (without
                  pretarsus).</p>
            <p>METASOMA. Length almost as long as mesosoma and head combined. First tergite with
                  distinct pointed and directed downwards basolateral processes, without spiracular
                  tubercles, distinctly and linearly widened from base to apex. Maximum width of
                  first tergite 2.5 times minimum width; length 1.2 times its apical width, 1.1
                  times length of propodeum. Second tergite with rather distinct shallow and
                  transverse furrow in posterior quarter separating rather short transverse apical
                  area. Length of second tergite 0.7 times its basal width, almost twice length of
                  third tergite. Second suture rather deep, almost straight, weakly curved
                  laterally. Fourth tergite enlarged, weakly convex in posterior margin, without
                  median emargination and postero-ventral lobes, 1.7 times as long as third tergite,
                  1.3 times as long as fifth tergite. Ovipositor sheath 1.1 times as long as
                  metasoma, 1.3 times as long as mesosoma, 0.55 times as long as fore wing.</p>
            <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex very finely transversely striate, almost smooth in
                  posterior third; frons mostly smooth, finely rugulose-coriaceous in anterior
                  third; face distinctly densely striate, smooth medially and below; temple smooth.
                  Mesoscutum entirely densely granulate, without rugosity along notauli, rugose on
                  its small medio-posterior area. Scutellum densely granulate. Mesopleuron finely
                  coriaceous, granulate-coriaceous upper, very finely coriaceous to smooth near
                  sternauli. Metapleuron densely rugose-reticulate, finer sculptured in anterior
                  third. Propodeum with rugulose-granulate at most part and almost smooth basally
                  basolateral areas distinctly delineated by carinae; with distinct median carina in
                  its basal 0.5; remainder of propodeum rugose-reticulate with granulation; areola
                  indistinct. Hind coxa granulate, finely coriaceous below. Hind femur finely and
                  densely striate, smooth below. First and second tergites densely longitudinally
                  striate with dense ground reticulation between striae; apical area of second
                  tergite finer and irregularly striate. Third tergite laterally in basal two–thirds
                  and fourth tergite laterally in basal half densely striate, these tergites
                  medially very shortly striate or rugulose basally. Remaining parts of tergites
                  smooth. Vertex with very sparse short semi-erect setae. Mesoscutum with sparse,
                  rather short and semi-erect setae arranged along notauli and marginally.
                  Mesopleuron glabrous on wide median area.Hind tibia with short and dense
                  semi-erect setae; length of these setae about half maximum width of hind
                  tibia.</p>
            <p>COLOUR. Body black with reddish tint. Antenna mainly almost black, five basal
                  segments yellow or light brown. Palpi yellow. Legs brownish yellow, coxae faintly
                  infuscate. Ovipositor sheath brown, almost black apically. Fore wing faintly and
                  evenly infuscate. Pterostigma brown, yellow in basal third.</p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> This new species is morphologically very similar to the Eastern Palaearctic
                        <tp:taxon-name> Rh. heterospiloides (Belokobylskij) </tp:taxon-name> , but
                  differs from the latter by having the malar space 0.45 times height of eye and 0.9
                  times basal width of mandible (vs 0.3 and 0.55 times, correspondingly), pronotal
                  carina situated more closely to mesoscutum (vs situated submedially), second
                  radial abscissa (3-SR) of fore wing 1.1 times as long as first radiomedial vein
                  (2-SR) (vs only 0.8 times), hind femur 3.7 times as long as wide (vs 3.2 times),
                  ovipositor sheath 1.3 times as long as mesosoma and 0.55 times as long as fore
                  wing (vs about 2.0 and 0.75 times, correspondingly), and it is also distributed in
                  the Afrotropical region (vs the Eastern Palaearctic). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Republic of South Africa . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
