<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Euryphrymnus Cameron 1910</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651603</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/259C20534E90912ED94799D2A82119C0</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus
Cameron, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus
Cameron, 1910: 100
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Euryphrymnus
)
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Belokobylskij 1996a: 154

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Yu 
et al.
2016

(as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
). — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 167


(as synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus testaceiceps
Cameron, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(
Figs 8–11
)
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head not depressed, high, transverse. Ocelli arranged in weakly obtuse triangle. Frons almost flat, with very shallow median furrow. Eyes glabrous or rarely sparsely and shortly setose. Occipital carina dorsally complete, obliterate below and not joining ventrally with hypostomal carina at short distance. Malar suture absent. Clypeal suture distinct and complete. Hypoclypeal depression medium-sized, rounded. Postgenal bridge narrow, but distinct. Palpi relatively long; maxillary palps 6-segmented; labial palps 4-segmented, its third segment not shortened. Scapus wide and rather short, without apical lobe and basal constriction, its ventral margin (lateral view) not longer than dorsal margin. Pedicel weakly enlarged. First flagellar segment subcylindrical, almost straight, as long as second segment.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed and weakly elongate. Neck of prothorax rather short. Pronotum dorsally distinctly convex, with distinct pronotal carina situated submedially; propleural dorsoposterior flange long and rather wide. Mesonotum rather highly and roundly or gently roundly elevated above pronotum, mainly entirely granulate. Median lobe of mesonotum with or without median longitudinal furrow, without anterolateral corner. Notauli distinct and complete. Prescutellar depression relatively short, with several distinct carinae. Lateral longitudinal wing-like flanges on the level of prescutellar depression low but distinct. Scutellum convex, usually with fine lateral carinae. Metanotum with distinct, rather narrow and acuminate tooth (lateral view). Sternaulus (precoxal sulcus) more or less distinct, narrow, long, running almost along whole length of lower part of mesopleuron, often weakly sinuate. Prepectal carina distinct and complete, rather high below. Postpectal carina absent. Metapleural flange long, narrow, rounded apically, without dense setosity along its posterior margin. Propodeum with basolateral areas distinctly delineated by carinae, areola and other areas absent; lateral tubercles and propodeal bridge absent. Propodeal spiracles small and round.</p>
      <p>WINGS.Pterostigma of fore wing wide and long.Radial vein(r) arising usually from middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell never shortened. Both radiomedial veins (2-SR, r-m) present. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell medium-sized or rather long, rather wide, often widened towards apex. Recurrent vein (m-cu) postfurcal. Discoidal (discal) cell petiolate anteriorly, petiole (1-SR) short. Nervulus (cu-a) distinctly postfurcal. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) distinctly sinuate. Brachial (subdiscal) cell gentlyroundly closed postero-apically weakly before recurrent vein (m-cu), without antero-posterior corner. Parallel vein (CU1a) always interstitial. Transverse anal veins (2A, a) absent. Hind wing with three hamuli. Radial (marginal) cell weakly widened in basal half and weakly narrowed in apical half, without transverse vein (r). Medial (basal) cell narrow, weakly widened towards apex. Nervellus (cu-a) present. Submedial (subbasal) cell short; first abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.4–0.5 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) present, finely sclerotised or pigmented, weakly curved, distinctly oblique towards base of wing.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore and middle tibiae with short and thick spines arranged in narrow short stripe. Middle tarsal segments rather short, but elongate. Hind coxa relatively long and wide, with distinct basoventral corner and tubercle. Hind femur relatively narrow, with low and wide dorsal protuberance. Hind basitarsus 0.6–0.7 times as long as second–fifth segments combined. Claws short and simple.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. With only five visible tergites, with separated laterotergites on second–fifth tergites. Acrosternite of first segment short, about 0.2 times as long as first tergite, its apical margin situated before level of spiracles. First tergite not petiolate, rather long and distinctly widened towards apex; with distinct dorsope; with relatively long or only distinct basolateral process; spiracles situated in basal 0.3 of tergite. Second tergite movably connected with first tergite, with short or rather long basal area, delineated posteriorly by distinct and usually complete semi-circular or sinuate posterior sulcus; apical area always present, long, lenticular, distinctly separated by deep and curved furrow anteriorly and second suture posteriorly. Second suture deep, rather wide, complete, evenly curved. Fourth and fifth tergites with deep and crenulate subbasal transverse furrows. Fifth tergite distinctly enlarged, longer than previous tergite, covered following apical segments. Ovipositor sheath shorter than metasoma.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Members of this genus with five metasomal tergites are very similar to the nominative genus of the tribe, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
Ruthe, 1854
</tp:taxon-name>
but can be distinguished from the latter by the presence of a transverse or semi-oval basal area on the second tergite distinctly delineated by a deep furrow, and always together with an apical lenticular area sharply delineated anteriorly by deep sulcus and posteriorly by a second suture. A similar structure on the second metasomal tergite is also know in species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bathycentor
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
, though members of these genera always have more than five dorsally visible metasomal tergites.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Composition
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus basoareolus
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. gaullei
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. testaceiceps
Cameron, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Hosts
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Afrotropical and 
Oriental
regions.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Fifth tergite on posterior margin with two wide and distinct submedial processes and emargination between it. Body length 6.0 mm. 
Madagascar
....................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. gaullei
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Fifth tergite on posterior margin without submedial processes and emargination between it, evenly rounded (
Figs 9C
; 
11B
) .................................................................................................................... 2

</p>
      <p>

2. Mesoscutum densely granulate and with distinct rugosity around notauli, setose on wide area along notauli and along sides of mesoscutum (
Fig. 8F
). Mesopleuron entirely and densely setose (
Fig. 8G
). Apical area of second metasomal tergite entirely coarsely striate (
Fig. 9C
). Fifth tergite entirely striate-reticulate, 1.6 times as long as fourth tergite (
Fig. 9C
). Body length 
5.1 mm
. 
Indonesia
............................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. testaceiceps
Cameron, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Mesoscutum densely granulate and without rugosity around notauli, mainly glabrous, with only few setae medio-posteriorly (
Fig. 10G
). Mesopleuron mainly glabrous (
Fig. 10F
). Apical area of second metasomal tergite almost entirely smooth (
Fig. 11B
). Fifth tergite striate in basal half and smooth in posterior half, 1.2–1.3 times as long as fourth tergite (
Fig. 11B
). Body length 
2.5–2.7 mm
, 
Malaysia
, 
Vietnam
................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. basoareolus
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
