<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ipodoryctes (Afroipodoryctes) Belokobylskij
            &amp; Zaldívar-Riverón 2021, subgen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651666</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD495F22FD86E3303F533905</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
            Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Subgenus <tp:taxon-name> Afroipodoryctes </tp:taxon-name> subgen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 36CDE5C4-B0FF-4939-BA6C-1C985F9F8846 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Ipodoryctes insignis Granger, 1949 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> From combination of the words “Africa” and the generic name “ <tp:taxon-name> Ipodoryctes
         </tp:taxon-name> ”, since members of this subgenus were only recorded in the African
         continent. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description ( Figs 16–21 ) </p>
      <p>HEAD. Head transverse. Ocelli arranged in weakly obtuse triangle with base weakly larger
         than its sides. Eyes glabrous. Occipital carina incomplete, obliterate below and not
         joining ventrally with hypostomal carina at short distance. Malar suture absent.
         Hypoclypeal depression medium size, subround. Postgenal bridge very narrow. Scapus of
         antenna more or less wide. First flagellar segment subcylindrical, almost straight, not
         shorter than second segment. Apical segment apically acuminate.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed and relatively long. Pronotum dorsally weakly convex, with
         more or less fine pronotal carina. Mesonotum more or less highly and gently roundly
         elevated above pronotum; mainly smooth and glabrous. Notauli distinct, almost incomplete,
         smoothed posteriorly, smooth or partly finely crenulate. Prescutellar depression rather
         long, with several carinae. Metanotum with short and more or less pointed median tooth
         (lateral view). Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) rather deep, long, running along anterior
         0.6–0.8 of lower part of mesopleuron. Propodeum with basolateral areas and areola
         distinctly delineated by carinae; lateral tubercles short.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Wings not shortened. Pterostigma of fore wing wide. Radial vein of fore wing arising
         almost from middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Second radiomedial
         (submarginal) cell long. Recurrent vein (m-cu) distinctly postfurcal. Nervulus (cu-a)
         postfurcal. Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial or not interstitial and arising from anterior
         0.3 of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell. Brachial (subdiscal) cell subvertically
         closed postero-apically before recurrent vein (m-cu) and with antero-posteriorly corner. In
         hind wing, first abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.4–0.5 times as long as second
         abscissa (1-M).</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa without or with small basoventral tubercle. Hind femur rather wide, almost
         without dorsal protuberance. Hind basitarsus 0.7 times as long as second–fifth segments
         combined.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. First tergite not petiolate, rather long and widened toward apex. Second tergite
         with narrow basal area delineated by rather distinct furrow; with lenticular apical area
         distinctly delineated anteriorly by deep crenulate furrow and posteriorly by second suture.
         Second suture deep, complete and regularly curved. Sixth tergite not or weakly enlarged,
         not longer than previous tergite, smooth, more or less covered following apical segments,
         posteriorly evenly curved, without emargination. Ovipositor sheath not longer than
         metasoma.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> This new subgenus differs from <tp:taxon-name> Ipodoryctes </tp:taxon-name> s.str. in
         having the hind coxa without or sometimes with indistinct basoventral tubercle; pro- and
         mesothorax almost entirely smooth; propodeum with areola delineated by distinct carinae,
         notauli smooth or almost smooth. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Composition </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Ipodoryctes ( Afroipodoryctes ) insignis ( Granger, 1949 ) (AF)
         </tp:taxon-name> ; <tp:taxon-name> I . ( A. ) reunionus </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ;
            <tp:taxon-name> I . ( A. ) saintphillipensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p>Afrotropical region.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Key to species of <tp:taxon-name> Ipodoryctes (Afroipodoryctes) </tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p> 1. Mesoscutum entirely densely and distinctly granulate and almost entirely covered by
         short pale setae ( Figs 20F–G ). Body length 2.1–3.2 mm . La Reunion ............
            <tp:taxon-name> I. ( A. ) saintphillipensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </p>
      <p> – Mesoscutum entirely smooth and mainly glabrous ( Figs 16C–D ; 18H–I )
         ....................................... 2 </p>
      <p> 2. Areola of propodeum narrow ( Fig. 16C ). Brachial (subdiscal) cell of fore wing
         apically closed before recurrent vein (m-cu); parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing
         interstitial ( Fig. 17A ). Hind femur yellow basally and dark reddish brown in posterior
         0.6 ( Fig. 16 CB. First metasomal tergite narrow and long, its length 1.6 times apical
         width. Second metasomal suture evenly curved ( Fig. 17B ). Body length 4.0 mm. Madagascar
         .................................................... <tp:taxon-name> I. ( A. ) insignis (
            Granger, 1949 ) </tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p> – Areola of propodeum wide ( Fig. 18H ). Brachial (subdiscal) cell of fore wing apically
         closed behind recurrent vein (m-cu); parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing often arising from
         anterior 0.2–0.3 of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell ( Fig. 19A ). Hind femur
         almost entirely pale brown to yellow ( Fig. 18J ). First metasomal tergite wide and short,
         its length 1.0–1.2 times its apical width. Second metasomal suture sinuate ( Figs 19B, D ).
         Body length 3.1–4.3 mm . La Reunion
         ......................................................................................................
            <tp:taxon-name> I. ( A. ) reunionus </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
