<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Rhaconotinus (Hexarhaconotinus) Belokobylskij &amp; Zaldívar-Riverón 2021, subgen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651710</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD085F61FDA8E330386A3FDC</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hexarhaconotinus
</tp:taxon-name>
subgen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D0729E6D-6753-4910-9B10-CDFC2C5E7CCC
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus hexatermus
</tp:taxon-name>
species group Belokobylskij, 2001: 134.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From combination of the Greek word “hexa”, which means “six”, and the generic name “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotinus
</tp:taxon-name>
”, since members of this subgenus have six visible metasomal tergites.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus hexatermus
Belokobylskij, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(
Figs 42–43
)
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head transverse. Ocelli arranged in weakly obtuse or equilateral triangle with base weakly larger than or almost equal to its sides. Eyes glabrous. Occipital carina complete dorsally, obliterate below and not joining ventrally with hypostomal carina at distinct distance. Malar suture absent. Hypoclypeal depression medium size, subround. Postgenal bridge narrow. Scapus of antenna wide and rather short. First flagellar segment subcylindrical, almost straight, not shorter than second segment. Apical segment acuminate apically.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not or weakly depressed dorso-ventrally and relatively long. Pronotum dorsally convex, with distinct pronotal carina submedially. Mesonotum usually not highly and gently-roundly elevated above pronotum; mainly granulate. Notauli complete, distinct anteriorly and shallow posteriorly, crenulate. Prescutellar depression rather long, with distinct median carina. Metanotum with short and subrounded median tooth (lateral view). Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) rather deep, long, running along anterior 0.8–0.9 of lower part of mesopleuron. Propodeum with basolateral areas and often areola distinctly delineated by carinae; lateral tubercles short.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Wings not shortened. Pterostigma of fore wing relatively wide. Radial vein (r) arising almost from middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell relatively short. Recurrent vein (m-cu) postfurcal. Nervulus (cu-a) postfurcal. Parallel vein (CU1a) usually interstitial, but rarely not interstitial and arising from anterior 0.25 of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell. Brachial (subdiscal) cell subvertically closed postero-apically before or on level of recurrent vein (m-cu) and with marked antero-posteriorly corner. In hind wing, first abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.4–0.6 times as long as second abscissa (1-M).</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa with distinct basoventral corner and tubercle. Hind femur rather wide, with low dorsal protuberance. Hind basitarsus 0.6–0.7 times as long as second–fifth segments combined.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. First tergite not petiolate, rather long and distinctly widened toward apex. Second tergite without basal and apical areas delineated by furrows and second suture. Second suture deep, complete and regularly curved, without sublateral breaks. Sixth tergite at least weakly enlarged, usually longer than previous tergite, entirely coarsely sculptured, usually covered following apical segments, posteriorly evenly curved, without medial emargination. Ovipositor sheath not longer than metasoma.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This subgenus differs from the nominative subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotinus
</tp:taxon-name>
s. str.
by the absence of apical area on the second metasomal tergite bordered by second suture and deep anterior transverse additional furrow.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Composition
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotinus
(
Hexarhaconotinus
) 
ashmeadi
(Baker, 1917)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
brevitergum
Belokobylskij, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
caophongus
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
hexatermus
(Belokobylskij, 1988)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
fujianus
(
Belokobylskij &amp; Chen, 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
icterus
(Shi &amp; 
Chen, 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
longi
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
micholitzi
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(AU); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
rugosus
(
Chen &amp; Shi, 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh.
(
H.
) 
staudingeri
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Australasian and 
Oriental
regions.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
