<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Troporhaconotus Belokobylskij &amp;
            Zaldívar-Riverón 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651756</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27ADE25F8EFDF9E7E83E7E392E</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
            Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Troporhaconotus </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 6D821B9C-95EC-4CAC-873F-1FA1F40902A6 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Rhaconotus jacobsoni </tp:taxon-name> species group – Belokobylskij 2001:
         134. — Qanh &amp; Long 2019: 37 . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> From “tropics”, the climatic region where this taxon appears to be restricted, and the
         generic name “ <tp:taxon-name> Rhaconotus </tp:taxon-name> ”. Gender: masculine. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Pseudospathius jacobsoni Szépligeti, 1908 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description ( Figs 58–59 ) </p>
      <p>HEAD. Head subglobular. Vertex densely and finely granulate or granulate-reticulate. Ocelli
         arranged often in almost equilateral triangle. Frons almost flat and without median keel.
         Eyes with distinct emargination opposite eyes, glabrous. Occipital carina complete
         dorsally, not joining ventrally with hypostomal carina being obliterated at short distance.
         Malar suture absent. Clypeal suture distinct and complete. Clypeus with more or less
         distinct ventral flange. Hypoclypeal depression medium size, round. Postgenal bridge rather
         wide. Palps rather short; maxillary palps 6-segmented, labial palps 4-segmented. Scapus
         wide and rather short, without apical lobe or basal constriction. First flagellar segment
         subcylindrical, almost straight, always longer than second segment.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma long and narrow, 2.5–3.0 times as long as its high. Pronotum dorsally
         distinctly convex, with more or less distinct pronotal carina in anterior 0.3–0.4.
         Mesonotum not highly and weakly gently-roundly elevated above pronotum (lateral view); its
         all three lobes medially widely glabrous. Notauli complete, deep, crenulate. Prescutellar
         depression relatively long, with median carina, rugulose. Scuto-scutellar suture rather
         distinct. Scutellum with distinct lateral carinae at least in anterior half. Metanotum
         often with long and acuminate median tooth (lateral view). Sternaulus (precoxal furrow)
         distinct, relatively deep, long, running along all length of lower part of mesopleuron,
         distinctly crenulate. Prepectal carina complete, enlarged below opposite fore coxa.
         Postpectal carina absent. Propodeum at least with long median and two lateral carinae,
         often basolateral areas not delineated posteriorly, areola indistinct; lateral tubercles
         and propodeal bridge absent.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Pterostigma bicolorated, mostly dark brown with pale its basal part. Radial vein (r)
         arising usually from or more or less behind middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell
         not shortened. Both radiomedial veins (2-SR, r-m) present. Recurrent vein (m-cu) distinctly
         postfurcal. Discoidal (discal) cell petiolate, narrow and long. Nervulus (cu-a) weakly
         postfurcal or sometimes subinterstitial. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) rather distinctly curved
         distally to anal vein (2-1A). Parallel vein (CU1a) always interstitial. Brachial
         (subdiscal) cell closed usually before or (rarely) on level of recurrent vein (m-cu). Hind
         wing with three hamuli. Radial (marginal) cell without additional transverse vein (r).
         Medial (basal) cell rather narrow, but distinctly widened apically. Nervellus (cu-a)
         present. Submedial (subbasal) cell small. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU)
         distinctly shorter than second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) present, but often not
         pigmented.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore tibiae with several distinct spines arranged in almost single line. Middle leg
         short and with short tarsal segments. Hind coxa with distinct basoventral corner and
         distinct, but small tubercle. Hind femur with rather distinct dorsal protuberances; femur
         of male distinctly broaded. Hind tibia with long, more or less dense and semi-erect setae.
         Hind basitarsus 0.6–0.7 times as long as second–fifth segments combined. Legs usually with
         dark and pale colour pattern.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Six dorsally visible and hardly sclerotised tergites. First tergite not
         petiolate, but very long, its dorsope rather large, basolateral lobes absent. Acrosternite
         of first segment 0.15–0.2 times as long as first tergite, its apical margin situated
         distinctly before level of spiracles. First and second tergites not fused immovably. Second
         tergite without basal area delineated posteriorly by furrow; apical area of second tergite
         present, long, coarsely sculptured, delineated anteriorly by relatively shallow and wide
         crenulate furrow and posteriorly by rather deep and wide curved second suture. Second–sixth
         tergites with separated laterotergites. Sixth tergite of female always enlarged, distinctly
         longer than fifth tergite, covered following apical segments, with usually distinctly
         convex its posterior margin, but only sometimes with more or less distinct incurvation
         posteriorly.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> This new genus differs from the remaining <tp:taxon-name>Rhaconotini</tp:taxon-name>
         genera by having more than five dorsally visible metasomal tergite and with distinctly
         enlarged sixth tergite covering following tergites, first metasomal tergite long, more than
         2.0 times as long as its apical width, second tergite without basal area and always </p>
      <p>with apical lenticular area rather distinctly delineated anteriorly by deep and rather wide
         furrow, and mesosoma long with mesoscutum weakly and gently elevated above pronotum.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Composition </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Troporhaconotus anivoranensis ( Granger, 1949 ) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov.
         (AF); <tp:taxon-name> T. asulcus (Shi &amp; Chen, 2004 ) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T. ceylonicus (Belokobylskij, 2001) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T. chinensis ( Belokobylskij &amp; Chen, 2004 ) </tp:taxon-name> comb.
         nov. (OR); <tp:taxon-name> T. directus (Long, 2019) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T. glaphyrus ( Chen &amp; Shi, 2004 ) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T. jacobsoni ( Szépligeti, 1908 ) </tp:taxon-name> [= <tp:taxon-name>
            Rhaconotus filicornis ( Enderlein, 1912 ) </tp:taxon-name> ] comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T. laevigatus (Long, 2019) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T. longithorax (Belokobylskij, 2001) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T. robustus (Long, 2019) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T . simulatus (Long, 2019) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR);
            <tp:taxon-name> T. thayi Belokobylskij, 2001 </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. (OR). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p> Hosts </p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Afrotropical and Oriental regions. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> In Jasso-Martínez et al. (2019) , the only included species of this genus, <tp:taxon-name>
            T. thayi (Belokobylskij, 2001) </tp:taxon-name> , was nested at the base of a large
         clade with taxa having mainly five-tergited metasoma. Despite its absence of sharp
         morphological diagnostic characters, the above combination of features together with its
         phylogenetic affinities allowed us to propose the erection of this new genus. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
