<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Antespathius buonluoicus
                        Belokobylskij &amp; Zaldívar-Riverón 2021, stat. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651644</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD705F1EFE09E0913B0C3E48</uri>
                  <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
                        Braconidae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Antespathius buonluoicus ( Belokobylskij, 1995 ) </tp:taxon-name> stat.
            nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 1–2 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Spathius ( Antespathius ) buonluoicus Belokobylskij, 1995: 49
                  </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Spathius ( Antespathius ) buonluoicus </tp:taxon-name> – Yu et al.
                  2016 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype VIETNAM • ♀ ; “ Vietnam , prov. GaiLai – ConTum ,
                        20 km N Buon-Luoi , Tram Lap , 1–14.XII.1988 , A. Sharkov ”; ZISP .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes VIETNAM • 10 ♀♀ , 3 ♂♂ ; same collection data as
                        for holotype but 30 Nov. , 1–14 Dec. 1988 ; ZISP </tp:material-citation> .
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 2.6–3.3 mm ; fore wing length 1.9–2.2 mm . </p>
            <p>HEAD. Width 1.3–1.4 times its median length, 1.3 times width of mesoscutum. Head
                  behind eyes (dorsal view) roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 1.3–1.5
                  times as long as temple. Ocelli small, arranged in triangle with base 1.2 times as
                  wide as its sides. POL 1.3–1.7 times OD, 0.3–0.5 times OOL. Eyes almost without
                  emargination opposite antennal sockets, weakly directed forwards, 1.2–1.3 times as
                  high as broad. Malar space 0.6 times height of eye, 1.0–1.2 times basal width of
                  mandible. Face distinctly convex, its width 1.1–1.25 times eye height, almost
                  equal to height of face and clypeus combined. Hypoclypeal depression width 0.7–0.8
                  times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.4 times width of face. Tentorial
                  pits distinct. Head below eyes (front view) roundly narrowed. Hypostomal flange
                  rather wide. Maxillary palps about 1.1 times height of head (without mandibles).
                  Antennae slender, almost filiform, 25–28-segmented. Scapus 1.8 times as long as
                  its maximum width. First flagellar segment 4.5–5.3 times as long as its apical
                  width, 1.25 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 2.7–3.1 times as
                  long as wide, nearly as long as apical segment.</p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma elongated, its length 2.1 times maximum height. Maximum width of
                  mesoscutum 1.1 times its length. Median lobe of mesoscutum protruding forwards,
                  distinctly convex anteriorly (dorsal view). Prescutellar depression long, rather
                  deep, with five distinct carinae, finely reticulate between carinae, medially 0.3
                  times as long as scutellum. Scutellum weakly convex, 1.2 times as long as its
                  maximum width. Subalar depression entirely longitudinally striate with dense
                  reticulation between striae. Propodeum (lateral view) distinctly and weakly
                  curvedly inclined from base to apex.</p>
            <p> Fig. 1. <tp:taxon-name> Antespathius buonluoicus ( Belokobylskij, 1995 )
                  </tp:taxon-name> , ♀, holotype, ZISP. A . Habitus, lateral view. B . Basal
                  segments of antenna. C . Head, front view. D . Head, dorsal view. E . Head,
                  lateral view. F . Mesosoma, dorsal view. G . Mesosoma, lateral view. H . Hind leg.
                  I . Propodeum and petiole, dorsal view. J . Propodeum and petiole, lateral view. </p>
            <p> Fig. 2. <tp:taxon-name> Antespathius buonluoicus ( Belokobylskij, 1995 )
                  </tp:taxon-name> , ♀, holotype, ZISP. A . Wings. B . Fore wing, median part. C .
                  Metasoma, dorsal view. D . Metasoma, lateral view. </p>
            <p>WINGS. Fore wing 4.5–5.0 times its maximum width. Pterostigma 5.5 times as long as
                  wide. Metacarpus (1-R1) 0.9–1.0 times as long as pterostigma. First radial
                  abscissa (r) inclivous to pterostigma, 0.5 times as long as maximum width of
                  pterostigma, forming obtuse angle with second radial abscissa (3- SR). Second
                  radial abscissa (3-SR) 6.0–7.4 times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.9–1.0 times
                  as long as straight third abscissa (SR1), about as long as track of first
                  radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell (between recurrent
                  (m-cu) and second radiomedial (r-m) veins) long and wide, about 4.0 times as long
                  as its maximum width, 1.3 times as long as the wide brachial (subdiscal) cell.
                  First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) weakly sinuate. Discoidal (discal) cell wide and
                  short, 1.5–1.8 times as long as wide. Basal (1-M) and recurrent (m-cu) veins
                  divergent posteriorly. Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal (1-M) vein 0.5–1.5
                  times nervulus (cu-a) length, nervulus (cu-a) straight and distinctly oblique
                  towards base of wing. Hind wing 6.0 times as long as wide. Medial (basal) cell
                  14.8 times as long as its maximum width, 0.40–0.45 times as long as wing. Radial
                  (SR) and medial (2-M) veins almost indistinct. First abscissa of mediocubital vein
                  (M+CU) 0.4 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) strongly
                  desclerotised, weakly curved, strongly antefurcal.</p>
            <p>LEGS. Hind coxa 1.8 times as long as maximum width, 0.7 times as long as propodeum.
                  Hind femur 3.0– 3.1 times as long as wide. Hind tibia slender. Hind tarsus nearly
                  as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus weakly thickened, without distinct ventral
                  keel. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.5 times as long as first segment, 1.1–1.2
                  times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
            <p>METASOMA. Weakly longer than head and mesosoma combined. Petiole dorsally convex in
                  basal half and almost linear in apical half (lateral view), weakly widened on
                  level of spiracles and apically (dorsal view), without convex median area. Apical
                  width of petiole 1.2–1.5 times its width at level of spiracles, 1.6–2.0 times its
                  minimum basal width; length of tergite 2.7–3.0 times its apical width, 1.4–1.5
                  times length of propodeum, 0.65–0.70 times length of other tergites combined.
                  Median length of second and third tergites combined 2.0–2.1 times basal width of
                  second tergite, 0.75–0.9 times their maximum width. Ovipositor sheath 1.5–1.6
                  times as long as petiole, 0.6 times as long as metasoma, 0.85 times as long as
                  mesosoma, 0.4–0.5 times as long as fore wing.</p>
            <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex finely transversely striate-reticulate to
                  coriaceous; frons entirely densely, sinuate aciculate; face as in generic
                  description; temple almost smooth in anterior half and finely vertically striate
                  in posterior half, almost smooth below. Mesoscutum densely and finely
                  granulate-reticulate, with two distinct and weakly convergent posteriorly carinae
                  in its medioposterior half. Scutellum finely and densely areolate-granulate.
                  Mesopleuron mainly smooth, with fine striation anteriorly and rugulosity
                  posteriorly. Metapleuron vertically striate with dense reticulation between
                  striae. Propodeum rugose-granulate in basal 0.4 and transverse striate with
                  reticulation between striae in posterior 0.6,without areas, with medial carina in
                  basal third.Hind coxa transverse striate dorsally, densely granulate-coriaceous to
                  finely coriaceous laterally. Hind femur densely and finely granulate-coriaceous.
                  Petiole densely undulately striate with dense rugulosity between striae. Second
                  and third tergites very densely concentrically aciculate, third tergite smooth
                  apically, fourth and fifth tergites densely and finely transversely aciculate in
                  basal halves and smooth ion apical halves. Vertex mainly glabrous, with sparse,
                  long and semi-erect pale setae laterally and posteriorly. Mesoscutum mainly
                  glabrous, with very sparse, semi-erect and long pale setae arranged along notauli
                  and laterally. Metapleuron mainly glabrous. Hind tibia dorsally with rather long,
                  sparse, semi-erect, pale setae, their length 0.5–1.0 times maximum width of
                  tibia.</p>
            <p> COLOUR. Head reddish brown to light reddish brown. Mesosoma reddish brown to partly
                  dark reddish brown. Petiole light reddish brown, second metasomal tergite dark
                  reddish brown, remaining metasoma almost black. Antennae yellow to light brown in
                  basal half, scapus brown dorsally, brown to dark brown in apical half. Palps
                  reddish brown basally to yellow apically. Legs reddish brown to dark reddish
                  brown, all coxae and tarsi (excluding fifth segments) and hind femur light reddish
                  brown to brownish yellow; middle and hind tibiae subbasally yellow. Fore wing
                  distinctly maculate, with brown spots nearly middle of medial (basal) cell, around
                  basal (1-M) and recurrent (m-cu) veins and around second radiomedial (submarginal)
                  cell. Pterostigma dark brown, pale yellow in basal ⅓ or 2 ⁄ 5 . </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body Length 2.6–2.8 mm ; fore wing length 1.7–2.0 mm. </p>
            <p>METASOMA. First metasomal tergite slender, 3.6 times as long as apical width, 1.5–1.6
                  times as long as propodeum.</p>
            <p>Otherwise, similar to female.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Vietnam . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
