<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Himerometridae A. H. Clark
            1908</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4419818</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B30387D7FF95CB37542EBED5C5A7E3F5</uri>
         <article-title>Discometra luberonensis sp. nov. (Crinoidea, Himerometridae), a new feather
            star from the Late Burdigalian</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> Hess &amp; Messing (2011) placed <tp:taxon-name>Himerometridae</tp:taxon-name> within the
         superfamily <tp:taxon-name> Mariametroidea A.H. Clark, 1909 </tp:taxon-name> (later changed
         to <tp:taxon-name>Himerometroidea</tp:taxon-name> by Taylor et al. 2017 ) in which
         rod-shaped basals are absent.All genera in <tp:taxon-name>Himerometridae</tp:taxon-name> (
            <tp:taxon-name> Heterometra A.H. Clark, 1909 </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name>
            Himerometra </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Craspedometra A.H. Clark, 1909
         </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Amphimetra A.H. Clark, 1909 </tp:taxon-name> ), except
            <tp:taxon-name> Discometra </tp:taxon-name> , show coelomic grooves on the adoral side
         of centrodorsal. <tp:taxon-name> Amphimetra </tp:taxon-name> has multiple radiate coelomic
         grooves while <tp:taxon-name> Heterometra </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Himerometra
         </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Craspedometra </tp:taxon-name> show Y-shaped grooves
         with more or less wide branches. In <tp:taxon-name> Discometra </tp:taxon-name> , such
         Y-shaped features are present as canals included in the stereom and located just beneath
         the surface of the proximal facet of radials ( Fontannes 1880 ; Sieverts-Doreck 1961). As a
         consequence, coelomic grooves are absent from the adoral surface of the centrodorsal. In
            <tp:taxon-name> Himerometra </tp:taxon-name> , the aboral facet of each radial displays
         a pair of wide grooves running in parallel in the inner part and diverging in a Y shape in
         the outer part; this feature is also visible on the oral side of the centrodorsal ( Fig. 3A
         ). Coelomic groove patterns are very similar in <tp:taxon-name> Himerometra
         </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 3A ) and <tp:taxon-name> Discometra </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 4 ) but
         differ markedly in each of the other genera ( Rasmussen 1978 : figs 593–594). The numerous
         radiating coelomic grooves (A.H. Clark 1915 ) distinguish <tp:taxon-name> Amphimetra
         </tp:taxon-name> the most from the other genera, and Hemery (2011), Summers &amp; Rouse
         (2014) and Taylor et al. (2017) questioned its attribution to
            <tp:taxon-name>Himerometridae</tp:taxon-name> . In <tp:taxon-name> Himerometra
         </tp:taxon-name> , the general shape of the centrodorsal varies from hemispherical to
         almost discoidal. The insertions of cirri on the centrodorsal have a very variable aspect
         on the same individual, with or without a slight rectangular transverse relief ( Fig. 3B ).
         The radial circlet delimits a more or less wide adoral cavity whose flanks corresponding to
         the inner face of the radials are sculpted by strong vermiculate figures ( Fig. 3C ). The
         distal articular facet of the radials is sub-trapezoidal, the internal (adoral) ligamentary
         areas, with no distinguishable limit adorally, are separated by a large depression, and the
         muscular areas are reduced and nearly inconspicuous ( Fig. 3D ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Stratigraphical range </p>
      <p>Miocene–Recent (Western Pacific), possibly since the Eocene.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
