<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Discometra luberonensis Eléaume
                        &amp; Roux &amp; Philippe 2020, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4419843</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B30387D7FF96CB355461BC57C27CE2AD</uri>
                  <article-title>Discometra luberonensis sp. nov. (Crinoidea, Himerometridae), a new
                        feather star from the Late Burdigalian</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Discometra luberonensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 2C82EC72-FEDC-4BCB-9716-88EEFDB0146D </p>
            <p> Fig. 2 A–F </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Robust species with arms up to 60 in number. Centrodorsal a rounded pentagonal,
                  flattened, truncated cone; basal diameter up to 14.3 mm ; aboral pole cirrus-free,
                  flattened and slightly depressed, smooth or very slightly granular, reaching ¾ of
                  centrodorsal diameter. Cirrus sockets in 2–3 irregular marginal rows. Cirri XXX–L
                  of up to at least 30 never higher than wide cirrals, 27.5 mm long. Arm pattern
                  with Ibr2ax, IIbr1-2 3+4ax; br1-2ax frequent up to fifth brachitaxis; ligamentary
                  synarthry at br1-2; multiradiate syzygy at br3+4; very oblique muscular
                  synarthries in proximal part of arms. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The epithet refers to the Massif du Lubéron, a major mountain range in the Provence
                  area where the specimens on which the description is based were collected. Lubéron
                  is part of the greater administrative area (Région) called Provence-Alpes-Côte
                  d’Azur in the southeast of France . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <tp:material-citation>
                  <p> Holotype </p>
                  <p> FRANCE • SE France , Vaucluse , Bassin d’Apt , Ménerbes-Lacoste Plateau ; MHNL
                        20.062682 . </p>
            </tp:material-citation>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> FRANCE • same collection data as for holotype; MHNL
                        20.056148 , 20.056151 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Locus typicus </p>
            <p> “Calcaire de Ménerbes” ( Demarcq 1970 ), facies with large pectinids (
                        <tp:taxon-name> Gigantopecten restitutensis </tp:taxon-name> ), quarries in
                  Ménerbes-Lacoste Plateau (Bassin d’Apt, Vaucluse, southeastern France ), Late
                  Burdigalian. </p>
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Holotype ( Fig. 2 A–B) </p>
            <p> Specimen well exposed aborally, displaying centrodorsal, proximal part of three
                  rays, about ten free arms visible in profile and recurved aborally, five cirri
                  still attached to centrodorsal, and many fragments of arms and isolated cirri.
                  Centrodorsal a flattened truncated cone; apex broad, almost flat and smooth,
                  devoid of cirrus sockets; cirrus sockets arranged in 2 to 3 irregular rows.
                  Maximum length of complete attached cirrus 27.50 mm with 30 cirrals; cirrals
                  subcylindrical; c1–c5 wider than high; following cirrals as high as wide; maximum
                  cirral diameter 1.0 mm, average width of proximal half of cirri 2.0 mm, most
                  frequent height of cirrals about 1 mm ; terminal claw slightly curved and about
                  twice as long as preceding segment. Radial circlet hidden. Arms divided 4 or 5
                  times; Ibr2 always axillary; secundibrachitaxes IIbr1-2 3+4ax (4 cases), IIbr
                  undivided (1); pattern observed in the following brachitaxes: IIIbr1-2ax (5), IVbr
                  1-2ax (4), IVbr 1-2 3+4ax (1), IVbr undivided (1), Vbr1-2ax (2), Vbr1-2 then
                  broken (2), Vbr1 2+3 4... (1), VIbr1-2 3+4... (2), estimated total number of arms
                  close to 60. Non-muscular (ligamentary) articulations: ligamentary synarthry at
                  1-2 and syzygy with multiradiate crenularium at 3+4 (most often ankylosed at
                  IIbr3+4); syzygies or synostoses irregularly arranged along free arms, separated
                  by 4 to 8 muscular synarthries; br1-9 more or less rectangular, following
                  brachials wedge-shaped. Maximum primibrachial width 7.10 mm ; maximum
                  primibrachitaxis length 6.30 mm ; Ibr2ax height 3.42 mm ; secondibrachial width
                  4.90 mm ; IIbr1-2 height 3.35 mm ; IIbr1-2 3+4ax maximum length 6.25 mm ; IIIbr1-2
                  width 3.50 mm , height 3.35 mm ; maximum height of tertibrachial axillary 2.0 mm;
                  average width of proximal half of distalmost free arm 2.65 mm ; longest isolated
                  fragment of free arm 38 mm with 26 brachials; maximum length of an attached free
                  arm 50.0 mm. Preserved pinnules rare, proximal part of P II robust, composed of
                  more or less squarish segments; more distal part of proximal pinnule getting
                  thinner and flexible with relatively short pinnulars (less than twice as high as
                  wide). </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p> Specimen MHNL 20.056148 ( Fig. 2 C–D) with largest centrodorsal diameter, aboral
                  cirrus-free depression flat and very slightly granular; about 30 cirri preserved
                  around centrodorsal hiding proximal part of crown; complete cirrus with 25
                  cirrals, length 26 mm , longest cirrus fragment 27 mm with 28 cirrals. Specimen
                  MHNL 20.056151 ( Fig. 2 E–F) with most flattened centrodorsal, aboral surface flat
                  and smooth with two small pits; only ¾ of crown preserved, one brachitaxis
                  visible, with same pattern as holotype ; visible arms 38, allowing an estimated
                  total number close to 60. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
