<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Phrynidius guifarroi Santos-Silva &amp; Roie &amp; Jocqué 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5237340</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B90887C9FFBAA612F06DFA360193A7E7</uri>
         <article-title>Longhorned woodboring beetles (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae) from Cusuco National Park, Honduras: new species, new records, and revalidation</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynidius guifarroi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
A45ED7C3-2D75-4648-A768-4B1C64F1768F
</p>
      <p>
Figs 20–25
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynidius guifarroi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. jonesi
Gutiérrez, Toledo-Hernández &amp; Noguera, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Figs 26–30
), but differs as follows: pronotum with wide, elevated crest centrally, from anterior fifth to after middle, with its dorsal surface rugose and uniformly convex (
Figs 24–25
); elytra with nearly glabrous area on basal fifth, close to scutellum and suture; and posterior tubercles of the elytra smaller. In 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. jonesi
</tp:taxon-name>
, the central crest of the pronotum is nearly conical, placed before the middle (
Fig. 26
), elytra with large nearly glabrous area placed centrally, and posterior tubercles of the elytra distinctly larger.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This species is named after Mario Guifarro from 
Olancho
, 
Honduras
, a hunter and gold miner who turned into a dedicated conservationist when he experienced the degradation of rainforests in eastern 
Honduras
. He was murdered in Moskitia in 2007 while setting up a protected forest zone.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
HONDURAS
• 
♀
; 
Cortés
, 
Cusuco National Park
, 
Danto
, 
close to camp
; 

29 Jun. 2015

; 
M. Jocqué
leg.; 
RBINS 34.248
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
HONDURAS
• 
♀
; 
Cortés
, 
Cusuco National Park
, 
Base Camp
, 
Transect
4; 

14 Jul. 2015

; 
T. Brown
leg.; 
MZSP
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Measurements in mm
(female 
holotype
/ female 
paratype
)
</p>
      <p>Total length, 11.25/ 12.05; prothoracic length, 3.05 / 3.45; anterior prothoracic width, 2.65 / 3.10; posterior prothoracic width, 2.60 / 2.90; widest prothoracic width, 3.10 / 3.45; humeral width, 2.70 / 3.10; elytral length, 7.30 / 7.85.</p>
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>

Female 
holotype

(
Figs 20–24
)
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Integument mostly black dorsally and laterally, mostly dark brown ventrally; head mostly black except apex of labrum orangish brown, basal area of anteclypeus, parts of labium, and apex of palpomeres reddish brown; scape, pedicel, and antennomeres III–IV dark brown; remaining antennomeres dark reddish brown. Posterocentral area of pronotum dark reddish brown. Scutellum orangish brown.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Frons with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence obscuring integument, and short, sparse whitish setae interspersed. Vertex and area behind eyes coarsely, sparsely punctate; with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence obscuring integument, except glabrous median groove. Antennal tubercles moderately elevated, slightly separated from each other, together forming V-shaped sulcus; pubescence as on frons, except narrow glabrous apex. Median groove distinct from clypeus to prothoracic margin (more distinct on vertex). Genae coarsely, sparsely punctate; with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence except narrow glabrous apex. Wide central area of postclypeus with pubescence as on frons, with long, erect brownish setae near anteclypeus; sides glabrous. Labrum coplanar with anteclypeus at posterior ⅔, inclined at anterior third; posterior ⅔ smooth close to anteclypeus, finely punctate close to inclined area; with very sparse yellowish-white pubescence on posterior ⅔, nearly glabrous close to anteclypeus, and long, erect yellowish-brown setae directed forward close to inclined area; anterior third with moderately short and abundant nearly golden setae. Gulamentum glabrous except narrow anterior area with pale yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument. Lower eye lobes 0.43 times as long as genal length; distance between upper eye lobes 0.42 times length of scape, 0.40 times distance between outer margins of eyes; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.75 times length of scape, 0.71 times distance between outer margins of eyes. Antennae 1.55 times elytral length, almost reaching elytral apex. Scape, pedicel, antennomere III, and basal 4/5 of IV with dense pale yellowishbrown pubescence obscuring integument, and short, sparse, decumbent or arched yellowish-white and brown setae interspersed; apical fifth of antennomere IV, and remaining antennomeres with very sparse yellowish-white pubescence. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.98; pedicel = 0.09; IV = 0.81; V = 0.32; VI = 0.30; VII = 0.30; VIII = 0.28; IX = 0.30; X = 0.26; XI = 0.28.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Prothorax as long as wide; sides arched on anterior quarter, slightly convergent, irregular on posterior ¾. Pronotum entirely rugose; in lateral view, distinctly, gradually elevated from anterior margin to near middle, then distinctly, gradually inclined toward posterior margin; with wide, elevated crest centrally, from anterior fifth to after middle, with its dorsal surface rugose and uniformly convex; coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with dense pale yellow pubescence, not obscuring punctures, except nearly glabrous posterocentral area, and small, irregular glabrous area on each side of middle. Sides of prothorax entirely rugose; coarsely, moderately abundantly punctate; with dense pale yellowishbrown pubescence not obscuring punctures. Prosternum with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence obscuring integument laterally, moderately sparser centrally. Prosternal process gradually widened from base to posterior quarter, strongly, moderately abruptly widened on posterior quarter; with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence, and irregular areas with slightly sparser pubescence interspersed. Central area of mesoventrite with moderately abundant pale yellowish-brown pubescence distinctly not obscuring integument; sides of mesoventrite, mesanepisternum, mesepimeron, metanepisternum, metaventrite, and mesoventral process with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence; mesanepisternum coarsely, moderately sparsely punctate; apex of mesoventrite emarginate centrally; metaventrite with short, decumbent, sparse yellowish-white setae interspersed. Scutellum very narrow, transverse, glabrous.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Entirely rugose, coarsely, deeply, moderately abundantly punctate; widest area (without tubercles) 1.8 times humeral width; with large conical tubercles, with glabrous apex; surface with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence, except glabrous apex of tubercles and glabrous large area close to scutellum and suture on basal fifth.</p>
      <p>
Figs 20–23.
<tp:taxon-name>
Phrynidius guifarroi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RBINS 34.248). 
20
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
21
. Habitus, ventral view. 
22
. Habitus, lateral view. 
23
. Head, frontal view. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 24–30. 24–25
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phrynidius guifarroi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, prothorax, lateral view. 
24
. Holotype, ♀ (RBINS 34.248). 
25
. Paratype, ♀ (MZSP). — 
26–30
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phrynidius jonesi
Gutiérrez, Toledo-Hernández &amp; Noguera, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (FSCA). 
26
. Prothorax, lateral view. 
27
. Head, frontal view. 
28
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
29
. Habitus, ventral view. 
30
. Habitus, laetral view. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Femora with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence, glabrous or almost so on apex, and short, decumbent yellowish-white setae interspersed. Tibiae with dense light beige pubescence, and short, decumbent yellowish-white setae interspersed, except almost glabrous area close to apex; apical margin of all tibiae, and dorsal area close to apex of mesotibiae with thick, nearly golden setae. Dorsal surface of tarsomeres with minute, slightly distinct yellowish-brown pubescence, not obscuring integument; central area of apex of tarsomeres I and II with two pairs of short, thick yellowish setae.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Ventrites with dense pale yellowish-brown pubescence.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The male of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. jonesi
</tp:taxon-name>
examined by us is from the same Mexican state as the 
holotype
(

Gutiérrez 
et al.
2020

): “ 

Chiapas

: Montebello lake area, 
15-16.VI.1987
, J.E. Wappes leg.” (ACMT).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
