<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Strangalia lunai Santos-Silva &amp; Roie &amp; Jocqué 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5237342</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D543BF0DB56499038CBD69C928263DA9</uri>
         <article-title>Longhorned woodboring beetles (Coleoptera, Cerambycidae) from Cusuco National Park, Honduras: new species, new records, and revalidation</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Strangalia lunai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3E106974-DA9C-4583-8C19-1948CF655C00
</p>
      <p>
Figs 31–35
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The general appearance of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Strangalia lunai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. beltii
(Bates, 1872)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. bivittata
(Bates, 1870)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. doyeni
Chemsak &amp; Linsley, 1976
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. eickworti
Chemsak &amp; Noguera, 1997
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. elegans
Giesbert, 1997
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. emaciata
(Bates, 1880)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. instabilis
Giesbert, 1985
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. occidentalis
Linsley &amp; Chemsak, 1976
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. pectoralis
(Bates, 1885)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. picticornis
(Bates, 1869)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. sallaei
(Bates, 1885)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. saltator
(Bates, 1885)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. sexocellata
Hovore &amp; Chemsak, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. veracruzana
Hovore &amp; Chemsak, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
(see photographs on 
Bezark 2021b
). Males of the new species differ from those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. beltii
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. bivittata
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. elegans
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. picticornis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. saltator
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. veracruzana
</tp:taxon-name>
by the pronotum lacking two longitudinal dark bands (present in all these species); from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. doyeni
</tp:taxon-name>
by the pronotum mostly black (orange in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. doyeni
</tp:taxon-name>
), and by the sides of the abdominal ventrite V not strongly flap-shaped (noticeably flap-shaped in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. doyeni
</tp:taxon-name>
); from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. eickworti
</tp:taxon-name>
by the distal antennomeres not distinctly yellowish (distinctly yellowish in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. eickworti
</tp:taxon-name>
), and profemora bicolorous (unicolorous in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. eickworti
</tp:taxon-name>
); from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. emaciata
</tp:taxon-name>
by last antennomeres not distinctly yellowish (distinctly yellowish in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. emaciata
</tp:taxon-name>
), and maxillary palpomere IV not widened apically (widely expanded in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. emaciata
</tp:taxon-name>
); from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. instabilis
</tp:taxon-name>
by the distal antennomeres not distinctly yellowish (distinctly yellowish in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. instabilis
</tp:taxon-name>
), and sides of the abdominal ventrite V not strongly flap-shaped (noticeably flap-shaped in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. instabilis
</tp:taxon-name>
); from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. occidentalis
</tp:taxon-name>
by the sides of the abdominal ventrite V not strongly flap-shaped (noticeably flap-shaped in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. occidentalis
</tp:taxon-name>
); from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. pectoralis
</tp:taxon-name>
by the elytra proportionally longer (shorter in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. pectoralis
</tp:taxon-name>
); from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. sexocellata
</tp:taxon-name>
by the antennae only surpassing middle of elytra (reaching elytral apex in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. sexocellata
</tp:taxon-name>
). Males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. sallaei
</tp:taxon-name>
are unknown. However, based on other similar species, the pronotum probably has two dark longitudinal bands and the antennae are distinctly bicolorous.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This species is named after Carlos Antonio Luna Lùopez (Carlos Luna for short), former director of La Unidad Ambientalista (UMA) and environmental activist. He was murdered in Catacamas, 
May 1998
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
HONDURAS
• 
♂
; 
Cortés
, 
Cusuco National Park
, 
Base Camp
; 

12 Jun. 2015

; local collector leg.; 
RBINS 34.248
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Measurements in mm
(male 
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>Total length, 19.50; prothoracic length, 3.00; anterior prothoracic width, 1.45; posterior prothoracic width, 2.90; humeral width, 3.50; elytral length, 11.30.</p>
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>

Male 
holotype

(
Figs 31–35
)
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Head mostly black; anterior area of clypeus orangish brown; labrum brown; mouthparts with some areas orangish brown; antennae black except ventral surface of antennomeres IX–XI partially orangish brown; mandibles black. Prothorax black except orange posterocentral macula on pronotum, most of posterolateral angles, and irregular macula on sides of prothorax, between posterolateral angles and coxal cavity. Mesoventrite dark brown, almost black; mesanepisternum brownish, with large orange macula near mesepimeron, and margins darkened; mesepimeron orange close to metanepisternum; mesoventral process orange except black margins. Metanepisternum brown with irregular orangish areas interspersed. Metaventrite brown (darker on large central area), except wide V-shaped orange macula anteriorly (this macula distinctly widened laterally). Scutellum brown. Elytra mostly orange, except: narrow black band along suture, from scutellum to apex; black epipleural margin, from base to near apex; macula on anterior quarter, fused with epipleural black area, following toward dorsal surface, not reaching black sutural area and humerus (anterior margin of this macula deeply notched laterally and dorsally); black semicircular macula before middle, fused with epipleural black macula, following toward dorsal surface, not reaching black sutural area; large, elongate black macula starting centrally, ending about posterior quarter, distinctly reaching dorsal surface, not reaching black sutural area, with its anterior region fused with black epipleural margin, then gradually separated from epipleural margins toward its narrowed apex (this macula gradually brownish toward its apex); posterior seventh mostly brownish. Pro- and mesocoxae black basally, orange on remaining surface; metacoxae mostly orange, with some areas slightly brownish. Profemora orange except black posterior ⅔ of dorsal surface and superior area of sides; mesofemora orange except black posterior half of dorsal surface, and entire apex (black posterior area gradually narrowed laterally); metafemora orange on basal half, black on posterior half. Tibiae and tarsi black. Abdominal ventrite I orange except narrow, transverse brownish band close to posterior margin; II black, except orange centrally; III black basally (this area distinctly widened laterally), orange on remaining surface; IV mostly orangish brown, with on brown macula on each side of anterior region, and brown apex; V orangish brown centrally (this area slightly darker than on IV), brown laterally.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Frons somewhat elevated along median groove, this area drop-shaped with its widest area toward clypeus, depressed inside, its sides as a carinate projection of antennal tubercles, smooth except a few fine punctures on its widest area; sides and central area close to clypeus finely, abundantly punctate; with short, erect, moderately abundantly yellowish-brown setae on punctate area, with a few long, erect setae of same color interspersed, glabrous on elevated central area; frontoclypeal suture absent. Vertex finely, densely, partially confluently punctate before constricted neck, punctures finer and denser than on frons; neck finely, abundantly punctate, punctures coarser than on anterior region of vertex, not confluent, slightly sparser centrally; area before neck with short, abundant yellowish-brown setae, and a few long, erect setae of same color interspersed; neck with yellowish-brown setae shorter, distinctly sparser than on anterior region of vertex, especially centrally. Tumid area behind upper eye lobes smooth close to vertex, finely, sparsely punctate close to lower eye lobe; neck area finely, sparsely punctate (punctures coarser than on vertex); with abundant erect setae close to vertex, with short, sparse yellowish-brown setae on remaining surface. Tumid area behind lower eye lobes obliquely striate-punctate; neck area longitudinally striate-punctate; with short, sparse yellowish-brown setae, longer, slightly more abundant on tumid area close to inferior margin. Genae about as long as maximum width of lower eye lobe; carinate close to frons and clypeus, longitudinally depressed close to carina; finely, abundantly punctate on depressed area, finely, sparsely punctate on remaining surface; with short, sparse yellowish-brown setae, slightly longer and more abundant close to carina. Clypeus finely, moderately sparsely punctate close to frons, smooth close to labrum; with short, erect, moderately sparse yellowish-brown setae on punctate area, longer laterally, glabrous on smooth area. Labrum with short, sparse golden setae centrally, longer, abundant laterally, and fringe of golden setae on anterior margin. Maxillary palpomeres IV not widened apically, general shape nearly fusiform. Gulamentum somewhat rugose-punctate, with short, erect, moderately abundant yellowish-brown setae, and a few long setae of same color interspersed. Distance between upper eye lobes 0.95 times length of scape, 0.49 times distance between outer margins of eyes; in frontal view, distance between lower eye lobes 0.83 times length of scape, 0.42 times distance between outer margins of eyes. Antennae 1.35 times elytral length, surpassing middle of elytra; with yellowish-brown pubescence not obscuring integument, appearing to be darker due to integument color, especially depending on angle of light source; antennomeres III–IV cylindrical, antennomere V slightly widened toward apex; antennomeres VI–X subserrate; antennomere XI cylindrical in basal ⅔, acutely narrowed toward apex in posterior third; sensory depressions on antennomeres VIII–XI eroding apex of segment. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.68; pedicel = 0.11; IV = 0.82; V = 1.00; VI = 0.86; VII = 0.79; VIII = 0.68; IX = 0.65; X = 0.57; XI = 0.79.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Prothorax slightly longer than wide, with anterior constriction well-marked; sides gradually widened from rounded anterolateral angles to acute posterolateral angles, rounded, widened before middle. Pronotum with anterior margin straight, and posterior margin rounded, widely projected centrally; surface finely, densely punctate, except smooth central area near anterior margin, and central longitudinal sulcus from apex of anterior quarter to base of posterior quarter; with abundant golden pubescence close to anterior margin (pubescence absent on smooth area), sides, and on posterocentral orange macula; remaining surface with yellowish-brown pubescence distinctly not obscuring integument. Sides of prothorax finely, densely punctate, except nearly smooth anterior area, and coarse, shallow, sparse punctures interspersed on posterior half; with abundant golden pubescence not obscuring integument, except nearly glabrous anterior area (with a few long, erect setae close to prosternum on this latter area). Prosternum finely, densely punctate on sides of posterior half, punctures sparse centrally, mostly smooth centrally, somewhat rugose-punctate laterally on anterior half; sides with abundant, short, bristly golden setae, distinctly sparer centrally. Prosternal process laminiform on wide central area. Mesoventrite finely, densely punctate except smooth lateral apices; with golden pubescence not obscuring integument, except glabrous smooth areas. Mesoventral process somewhat tumid centrally; with abundant golden pubescence on posterior half. Mesanepisternum and mesepimeron with abundant yellowish pubescence. Metanepisternum and metaventrite with abundant golden pubescence; metaventrite lacking tubercles or carina centrally near apex. Scutellum with abundant golden pubescence.</p>
      <p>
Figs 31–35.
<tp:taxon-name>
Strangalia lunai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (RBINS 34.248). 
31
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
32
. Habitus, ventral view. 
33
. Habitus, lateral view. 
34
. Head, frontal view. 
35
. Apex of abdomen. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Distinctly narrowed from humerus to about middle, then with outer and sutural margins nearly parallel sided toward oblique apex; outer apical angle spiniform; sutural angle with short spiniform projection; moderately coarsely, abundantly punctate throughout; orange area with golden pubescence not obscuring integument, except area closer to dark integument with decumbent, moderately abundant black setae; black area with grayish pubescence not obscuring integument, appearing to be darker depending on angle of light source, especially due to integument color. Femora with yellowish pubescence not obscuring integument, appearing to be darker on black area due to integument color and angle source. Tibiae with golden pubescence, denser posteriorly, especially ventrally; metatibia with tubercle or plate apically.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Surpassing elytral apex about middle of forth segment. Ventrites with abundant yellowish pubescence not obscuring integument; ventrite V excavated for less than ¾ its length, with sides not strongly flap-shaped.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Strangalia lunai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be included in the alternative of couplet ‘26’ from 
Giesbert (1997)
:
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>26(25). Pronotum about as long as width across base; disk with narrow, longitudinal, median, glabrous line ......................................................................................................................................... 26’</p>
      <p>– Pronotum shorter than width across base; disk without glabrous line ................................... 27</p>
      <p>
26’(26). Antennae nearly reaching elytral apex; outer elytral margin entirely black; sides of abdominal ventrite V flap-shaped from base to apex. 
Guatemala
.................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. zacapensis
Giesbert, 1997
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Antennae distinctly not reaching elytral apex; outer elytral margin not entirely black; sides of abdominal ventrite V not flap-shaped from base to apex. 
Honduras
................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. lunai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
