<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amblypsilopus freidbergi Grichanov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4986010</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BA5B878EFFABA77A110CF9372A1E9156</uri>
         <article-title>Eleven new species of Amblypsilopus Bigot (Diptera: Dolichopodidae: Sciapodinae) and a key to the species of Madagascar and adjacent islands</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1399</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus freidbergi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
EFAF1461-1455-4045-9E80-891385BF1760
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Having all coxae entirely yellow and fore tibia with a long modified posterior seta, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus freidbergi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
keys to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. pallidicornis
</tp:taxon-name>
, which differs from the new species in the antenna yellow; the fore tibia as long as the basitarsus; the face broad, about three times as wide as the postpedicel; the fore basitarsus ventrally at base with cluster of very short bristlets and one longer and stronger black bristle. The antenna is black in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. freidbergi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, the fore tibia is 
7/10
as long as the basitarsus; the face is narrow, about as wide as the postpedicel; the fore tarsus has segment 4 black, segment 5 silvery white; the fore basitarsus is thin and long, with long white ventral hairs on basal 
1/5
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named for the collector of the 
types
, Dr Amnon Freidberg (SMNHTAU).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Analamazaotra Forest
; 
18°46ʹ S
, 
48°24ʹ E
; 

950 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Oct.–4 Nov. 2007

; 
A. Freidberg
leg.; 
SMNHTAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
MADAGASCAR
• 
2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
SMNHTAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 10A
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
5–5.25 mm
; antenna length 
1 mm
; wing length 
4.5 mm
; wing width 
1.2 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 10B
). Frons black (lateral view), white pollinose; strong short anterior vertical and long postvertical bristles; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white hairs; face black, white pollinose (lateral view), narrow, about 4 times as high as wide under antennae, 12–15 times as high as wide at clypeus, at clypeus half as wide as postpedicel; clypeus small, slightly bulging; antenna (
Fig. 10C
) black, about as long as height of head; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal bristle; postpedicel globular, as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus dorsoapical, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.06/0.06/0.09/0.83; proboscis orange-yellow; palpus small, brown, with white and black hairs.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum and scutellum metallic blue-green; pleura blackish brown, weakly pollinose; metepimeron yellow; 6 strong dorsocentral bristles gradually decreasing in size anteriorly with strongest posterior pair; acrostichals short, biserial, decreasing in size anteriorly, with strongest posterior pair at suture; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Mostly yellow; coxae yellow; segment 4 of fore tarsus black; segment 5 of fore tarsus silvery white; last segments of mid and hind tarsi brown; fore and mid coxae with light and dark hairs and 2–3 black subapical setae; hind coxa with 1 black seta at middle; femora without strong or long setae; fore tibia with long apicoventral light bristle, nearly three times as long as width of tibia; fore basitarsus thin and long, with long white ventral hairs on basal 
1/5
, two times as long as width of segment (
Fig. 10D
); segments 4–5 slightly thickened, segment 4 with black elongate setulae; segment 5 with white elongate setulae (
Fig. 10E
); mid tibia with 2 anterodorsals and 2 short posterodorsals, without conspicuous ventral setae; mid and hind tarsi simple, cylindrical; hind tibia with several short dorsal and ventral setae; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.29/1.79/3.06/0.58/0.41/0.26/0.14, mid leg: 1.45/2.92/2.13/0.4/0.25/0.18/0.13, hind leg: 2.09/3.22/1.37/0.59/0.34/0.21/0.15.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 10F
). Widest at middle, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M inconspicuously sinuate in basal half, slightly convex anteriad in middle part; M 
1
with strong elbow, forming right angle with M 
1+2
; ratio of parts of costa between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
to those between R 
4+5
and M 
1
, 5/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M4, 0.46/0.79/0.19; anal vein and lobe reduced; anal angle absent; lower calypter brownish, with fine brown cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
1+2
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Elongate, mostly greenish blue, with short black hairs and marginal setae; tergite 1 yellow; tergites 2–5 each with large lateral yellow spot; pregenital segments combined two times as long as mesonotum; segment 7 short, semicircular, embracing basolateral sides of epandrium; segment 8 as a weak plate hidden under segment 7 and covering basal symmetrical foramen; hypopygium (
Fig. 10G
) brown, with brown appendages; hypandrium short, arising at apical third of epandrium, with 2 unequal arms; phallus thick, with subtriangular thickening at apex; cercus yellow, bifurcated from base; dorsal arm two times as long as epandrium, thin, flattened, slightly wider on basal half, covered with long hairs dorsally and apically, with lateral row of 12–14 long brownish setae along entire length; ventral arms of cerci fused to apex, S-shaped, mostly hidden by surstyli, projected ventrally; ventral arm of each cercus with 2 long thick apical bristles, as long as height of epandrium, and one shorter simple ventral subapical seta; surstylus strongly sclerotized, bilobed, with large flat rounded arms expanding distally, subequal in size, without remarkable setae; basal half of dorsal arm of surstylus concealed; large epandrial lobe projected distally, with one long thick apical bristle, strong spine-like inner process at apex, big subtriangular ventral subapical projection bearing 2 simple setae; small finger-like lobe at base of distoventral epandrial lobe, with 2 apical setae; 1 epandrial seta at base of hypandrium (
Fig. 10H
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus freidbergi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–F
. Holotype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
G–H
. Paratype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
A
. Habitus. 
B
. Head. 
C
. Antenna. 
D
. Fore basitarsus. 
E
. Fore tarsomeres 2–5. 
F
. Wing. 
G
. Hypopygium, left lateral view, reflected light. 
H
. Distoventral appendages of hypopygium, transmitted light.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
