<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amblypsilopus leonidi Grichanov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4986018</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BA5B878EFFA8A744113EFC962A1E9793</uri>
         <article-title>Eleven new species of Amblypsilopus Bigot (Diptera: Dolichopodidae: Sciapodinae) and a key to the species of Madagascar and adjacent islands</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1399</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus leonidi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
7436C062-7C49-4E10-BBB7-D9C511C8D7BD
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 11
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus leonidi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. andasibensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. olgae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in habitus. The last two species differ from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. leonidi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in the fore tarsomeres 4–5 white or tarsomere 5 entirely white, and the male cercus with a strongly projected median lobe. The fore tarsomeres 4–5 are entirely black in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. leonidi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; the cercus has median and ventral lobes subequal in length.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name is dedicated to Leonid Grichanov, one of my grandsons (
St. Petersburg
, 
Russia
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Analamazaotra Forest
; 
18°46ʹ S
, 
48°24ʹ E
; 

950 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Oct.–4 Nov. 2007

; 
A. Freidberg
leg.; 
SMNHTAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
MADAGASCAR
• 
6 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
SMNHTAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 11A
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
6.3 mm
; antenna length 
1.3 mm
; wing length 
5.2 mm
; wing width 
1.2 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 11B
). Frons black, white pollinose; strong short anterior vertical and long postvertical bristles; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white hairs; face densely silvery-white pollinose, narrow, 4.5 times as wide under antennae, 9 times as high as wide at clypeus, at clypeus as wide as postpedicel; clypeus small, slightly bulging; antenna (
Fig. 11C
) with scape and pedicel dirty yellow, postpedicel orange on basal half and brown distally, 1.7 times as long as height of head; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal bristle; postpedicel ovate, 1.3 times as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus dorsal, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.08/0.08/0.11/1.04; proboscis orange; palpus blackish, with white and brown hairs.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum orange, with brown, shining greenish blue, medial stripe expanding posteriorly; scutellum metallic blue; pleura yellow, weakly pollinose; 6 strong dorsocentral bristles gradually decreasing in size anteriorly with strongest posterior pair; acrostichals short, biserial; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 11.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus leonidi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–E
. Holotype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
F–G
. Paratype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
A
. Habitus. 
B
. Head. 
C
. Antenna. 
D
. Fore tarsomeres 4–5. 
E
. Wing. 
F
. Hypopygium, left lateral view, reflected light. 
G
. Cercal lobes, lateral view, transmitted light.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Mostly yellow; coxae yellow; tarsi brown from tip of basitarsus; segments 4 and 5 of fore tarsus black; fore and mid coxae with light and dark hairs and 2–3 black subapical setae; hind coxa with 1 black seta at middle; femora without strong or long setae; fore tibia without conspicuous setae; fore basitarsus thin and long, with 6 short ventral setae, two times as long as width of segment; segments 4–5 flattened dorsoventrally, slightly widened, with black flattened setae laterally, longer than tarsomere width (
Fig. 11D
); mid tibia with one short anterodorsal and two short posterodorsals, without conspicuous ventral setae; mid and hind tarsi simple, cylindrical; hind tibia with several short dorsal and ventral setae; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.43/2.08/5.21/0.55/0.6/0.26/0.2, mid leg: 1.77/4.13/3.27/0.63/0.41/0.22/0.17, hind leg: 2.83/4.68/2.06/0.74/0.43/0.22/0.16.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 11E
). Widened distally, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M 
1+2
straight in basal half, slightly convex anteriad in middle part; M 
1
with strong elbow, forming right angle with M 
1+2
; ratio of parts of costa between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
to those between R 
4+5
and M 
1
, 6/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M 
4
, 0.43/1.24/0.31; anal vein and lobe reduced; anal angle absent; lower calypter brownish, with fine brown cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Thin and long, mostly orange-yellow, brown along distal margin of tergite 2 and along dorsal side of tergites 3–6, with short black hairs and marginal setae; pregenital segments combined nearly three times as long as mesonotum; hypopygium (
Fig. 11F
) brown, with brown to black appendages; cercus (
Fig. 11G
) brown, trilobed; dorsal arm short, half as long as epandrium, thick at base, narrow distally, densely covered with numerous setulae at base, with long dark setae along narrow part; median lobe of cercus as long as epandrium, thin, with triangular subapical dorsal process and one long flat falcate seta; ventral arm of cercus as long as epandrium, thicker than median lobe, with one long flat subapical seta directed distally, 3 short thick apicoventral setae directed basally, one long thick subapical L-shaped process; arms of cerci fused at base; surstylus bilobed, with sclerotized arms; dorsal arm of surstylus thin, with 2 pointed apical processes and 2 subapical processes ending with long thick seta each; ventral arm of surstylus broad, curved towards median axis of epandrium, bearing 3 long strong bristles at apex; epandrial lobe projected, sclerotized, with 1 apical and 2 ventral short setae; 1 epandrial seta at base of epandrial lobe.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
