<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amblypsilopus bairae Grichanov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4985990</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/44D67C3BEFDF4E4CEE4723E4FEABA393</uri>
         <article-title>Eleven new species of Amblypsilopus Bigot (Diptera: Dolichopodidae: Sciapodinae) and a key to the species of Madagascar and adjacent islands</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1399</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus bairae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
B618714C-44F2-4845-AAC7-572FDE8890DD
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus bairae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. flavus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. friedmani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in habitus. The last two species differ from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. bairae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in the fore basitarsus at least two times as long as tibia and in a bifurcated cercus. Fore basitarsus 1.5 times as long as tibia in the new species; fore tibia and tarsus entirely covered with erect setulae, about as long as diameter of podomeres, somewhat longer at base of tibia and at base of basitarsus; cercus with broad and high basal part and long filiform distal part (
Fig. 2F–G
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name is dedicated to Baira Grichanova, mother of my grandchildren (
St. Petersburg
, 
Russia
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Analamazaotra Forest
; 
18°46′ S
, 
48°24ʹ E
; 

950 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Oct.–4 Nov. 2007

; 
A. Freidberg
leg.; 
SMNHTAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 2A
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
5.7 mm
; antenna length 
3.3 mm
; wing length 
5.4 mm
; wing width 
1.7 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 2B
). Frons greenish blue-black, whitish pollinose; anterior vertical seta absent; long and strong postvertical bristle; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white long hairs; face blue-black, white pollinose, broad, 1.2 times as high as wide under antennae, 2.2 times as high as than wide at clypeus, at clypeus 2.5 times as wide as postpedicel; clypeus large, slightly bulging, as high as wide; antenna (
Fig. 2C
) with scape and pedicel dirty yellow, postpedicel brown-black, 3.6 times as long as height of head; scape swollen; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal and two long ventral bristles; postpedicel elongate-conoid, 1.25 times as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus black, apical, separated from postpedicel, with fused segments, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.09/0.08/0.15/3.03; proboscis and palpus orange, with white and black hairs; palpus with 1 black bristle.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus bairae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Holotype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
A
. Habitus. 
B
. Head. 
C
. Antenna. 
D
. Fore tibia. 
E
. Wing. 
F
. Hypopygium, left lateral view, reflected light. 
G
. Epandrial lobe, surstylus and base of cercus, lateral view, transmitted light.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum orange-brown, shining, weakly pollinose; scutellum black dorsally, metallic bluish green; pleura dark brown, white pollinose; metepimeron yellow; 2 long dorsocentral bristles with strongest posterior pair, and 3 hairlike setae anteriorly; acrostichals long, biserial, gradually decreasing in size anteriorly, with posterior setae as long as penultimate dorsocentrals; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Mostly yellow or dirty yellow; coxae yellow, but mid and hind coxae brownish from outside; fore tarsus brown from tip of basitarsus; mid and hind tarsi black from tip of basitarsus; fore and mid coxae with long white and black hairs and 2–4 black subapical bristles; hind coxa with 1 black seta at middle; fore femur with anterior row of long setae on basal half, about as long as diameter of femur, and 2–3 posterior long setae at base; mid femur with posteroventral subapical seta; fore tibia (
Fig. 2D
) and tarsus entirely covered with erect setulae, about as long as diameter of podomeres, somewhat longer at base of tibia and at base of basitarsus; mid tibia with 2 anterodorsals and 2 posterodorsals, with 1 ventral seta; mid and hind tarsi simple, cylindrical; hind tibia with several dorsal and short ventral setae; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.78/1.88/2.51/0.78/0.7/0.46/0.21, mid leg: 1.74/2.5/2.06/0.74/0.51/0.3/0.14, hind leg: 2.13/3.34/1.49/0.85/0.43/0.14/0.1.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 2E
). Weakly widened distally, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M1+2 straight; M1 with strong elbow, forming nearly right angle with M1+2 and obtuse angle with M 
2
; ratio of parts of costa between R and R 
4+5
to those between R 
4+5
and M 
1
, 3.35/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M 
4
, 0.66/1.08/0.35; anal vein and lobe weakly developed; anal angle obtuse; lower calypter yellow, with black cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
2+3
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Thin, mostly shining blue-green, with short black hairs and long marginal setae; segment 1 yellow, with white and dark hairs; segments 2–3 mostly orange-yellow, blackish distally; segments 4–6 black; pregenital segments combined 2.3 times as long as mesonotum; hypopygium (
Fig. 2F
) orange-brown, with brown appendages; cercus with short narrow neck bearing 2 very long and 2 short pedunculate setae, with broad and high basal part bearing short setae along distal and ventral margins, with long filiform distal part covered with brown-black setae along whole length and curved hairs ventrally; surstylus (
Fig. 2G
) projected, bilobed; dorsal arm of surstylus deeply cleft, with 3 apical and subapical setae on each lobe; ventral arm of surstylus small, finger-like, with 3 small setae apically; epandrial lobe small, triangular, with 1 basal, 1 median and 1 apical seta.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
