<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amblypsilopus friedmani Grichanov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4985992</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/39F6AA005829AF9ABD5C3F63A3E0BCBA</uri>
         <article-title>Eleven new species of Amblypsilopus Bigot (Diptera: Dolichopodidae: Sciapodinae) and a key to the species of Madagascar and adjacent islands</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1399</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus friedmani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
181E8507-D660-4EF4-92A1-56E9BEFF963D
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus friedmani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is very close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. flavus
</tp:taxon-name>
in habitus. The latter differs from the new species in the fore and mid femora with at most a few elongate anteroventral and posteroventral setae, at most half as long as femur diameter; the fore tibia and basitarsus without groups of elongate ventral setae at base; the cercus with one bristle between lobes, half as long as ventral lobe. Fore and mid femora of the new species are covered with anteroventral and posteroventral rows of setae, nearly as long as femur diameter; the fore tibia and basitarsus each bear group of elongate ventral setae at base, longer than podomere diameter; cercus has moderately broad neck and 2 long filiform arms and one very long seta between arms.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named for the collector of the 
types
, Dr Leonid Friedman (SMNHTAU).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Feon’Ny Ala Hôtel
; [
18°56′49.7″ S
, 
48°25′08.8″ E
]; 

5 Dec. 2007

; 
L. Friedman
leg.; 
SMNHTAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
SMNHTAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 4A
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
5.9 mm
; antenna length 
3.2 mm
; wing length 
5.9 mm
; wing width 
1.7 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 4B
). Frons greenish blue-violet, weakly pollinose; very short anterior vertical and long and strong postvertical bristles; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white long hairs; face greenish blue-violet, weakly pollinose, broad, 1.2 times as high as wide under antennae, 1.9 times as high as wide at clypeus, at clypeus three times as wide as postpedicel; clypeus white pollinose, large, slightly bulging, as high as wide; antenna (
Fig. 4C
) dirty yellow, brown at apex of postpedicel, three times as long as height of head; scape swollen; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal bristle; postpedicel conoid, 1.2 times as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus brown-black, apical, separated from postpedicel, with fused segments, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.09/0.07/0.13/2.87; proboscis and palpus orange, with white and black hairs; palpus with 2 black bristles.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum and scutellum mostly metallic bluish green, weakly pollinose; mesonotum brown on anterior slope; pleura brown-black with bronze-green reflection, grey pollinose; metepimeron yellow; 2 long dorsocentral bristles with strongest posterior pair, and 2–3 hairlike setae anteriorly; acrostichals long, biserial, gradually decreasing in size anteriorly, with posterior setae as long as penultimate dorsocentrals; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 minute hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Mostly yellow; coxae yellow, but mid coxa brownish from outside; fore tarsus brown from tip of basitarsus; mid and hind tarsi black from tip of basitarsus; fore and mid coxae with long white hairs and 2–4 yellow subapical bristles; mid and hind coxae with 1 black seta at middle; fore femur with anterior row of setae, at most as long as diameter of femur, and 1–2 posterior setae at base; mid femur with anterior and posteroventral rows of elongate setulae, with posteroventral subapical seta; hind femur without long hairs; fore tibia with 1 anterodorsal row of erect setulae, longer at base; fore basitarsus long, without setae; all segments of fore tarsus (
Fig. 4D
) with ventral rows of erect and semi-erect hairs, longer at base of basitarsus; mid tibia with 3 anterodorsals and 3 posterodorsals, without conspicuous ventral setae; mid and hind tarsi simple, cylindrical; hind tibia with several strong dorsal and short ventral setae; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.42/1.71/3.39/0.76/0.65/0.37/ 0.19, mid leg: 1.73/2.49/2.61/0.62/0.42/0.23/0.16, hind leg: 2.09/3.69/1.91/0.75/0.48/0.26/0.14.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus friedmani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–E
. Holotype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
F–G
. Paratype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
A
. Habitus. 
B
. Head. 
C
. Antenna. 
D
. Fore tarsomeres 2–5. 
E
. Wing. 
F
. Hypopygium, left lateral view, reflected light. 
G
. Distoventral appendages of hypopygium, transmitted light.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 4 E
). Weakly widened distally, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M straight in basal half, slightly convex anteriad in middle part; M 
1
with strong elbow, forming right angle with M 
1+2
; ratio of parts of costa between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
to those between R 
4+5
and M 
1
, 4/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M4, 0.74/1.13/0.37; anal vein weak; anal lobe well developed; anal angle acute; lower calypter yellow, with brown cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
1+2
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Thin, mostly shining blue-green, with short black hairs and long marginal setae; segment 1 yellow, with white and dark hairs; segments 2–3 orange, brown along distal margin; pregenital segments combined two times as long as mesonotum; hypopygium (
Fig. 4F
) brown, with black hypandrium and yellow cercus; cercus with moderately broad neck and 2 long filiform arms and one very long seta between arms; dorsal arm of cercus covered with light setae dorsally, with one very long apical seta; ventral arm of cercus with 5–7 short apical and subapical setae; surstylus (
Fig. 4G
) broad, projected, bilobed; dorsal arm of surstylus deeply cleft, with 2–3 apical and subapical setae on each lobe; ventral arm of surstylus small, finger-like, with 2 small setae apically; epandrial lobe small, triangular, with 1 basal, 1 median and 1 apical seta.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
      <p>
Notes
</p>
      <p>
The Feon’Ny Ala Hôtel (
Fig. 13
) is beside the Analamazaotra Special Reserve. The new species is collected at the damp forest edge close to hotel huts (L. Friedman, pers. com. 2020).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
