<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amblypsilopus marinae Grichanov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4985994</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/88510E2FD7D2AAFE66263F3F40027DE0</uri>
         <article-title>Eleven new species of Amblypsilopus Bigot (Diptera: Dolichopodidae: Sciapodinae) and a key to the species of Madagascar and adjacent islands</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1399</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus marinae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
2FD8C8FF-FE43-43CC-B0D1-364A2AA3DCF5
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus marinae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is very close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. grootaerti
</tp:taxon-name>
in habitus. The latter differs from the new species in the mid tibia with dorsal row of erect hairs except basal fifth, slightly longer than diameter of tibia; the fore and mid basitarsi without long erect setae; ventral lobe of cercus expanded distally; apical bristle on dorsal lobe of cercus at most 1.5 times as long as other cercal setae (
Grichanov 1998
: fig. 27). Mid tibia in the new species has a dorsal row of short erect hooked setae along entire length, nearly two times as long as diameter of tibia; the mid basitarsus bears a posterodorsal row of fine curved erect setae along entire length, ending with a small leaf-like seta; segments 2–3 of mid tarsus each with posterodorsal row of 5 small leaf-like setae; segment 4 with 2 leaf-like setae; ventral lobe of cercus narrow to apex; apical bristle on dorsal lobe of cercus at least two times as long as other cercal setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name is dedicated to Marina Grichanova, mother of my grandsons (
St. Petersburg
, 
Russia
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Analamazaotra Forest
; 
18°46ʹ S
, 
48°24ʹ E
; 

950 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Oct.–4 Nov. 2007

; 
A. Freidberg
leg.; 
SMNHTAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
MADAGASCAR
• 
3 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
SMNHTAU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 5A
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
5.2 mm
; antenna length 
2.7 mm
; wing length 
4.7 mm
; wing width 
1.3 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 5B
). Frons greenish blue-violet, weakly pollinose; short and strong anterior vertical and long and strong postvertical bristles; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white long hairs; face greenish blue-violet, weakly pollinose, broad, 1.4 times as high as wide under antennae, 2.2 times as high as wide at clypeus, at clypeus 2.5 times as wide as postpedicel; clypeus shining, large, slightly bulging, as high as wide; antenna (
Fig. 5 C
) dirty yellow, brownish at apex of postpedicel, three times as long as height of head; scape swollen; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal bristle; postpedicel conoid, 1.5 times as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus black, brownish at base, apical, separated from postpedicel, with fused segments, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.11/0.08/0.15/2.33; proboscis and palpus orange, with white and black hairs; palpus with 2 black bristles.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum and scutellum mostly metallic bluish green, weakly pollinose; pleura brownblack with bronze-green reflection, grey pollinose; metepimeron yellow; 3 long dorsocentral bristles behind suture with strongest posterior pair; acrostichals short, biserial, decreasing in size anteriorly, with strongest posterior pair at suture; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 minute hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Mostly yellow; coxae yellow, but mid coxa brown from outside; fore tarsus with brownish basitarsus and black segment 5; mid and hind tarsi with black segment 5; fore and mid coxae with mostly black hairs and 2–4 black subapical bristles; mid and hind coxae with 1 black seta at middle; fore femur with several anteroventral setae at base, at most as long as diameter of femur, and row of posterodorsal setae on basal half decreasing in length distally with 2 basal setae two times as long as diameter of femur; mid femur with anteroventral row of elongate setulae, with posteroventral subapical seta; hind femur without long hairs; fore tibia devoid of setulae on dorsal surface, with posterior row of elongate setulae, longer at base; fore basitarsus long, thin and covered with microscopic setulae on basal half except base, with rows of erect setae at base and on distal half, two times as long as diameter of basitarsus; segments 2–5 with rows of short erect and semi-erect hairs (
Fig. 5D
); mid tibia with posterodorsal row of fine curved setae along entire length, nearly two times as long as diameter of tibia, without conspicuous ventral setae; mid basitarsus with posterodorsal row of fine curved setae along entire length, ending with small leaf-like seta; segments 2–3 each with posterodorsal row of 5 small leaf-like setae; segment 4 with 2 leaf-like setae (
Fig. 5E
); hind tibia with several short dorsal and ventral setae; hind tarsus simple, cylindrical; hind basitarsus with 3 posteroventral rows of short flattened setulae on basal third; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.41/1.56/1.81/0.49/0.61/0.29/0.18, mid leg: 1.47/2.97/1.43/0.54/0.4/0.22/0.15, hind leg: 2.04/3.17/1.09/0.7/0.41/0.27/0.17.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 5F
). Weakly widened distally, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M 
1+2
straight in basal half, slightly convex anteriad in middle part; M 
1
with strong elbow, forming right angle with M 
1+2
; ratio of parts of costa between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
to those between R 
4+5
and M 
1
, 5/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M4, 0.4/1.03/0.38; anal vein fold-like; anal lobe well developed; anal angle right; lower calypter yellow, with brown cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus marinae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–F
. Holotype, ♂(SMNHTAU). 
G–H
. Paratype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
A
. Habitus. 
B
. Head. 
C
. Antenna. 
D
. Fore tarsus. 
E
. Mid tarsus. 
F
. Wing. 
G
. Hypopygium, left lateral view, reflected light. 
H
. Cercal lobes and surstylus, transmitted light.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Thin, mostly shining blue-green, with short black hairs and long marginal setae; segment 1 dirty yellow, with white and black hairs; segments 2–3 orange, brown along distal margin; pregenital segments combined two times as long as mesonotum; hypopygium (
Fig. 5G
) black, with black appendages; cercus bifurcated from base; dorsal arm nearly as long as epandrium, thin, slightly widened at base, covered with long hairs dorsally, with lateral row of 6 long black setae on distal half, with 1 extremely long black subapical dorsal seta, longer than cercus (
Fig. 5H
); inner lobes of ventral arms of cerci fused to apex, having distinct suture; ventral arm of each cercus trilobed (dorsal view), with broad triangular median lobe and thin and long inner and outer lobes; each lobe bearing 2–4 strong apical setae; surstylus projected, bilobed, with large flat leaflike arms expanding distally; dorsal arm of surstylus larger than ventral arm, with wide distal emargination and few short marginal setae; ventral arm of surstylus with one long seta inserted in small emargination at apex and few short marginal hairs; epandrial lobe small, elongate-triangular, with ventral seta; 2 long epandrial setae at base of epandrial lobe.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
