<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus flavus
(
Vanschuytbroeck, 1962
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Megistostylus flavus
Vanschuytbroeck, 1962: 353
</tp:taxon-name>

. 
Type
locality: 
Madagascar
: Ambodivoangy.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Chrysosoma flavum
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Dyte &amp; Smith 1980: 445

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Plagiozopelma flavum
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Bickel 1994: 231

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus flavus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Grichanov 1998: 84

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus flavus
</tp:taxon-name>
is very close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. friedmani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in habitus, differing from the latter species in the fore and mid femora with at most few elongate anteroventral and posteroventral setae, at most half as long as femur diameter; the fore tibia and basitarsus without groups of elongate ventral setae at base; the cercus with one bristle between lobes, half as long as ventral lobe.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Ambodivoangy
; 

Dec. 1949

; 
I. Vadon
leg.; 
P. Vanschuytbroeck
det. 1961?; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Megistostylus flavus
</tp:taxon-name>
n. sp.
; [ex.] Coll. Mus. Congo; 
MNHN
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratype
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 ♂
; 
Ambodivoangy
; 

Dec. 1949

; 
I. Vadon
leg.; 
P. Vanschuytbroeck
det. 1961?; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Megistostylus flavus
</tp:taxon-name>
n. sp.
; Coll. Mus. Congo; 
MRCA

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 ♂
; 
Ambodivoangy
; 

Dec. 1949

; 
I. Vadon
leg.; 
P. Vanschuytbroeck
det. 1950; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sciopus
</tp:taxon-name>
♂
tropicalis
Parent; Coll. Mus. Congo; 
MRCA

• 

1 ♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Analamazaotra Forest
; 
18°46ʹ S
, 
48°24ʹ E
; 

950 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Oct.–4 Nov. 2007

; 
A. Freidberg
leg.; 
SMNHTAU

• 

1 ♂
; 
Ambohitra
, 
Joffreville
; 

800 m
a.s.l.

; 

9–12 Apr. 1991

; 
A. Freidberg
and 
Fini Kaplan
leg.; 
SMNHTAU

• 

1 ♂
(in glycerol); 
Fianarantsoa Province
, 
Ranomafana Nat. Park
; 

19 Jan.
l952

; forest; 
A. Pauly
leg.; ex coll. 
RBINS

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
6.8 mm
; antenna length 
5.6 mm
; wing length 
6.8 mm
; wing width 
1.9 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 3A
). Frons greenish blue-black, whitish pollinose; very short anterior vertical and long and strong postvertical bristles; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white long hairs; face blue-black, white pollinose, broad, 1.3 times as high as wide under antennae, 2.4 times as high as wide at clypeus, at clypeus 2.7 times as wide as postpedicel; clypeus large, slightly bulging, as high as wide; antenna (
Fig. 3B
) with scape and pedicel dirty yellow, postpedicel orange on basal half and black distally, 5 times as long as height of head; scape swollen; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal and one long ventral bristles; postpedicel elongate-conoid, nearly two times as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus black, apical, separated from postpedicel, with fused segments, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.09/0.1/0.21/5.33; proboscis and palpus orange, with white and black hairs; palpus with 2 black bristles.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum and scutellum metallic bluish green, weakly pollinose; pleura bronze-green, whitish grey pollinose; metepimeron yellow; 2 long dorsocentral bristles with strongest posterior pair, and 2 hairlike setae anteriorly; acrostichals long, biserial, gradually decreasing in size anteriorly, with posterior setae as long as penultimate dorsocentrals; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 minute hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Mostly yellow; coxae yellow, but mid coxa blackish brown from outside; fore and mid tarsi brownish to brown; hind tibia yellow to brownish; hind tarsus brown to black; fore and mid coxae with long white hairs and 2–4 black subapical bristles; hind coxa with 1 black seta at middle; femora without strong or long setae; fore femur with few ventral light hairs at base, with anterior and posterior incomplete rows of elongate setulae; mid femur with posteroventral row of elongate setulae on distal ⅔; hind femur with few long white hairs at base; fore tibia with one short posterodorsal seta at base; fore basitarsus long, without setae; all segments with ventral rows of erect and semi-erect hairs, slightly longer than width of segments, with elongate setulae on distal apex dorsally (
Fig. 3C
); mid tibia with 2 anterodorsals and 3 posterodorsals, with one short ventral seta; mid and hind tarsi simple, cylindrical; hind tibia with several short dorsal and ventral setae; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.83/2.19/4.92/0.99/0.71/0.37/0.21, mid leg: 1.85/3.15/3.16/0.8/0.48/0.28/0.14, hind leg: 2.65/4.23/2.15 /1.02/0.63/0.22/0.16.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 3D
). Widened distally, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M1+2 straight in basal half, slightly convex anteriad in middle part; M1 with strong elbow, forming right angle with M 
1+2
; ratio of parts of costa between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
to those between R 
4+5
and M 
1
, 4/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M 
4
, 0.7/1.39/0.46; anal vein and lobe reduced; anal angle absent; lower calypter yellow, with brown cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Thin, mostly shining blue-green, with short black hairs and long marginal setae; segment 1 yellow, with white and dark hairs; segments 2–4 each with yellow lateral spot; pregenital segments combined two times as long as mesonotum; hypopygium (
Fig. 3E
) brown basally, yellow distally, with yellow appendages; cercus with broad neck covered with hairs dorsally, 2 long arms of about equal length and one long seta between arms, half as long as arms; dorsal arm of cercus filiform, with about 8 long light setae dorsally, with one very long curved subapical seta; ventral arm of cercus with several simple and flattened setae at apex, with distal process bearing large leaf-like seta; surstylus broad, projected, bilobed; dorsal arm of surstylus deeply cleft, with 2–3 apical and subapical setae on each lobe; ventral arm of surstylus small, finger-like, with 3 small setae apically; epandrial lobe small, triangular, with 1 basal and 2 apical setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus flavus
(
Vanschuytbroeck, 1962
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂,Andasibe,Analamazaotra Forest (SMNHTAU). 
A
. Head. 
B
. Antenna. 
C
. Fore tarsomeres 2–5. 
D
. Wing. 
E
. Hypopygium, left lateral view, reflected light.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Madagascar
(Alaotra-Mangoro, Diana, Vatovavy-Fitovinany).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
