<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amblypsilopus olgae Grichanov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4986022</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BA5B878EFF96A7461131FA512A1E9049</uri>
         <article-title>Eleven new species of Amblypsilopus Bigot (Diptera: Dolichopodidae: Sciapodinae) and a key to the species of Madagascar and adjacent islands</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1399</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus olgae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
06A4A8A3-6A63-4EBF-BA25-4DA0E45A1AA9
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 12
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus olgae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is very close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. andasibensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in habitus. The latter differs from the new species in the fore tarsomere 4 entirely black, tarsomere 5 white. The fore tarsomeres 4–5 are entirely white in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. olgae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; the long lobe of the cercus ends with one long and one short thick setae, but no long setae at middle.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name is dedicated to Olga Grichanova, a member of my family (
St. Petersburg
, 
Russia
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Analamazaotra Forest
; 
18°46ʹ S
, 
48°24ʹ E
; 

950 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Oct.–4 Nov. 2007

; 
L. Friedman
leg.; 
SMNHTAU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
5.7 mm
; antenna length 
1.2 mm
; wing length 
4.8 mm
; wing width 
1.2 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 12A
). Frons black, white pollinose; strong short anterior vertical and long postvertical bristles; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white hairs; face densely silvery-white pollinose, narrow, 3.8 times as high as wide under antennae, 8.7 times as high as wide at clypeus, at clypeus nearly as wide as postpedicel; clypeus small, slightly bulging; antenna (
Fig. 12B
) with scape and pedicel dirty yellow, postpedicel orange on basal half and brown distally, 1.3 times as long as height of head; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal bristle; postpedicel ovate, 1.1 times as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus dorsal, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.08/0.07/0.1/0.99; proboscis orange; palpus blackish, with white and brown hairs.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum orange, with brown, shining greenish blue, medial stripe expanding posteriorly; scutellum metallic blue; pleura yellow, weakly pollinose; 6 strong dorsocentral bristles gradually decreasing in size anteriorly with strongest posterior pair; acrostichals short, biserial; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Mostly yellow; coxae yellow; tarsi brown from tip of basitarsus; segments 4 and 5 of fore tarsus white (
Fig. 12C
); fore and mid coxae with light and dark hairs and 2–3 black subapical setae; hind coxa with 1 black seta at middle; femora without strong or long setae; fore tibia without conspicuous setae; fore basitarsus thin and long, with 6 short ventral setae, two times as long as width of segment; segments 4–5 flattened dorsoventrally, slightly widened, with black flattened setae laterally, longer than tarsomere width; mid tibia with one short anterodorsal and two short posterodorsals, without conspicuous ventral setae; mid and hind tarsi simple, cylindrical; hind tibia with several short dorsal and ventral setae; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.33/1.69/3.83/0.7/0.54/0.22/0.13, mid leg: 1.55/3.12/2.19/0.63/0.39/0.21/0.13, hind leg: 2.37/3.77/1.46/0.75/0.4/0.23/0.13.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 12D
). Widened distally, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M 
1+2
straight in basal half, slightly convex anteriad in middle part; M 
1
with strong elbow, forming right angle with M 
1+2
; ratio of parts of costa between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
to those between R 
4+5
and M 
1
, 4.5/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M4, 0.47.1.07/0.44; anal vein and lobe reduced; anal angle absent; lower calypter brownish, with fine brown cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Thin and long, mostly orange-yellow, brown along distal margin of tergite 2 and along dorsal side of tergites 3–6, with short black hairs and marginal setae; pregenital segments combined three times as long as mesonotum; hypopygium (
Fig. 12E
) brown, with brown to black appendages; hypandrium short, with reduced arms; cercus (
Fig. 12F
) brown, bifurcated from base; dorsal lobe partly concealed, flat, subtriangular, half as long as epandrium, with pointed apex, sparsely covered with long dark setae along entire length, densely covered with numerous setulae at base; ventral arms of cerci fused at base, as long as epandrium; ventral arm of each cercus directed ventrally, bifurcated from point of fusion, with long thin distal lobe ending with one long and one short thick setae; proximal lobe of ventral arm thick, with ventral series of setae on distal half, beginning with very long thick curved seta at middle, then about 5 short thick setae, ending with 3–4 very long simple setae; surstylus projected, bilobed, with irregularly curved broad flat arms; dorsal arm of surstylus with small process at apex; ventral arm of surstylus larger and stronger sclerotized than dorsal arm, with small spine at base, with pointed subapical projection and 3 big and thick apical setae; epandrial lobe simple, projected, sclerotized; 2 long epandrial setae at base of epandrial lobe.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
