<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Harpedona vittlaensis Yeshwanth
                        &amp; Konstantinov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4690270</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BE301C0DF86FFF87FDEF886373F5F879</uri>
                  <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera:
                        Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new
                        genera and six new species</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Harpedona vittlaensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: DABBC105-68F2-46CC-8DB0-E1E95ED33118 </p>
            <p> Figs 2D , 16 , 25A </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Easily recognized from all congeners by the following characters: dorsum dirty pale
                  brown, with an orange brown head and pronotal collar, and dark brown scutellum (
                  Fig. 2D ); pronotum heavily punctate, distinctly transverse, about 1.7× as wide as
                  long, with an indistinct impressed line behind calli; labium long, reaching at
                  least IV abdominal segment, apex of segment III surpassing hind coxa; genital
                  capsule without spinelike processes and complex sclerotization on dorsal wall,
                  with large, lobate ventral process ( Fig. 16A ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> Named after the type locality, Vittla, <tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p> Holotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation>
                        <tp:taxon-name> INDIA </tp:taxon-name> • ♂ ; Karnataka , Dakshina Kannada ,
                        Vittla ; 20°45.814ˊ N , 75°06.095ˊ E ; 60 m a.s.l. ; 28 Nov. 2011 ; H.M.
                        Yeshwanth leg.; at light; UASB . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation>
                        <tp:taxon-name> INDIA </tp:taxon-name> • 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for
                        holotype ; UASB </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same
                        collection data as for holotype ; ZISP </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> COLORATION. Dirty pale brown ( Fig. 2D ). Head orange brown, with a transverse
                  diffuse brown band on vertex and dark brown apex of clypeus; eye black; antennal
                  segment I with pale chestnut base and darkened apex, segments II–IV dark brown;
                  labium pale brown with darkened apex of segment IV; pronotum pale brown, with a
                  yellow brown pronotal collar and slightly darkened calli; scutellum dark brown;
                  thoracic pleurites dark brown, posterior margin of mesopleuron with yellowish
                  edging; hemelytron uniformly pale brown, membrane semitransparent, fuscous; legs
                  uniformly pale brown, tibiae with an indistinct reddish tinge; abdomen brown. </p>
            <p>SURFACE AND VESTITURE. Dorsum shining, head and pronotal collar smooth, shining,
                  calli rugose, disc of pronotum with dense deep punctures, scutellum, hemelytron,
                  thoracic venter, and abdomen weakly rugose; entire dorsum clothed with short,
                  dense, adpressed, silvery yellow simple setae; thoracic venter, abdomen and legs
                  with similar but somewhat longer, semierect setae.</p>
            <p> STRUCTURE. Body elongate-oval, 2.9× as long as basal width of pronotum, total length
                  3.1. Head: transverse, moderately produced anteriad of eyes in dorsal view,
                  somewhat wider than high in frontal view; frons weakly convex, without
                  longitudinal sulcus, epistomal suture slightly depressed; eyes sessile, relatively
                  small, oval, about half height of head in lateral view, posterior margin almost
                  contiguous with pronotal collar; vertex convex, twice as wide as dorsal width of
                  one eye; antennal fossa located just above ventral margin of eye, at small
                  distance from inferior margin of eye; antennal segment I short, tubular, narrowed
                  at base, subequal to width of vertex, segment II subequal to head width, segments
                  III and IV filiform, subequal in length; labium long, reaching abdominal segment 4
                  or 5. Thorax: pronotum 1.7× as wide as long, with a prominent, medially concave
                  collar posteriorly delimited by a deep impressed line; calli raised, contiguous
                  and reaching lateral margins of pronotum, with a deep pit in between, posteriorly
                  delimited by a weak punctate line distinctly constricted at sides; disc weakly
                  convex; lateral margins of pronotum sinuate, posterior margin nearly straight;
                  mesoscutum almost entirely covered by pronotum; scutellum broadly triangular,
                  slightly raised and anteromedially excavated; peritreme of metathoracic
                  scent-gland lanceolate, extended posteriorly along ventral margin of metapleuron;
                  evaporative area reduced to a narrow falciform area along dorsal margin of
                  peritreme and devoid of characteristic mushroom bodies ( Fig. 25A ). Hemelytron:
                  semitransparent, corium with almost straight lateral margin, R+M vein well
                  developed, reaching apex of corium, medial fracture distinct, reaching medioapical
                  area of corium; cuneus narrow, twice as long as wide at base; membrane with single
                  angulate cell slightly surpassing apex of cuneus. Legs: all femora relatively
                  long, cylindrical; tibiae straight, subequal to length of respective femur; tarsi
                  three-segmented, with distinctly swollen segment III; claw bent close to apex,
                  inner surface of claw with large semicircular pulvillus equipped with pulvillar
                  combs. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA. Genital capsule with large, roughly rectangular right lateral process and
                  contrastingly long, tongue-shaped and posteriorly oriented ventral process
                  exceeding length of genital capsule ( Fig. 16A ); aedeagus small, with entirely
                  membranous phallotheca, simple sac-like endosoma and spine-like ductus seminis
                  sclerotized along almost entire length except base ( Fig. 16F ); parameres larger
                  and more robust than in other congeners, left paramere with strongly upturned and
                  hooked apex ( Fig. 16B–C ), right paramere subquadrate, with short and strongly
                  curved apical process ( Fig. 16D–E ). </p>
            <p> Female Similar to male. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Host </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Southwestern <tp:taxon-name>India (Karnataka)</tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> This new species differs from all congeners by several unique features, including a
                  comparatively wide pronotum with an indistinct line delimiting the calli
                  posteriorly and a heavily punctate disc, the exceptionally long labium reaching at
                  least the fourth abdominal sternite, and the pale brown coloration of dorsum. Many
                        <tp:taxon-name> Harpedona </tp:taxon-name> spp. have two-celled membrane
                  with a small, narrow secondary cell near inner margin of the cuneus, but this
                  secondary cell is missing in <tp:taxon-name> H. vittlaensis </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. Additionally, the genital capsule of this new species is relatively simple
                  and devoid of complex bulbous and spine-like processes on the dorsal wall, which
                  are typical for most species of the genus. However, <tp:taxon-name> H. vittlaensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. shares all essential features of the genus mentioned in
                  the diagnosis viz., body shape and proportions, the structure of pronotal collar
                  and calli, the constriction of pronotum behind calli, the presence of a large,
                  lobate process on the right wall of the genital capsule, the characteristically
                  simple aedeagus, and the shape of both parameres. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
