<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Namyatovia sirsiensis Yeshwanth &amp; Konstantinov 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4695064</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BE301C0DF87DFF91FDB18FE27323F879</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new genera and six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Namyatovia sirsiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
F66665F1-8FDC-4A1C-80FA-AC2E456419C9
</p>
      <p>
Figs 4A–C
, 
22
, 
25F
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Recognized by the following characters: body length 3.3–3.4; corium with diffuse oval pale brown spot behind apex of clavus (
Fig. 4A
); antennal segment II darkened at base, yellow on apical two-thirds; genital capsule without ornamentation, spines or processes (
Fig. 22A
); right paramere scythe-shaped (
Fig. 22C
); basal part of aedeagus evenly sclerotized, tubular, without additional processes; apical part of aedeagus forming a single, narrow membranous lobe terminating with claw-shaped sclerite (
Fig. 22D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Named after the 
type
locality, Sirsi village.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
<tp:taxon-name>
INDIA
</tp:taxon-name>
• 
♂
; 
Karnataka
, 
Sirsi
; 
14°44.023ˊ N
, 
74°46.711ˊ E
; 

506 m
a.s.l.

; 

25 May 2010

; 
H.M. Yeshwanth
leg.; at light; 
UASB
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
<tp:taxon-name>
INDIA
</tp:taxon-name>
• 
2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for 
holotype
; 
UASB
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
4 ♂♂
; 
Karnataka
, 
Mudigere
; 
13°7.190ˊ N
, 
75°37.670ˊ E
; 

913 m
a.s.l.

; 

29 Aug. 2018

; 
H.M. Yeshwant
leg.; at light; 
UASB
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Pale lemon yellow to pale brown (
Fig. 4A–C
); head yellow, antennal segment I brown, segment II brown in basal third, yellow apically, segment III pale yellow, segment IV pale brown; pronotum yellow dorsally, laterally brown to reddish brown; meso- and metathorax laterally brown, ventrally pale yellow; scutellum pale brown to dark brown; hemelytron lemon yellow, with narrowly brown or black costal margin and claval commissure, sometimes base of hemelytron also darkened, corium with pale brown diffuse medial spot behind apex of clavus; legs pale yellow.
</p>
      <p>STRUCTURE. Total length 3.3–3.6; body 3.3–3.4× as long as basal width of pronotum; vertex 2.1–2.2× as wide as dorsal width of one eye, 0.8–0.9× as wide as length of antennal segment I; antennal segment II 0.6–0.7× as long as basal width of pronotum, 0.9× as long as width of head; pronotum 1.9–2.0× as wide as long.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Genital capsule roughly trapeziform, short and broad, about twice as wide as long, without spines or processes (
Fig. 22A
); aperture of genital capsule large, right lateral wall somewhat excavated. Left paramere L-shaped, with slightly swollen body and almost straight apical process (
Fig. 22B
). Right paramere slightly larger than left one, scythe-shaped, gradually curved along entire length (
Fig. 22C
). Aedeagus elongate, tubular, with C-shaped, evenly sclerotized basal part followed by long, narrow, membranous lobe and terminating with acute claw-shaped sclerite (
Fig. 22D
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host
</p>
      <p>Unknown. All specimens were attracted to light.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Southwestern 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Karnataka state
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
