<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Eccritotarsini Berg 1883</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4695038</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BE301C0DF865FF89FDD68E507438F878</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new genera and six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Recognized among 
<tp:taxon-name>Miridae</tp:taxon-name>
by the presence of large, circular pulvilli broadly attached to the inner surface of the claw. Refer to 

Konstantinov 
et al
. (2018)

for detailed discussion of distinctive features.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key to genera of the tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Eccritotarsini</tp:taxon-name>
of 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Sri Lanka
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Cuneus reaching apex of hemelytral membrane (
Figs 3D
, 
4A
, 
9G, I
, 
10
). Vertex between eyes with a distinct transverse depression ........................................................................................................ 2

</p>
      <p>
– Cuneus terminating well anteriad of apex of membrane. Vertex without a transverse depression, sometimes with longitudinal, median sulcus .................................................................................... 3
</p>
      <p>

2. Dorsum brightly reddish orange (
Figs 9G–H
, 
10
). Larger, total length 4.9–5.4. Left wall of genital capsule with a spinelike process. Left paramere apically bifid ...... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumastomiris
Kirkaldy, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Dorsum lemon yellow (
Figs 3D–F
, 
4A–C
). Smaller, total length 3.2–3.7. Genital capsule without spinelike processes. Left paramere gradually tapering apically (
Figs 21E
, 
22B
) ............................... .......................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Namyatovia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
      <p>

3. Vertex distinctly carinate posteriorly. Pronotal collar narrow, posteriorly delimited with a deep suture. Costal margin of hemelytron basally serrated (
Fig. 1
) ...................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dioclerus
Distant, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Vertex not carinate. Pronotal collar posteriorly delimited with a shallow sulcus. Costal margin of hemelytron smooth ........................................................................................................................... 4
</p>
      <p>

4. Dorsum uniformly pale yellow. Body elongate, gracile, with long appendages. Eyes distinctly separated from anterior margin of pronotum (
Figs 4D–F
, 
9A, C, E
, 
27C–D
) .................................. 5

</p>
      <p>
– Dorsum with variable color-pattern or uniformly dark brown, but never uniformly pale yellow. Body more robust, broadly oval to elongate-oval. Eyes in contact with or slightly separated from pronotum ........................................................................................................................................... 6
</p>
      <p>

5. Eyes large, distinctly stylate. Vertex with a shallow longitudinal sulcus along midline. Antennal segment I bottle shaped, with a narrowed basal one-fourth (
Fig. 9A–E
) ........................................... .................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Prodromus
Distant, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Eyes small, not stylate. Vertex without a sulcus. Antennal segment I uniformly slender, narrowed only at extreme base (
Fig. 4D–F
) .................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stonedahlia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
      <p>
6. Calli anteromedially delimited with impressed line forming characteristic subtriangular region between collar and calli .................................................................................................................... 7
</p>
      <p>
– Anterior part of pronotum without clearly delimited subtriangular region between collar and calli. ........................................................................................................................................................... 8
</p>
      <p>

7. Dorsum pale brown to reddish yellow, with dark longitudinal interrupted stripes. Pronotal collar at least twice as wide as antennal segment II (
Fig. 6D–I
) .............................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lopidolon
Poppius, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Dorsum bicolored; reddish anteriorly, bluish black to black posteriorly. Pronotal collar as wide as or narrower than diameter of antennal segment II (
Figs 3A–B
, 
8A, D, G
) .......... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mertila
Distant, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

8. Coloration of dorsum uniform, dirty yellow to black, sometimes with paler embolium. Calli dorsally and laterally separated by deep impressed lines giving appearance of three distinct sections of pronotum (
Figs 2C–D
, 
5J, L
) ..................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Harpedona
Distant, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Coloration of dorsum contrasting, with clavus, transverse spot in medioapical part of corium, apex of cuneus, and cells uniformly brown to dark brown; remaining part of hemelytron and legs whitishyellow. Calli distinct, but not separated by impressed lines (
Figs 2A–B
, 
6A–B
, 
26B–C, F
) ........... 9

</p>
      <p>

9. Pronotum uniformly black and coarsely punctured. Hemelytra with slightly convex costal margin (
Fig. 2A–B
) ................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ernestinus
Distant, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Pronotum behind calli with narrow, impunctate whitish carina along midline. Hemelytra slightly constricted on basal fourth, with concave costal margin (
Fig. 6A
) ...... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jessopocoris
Carvalho, 1981
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
