<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Namyatovia Yeshwanth &amp; Konstantinov 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4695087</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BE301C0DF872FF93FD128A307438FA90</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new genera and six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Namyatovia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E6601571-0919-446A-BE3B-93A4DF01048B
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3D–F
, 
4A–C
, 

21– 
22

, 
25E
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Namyatovia castlerockensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Recognized by the following characters: dorsum lemon yellow with limited fuscous markings (
Figs 3D– F
, 
4A–C
); head transverse, with distinct transverse depression on vertex and convex frons anteriorly protruding one-half of eye length; labium reaching middle coxa; pronotum heavily punctate, with flat pronotal collar posteriorly delimited by weak depression; calli reaching medial margins of pronotum, medially separated by small deep pit; cuneus long, falciform, reaching apex of single-celled membrane; genital capsule distinctly wider than long, with large aperture (
Figs 21A–B
, 
22A
); left paramere L-shaped, somewhat smaller than right one, with simple, gradually tapering apical process (
Figs 21E
, 
22B
); aedeagus tubular, long and thin, C-shaped, evenly sclerotized except membranous apical portion (
Figs 21F
, 
22D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The new genus is named after Anna A. Namyatova in recognition of her important contributions to bryocorine taxonomy. The gender is feminine.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Dorsum lemon yellow to dirty yellow (
Figs 3D–E
, 
4A–B
); antenna entirely or basally dark brown; head and pronotum dark yellow, somewhat darker than hemelytron, scutellum apically or entirely darkened; hemelytron lemon yellow, with narrowly darkened claval commissure and costal margin, sometimes darkened at base and with diffuse brown spot in medioapical area of corium; membrane semitransparent, with brown vein; legs lemon yellow; thorax ventrally yellow, with brown pleurites 
Figs 3F
, 
4C
), abdominal venter yellow with lateral pleural region pale brown.
</p>
      <p>SURFACE AND VESTITURE. Dorsum shining, head and calli smooth, pronotal collar and disc behind calli with dense deep punctures, hemelytron rugose, weakly punctate; body clothed with dense, short, adpressed, yellowish simple setae.</p>
      <p>
STRUCTURE. Elongate-oval, total length 3.2–3.7. Head: distinctly transverse in dorsal view, frons convex, extending anteriorly about half-length of eye; vertex with deep transverse depression posteriorly between eyes; eye large, projecting posteriorly almost to level of posterior margin of pronotal collar, occupying half-length of head in lateral view; antennal fossa large, located at level of middle eye height, narrowly removed from eye margin; antennal segment I cylindrical, basally narrow, slightly longer than width of vertex, segment II subequal to head width, segments III and IV subequal in length, slightly thinner than segment II; labium short and stout, reaching mesocoxa. Thorax: pronotum trapeziform, strongly narrowed anteriorly, lateral margins concave, posterior margin broadly rounded laterally and weakly concave medially; pronotal collar flat, distinctly broader than diameter of antennal segment I, posteriorly delimited by weak depression; calli large, weakly raised, extending to lateral margins of pronotum, medially separated by small deep pit; mesoscutum moderately exposed; scutellum broadly triangular, with somewhat extended apex and shallow medial depression; scent efferent system with well-developed, lanceolate peritreme extending along ventral margin of metapleuron and reduced, narrow evaporatory area dorsal to peritreme (
Fig. 25E–F
). Hemelytron: broadly rounded laterally, widest at level of claval apex; embolium well delimited, of same width along almost entire length; cuneus long, falciform, reaching apex of single-celled membrane; cuneal incisure shallow; membrane from base to apex subequal in length to distance between wing base and base of membrane; cell of membrane large, with almost straight vein apically curving towards cuneus and terminating close to apex of cuneus. Legs. elongate, all femora cylindrical, slightly flattened dorsoventrally, tibia cylindrical, hind leg more elongate; tarsus three-segmented, apically dilated, with long guard setae, all segments subequal in length; claw bent close to apex, with large semicircular pulvillus equipped with pulvillar comb on inner surface.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Genital capsule broad, subquadrate to trapeziform, almost twice as wide as long, with large aperture and moderately to strongly excavate right lateral wall (
Figs 21A–B
, 
22A
); paramere sockets uneven, supragenital bridge absent; Left paramere somewhat smaller than right one, hook-shaped, with slightly dilated body and simple, gradually tapering apical process (
Figs 21E
, 
22B
); right paramere variable, simple scythe-shaped (
Fig. 22C
) or flattened, with strongly expanded, semicircular body (
Fig. 21C–D
); aedeagus tubular, long and thin, C-shaped, evenly sclerotized except membranous apical portion; endosoma not clearly separated from phallotheca, non-retractable, entirely expanded from phallotheca in repose; apical portion of aedeagus takes form of single narrow sac, entirely membranous in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. castlerockensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Fig. 21F
) and apically sclerotized in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. sirsiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Fig. 22D
). Base of aedeagus in the latter species dorsally equipped with characteristically large, narrow, hook-shaped, sclerotized, apically flattened and serrated outgrowth.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host
</p>
      <p>Unknown; all specimens were collected at light.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Southwestern 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Karnataka state
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new genus is most closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumastomiris
Kirkaldy, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Taricoris
Carvalho, 1981
</tp:taxon-name>
, based on the following common characters: vertex with transverse depression between eyes; body wide, with broadly arcuate costal margin; cuneus long, narrow, falciform, almost reaching apex of membrane; aedeagus C-shaped, narrowly tubular, evenly sclerotized, with one or several membranous lobes apically. The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumastomiris
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Figs 9G–H
, 
10
) currently contains seven species distributed from northern 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
and 
Sri Lanka
to New 
Guinea
whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>
Taricoris
</tp:taxon-name>
was described by Carvalho (1981) to accommodate two species from 
Papua New Guinea
. 
Stonedahl (1988)
considered a sister group relationship between these two genera based on the bifurcate apex of the left paramere and the presence of a spine-like sclerotized subapical process of the aedeagus. He also suggested that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumastomiris dissimilis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Philippines
, 
Fig. 9I–J
) may in fact belong to the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Taricoris
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Namyatovia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
clearly differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumastomiris
</tp:taxon-name>
in the lemon-yellow general coloration, the shorter labium reaching mesocoxa, the absence of spinelike processes on the genital capsule, and the shape of both parameres and aedeagus. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumastomiris
</tp:taxon-name>
spp. have brightly reddish coloration of dorsum (
Fig. 10
) and robust labium reaching or surpassing hind coxa, with segment II somewhat longer than segments III and IV combined. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Thaumastomiris
</tp:taxon-name>
is further characterized by the presence of two or single spines on left distal margin of the genital capsule, the almost straight right paramere, and the apically bifurcate apex of the left paramere (
Stonedahl 1988
: figs 96–100).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Taricoris
</tp:taxon-name>
can be separated from the new genus by the conspicuous dark pattern on hemelytron (
Carvalho 1981a
: figs 187–188, 193), the bifurcate apex of the left paramere (
Carvalho 1981a
: figs 190, 196), and the shape of aedeagus, particularly the presence of several membranous apical lobes (
Carvalho 1981a
: figs 189, 194).
</p>
      <p>

Key to species of genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Namyatovia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Antennal segment II dark brown to reddish brown. Corium uniformly lemon yellow, without a brown spot behind apex of clavus (
Fig. 3D
). Right paramere flattened, with expanded semicircular body (
Fig. 21C–D
). Base of aedeagus with characteristically large, apically serrate, hook-shaped sclerotized outgrowth on dorsal wall (
Fig. 21F
) ........................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. castlerockensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Antennal segment II with a dark brown base and yellow apical two-thirds. Corium with a diffuse pale brown spot behind apex of clavus (
Fig. 4A
). Right paramere scythe-shaped (
Fig. 22C
). Aedeagus without sclerotized outgrowth at base (
Fig. 22D
) ................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. sirsiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
