<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Lopidolon dandeliensis Yeshwanth
                        &amp; Konstantinov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4695062</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BE301C0DF874FF99FDD68A9D739AFDB6</uri>
                  <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera:
                        Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new
                        genera and six new species</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Lopidolon dandeliensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 4A2EE39E-5C7F-4118-8BC5-1E677F85261F </p>
            <p> Figs 2E–F , 17– 18 , 27E </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Recognized by the yellow or orange-yellow ground color with contrasting dark
                  pattern, specifically distinguished by the uniformly black antennal segments I and
                  II, dark brown tibiae, presence of black longitudinal stripes at sides of anterior
                  part of pronotum, and the two more stripes close to midline on posterior part and
                  the almost entirely black hemelytron with the apex of clavus, the basal half of
                  cuneus, and the base and extreme apex of endocorium yellow ( Fig. 2E–F ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The name of the new species is derived from the type locality, Dandeli city. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype <tp:taxon-name> INDIA </tp:taxon-name> • ♂ ;
                        Karnataka , Dakshina Kannada , Dandeli ; 15.236° N , 74.616° E ; H.M.
                        Yeshwanth leg.; 10 Nov. 2012 ; at light; UASB . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes <tp:taxon-name> INDIA </tp:taxon-name> : • 3 ♂♂ ;
                        same collection data as holotype ; UASB </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 2 ♀♀ ; Karnataka , Chickballapur , Nandi Hills ;
                        13°22.320ˊ N , 77°741.108ˊ E ; 1443 m a.s.l. ; 29 Aug. 2019 ; H.M. Yeshwanth
                        leg.; Ex : <tp:taxon-name> Diplocentrum recurvum </tp:taxon-name> ; UASB
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> COLORATION. Yellow to orange yellow, with contrasting black pattern ( Fig. 2E ).
                  Head: yellow to orangeyellow, with postocular region of vertex black and sometimes
                  with a narrow brown mark on frons along midline; eye silvery with black band along
                  inner margin in frontal view; antennal segments I and II black, remaining segments
                  brown; labium brown. Thorax: pronotal collar and calli with longitudinal black
                  stripes laterally, disc of pronotum with two black stripes close to midline and
                  darkened posterior angles; thoracic venter pale brown, propleura with similar
                  black longitudinal stripe; exposed part of mesoscutum and scutellum yellow to
                  orange-yellow, with lateral black patches at base. Hemelytron: clavus black, with
                  V-shaped yellow region apically; corium yellow to orange yellow, with entirely
                  black exocorium and with three large, almost confluent, longitudinal black patches
                  separated by branches of R+M vein and occupying most of endocorium except base and
                  extreme apex; cuneus yellow to orange yellow with black apical half. Legs: coxae
                  pale brown to pale yellow; femora yellow with darkened apices and a diffuse dark
                  brown ring on apical third; tibiae brown to dark brown, pale yellow medially.
                  Abdomen: yellow to orange yellow, with lateral black patches. </p>
            <p>SURFACE AND VESTITURE. Dorsum finely punctate; head, pronotum and hemelytra weakly
                  rugose, with yellow, long, erect simple setae, antenna and legs with setae
                  somewhat longer than elsewhere.</p>
            <p> STRUCTURE. Body elongate-oval, total length 2.5× as long as basal width of pronotum.
                  Head: transverse, with distinctly convex and anteriorly projecting frons; eye
                  sessile, large, occupying half of head height in lateral view, not in contact with
                  anterior margin of pronotum due to well-developed postocular region of vertex;
                  vertex slightly convex; antennal fossa, prominent, round, narrowly separated from
                  eye, located near ventral eye margin; antennal segment I short, subequal to vertex
                  width, tubular and narrowing at base; segment II 1.2× as long as head width, about
                  half as thin as segment I, slightly dilate apically; segments III and IV short,
                  filiform, subequal in length; labium long, reaching abdominal sternite III.
                  Thorax: pronotum 1.6× as wide as long, with collar concave, distinctly wider than
                  diameter of antennal segment I, slightly narrowing towards midline, posteriorly
                  well delimited by an impressed line; calli raised, anteriorly and posteriorly
                  delimited by impressed lines; disc of pronotum slightly raised, trapeziform, with
                  strongly sinuate posterior margin; mesoscutum largely exposed; scutellum slightly
                  longer than exposed part of mesocutum, slightly raised; metathoracic scent gland
                  efferent system reduced, with narrow opening and peritreme ( Fig. 25B ).
                  Hemelytron: costal margin slightly concave, hemelytron broadest at level with apex
                  of clavus; slightly above cuneus, cuneus about 1.5× as long as wide, with distinct
                  cuneal fracture; primary cell of membrane large, far exceeding apex of cuneus,
                  secondary cell narrow. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA. Genital capsule short and wide, with a large, posteriorly directed
                  aperture ( Figs 17 , 18A– B ); dorsal margin with very large, spoon-shaped lobe
                  more than twice as long as genital capsule and equipped with groove running
                  towards apex; lateral margins of genital capsule with large, slightly asymmetrical
                  lobes resembling parameres; aedeagus and parameres strongly reduced, parameres
                  almost equal in length, located close to each other on ventral margin of capsule;
                  left paramere as in Fig. 18C–D , right paramere as in Fig. 18E . aedeagus with
                  entirely membranous phallotheca, simple membranous endosoma, and ductus seminis
                  with membranous basal part and sclerotized, spine-like apical part ( Fig. 18F ). </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>Similar to male but slightly smaller. Coloration as in male but vertex with a
                  longitudinal pale brown marking and eye entirely silver, without any black
                  markings.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Host </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Diplocentrum recurvum Lindl. </tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Orchidaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) ( Fig. 27E ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Southwestern <tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name> ( Karnataka state ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> The new species is most similar to <tp:taxon-name> L. pallescens Poppius, 1912
                  </tp:taxon-name> in size, body proportions, vestiture, and general color-pattern
                  but it differs from <tp:taxon-name> L. dandeliensis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. in
                  the pale-brown ground color, the diffuse, weakly expressed dark markings on the
                  dorsum, and the coloration of antennal segment II and tibiae. <tp:taxon-name>
                        Lopidolon sordidus </tp:taxon-name> is similar to the new species in the
                  contrasting black and orange coloration but differs from it in the largely
                  darkened head, uniformly dark brown antennal segments I–II, reddishbrown tibiae,
                  presence of a pair of uninterrupted black stripes on pronotum running from collar
                  to posterior margin of disc, and longer vestiture. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
