<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Stonedahlia Yeshwanth &amp;
                        Konstantinov 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4695095</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BE301C0DF879FF94FD128C9870A9FA37</uri>
                  <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera:
                        Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new
                        genera and six new species</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Stonedahlia </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 98840AE6-FFED-494B-A796-7845DE858B32 </p>
            <p> Figs 4D–F , 23–24 , 25D , 27D </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p> Type species </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Stonedahlia mishmiensis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. (by
                  monotypy). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Recognized by the following combination of characters: Total length 4.4–4.7;
                  coloration uniformly pale yellow to pale brownish yellow, only apices of tarsi,
                  labium, and sometimes antennal segments II–IV darkened ( Fig. 4D ); body long and
                  gracile, parallel-sided, 3.7–4.0× as long as basal width of pronotum; head
                  vertical, strongly produced ventrally but not produced anteriad of antennal fossae
                  in dorsal view; antennal segment I subequal to head width; eyes small, not in
                  contact with pronotum, vertex about 3× as wide as eye ( Fig. 4E ); pronotum
                  heavily punctate, with wide and flat pronotal collar, weakly raised calli and
                  distinctly expanded disc; hemelytron translucent, long, apex of abdomen not
                  reaching or barely surpassing cuneal fracture ( Fig. 4F ); cuneus elongate,
                  2.5–3.0× as along as broad; single cell of membrane forming almost right angle and
                  reaching apex of cuneus; legs elongate; genital capsule boatshaped, with spinelike
                  subapical process on left side of aperture ( Fig. 23 ); left paramere hook-shaped
                  ( Fig. 24E–F ); aedeagus tubular, C-shaped, sclerotized throughout except at apex
                  ( Fig. 24G ); endosoma not clearly separated from phallotheca, non-retractable,
                  entirely expanded from phallotheca in repose; apex of aedeagus membranous, with
                  anchor-shaped apex formed by three oppositely directed processes. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>The genus is named after Gary M. Stonedahl in recognition of his outstanding
                  contribution to plant bug taxonomy and particularly his seminal studies of
                  eccritotarsines. The gender is feminine.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> COLORATION. Pale yellow, with darkened apices of labium, antennal segments II–IV,
                  and tarsi ( Fig. 4D– F ). </p>
            <p>SURFACE AND VESTITURE. Head smooth, moderately shining, pronotal collar and calli
                  weakly punctate, disc of pronotum coarsely punctate, scutellum smooth, hemelytron
                  weakly rugose, shining; dorsum clothed with dense, adpressed to semierect,
                  comparatively short, whitish simple setae, appendages, thoracic venter and abdomen
                  with longer simple setae, erect to semierect on femora, adpressed elsewhere.</p>
            <p> STRUCTURE. Body elongate, parallel sided, 3.7–4.0× as long as basal width of
                  pronotum. Head: vertical, strongly produced ventrally below eyes; in dorsal view
                  transverse, not produced anteriad of antennal fossae, with small sessile eyes
                  separated from pronotum by distance almost equal to eye length; vertex broad,
                  3.0–3.2× as wide as dorsal width of one eye, with shallow transverse depression;
                  eye occupying about one-third of head height in lateral view; frons weakly convex,
                  vertical, clypeus not prominent oriented ventroposteriorly; mandibular and
                  maxillary plates comparatively large, subquadrate; antennal fossa located close to
                  inferior eye margin at mid-height of eye in frontal view; antennal segment I
                  tubular, about twice diameter of segment II, slightly longer than head width,
                  segment II 1.9–2.0× as long as head width, 1.0–1.1× as long as pronotum width;
                  segments II and III filiform, subequal in length and slightly shorter than segment
                  II; labium reaching mesocoxa, with segment I long, reaching procoxa, length of
                  segment II subequal to segment I, segments III and IV combined subequal in length
                  to segment II. Thorax: pronotum 1.4–1.5× as wide as long, campaniform; pronotal
                  collar wide and flat, more than twice as wide as diameter of antennal segment I,
                  not delimited by impressed line posteriorly; calli weakly raised and poorly
                  demarcated, reaching lateral margins of pronotum, separated by small deep pit;
                  disc of pronotum behind calli noticeably widened, trapeziform, raised, with
                  slightly convex lateral margins, rounded posterior angles and somewhat concave
                  medially posterior margin; mesoscutum almost entirely covered with pronotum,
                  separated from scutellum by distinct recession; scutellum slightly raised above
                  hemelytron; metathoracic scent efferent system typical for eccritotarsines ( Fig.
                  25D ). Hemelytron: translucent, long, with nearly straight costal margin, distance
                  between base of hemelytron and apex of clavus subequal to distance between apex of
                  clavus and cuneal fracture, apex of abdomen not reaching or barely surpassing
                  cuneal fracture; embolium inflated; cuneus elongate, 2.5–3.0× as along as broad,
                  cuneal fracture obsolete; single cell of membrane forming almost right angle and
                  reaching apex of cuneus. Legs: elongate, slender, hind femur surpassing apex of
                  abdomen, tibiae cylindrical, slightly dilated apically; tarsi 2-segmented with
                  apical segment elongate, slightly swollen; pretarsus typical eccritotarsine. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA. Genital capsule boat-shaped, slightly compressed laterally, dorsolateral
                  wall of capsule protruded into large subapical fold and equipped with spinelike
                  subapical process at base of fold ( Fig. 23 ); right paramere slightly larger than
                  left one, L-shaped, apical process prominent, straight, with abruptly curved apex
                  and long subapical spine ( Fig. 24A–D ); left paramere hook-shaped ( Fig. 24E–F );
                  aedeagus tubular, C-shaped, sclerotized throughout except at apex, with
                  subapically serrate dorsal wall; endosoma not clearly separated from phallotheca,
                  non-retractable, entirely expanded from phallotheca in repose ( Fig. 24G ); apex
                  of aedeagus weakly sclerotized, anchor-shaped, with three oppositely directed,
                  gradually curved, weakly sclerotized processes, dorsal and ventral processes
                  simple, lateral process apically sclerotized, twin-coned. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>STRUCTURE, SURFACE AND VESTITURE. As in male.</p>
            <p>GENITALIA. Not examined.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Host </p>
            <p> Similarly to <tp:taxon-name> Ernestinus </tp:taxon-name> spp., specimens of this
                  monotypic genus were found in large groups breeding on under surfaces of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Colocasia </tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Araceae</tp:taxon-name> ) leaves ( Fig. 27D ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> The new genus undoubtedly belongs to a group of six genera outlined by Stonedahl
                  (1988) and related to <tp:taxon-name> Ernestinus </tp:taxon-name> (see relevant
                  Remarks section for additional details). Within this group, <tp:taxon-name>
                        Stonedahlia </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. appears to be most closely related to
                        <tp:taxon-name> Myiocapsus Poppius, 1914 </tp:taxon-name> . Both genera may
                  be easily distinguished from <tp:taxon-name> Eofurius </tp:taxon-name> ,
                        <tp:taxon-name> Ernestinus </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Microbryocoris
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Palaeofurius </tp:taxon-name> , and
                        <tp:taxon-name> Stylopomiris </tp:taxon-name> by the ventrally produced head
                  with vertical frons, pale yellow coloration, and genital capsule with spinelike
                  process on the left wall. <tp:taxon-name> Myiocapsus </tp:taxon-name> spp. differ
                  from <tp:taxon-name> Stonedahlia </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. in having distinctly
                  larger eyes contacting anterior margin of pronotum and projecting laterally beyond
                  anterolateral angles of pronotum, and male genitalia structure, particularly the
                  simple, straight, gradually tapering right paramere ( Stonedahl 1988 : figs 49e,
                  50e, 51g ), and the apex of aedeagus with small membranous lobes and one or two
                  sclerotized appendages ( Stonedahl 1988 : figs 49g , 50g , 51d). </p>
            <p> Based on gracile body, ventrally produced head, slender legs, and pale yellow
                  coloration, the new genus is superficially similar to <tp:taxon-name> Prodromus
                        Distant, 1904 </tp:taxon-name> (compare Fig. 27C–D ) but the distinctly
                  stylate eyes, longitudinal sulcus on vertex, strongly narrowed basal part of
                  antennal segment I, sickle-shaped left paramere, entirely sclerotized aedeagus,
                  and other characters of the latter genus suggest that the two taxa are only
                  distantly related. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
