<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Namyatovia castlerockensis Yeshwanth &amp; Konstantinov 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4695089</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/26E9B184C441D4CC93404BA72EF2BA6C</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new genera and six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Namyatovia castlerockensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
C1B27D3C-BCD9-4376-A9B4-2C6623D7F2E6
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3D–F
, 

21
, 
25E
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Recognized by the following characters: total body length 3.2–3.7; corium uniformly yellow, without dark pattern (
Fig. 3D
); antenna uniformly dark brown, usually with reddish tinge; right lateral wall of genital capsule deeply excavated, with large, apically rounded sclerotized outgrowth (
Fig. 21A–B
); right paramere flattened, with broadly semicircular dorsal expansion (
Fig. 21C–D
); base of aedeagus with large, characteristic, uniformly sclerotized outgrowth; apex of aedeagus with small, entirely membranous lobe (
Fig 21F
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Named after the 
type
locality, Castle Rock, a village in the Western Ghats Mts, 
Karnataka
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
<tp:taxon-name>
INDIA
</tp:taxon-name>
• 
♂
; 
Karnataka
, 
Belgaum
, 
Castle Rock
; 
15°25.293ˊ N
, 
76°19.734ˊ E
; 

569 m
a.s.l.

; 

26 Oct. 2011

; 
H.M. Yeshwanth
leg.; at light; 
UASB
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
<tp:taxon-name>
INDIA
</tp:taxon-name>
• 
2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for 
holotype
; 
UASB
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Karnataka
, 
Shivamogga
, 
Nagavalli
; 
13.218° N
, 
77.054° E
; 

6 Sep. 2015

; 
H.M. Yeshwanth
leg.; at light; 
UASB
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Dorsum pale lemon yellow to pale brown (
Fig. 3D–E
); head pale yellow, antennal segments dark brown to reddish brown; pronotum yellow, sometimes with pale brown anterior angles; pro-, meso- and metathorax laterally brown, ventrally pale brown or yellow; scutellum pale brown to dark brown; hemelytron uniformly lemon yellow, with narrowly brown or black costal margin and claval commissure; legs uniformly yellow; abdomen yellow ventrally, pale brown at sides.
</p>
      <p>STRUCTURE. Total length 3.2–3.5; body 3.5–3.7× as long as basal width of pronotum; head transverse, vertex 1.8–2.0× as wide as dorsal width of one eye, 0.8–0.9× as wide as length of antennal segment I; segment II 0.8–0.9× as long as head width, 0.6× as long as basal width of pronotum; pronotum 1.8–1.9× as wide as long.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Genital capsule (
Fig. 21A–B
) subquadrate, short and broad, about 1.5× as wide as long, with large aperture; right lateral wall of capsule deeply excavated, with prominent, apically rounded process. Left paramere (
Fig. 21E
) scythe-shaped, with slightly and uniformly swollen body and gradually tapering, apically upturned apical process. Right paramere (
Fig. 21C–D
) somewhat larger than left one, broad, lamellate, with strongly expanded, semicircular body. Aedeagus (
Fig. 21F
) tubular, C-shaped, very thin and evenly sclerotized, with small, entirely membranous apical lobe; Dorsal wall of aedeagus at base with large, hook-shaped sclerotized outgrowth, apically flattened and serrated.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host
</p>
      <p>Unknown. All specimens were attracted to light.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Southwestern 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Karnataka state
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new species is easily distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. sirsiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
by its more uniform dorsal coloration and striking features of the male genitalia. A peculiar sclerotized outgrowth originating from the extreme base of the aedeagus seems to be a unique feature within eccritotarsines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
