<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Acritozosime Kim &amp; Lee 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5114986</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C10D87F40265FFE9FDEBFEBE531DF18C</uri>
         <article-title>Proposal of two new genera of the family Zosimeidae Seifried (Copepoda: Harpacticoida): Heterozosime gen. nov. and Acritozosime gen. nov.</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acritozosime
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Acritozosime spinesco
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, by monotypy.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Body subcylindrical, with distinct constriction between prosome and urosome. Penultimate somite with weak pseudoperculum. Rostrum undefined at base, with 1 pair of long sensilla distally. Caudal rami short, slightly longer than wide; principal seta 
V
very long, about 4/5 of body length. Antennule robust, 7-segmented, with ae on second and distal segment, respectively. Antennary exopod 3-segmented; setal armature, from proximal: 2.0.4; distal endopodal segment with lateral armature comprising 3 stout elements and distal armature composed of 7 elements. Mandibular palp well-developed, with 2 setae on basis; exopod 1-segmented, with 4 setae; endopod 1-segmented, with 4 distal setae and 1 lateral seta. Maxillular coxa without epipodite; exopod 1-segmented, with 2 setae; endopod 1-segmented, with 5 setae. Maxillary syncoxa with 3 endites; endopod 2-segmented. Maxilliped stenopodial, forming right angle between syncoxa and basis; syncoxa with 2 setae; basis gradually extended toward distal end, with 1 seta; endopod small, 1-segmented, with 4 setae. P1 with 2-segmented exopod and endopod; enp-1 without inner seta. P2–P4 with 3-segmented exopod and 2-segmented endopod; exp-3 with 2 outer spines; P2–P3 enp-1 without inner seta. Female P5 exopod and baseoendopod separate; exopod with 3 marginal setae. P6 represented by 1 long and 2 small setae. Male unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The generic name is a combination of the Greek ‘ 
akritos
’ meaning ‘confused’ or ‘mixed’ and the name of the 
type
genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zosime
</tp:taxon-name>
. It refers to several morphological features intermediate between the families 
<tp:taxon-name>Idyanthidae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Zosimeidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
