<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Heterozosime tenuis Kim &amp; Lee
                        2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5114984</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C10D87F40271FFF4FDC6FE085530F443</uri>
                  <article-title>Proposal of two new genera of the family Zosimeidae Seifried
                        (Copepoda: Harpacticoida): Heterozosime gen. nov. and Acritozosime gen.
                        nov.</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Heterozosime tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 2–8 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The species epithet reflects the Latin adjective ‘ <tp:taxon-name> tenuis
                  </tp:taxon-name> ’ (‘thin’ or ‘weak’), referring to the very small seta on the
                  distal margin of P4 enp-3. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Holotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SOUTH KOREA • ♀ ; the Southern Sea ; 33º59′53.04″ N ,
                        127º29′27.60″ E ; stn B4; depth 78.7 m ; 8 Jun. 2015 ; O.H. Yu leg.; MABIK
                        CR00247785 (on 11 slides, unfortunately P5 damaged during mounting process
                        after drawing). </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Allotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SOUTH KOREA • ♂ ; same collection data as for holotype;
                        MABIK CR00247786 (preserved in 80% ethanol). </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SOUTH KOREA • 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype;
                        MABIK CR00247787 (on 11 slides) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; MABIK
                        CR00247788 (preserved in 80% ethanol) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for holotype; MABIK
                        CR00247789 (on seven slides, unfortunately, its mouthparts damaged)
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Other material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SOUTH KOREA • 1 ♀ ; the Southern Sea ; 33º30′11.88″ N ,
                        125º59′48.84″ E ; stn E9; depth 96.4 m ; 3 Jun. 2015 ; O.H. Yu leg.;
                        MInRB-Hr60-S001 (on four slides) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for preceding;
                        MInRB-Hr60-S002 (on four slides) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 2 ♀♀ , 3 ♂♂ ; same collection data as for preceding;
                        MInRB-Hr 60-L001 (preserved in 80% ethanol) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; the Southern Sea ; 32º59′49.41″ N ,
                        126º00′04.82″ E ; stn F11; depth 82.7 m ; 6 Aug. 2016 ; O.H. Yu leg.;
                        MInRB-Hr60-L002 (preserved in 80% ethanol) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; the Southern Sea ; 35º59′52.62″ N ,
                        127º29′58.19″ E ; stn B4; depth 78.7 m ; 26 Apr. 2016 ; T . W. Kang leg.;
                        MInRB-Hr60-L003 (preserved in 80% ethanol) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 2 ♂♂ ; the Southern Sea ; 33º34′46.66″ N ,
                        126º28′45.12″ E ; stn C9; depth 116.3 m ; 9 Aug. 2016 ; O.H. Yu leg.;
                        MInRB-Hr60-L004 (preserved in 80% ethanol) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 8 ♀♀ ; the Southern Sea ; 33º00′00.84″ N ,
                        125º30′00.72″ E ; stn F8; depth 97.0 m; O.H. Yu leg.; 12 Nov. 2015 ;
                        MInRB-Hr60-L005 (preserved in 80% ethanol) </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female (based on the holotype , MABIK CR00247785) </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length about 473–631 µm (mean = 569 µm, n = 12; holotype 572 µm)
                  measured from anterior tip of rostrum to posterior end of caudal rami in lateral
                  aspect. </p>
            <p> HABITUS ( Fig. 2A–B ). Subcylindrical, slightly depressed dorsoventrally, tapering
                  posteriorly, with inconspicuous distinction between prosome and urosome. Rostrum (
                  Fig. 2C ) large, triangular, fused with cephalothorax basally; anterior tip bifid,
                  with 2 long sensilla; anterior half ornamented with fine setules laterally.
                  Cephalothorax large, with almost parallel lateral margins in dorsal aspect. Second
                  to fourth free pedigerous somites tapering posteriorly. Urosome ( Figs 2A–B , 3A )
                  comprising P5 bearing-somite, genital double-somite, 3 free abdominal somites,
                  more slender than prosome, tapering posteriorly; urosomites except for penultimate
                  and anal somites with ventrolateral pleural extensions bearing sensillum distally.
                  Genital double-somite ( Figs 2A–B , 3A ) separate dorsally and laterally, but
                  completely fused ventrally; genital field located at anterior half of genital
                  somite, with single genital slit formed by fusion of both gonopores and large
                  mid-ventral copulatory pore posterior to genital slit; genital slit ( Fig. 3A, C )
                  covered by single large plate, on both sides with 1 stout plumose seta and 2 bare
                  setae (inner one about 3 times as long as outer one), representing P6; each P6
                  distinguished by deep incision on both sides of distal margin. Penultimate somite
                  with weak pseudoperculum comprising 4 crenate projections ( Fig. 3B ). Anal somite
                  ( Figs 2A–B , 3A–B ) small, with semicircular operculum ornamented with small
                  spinules and 1 pair of small peduncles bearing sensillum dorsally; anal opening
                  wide, armed with 2 diagonal rows of setules. </p>
            <p> BODY ORNAMENTATIONS. Integument of cephalothorax ornamented with several paired
                  sensilla; posterior and ventrolateral margins armed with crenate processes,
                  forming weak pseudoperculum, and small peduncles bearing sensillum. Posterior
                  margins of somites except for penultimate and anal somites dorsally ornamented
                  with crenate or pointed processes and small peduncles bearing sensillum; genital
                  double-somite and second abdominal somite ventrally serrate, with 1 pair of small
                  peduncles bearing sensillum; penultimate somite with 3 crenate protrusions
                  laterally and row of spinules ventrally; anal somite ventrally with row of
                  spinules at base of caudal rami. Epimera of free pedigerous somites with 1 (in
                  P3–P4) or 2 (in P2) crenate processes, 2 small peduncles bearing sensillum and 1
                  row of anterior minute spinules. Pleural extensions on urosomites armed with
                  spinules. Dorsal surface of genital doublesomite, second and third abdominal
                  somites ornamented with minute spinules posteriorly. Anal somite with 1 pair of
                  dorsolateral pores and 3 pairs of ventrolateral pores. </p>
            <p> CAUDAL RAMI ( Figs 2A–B , 3A–B ). About 2.8 times as long as greatest width, about
                  1.5 times as long as anal somite, with 1 pore on ventrolateral surface; with 7
                  setae: ventrolateral seta I bare, short, slightly shorter than half length of
                  ramus, inserted in mid-length of outer margin; dorsolateral seta II bare, shorter
                  than seta I; seta III ventrally arising from outer distal corner, slightly shorter
                  than caudal ramus, with weakly pinnate outer margin; principal setae IV and V
                  well-developed, covered with minute spinules distally, with internal fracture
                  plane proximally; seta IV about 2.7 times as long as ramus; seta V about twice as
                  long as seta IV ; seta VI located at inner distal corner, slightly longer than
                  seta I; seta VII triarticulate basally, arising from small peduncle located on
                  dorsal surface subdistally. </p>
            <p> ANTENNULE ( Fig. 4A ). Robust, short, 6-segmented. First segment ornamented with 2
                  rows of spinules along inner margin, with 1 long pinnate seta subdistally. Second
                  segment largest, subdivided by incomplete suture, with 1 bare seta, 7 plumose
                  setae (1 bi-articulate basally and 6 non-articulate), 6 spinulose setae, 5 stout
                  tri-spinulose setae and 1 ae, which is basally fused to adjacent tri-spinulose
                  seta. Third segment small, with 1 weakly pinnate seta and 1 stout tri-spinulose
                  seta. Fourth segment with 1 small spinulose seta, 2 plumose setae and 3
                  tri-spinulose setae; outer margin produced, with 1 bare bi-articulate seta
                  distally. Fifth segment smallest, with 1 weakly pinnate seta. Distal segment
                  small, with 1 stout tri-spinulose, 2 weakly pinnate and 4 bi-articulated bare
                  setae and 1 ae, which is basally fused to adjacent tri-spinulose seta. Setal
                  armature formula as: 1-[1], 2-[18 + (1 + ae)], 3-[2], 4-[7], 5-[1], 6-[6 + (1 +
                  ae)]. </p>
            <p> ANTENNA ( Fig. 4B ). Coxa small, unornamented. Basis elongate, ornamented with 1 row
                  of spinules on lateral surface and 2 short rows of spinules along abexopodal
                  margin, with 1 spinulose abexopodal seta. Exopod 3-segmented; proximal segment
                  elongate, with 1 plumose seta; middle segment smallest, with 1 spinulose seta;
                  distal segment longer than first and middle segments combined, with 1 spinulose
                  seta on lateral margin proximally and 1 serrate and 2 spinulose setae on distal
                  margin. Endopod 2-segmented; proximal segment with 1 long spinulose seta on
                  abexopodal margin; distal segment about 1.8 times as long as preceding segment,
                  ornamented with 1 group of lateral spinules and 1 row of subdistal spinules;
                  lateral armature comprising 1 small bare and 2 stout spinulose setae; distal
                  armature comprising 1 stout spinulose spine, 1 stout spinulose seta, 3 pinnate
                  geniculate setae and 1 slender seta, which is fused basally with adjacent
                  spinulose seta. </p>
            <p> Fig. 2. <tp:taxon-name> Heterozosime tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov.
                  Holotype, ♀ (MABIK CR00247785). A . Habitus, dorsal view, inserts show details of
                  surface at high magnification (×1000). B . Habitus, lateral view. C . Rostrum,
                  dorsal view. </p>
            <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name> Heterozosime tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov.
                  Holotype, ♀ (MABIK CR00247785). A . Urosome excluding P5-bearing somite, ventral
                  view. B . Posterior end of penultimate somite, anal somite, and caudal rami,
                  dorsal view. C . Genital field, ventral view. D . P5. </p>
            <p> Fig. 4. <tp:taxon-name> Heterozosime tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov.
                  Holotype, ♀ (MABIK CR00247785). A . Antennule. A' . Antennule without
                  ornamentation. B . Antenna. C . Mandible. </p>
            <p> MANDIBLE ( Fig. 4C ). Coxa with bulge medially; gnathobase armed with 1 small and 3
                  multicuspidate teeth and 1 pinnate dorsal seta. Palp composed of basis, endopod
                  and exopod; basis elongate, with 3 plumose setae distally; exopod 1-segmented,
                  slightly smaller than endopod, with 1 plumose and 2 pinnate setae; endopod
                  1-segmented, with 4 plumose setae. </p>
            <p> MAXILLULE ( Fig. 5A ). Praecoxal arthrite well-developed, with 2 juxtaposed setae on
                  anterior surface; distal margin armed with 8 stout spines and 1 delicate seta.
                  Coxa ornamented with 1 row of spinules on anterior surface distally; epipodite
                  represented by 1 plumose seta; endite with 3 bare setae distally and 1 bare seta
                  subdistally. Basis armed with 1 row of spinules on dorsal margin and 1 row of
                  spinules on anterior surface subdistally; with 2 endites: dorsal endite with 1
                  plumose and 2 bare setae distally and 2 bare setae subdistally; ventral endite
                  weak, with 2 bare setae distally. Exopod 1-segmented, with 3 plumose setae.
                  Endopod 1-segmented, larger than exopod, with 3 plumose and 3 bare setae. </p>
            <p> MAXILLA ( Fig. 5B ). Syncoxa large, ornamented with 2 short rows of spinules along
                  outer margin; two praecoxal endites fused basally, proximal one with 3 setae (1
                  plumose, 1 bare and 1 spinulose) and distal one with 3 setae (1 bare and 2
                  spinulose); proximal coxal endite elongate, with 3 setae (1 bare, 1 pinnate and 1
                  spinulose); distal coxal endite with 1 stout serrate spine and 2 setae (1 slender
                  bare and 1 stout spinulose). Allobasis with 1 seta near base of endopod; endite
                  with 2 stout serrate spines distally and 2 bare setae subdistally. Endopod small,
                  2-segmented; proximal segment with 3 bare setae laterally; distal segment with 3
                  bare setae distally. </p>
            <p> MAXILLIPED ( Fig. 5C ). Maxilliped 3-segmented, comprising syncoxa, basis and
                  1-segmented endopod. Syncoxa trapezoidal, ornamented with 1 row of long inner
                  spinules proximally. Basis elongate, as long as preceding segment, ornamented with
                  1 row of inner spinules subdistally, with 1 stout spinulose seta distally. Endopod
                  small, rectangular, with 2 plumose setae on distal margin, of which inner one
                  about twice as long as outer one and 2 bare setae on lateral margin. </p>
            <p> P1 ( Fig. 5D ). Praecoxa lacking in the figure. Intercoxal sclerite wide,
                  unornamented. Coxa large, ornamented with 3 rows of spinules on anterior surface,
                  1 row of minute spinules on distal margin and 1 row of posterior spinules near
                  outer distal corner. Basis ornamented with 2 groups of spinules on anterior
                  surface, 1 row of spinules on distal margin of pedestal of inner ramus and 1 row
                  of long setules along inner margin; outer setophore small, with a few anterior
                  spinules and 1 spinulose spine; inner spine spinulose, reaching to mid-length of
                  enp-2, arising from small peduncle bearing few anterior spinules. Both rami
                  2-segmented; exopod reaching to mid-length of enp-2; exp-1 ornamented with outer
                  spinules and inner setules, with 1 spinulose outer spine; exp-2 ornamented with
                  outer spinules, with 3 spinulose spines along outer margin, 1 small spinulose
                  spine and 1 long spinulose seta on distal margin and 2 plumose setae on inner
                  margin; all outer spines on exopod with gradually enlarged outer spines toward
                  distal tip; enp-1 slightly longer than wide, ornamented with 1 row of setules on
                  outer margin and 1 row of spinules near outer distal corner, with 1 plumose seta
                  on inner margin; enp-2 elongate, about 1.2 times as long as enp-1, ornamented with
                  outer spinules along outer margin, with 1 small spinulose outer spine, 1 long
                  spinulose distal spine and 2 plumose inner setae ( Table 2 ). </p>
            <p> P2–P4 ( Figs 6A–B , 7A ). Praecoxae short but wide, ornamented with 1 row of minute
                  spinules on distal margin (praecoxa of P3 lost during dissection). Intercoxal
                  sclerite pentagonal, with concave rear edge. Coxae large, ornamented with 3 rows
                  of spinules on anterior margin, 1 row of spinules at outer distal corner and 1 row
                  of posterior setules (absent in P4) near lateral margin. Bases ornamented with 1
                  row of distal spinules on pedestal of inner ramus and 1 row of long setules on
                  inner margin; anterior surface with 2 groups of spinules in P2; outer seta stout,
                  plumose, arising from outer setophore bearing 1 row of anterior spinules; length
                  of outer setae gradually increasing from P2 to P4. Both rami 3-segmented; exopod
                  longer than endopod; endopod reaching to mid-length of exp- 3 in P2, slightly
                  exceeding end of exp- 2 in P3, and reaching to distal fourth of exp- 2 in P4; each
                  exopodal segment ornamented with outer and distal spinules and inner setules;
                  exp-1 elongate and exp-2 shortest, each with 1 pinnate outer spine and 1 plumose
                  inner seta; exp-3 with 2 pinnate outer spines, 1 pinnate outer distal spine (with
                  plumose inner margin), 1 plumose inner distal seta and 2 plumose inner setae;
                  enp-1 and enp-2 ornamented with outer setules, distal spinules and a few inner
                  spinules, with 1 plumose inner seta, respectively; enp-3 ornamented with outer
                  spinules, minute distal spinules, a few fine inner setules and 1 or 2 posterior
                  spinules; P2–P3 enp-3 with 1 pinnate outer spine, 2 plumose distal setae and 1
                  inner plumose seta; P4 enp-3 with 1 long pinnate outer spine, 1 delicate outer
                  distal seta, 1 plumose inner distal seta and 1 plumose inner seta; length of outer
                  spines on enp-2 gradually increasing from P2 to P4 ( Table 2 ). </p>
            <p> Fig. 5. <tp:taxon-name> Heterozosime tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov.
                  Holotype, ♀ (MABIK CR00247785). A . Maxillule. B . Maxilla. C . Maxilliped. D .
                  P1. E . Abnormal condition of P1 endopod; arrowhead indicates the absence of the
                  proximal seta on enp-2. </p>
            <p> P5 ( Fig. 3D ). Left and right legs connected by small intercoxal sclerite.
                  Baseoendopod short, wide; outer setophore well-developed, bearing 1 long pinnate
                  seta; endopodal lobe elongate, reaching to distal third of exopod, with 2 long
                  plumose distal setae, of which inner one about 1.4 times as long as outer one;
                  ornamented with a few spinules on outer margin. Exopod basally fused to
                  baseoendopod, with 3 marginal setae, of which inner most one about 1.8 times as
                  long as two other elements and 1 small seta arising from small peduncle on
                  anterior surface near outer margin. </p>
            <p> Male (based on the paratype MABIK CR00247789) </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body ( Fig. 8A ) length smaller than in female, 406–474 µm (mean 446
                  µm, n = 9; allotype 406 µm). Sexual dimorphisms shown in urosome, antennule, P2
                  endopod, P5 and P6. </p>
            <p> UROSOME ( Figs 7B , 8A ). Urosome 6-segmented; genital somite and first abdominal
                  somite separated; pleural extensions less developed than those of female; ventral
                  surfaces of first and second abdominal somites ( Fig. 7B ) with 1 row of medial
                  spinules posteriorly. </p>
            <p> ANTENNULE ( Fig. 8B ). Subchirocer, 8-segmented. First segment ornamented with 3
                  groups of spinules along inner margin, with 1 long pinnate seta. Second segment
                  with 1 long pinnate seta. Third segment with 1 bare bi-articulate, 1 tri-spinulose
                  and 6 pinnate setae. Fourth segment with 1 bare bi-articulate, 1 stout
                  tri-spinulose, 1 bare, 2 small pinnate and 3 long spinulose setae. Fifth segment
                  smallest, with 1 bare seta and 1 pinnate seta. Sixth segment stout, with 1 bare
                  seta, 3 plumose setae, 4 small pinnate setae, 3 tri-spinulose setae and 1 ae,
                  which is basally fused to adjacent long tri-spinulose seta. Seventh segment with 1
                  bare bi-articulate seta. Distal segment with 1 stout tri-spinulose, 3 plumose and
                  6 triarticulate setae and 1 ae, being basally fused to adjacent plumose seta.
                  Setal armature formula as: 1-[1], 2-[1], 3-[8], 4-[8], 5-[2], 6-[10 + (1 + ae)],
                  7-[1], 8-[9 + (1 + ae)]. </p>
            <p> P2 ENDOPOD ( Fig. 6C ). P2 endopod 2-segmented by fusion of original enp-2 and
                  enp-3; enp-1 as in female except for presence of anterior pore subdistally; distal
                  segment elongate ornamented with long outer spinules proximally, small outer
                  spinules distally, a few spinules on anterior surface and 1 anterior tube pore
                  subdistally; with 1 plumose inner seta proximally, 1 plumose distal seta and 1
                  stout outer apophysis. </p>
            <p> P5 ( Fig. 7B ). Basally fused with somite. Left and right baseoendopod confluent
                  medially; with welldeveloped outer setophore bearing 1 long weakly pinnate seta;
                  endopodal lobe rudimentary, represented by 2 bare setae. Exopod small, basally
                  fused with baseoendopod, with 1 weakly pinnate and 2 bare setae on distal and
                  subdistal margins and 1 small seta arising from anterior surface of baseoendopod
                  between outer setophore and exopod. </p>
            <p> Table 2. Setal formula of thoracic legs of two zosimeid species described in the
                  present study. The notation of the setal formula follows Huys et al . (1996) . </p>
            <p> P1 P2 P3 P4 Exopod Endopod Exopod Endopod Exopod Endopod Exopod Endopod
                        <tp:taxon-name> Heterozosime tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. 0.223
                  1.211 1.1.222 1.1.121 (1.11apo in ♂) 1.1.222 1.1.121 1.1.222 1.1.121
                        <tp:taxon-name> Acritozosime spinesco </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov.
                  0.123 0.011 1.1.122 0.011 1.1.222 0.120 1.1.222 1.120 </p>
            <p> P6 ( Fig. 7B ). Symmetrical, represented by well-developed plate; each plate with 2
                  lobes distally; outer one with 1 weakly pinnate spine; inner one ornamented with
                  few anterior spinules, with 1 weakly pinnate outer spine and 1 small bare inner
                  seta. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Variability </p>
            <p> Holotype female specimen ( MABIK CR00247785) displays an abnormal condition in the
                  P1 enp-2 of the right ramus, lacking a proximal inner seta ( Fig. 5E ; arrowhead). </p>
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> There is no doubt in allocating <tp:taxon-name> Heterozosime tenuis </tp:taxon-name>
                  gen. et sp. nov. to the <tp:taxon-name>Zosimeidae</tp:taxon-name> on account of
                  morphological features of the antenna, mouthpart appendages, P1 and P 5 in both
                  sexes, which are identical with autapomorphies given by Seifried (2003) .
                  Significantly, this new species is morphologically similar to the typica -group of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Zosime </tp:taxon-name> , as defined by Kim et al . (2016) ,
                  on the basis of certain features such as the mandibular endopod with four setae;
                  the maxillulary free endopod with six elements; the outer spines of the P1 exopod
                  with gradually increasing outer spinules toward the distal end; the typical female
                  P5 with a deep incision between the exopod and endopodal lobe and a well-developed
                  cylindrical outer setophore; and the outermost seta of the P5 exopod displaced by
                  a small peduncle toward the surface in both sexes. However, it is identified by a
                  two-segmented exopod in the P1. All known zosimeid copepods exhibit constant P1
                  segmentation with a three-segmented exopod. </p>
            <p> The two-segmented exopod in P1 is not common within the <tp:taxon-name>
                        Harpacticoida ( Moura &amp; Martínez Arbizu 2003 ) </tp:taxon-name> ; we
                  could not assign this Korean species to any well-defined genus in the family. We
                  thus postulate that the two-segmented exopod of P1 is a significant autapomorphy
                  of <tp:taxon-name> H . tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. within the family
                  and that our proposal of a new genus, <tp:taxon-name> Heterozosime
                  </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. , for <tp:taxon-name> H . tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen.
                  et sp. nov. is reasonable. In the Idyanthidimorpha, proposed by Seifried (2003) ,
                  which comprises only the two families <tp:taxon-name>Idyanthidae</tp:taxon-name>
                  and <tp:taxon-name>Zosimeidae</tp:taxon-name> , this striking feature is evident
                  in three idyanthid genera – <tp:taxon-name> Styracothorax Huys, 1993
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Aspinothorax Moura &amp; Martínez Arbizu, 2003
                  </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Meteorina George, 2004 </tp:taxon-name> – but
                  also in the new zosimeid genus <tp:taxon-name> Acritozosime </tp:taxon-name> gen.
                  nov. proposed in the present study ( Huys 1993 ; Moura &amp; Martínez Arbizu 2003
                  ; George 2004 ). </p>
            <p> Notably, this new species shares the presence of two outer spines on the P2–P4 exp-3
                  with four <tp:taxon-name> Zosime </tp:taxon-name> species: <tp:taxon-name> Z .
                        bathyalis Por, 1967 </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Z . changi
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Z . comata </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>
                        Z . gymnokosmosa </tp:taxon-name> . The latter three species were reported
                  from the Southern Sea of Korea , which includes the type locality of
                        <tp:taxon-name> H . tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. Nevertheless,
                        <tp:taxon-name> H . tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. displays an
                  additional noteworthy characteristic: fine setules on the lateral margins of the
                  rostrum in both sexes. </p>
            <p> The shape of the <tp:taxon-name> H . tenuis </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. male
                  P2 is very similar to that of <tp:taxon-name> Z . changi </tp:taxon-name> , which
                  also has a two-segmented endopod. As suggested by the position of the setal
                  armature in the P2 endopod, this is the result of the fusion of the original
                  middle and distal segments in both species. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
