<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Parallorhogas testaceus Belokobylskij &amp; Achterberg 2021, comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5559924</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/36F7D560C3375ADE7E0B4FDC8B8443D1</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and Yemen</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Parallorhogas testaceus
(
Szépligeti, 1914
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 34–35
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Coeloreuteus testaceus
Szépligeti, 1914: 203
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Coeloreuteus testaceus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Shenefelt 1975: 1193

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Opius
(
Opius
) 
testaceus
</tp:taxon-name>
— 

Yu 
et al.
2016

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Comparative diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species is similar to the Indian 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. colophon
(
Nixon, 1939
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, but differs from the latter species by having the body small (large in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. colophon
</tp:taxon-name>
), antenna 17–18-segmented (29-segmented in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. colophon
</tp:taxon-name>
), first flagellar segment short, 3.5–4.0 times longer than its apical width and as long as second segment (long, 4.5 and 1.3 times accordingly in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. colophon
</tp:taxon-name>
), recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing postfurcal or rarely subinterstitial (antefurcal in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. colophon
</tp:taxon-name>
), scutellum finely but distinctly reticulate-coriaceous (smooth in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. colophon
</tp:taxon-name>
) and mesoscutum almost entirely setose (setose only along notauli and laterally in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. colophon
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Parallorhogas testaceus
</tp:taxon-name>
is also similar to the Malagasy 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monolexis caudatus
Szépligeti, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
, but differs from it in having the second radiomedial vein (r-m) developed (always absent in the genus 

<tp:taxon-name>Monolexis</tp:taxon-name>
,

including 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. caudatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), transverse diameter of eye 1.6–1.8 times longer than temple (2.3 times in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. caudatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), radial vein of fore wing (r) arising distinctly before middle of pterostigma (from middle in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. caudatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), nervellus (m-cu) of hind wing present (absent in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. caudatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), length of first tergite almost equal to its posterior width (1.2 times larger in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. caudatus
</tp:taxon-name>
) and ovipositor shorter than metasoma (distinctly longer in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. caudatus
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
TOGO
• 
♀
; “Togo, Kete Kratje, Graf Zech S., 

vii.1899

”, “ 
Coeloreutes testaceum
(sic!) Sz.” (handwriting by Szépligeti); 
MNBG
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
•
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah
(514), 
light trap
, 

1–31.i.2005

, 
25º21′ N
, 
55º24′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♀♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah
(1700– 1706), 
light trap
, 

27.iv–5.vi.2005

, 
25º21′ N
, 
55º24′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same label data as for preceding; 
ZISP
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
1.9–2.8 mm
; fore wing length 
1.5–2.1 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width (dorsal view) 1.6–1.8 times its median length, 1.1–1.2 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex in anterior half, distinctly roundly narrowed in posterior half. Transverse diameter of eye 1.6–2.0 times longer than temple. Ocelli arranged in almost equilateral triangle; POL 1.2–1.4 times Od, 0.3–0.4 times OOL. Eye almost glabrous, 1.20–1.25 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.3–0.4 times eye height, 0.7–0.9 times basal width of mandible. Face width 0.85–0.90 times eye height and almost equal to height of face and clypeus combined. Malar suture absent. Hypoclypeal depression subround, its width 0.6–0.8 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.3–0.4 times width of face. Occipital carina not joined with hypostomal carina being obliterated ventrally on short distance upper base of mandible. Hypostomal flange very narrow.</p>
      <p>ANTENNA. Antenna rather thick, filiform, 17–18-segmented, almost as long as body. Scape 1.3–1.5 times longer than maximum width, 1.7–2.0 times longer than pedicel. First flagellar segment 3.5–4.0 times longer than its apical width, about as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 2.7–3.0 times longer than wide, 0.8–0.9 times as long as first flagellar segment, 0.9 times as long as apical segment; latter weakly acuminated apically.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 1.5–1.6 times its height. Neck of prothorax short, with distinct pronotal keel in anterior 0.3–0.4. Mesoscutum (lateral view) highly and perpendicularly elevated above pronotum; rather short (dorsal view), its width 1.30–1.35 times median length. Median lobe of mesoscutum (dorsal view) almost straight anteriorly, without median furrow. Notauli distinct, complete, rather narrow, sparsely distinctly crenulate. Prescutellar depression (scutal sulcus) rather deep, finely rugulose, with three–five distinct carinae, 0.35–0.40 times as long as scutellum. Subalar depression shallow, rather narrow, striate with rugosity partly. Precoxal sulcus deep, oblique, finely rugulose-crenulate to almost smooth, running along anterior half of lower part of mesopleuron. Metapleural flange narrow, subrounded distally. Propodeum without lateral tubercles.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 2.8–3.0 times its width. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.1–1.2 times longer than pterostigma. Radial vein (r) arising before middle of pterostigma, from basal 0.35. Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 1.2–1.6 times longer than first abscissa (r), 0.25–0.30 times as long as straight third abscissa (SR1), 0.6–0.8 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) present. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell rather short, 2.3–2.7 times longer than its maximum width, 1.0– 1.1 times as long as narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) distinctly curved and weakly sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) postfurcal or sometimes subinterstitial, 3.0–4.0 times longer than second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M). Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal vein (1-M) 0.5–0.7 times nervulus length. Hind wing 4.5–5.0 times longer than wide. First abscissa of costal vein (C+SC+R) 0.9–1.1 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). Basal vein (1r-m) almost 1.0–1.4 times as long as third costal abscissa (2-SC+R). Medial (basal) cell narrow, weakly widened posteriorly, 7.5– 9.0 times longer than wide, 0.3 times as long as hind wing. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.9–1.0 times as long as second and third abscissae combined (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) distinctly and evenly curved towards apex of wing, antefurcal, unsclerotised.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind femur 3.1–3.5 times longer than wide. Hind tibia weakly thickened. Hind tarsus almost as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus weakly thickened, 0.50– 0.55 times as long as second-fifth segments combined. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.6 times as long as basitarsus, 1.4–1.6 times longer than fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma 1.3–1.5 times longer than mesosoma and head combined. First metasomal tergite with small or very small spiracular protuberances in anterior 0.3, distinctly and almost linearly widened from base to apex. Length of first tergite almost equal to its posterior width; posterior width 2.0–2.5 times its minimum width. Second tergite with very shallow oblique sublateral depressions. Median length of second tergite 0.35–0.40 times its anterior width, 0.75–0.90 times length of third tergite. Second suture shallow and weakly sinuate. Third tergite without transverse furrow. Ovipositor sheath 0.8–0.9 times as long as metasoma, 1.4–1.8 times longer than mesosoma, 0.6–0.8 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 34.
<tp:taxon-name>
Parallorhogas testaceus
(
Szépligeti, 1914
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–F, I–K
. Holotype, ♀ (MNBG). 
G–H
. Arabian specimen (RMNH). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B, G
. Head, front view. 
C, H
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Head, lateral view. 
E
. Apical segments of antenna. 
F
. Basal segments of antenna. 
I
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
J
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
K
. Hind tibia and tarsus.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 35.
<tp:taxon-name>
Parallorhogas testaceus
(
Szépligeti, 1914
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A, C
. Holotype, ♀ (MNBG). 
B
. Arabian specimen (RMNH). 
A
. Fore wing. 
B
. Wings. 
C
. Metasoma, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex and frons entirely and rather distinctly densely and evenly curvedly subaciculate; face almost entirely distinctly transversely striate with dense rugulosity or granulation between striae; temple mainly smooth. Mesoscutum densely and finely granulate-reticulate, rugulose in rather narrow area in medio-posterior half. Scutellum finally reticulate-coriaceous. Mesopleuron transversely striate in upper 0.4–0.5, smooth or almost smooth in lower half. Metapleuron entirely densely rugose-reticulate. Propodeum with basolateral areas irregularly delineate by undulate carinae, smooth or almost smooth in anterior 0.3–0.5 and rugulose on remaining part; areola rather large, indistinctly delineated by carinae, sparse rugose-reticulate to striate; remaining part of propodeum rather coarsely rugose-striate. Hind coxa mainly smooth, dorsally more or less distinctly and curvedly rugose-striate with granulation partly. Hind femur mostly finely reticulate-coriaceus with fine and dense striation dorsally. First metasomal tergite entirely coarsely striate, with dense rugulosity between striae, with two distinct and weakly convergent posteriorly dorsal carinae. Second tergite almost entirely densely striate, almost without or sometimes with weak rugulosity between striae, smooth or almost smooth laterally. Remaining tergites (including third one) entirely smooth. Vertex mainly with sparse, short and semi-erect yellowish setae, sometimes partly glabrous medially. Mesoscutum almost entirely with rather dense, short and semi-erect yellow setae. Mesopleuron medially widely glabrous. Hind tibia dorsally with short, more or less dense and semi-erect setae, their length 0.3–0.6 times maximum width of tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head brownish yellow or light reddish brown, infuscate dorsally. Mesosoma light reddish brown to yellowish brown at least partly. Metasoma mainly brownish yellow, first tergite reddish brown and sometimes with yellow tint. Antenna brown to dark brown, three basal segments yellow to brownish yellow. Palpi yellow or pale yellow. Legs mainly yellow or brownish yellow. Ovipositor sheath dark brown to black. Fore wing hyaline. Pterostigma brown, pale brown basally and apically.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Togo
, * 
UAE
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
