<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Rhaconotus (Rhaconotus) microexcavatus Belokobylskij &amp; Achterberg 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514699</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/835486CB1C96BFB3E56CE8AF87054637</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and Yemen</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Rhaconotus
) 
microexcavatus

Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
4B0164DD-0977-49CF-8DE2-FCD562CABAF6
</p>
      <p>
Figs 55–56
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Comparative diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus bicoloricornis
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Madagascar
(
Granger 1949
), but differs from the latter by the POL of ocelli almost equal to Od, about 0.5 times OOL (0.7 and 0.3 times accordingly in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
); malar space height 0.35 times height of eye and almost equal to basal width of mandible (0.25 and 0.7 times accordingly in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
); antenna about as long as body (1.6 times longer in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
); mesosoma 2.4 times longer than its height (about 2.0 times in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
); radial (marginal) cell weakly shortened, metacarpus (1-R1) 0.9 times as long as pterostigma (not shortened and metacarpus (1-R1) 1.3 times longer than pterostigma in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
); second metasomal tergite with wide and sculptured posterior area and its median length 1.6 times length of remaining part of tergite (with short and smooth posterior area which is 0.6 times as long as length of remaining part of tergite in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
); fifth tergite on posterior margin with low and small median incision (without such incision in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
) and 1.7–1.8 times longer than fourth tergite (1.4 times in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
); propodeum with short basal carina which is about 0.3 times as long as propodeum (long basal carina which is about 0.7 times as long as propodeum in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
); and lateral lobes of mesoscutum widely glabrous (entirely setose in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. bicoloricornis
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus microexcavatus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is also similar with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but it differs from the latter in the temple shorter, transverse diameter of its eye 2.2–2.5 times temple length (1.4–1.7 times in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
); upper margin of clypeus situated distinctly upper than lower level of eyes (on or weakly below in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
); penultimate segment of antenna 4.0–4.5 times longer than wide (3.5–3.7 times in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
); radial (marginal) cell of fore wing weakly shortened (not shortened in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
); first metasomal tergite longer, 1.5–1.6 times longer than its posterior width (shorter, 1.2–1.4 times longer than its posterior width in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
); posterior area of second tergite large, 1.6–1.8 times longer than remaining part of tergite (shorter, only 1.3–1.4 times in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
); second tergite 1.4–1.6 times longer than third tergite (2.6–3.3 times in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
); fifth tergite on posterior margin with low and small median incision (without such incision in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
); and ovipositor sheath longer, 1.1–1.2 times longer than mesosoma, 0.50–0.55 times as long as fore wing (shorter, 0.8–0.9 and 0.4 times respectively in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. magniareolus
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This new species is named after the small median excavation on the posterior margin of the fifth metasomal tergite.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 55.
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Rh.
) 
microexcavatus
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B
. Head and mesoscutum, dorsal view. 
C
. Head, front view. 
D
. Head, lateral view. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Apical segments of antenna. 
G
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
H
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
I
. Hind leg. 
J
. Propodeum and first to third metasomal tergites, dorsal view. 
K
. Fifth metasomal tergite, dorsal view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
• 
♀
; “United Arab Emirates, 
Sharjah
Desert Park
(6491), 
light trap
, 

1–25. ii.2006

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
• 
1 ♀
; “United Arab Emirates, 
Sharjah
Desert Park
(1394), 
light tr.
, 

13–23. iv.2005

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Al-Ajban
(5937), 
Malaise tr.
, 

27.v–26.vi.2006

, 
24º36′ N
, 
55º01′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH

• 

2 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah
Desert Park
(2049–2074), 
light tr.
, 

30.iv–31.v.2005

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH

• 

1 ♀
; same label data as for preceding; 
ZISP

• 

1 ♀
(head missing); “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah
Desert Park
(1202), 
light tr.
, 

29.iii–6.iv.2005

, 
25°1′ N
, 
55°4′ E
. 
A.v. Harten
, RMNH’06”; 
RMNH

• 

2 ♀♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah
Desert Park
(1308), 
light tr.
, 

6–13.iv.2005

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
3.5–4.2 mm
; fore wing length 
2.4–2.9 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width 1.6–1.7 times its median length, 1.3–1.4 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes distinctly evenly convex-roundly narrowed; transverse diameter of eye 2.2–2.5 times larger than temple length. Ocelli medium-sized, arranged almost in equilateral triangle; POL 1.0–1.3 times Od, 0.5– 0.7 times OOL. Eye glabrous, weakly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.15–1.20 times as high as broad. Malar space height 0.35–0.40 times height of eye, almost equal to basal width of mandible. Malar suture shallow but distinct. Face width about 0.9 times height of eye and 1.2–1.3 times height of face and clypeus combined. Upper margin of clypeus situated distinctly upper than lower level of eyes. Hypoclypeal depression round, its width 0.7–0.8 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.35– 0.40 times width of face. Occipital carina not fused with hypostomal carina below being obliterated for short distance upper base of mandible. Vertex convex.</p>
      <p>ANTENNA. Antenna long, slender, weakly setiform, 29–31-segmented, as long as body. Length of scape 1.7–1.8 times its maximum width. First flagellar segment 4.3–5.5 times longer than its apical width, 0.90–0.95 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 4.0–4.5 times longer than wide, 0.6– 0.7 times as long as first segment, 0.8–0.9 times as long as apical segment; latter acuminate apically and with short spine.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.3–2.4 times its height. Pronotum anteriorly weakly or very weakly convex (dorsal view), weakly convex dorsally in posterior half (lateral view). Pronotal carina distinct and situated medially. Mesoscutum weakly and gently-roundly elevated above pronotum. Notauli deep, rather wide, complete and densely crenulate with reticulation. Mesoscutum without median longitudinal depression. Prescutellar depression long, rather deep, its posterior side distinctly and evenly curved, without median carina, with two additional carinae and weakly rugulose to smooth between carinae, 0.30–0.35 times as long as convex scutellum. Precoxal sulcus distinct, rather deep at most anterior part and shallow in posterior one-fifth, sparsely crenulate with fine additional reticulation, almost straight, long, running along almost entire lower part of mesopleuron. Prepectal carina distinct, weakly widened below, with not large lobes opposite fore coxae. Metanotum with short, oblique, acuminate distally and rather wide basally dorsal process (lateral view). Metapleural lobe distinct, wide, rounded distally.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 3.9–4.5 times its maximum width. Radial (marginal) cell weakly shortened, 3.7–4.2 times longer than maximum width. Metacarpus (1-R1) 0.9–1.0 times as long as pterostigma. Radial vein (r) arising weakly before middle of pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming very obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 2.7–3.0 times longer than first abscissa (r), 0.60–0.65 times as long as the weakly curved third abscissa (SR1), 1.6–1.9 times longer than first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell rather long, not widened distally, its length 3.4–3.6 times maximum width, 1.2–1.3 times longer than rather narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) distinctly sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) postfurcal. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) weakly curved to anal vein (1-1A) in distal half. Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal vein (1-M) 1.2–1.4 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Brachial (subdiscal) cell gently and roundly closed weakly before level of recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla on brachial vein (CU1b) present and short; posterior abscissa of anal vein (1-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) absent. Hind wing not narrowed basally, 6.0–7.0 times longer than wide. First costal abscissa (C+SC+R) 0.45–0.55 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.5–0.6 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) short, unsclerotised, antefurcal, oblique, straight.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 56.
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus (Rh.) microexcavatus
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
C
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind femur with distinct and wide basodorsal protuberance, its length 3.1–3.3 times maximum width. Hind tarsus about as long as hind tibia. Hind tibia distally with four outside spines. Hind basitarsus 0.45–0.55 times combined length of second–fifth segments. Second tarsal segment 0.6–0.7 times as long as basitarsus, 1.1–1.4 times longer than fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma 1.2–1.3 times longer than head and mesosoma combined, with five dorsally visible hardly sclerotised tergites. Maximum subposterior width of first tergite 2.0–2.2 times its anterior width; its length 1.5–1.6 times posterior width. Second tergite without anterior area, with long and wide posterior area separated anteriorly by deep and evenly curved crenulate transverse furrow. Median length of posterior area 1.6–1.8 times median length of remaining part of second tergite. Median length of second tergite (with posterior area) 0.8–0.9 times its anterior width, 1.4–1.6 times length of third tergite. Second suture deep and strongly evenly curved. Third and fourth tergites without posterior transverse furrow; fourth and fifth tergites with coarse crenulate and deep anterior transverse furrow. Fifth tergite enlarged, on posterior margin distinctly convexly curved, with low and small median incision, without tubercles laterally. Fifth tergite 1.7–1.8 times longer than fourth tergite. Ovipositor sheath 0.70–0.75 times as long as metasoma, 1.1–1.2 times longer than mesosoma, 0.50–0.55 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex entirely finely and almost evenly transversely striate with very dense reticulation or granulation between striae; frons entirely and distinctly reticulate-striate; temple mainly reticulate-coriaceous and almost smooth below. Face densely reticulate-granulate medially, finely coriaceous to smooth in wide lower lateral parts. Mesoscutum densely reticulate-rugulose, sculpture often situated in rather even curved and dense transverse lines, with rugosity in narrow area in medio-posterior third. Scutellum densely small reticulate. Mesopleuron densely reticulate-areolate, finely reticulatecoriaceous below precoxal sulcus. Propodeum with basolateral areas and areola delineated by rather distinct carinae, basolateral areas entirely densely reticulate-areolate, remainder of propodeum together with areola densely and rather coarsely rugose; basal carina 0.7–1.0 times as long as basolateral fork of areola; areola rather narrow and long, about 2.0 times longer than wide. Hind coxa densely reticulateareolate, almost coriaceous laterally; hind femur densely reticulate in dorsal half and almost smooth in ventral half. First tergite with distinctly and subparallel dorsal carinae at least in anterior half. First to fifth tergites distinctly and densely striate, with distinct and dense rugulosity between striae; striae on posterior half of fifth tergite weakly curved. Second–fifth tergites laterally with distinct dense striae and rugosity between it. Vertex with short and rather sparse semi-erect white setae directed forwards laterally and in posterior third, almost glabrous medio-anteriorly. Mesoscutum on median lobe often entirely or at least latero-posteriorly and on lateral lobes near notauli and laterally with rather dense and semi-erect white setae, medial parts of lateral lobes always widely glabrous, and sometimes medio-anterior part of medial lobe glabrous also. Mesopleuron almost entirely and sparse with distinct white setae. Metasoma dorsally with short and rather sparse semi-erect white setae on most part. Hind tibia dorsally with semi-erect and rather dense short white setae, length of these setae 0.5–1.1 times maximum width of hind tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head mainly brownish yellow or light brown, infuscate dorsally. Mesosoma and metasoma dark reddish brown to almost black in some places, partly reddish brown, metasomal third-fifth tergites posteriorly reddish brown to light reddish brown, posterior tergites and sternites brownish yellow. Scape and pedicel of antenna light reddish brown, basal third or quarter of flagellum yellow to yellowish brown, remaining long apical part of flagellum brown to almost black. Palpi pale yellow or yellow. Legs mainly yellow with brownish tint or brownish yellow, and darker basally, all fifth tarsal segments mainly dark brown. Ovipositor sheath yellow in anterior third and black in posterior two–thirds. Fore wing subhyaline. Pterostigma mainly brown of light reddish brown, pale yellow in basal third.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
Body length 
3.3 mm
; fore wing length 
2.3 mm
. Transverse diameter of eye 2.1 times larger than temple length. Antenna 26-segmented, weakly longer than body. Body 2.5 times longer than maximum height. Hind femur slender, its length 3.4 times maximum width. Metasoma 1.4 times longer than head and mesosoma combined, with 6 dorsally visible and hardly sclerotised tergites. Maximum subposterior width of first tergite 1.7 times its anterior width; its length 1.8 times posterior width. Median length of posterior area of second tergite 0.7 times median length of remaining part of second tergite. Median length of second tergite (with posterior area) 1.2 times its anterior width, 1.4 times length of third tergite. Fifth and sixth without median incisure on their posterior margins. Sixth tergite enlarged, on posterior margin distinctly convexly curved, weakly narrowed distally, almost as long as fifth tergite, 1.1 times longer than fourth tergite. Otherwise similar to female.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
UAE
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
