<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Hecabalodes maculatus Belokobylskij 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5559916</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C731E358FFECFFD1D52DFCE05273F94C</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and Yemen</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Hecabalodes maculatus
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
BDFDB8D0-4AC5-4FEF-97AE-19B8AC977E55
</p>
      <p>
Figs 28–29
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Comparative diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hecabalodes tadzhicus
Tobias, 1964
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Tajikistan
and * 
Turkmenistan
(
1 ♀
, 
Turkmenistan
, Kugitang-tau Ridge [= Koytendag], Khodzhaifilata [near Shalkan Village], 
19.v.1982
, Belokobylskij [leg.]; ZISP), but differs from it in having the vertex densely and coarsely transversely undulately striate with reticulation (only densely granulate in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. tadzhicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), notauli complete and rather distinct (almost absent posteriorly in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. tadzhicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), precoxal sulcus mainly very shallow (entirely rather deep in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. tadzhicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), second radial abscissa (3-SR) of fore wing distinctly evenly curved (almost straight or weakly and not evenly curved in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. tadzhicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), metacarpus (1-R1) distinctly shorter than distance from apex of radial (marginal) cell to apex of wing (almost equal to it in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. tadzhicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), and medial (basal) cell of fore wing almost glabrous or partly with very short setae (rather distinctly setose by medium length setae in 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. tadzhicus
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From the Latin word ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
maculatus
</tp:taxon-name>
’ (‘spotted’), because the fore wing in this species has numerous dark spots.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
• 
♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
NARC near Sweihan
(1410), 
light trap
, 

1.ii–14.iii.2005

, 
24º2′ N
, 
55º2′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
• 
1 ♀
; “United Arab Emirates, 
NARC near Sweihan
(1299), 
light trap
, 

9–20.iv.2005

, 
24º2′ N
, 
55º2′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same label data as for preceding; 
ZISP
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
(without metasoma); “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
NARC near Sweihan
(4387), 
light trap
, 

26.ii–2. iv.2006

, 
24º2′ N
, 
55º2′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah Desert Park
(1394), 
light tr.
, 

13–23.iv.2005

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Al-Ajban
(5937), 
Malaise tr.
, 

27.v–26.vi.2006

, 
24º36′ N
, 
55º01′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Al-Ajban
(6418), 
Malaise
&amp; 
light tr.
, 

7–28.xii.2006

, 
24º3′ N
, 
55º0′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’07”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
SSW of ad-Dhaid
(6390–6392), 
light tr.
, 

2–14.ix.2006

, 
25°0′ N
, 
55°4′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RMNH’07”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 28.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hecabalodes maculatus
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head and anterior part of mesosoma, lateral view. 
C
. Head, front view. 
D
. Head, dorsal view. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Apical segments of antenna. 
G
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
H
. Head and mesosoma, lateral view. 
I
. Hind leg.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 29.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hecabalodes maculatus
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
C
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
3.3–4.3 mm
; fore wing length 2.0– 
2.4 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width (dorsal view) 1.4–1.5 times its median length, 1.1–1.2 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly and convex-roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 1.5–1.7 times longer than temple. Ocelli arranged in triangle with base 1.15–1.20 times its side; POL 1.3–1.5 times Od, 0.5–0.6 times OOL. Eye large, glabrous, 1.2–1.3 times as high as broad, almost not concave opposite antennal socket. Malar space 0.35–0.40 times eye height, 0.7–0.9 times basal width of mandible. Face width 0.9–1.0 times eye height and 1.3–1.4 times height of face and clypeus combined. Malar suture absent. Clypeus rather narrow and high. Hypoclypeal depression oval, its width almost equal to distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.40–0.45 times width of face. Occipital carina joined with hypostomal carina by additional subtransverse carina on short distance upper base of mandible. Hypostomal flange narrow.</p>
      <p>
ANTENNA. Antenna weakly thickened, filiform, 20–23 
-
segmented, 0.6–0.7 times as long as body. Scape weakly elongate, 1.7–1.8 times longer than maximum width, 1.8–2.0 times longer than pedicel. First flagellar segment 4.5–5.0 times longer than its apical width, 1.0–1.1 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 1.8–2.2 times longer than its width, about 0.5 times as long as first segment, 0.7– 0.9 times as long as apical segment; latter acuminate apically and usually with short ‘spine’.
</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed dorsoventrally, it length 2.0–2.1 times its height. Neck of prothorax weakly elongate, with weak and undulate pronotal carina in anterior 0.3. Mesoscutum (lateral view) not high and curvedly elevated above pronotum; its width (dorsal view) almost equal to median length. Notauli wide, shallow, complete, rather distinct posteriorly, densely rugose. Median lobe of mesoscutum (dorsal view) distinctly convex anteriorly, without median furrow. Prescutellar depression (scutal sulcus) rather deep, with three–five carinae, finely rugulose to smooth between carinae, 0.25–0.35 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum convex, with carinae laterally, 1.1–1.2 times wider anteriorly than its median length. Subalar depression rather deep, narrow, rugose-reticulate. Precoxal sulcus mainly shallow but weakly deeper posteriorly, straight, reticulate-rugulose, running about along anterior 0.5 of lower part of mesopleuron. Metapleural flange wide and short, rounded distally. Propodeum without lateral tubercles.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 2.8–3.0 times its width; wing almost glabrous or with very short setae in basal third, its distal margin mainly glabrous. Radial (marginal) cell strongly narrowed, 2.9–3.0 times longer than maximum width. Metacarpus (1-R1) 0.30–0.35 times as long as pterostigma, 0.3–0.4 times as long as distance from apex of radial (marginal) cell to apex of wing. Radial vein (r) arising before middle of pterostigma, from its basal 0.4. First radial abscissa (r) 0.25–0.30 times as long as distinctly and evenly curved second abscissa (3-SR + SR1), 0.6–0.8 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) always absent. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) distinctly curved. Recurrent vein (m-cu) weakly antefurcal, 2.5–5.0 times longer than second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M). Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal vein (1-M) 0.5–0.8 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Hind wing 4.1–4.5 times longer than wide. First abscissa of costal vein (C+SC+R) 0.7–0.9 times as long as second abscissa (1- SC+R). Basal vein (1r-m) 0.7–1.0 times as long as third costal abscissa (2-SC+R). Medial (basal) cell rather narrow, weakly widened posteriorly, 7.0–8.0 times longer than wide. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 1.3–1.6 times longer than second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) straight or weakly curved, oblique towards base of wing, interstitial or weakly antefurcal, unsclerotised.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind femur 3.1–3.2 times longer than wide. Hind tibia distinctly thickened. Hind tarsus 1.1–1.2 times longer than hind tibia. Hind basitarsus weakly thickened, 0.6–0.7 times as long as second-fifth segments combined. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.55–0.60 times as long as basitarsus, 1.5–1.7 times longer than fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma 1.1–1.2 times longer than mesosoma and head combined. First metasomal tergite rather short and wide, with weak spiracular protuberances in anterior third, distinctly and weakly convex widened from base to subapex, then narrowed towards apex. Length of first tergite 0.9–1.1 times its maximum subposterior width; its posterior width 0.9 times its subposterior width, 2.1–2.2 times its minimum anterior width. Second tergite without oblique sublateral depressions. Median length of second tergite 0.45–0.50 times its anterior width, 1.3–1.5 times length of third tergite. Second suture distinct but fine, weakly sinuate and with weak, shallow sublateral breaks. Third tergite with very shallow and very weak transverse submedial furrow. Ovipositor sheath 1.0–1.1 times as long as metasoma, 1.5–1.6 times as long as mesosoma, 0.85–0.90 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex densely transversely undulately striate with dense reticulation; frons entirely densely rugose-reticulate; face densely and curvedly transversely striate with rugulosity, rugose with as few striae upper medially and lower laterally; temple mainly reticulate-rugulose, finely granulate to coriaceous in narrow subvertical stripe near eyes. Mesoscutum densely distinctly granulate, rugulose and undulately striate in rather wide area in medioposterior half. Scutellum finely coriaceous, almost smooth medially. Mesopleuron mostly densely reticulation, finer below. Metapleuron entirely densely rugose-reticulate. Propodeum without areas delineate by carinae, entirely and densely rugosereticulate. Hind coxa mainly densely reticulate-coriaceous, dorsally with additional rugosity in base, finely sculptured in lower half. Hind femur distinctly reticulate in dorsal half, finely reticulate to smooth in lower half. First metasomal tergite entirely distinctly striate, with dense rugulosity between striae, without distinct dorsal carinae. Second tergite entirely densely striate and with dense rugulosity between striae. Third tergite narrowly medially and wide laterally densely reticulate, finely coriaceous posteriorly, smooth in posterior three-fourths (medially) to one-fourths (laterally). Fourth to sixth tergites densely and finely to very finely reticulate-coriaceous in anterior two-thirds to half, smooth on remaining distal parts. Vertex with sparse, short and semi-erect yellowish setae. Mesoscutum widely glabrous, with sparse, short and semi-erect white setae arranged narrow along notauli and laterally and widely on median area. Mesopleuron medially widely glabrous. Hind tibia dorsally with short, sparse and semierect pale setae, their length 0.2–0.3 times maximum width of tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Body reddish brown, partly with light or dark reddish brown spots; metasoma laterally sometimes brownish yellow. Antenna light brown to light reddish brown in basal two- or three-fourths, brown to dark brown apically. Palpi yellow. Fore leg ma yellowish brown, middle and hind legs reddish brown; trochanter, trochantellus, base of tibia at short distance and almost all tarsi pale yellow. Ovipositor sheath brownish yellow to light brown in anterior half, brown to almost black in posterior half. Fore wing maculate, partly hyaline with distinct wide transverse stripes or areas around basal vein and on and below radial (marginal) cell. Pterostigma dark brown, pale yellow in basal quarter and yellow anteriorly.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
UAE
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
