<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Doryctinae Foerster 1863</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5526815</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C731E358FFD0FF96D512FA0F5604F98F</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and Yemen</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key to genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Doryctinae</tp:taxon-name>
in the Arabian Peninsula

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. First metasomal tergite distinctly petiolate; acrosternite of first segment long, 0.5–0.9 times as long as tergite (
Figs 14I
, 
15C–D
, 
19B–C
, 
23B, D
) ............................................................................................ 2

</p>
      <p>

– First metasomal tergite not petiolate or subpetiolate; acrosternite of first segment short or slightly elongate, 0.1–0.4 times as long as tergite (
Figs 2B–C
, 
8B–C
, 
10B, D
, 
13C–D
, 
27B–C
, 
48C–D
) ....... 4

</p>
      <p>

2. Laterotergites (epipleura) of second and third tergites fused (
Figs 17D
, 
19C
, 
21D
, 
23D
). First metasomal tergite (petiole) usually more or less abruptly dilated at apex (
Figs 16K
, 
18H
, 
23B
). Fore and middle femora without blister-like swelling ....................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Spathius
Nees, 1819
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Laterotergites (epipleura) of second and third tergites separated (
Figs 15D
, 
40C
, 
42C
). First metasomal tergite (petiole) gradually widened from spiracles to apex, never abruptly dilated at apex (
Figs 14J
, 
39J
, 
42B
). Fore and middle femora with a blister-like swelling near base above. Almost always dark brown specimens (
Figs 14A
, 
39A
, 
41A
). Hind tibiae never pale basally (
Figs 14I
, 
39G
, 
41J
). Second to fourth tergites always with distinctly separated laterotergites (
Figs 15D
, 
40C
, 
42C
). Fore wing strongly dappled with black and white. Medial vein (M+CU1) very strongly curved (
Figs 15A
, 
40A
, 
42A
) ... 3

</p>
      <p>

3. Nervulus (m-cu) of fore wing widely antefurcal (
Fig. 15A
). Infuscate part of fore wing proximal to basal hyaline fascia completely without pubescence (
Fig. 15A
). Basal vein (1r-m) of hind wing absent, costal vein (1-SC+R) fused just with mediocubital vein (1-M) (
Fig. 15A
). Precoxal sulcus almost absent (
Fig. 14H
). Acrosternite of petiole considerably longer than half of first tergite (
Fig. 15D
). ................................................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Parana
Nixon, 1943
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Nervulus (m-cu) of fore wing usually postfurcal or rarely interstitial (
Figs 40A
, 
42A
). Infuscate part of fore wing proximal to basal hyaline fascia always pubescent (
Figs 40A
, 
42A
). Basal vein (1r-m) of hind wing present, costal vein (1-SC+R) not fused just with mediocubital vein (1-M) (
Figs 40A
, 
42A
). Precoxal sulcus present, but often almost indistinct (
Figs 39I
, 
41H
). Acrosternite of petiole rather short, usually shorter than half of petiole tergite (
Figs 39K
, 
42C
) (see also couplet 7) .................................... ...................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
Viereck, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

4. Hind wing without nervellus (cu-a); submedial (subbasal) cell of hind wing absent (
Fig. 64A
). Labial palpus 3-segmented. First flagellar segment distinctly shorter than second segment (
Fig. 63C
). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing absent (
Fig. 64A
). Brachial (subdiscal) cell closed distally and basally; nervulus (cu-a) present (
Fig. 64A
) ................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aivalykus
Nixon, 1938
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Hind wing with nervellus (cu-a); submedial (subbasal) cell of hind wing present and closed distally (
Figs 2A
, 
8A
, 
10A
, 
27A
, 
44A
). Labial palpus 4-segmented ............................................................ 5

</p>
      <p>

5. Brachial (subdiscal) cell of fore wing closed apico-posteriorly; brachial vein (CU1b) present (
Figs 2A
, 
8A
, 
10A
, 
11F
, 
40A
, 
44A
, 
50A
). Medial (basal) cell of hind wing usually wide, more or less distinctly widened toward apex (
Figs 2A
, 
8A
, 
10A
, 
11F
, 
40A
, 
44A
, 
50A
). Usually second (rm) (except for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mimodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
: 
Fig. 13A–B
) and always first radiomedial vein (2-SR) of fore wing present (
Figs 2A
, 
8A
, 
10A
, 
11F
, 
40A
, 
44A
, 
50A
). Hind wing of males without pterostigma-like sclerotisation ..................................................................................................................................... 6

</p>
      <p>

– Brachial (subdiscal) cell of fore wing open apico-posteriorly; brachial vein (CU1b) absent (
Figs 27A
; 
29A
; 
35A
, 
37A; B
; 
38F
). Medial (basal) cell of hind wing narrow, usually not or weakly widened toward apex (
Figs 27A
; 
29A
; 
35A
, 
37A; B
; 
38F
). Often second (r-m) or first (2-SR) radiomedial vein of fore wing absent (
Figs 27A
; 
29A
; 
35A
, 
37A; B
; 
38F
). Hind wing of males often with pterostigma-like sclerotisation...............................................................13

</p>
      <p>

6. Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial to cubital vein (2-CU1) or rarely arising distinctly behind middle of vein (3-CU1), closed brachial (subdiscal) cell distally (
Figs 2A
, 
4A
, 
6A
, 
40A
, 
42A
, 
44A
, 
50A
). Recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing postfurcal (
Figs 2A
, 
4A
, 
6A
, 
40A
, 
42A
, 
44A
, 
50A
) ............... 7

</p>
      <p>

– Parallel vein (CU1a) arising distinctly before middle of vein (3-CU1), closed brachial (subdiscal) cell distally (closely to posterior margin of wing) (
Figs 8A
, 
10A
, 
11F
, 
13A
). Recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing antefurcal (
Figs 8A
, 
10A
, 
11F
, 
13A
) ...........................................................................11

</p>
      <p>

7. Hind tibia with row of sparse thick spines on dorsal surface. First flagellar segment smooth and concave on one side, convex and rugulose at least on basal half of opposite side. Acrosternite of first segment elongated, 0.35–0.40 times as long as tergite. Hind wing of male with pterostigma-like sclerotisation at least on part of costal vein .................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doryctophasmus
Enderlein, 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Hind tibia without row of spines on dorsal surface (
Figs 7L
, 
39G
, 
41J
, 
43J
, 
49G
). First flagellar segment smooth and more or less convex on both sides (
Figs 7F
, 
12G
, 
39F
, 
41F
, 
43E
, 
47E
). Acrosternite of first segment not elongate (except 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
: 
Figs 39K
, 
42C
), 0.25–0.30 times as long as tergite (
Figs 8C
, 
44C
, 
50C
). Hind wing of male without pterostigma-like sclerotisation. ........................................................................................................................................................... 8

</p>
      <p>

8. First metasomal tergite narrow and elongate, subpetiolate, 1.6–1.8 times longer than its posterior width; its acrosternite elongated, usually 0.3–0.4 times as long as tergite (
Figs 39K
, 
40C
, 
42C
) (see also couplet 3) ........................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
Viereck, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– First metasomal tergite wide and short or relatively short, sessile, 1.0–1.3 times longer than its posterior width; its acrosternite not elongated, usually 0.1–0.2 times as long as tergite (
Figs 2B–C
, 
4B–C
, 
6B–C
, 
44B–C
, 
48C–D
) ......................................................................................................... 9

</p>
      <p>

9. At most second metasomal tergite and sometimes third one with separated laterotergites (
Figs 2C
, 
4C
, 
6C
). Base of fourth to sixth tergites without transverse furrows (
Figs 2B
, 
4B
, 
6B
). Metasomal tergites behind third one always smooth (
Figs 2B
, 
4B
, 
6B
). Fifth and sixth metasomal tergites not enlarged, not longer than proceeding tergite and not concealing succeeding tergites (
Figs 2B
, 
4B
, 
6B
). Femora of all legs without dorsal tubercles (
Figs 1H
, 
3H
, 
5G
) .................................................. .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dendrosotinus
Telenga, 1941
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Second to fifth or sixth metasomal tergites with separated laterotergites (
Figs 44C
, 
46C
, 
48C
, 
50C
, 
52C
, 
54C
, 
56C
). Base of fourth to sixth tergites with deep and crenulate transverse furrows (
Figs 44B
, 
46B
, 
48B
, 
50B
, 
52B
, 
54B
, 
56B
). Metasomal tergites behind third one sculptured at least anteriorly (
Figs 44B
, 
46B
, 
48B
, 
50B
, 
52B
, 
54B
, 
56B
). Fifth or sixth metasomal tergites enlarged, usually longer than proceeding tergite and concealing succeeding tergites (
Figs 44B
, 
46B
, 
48B
, 
50B
, 
52B
, 
54B
, 
56B
). Femora of fore, middle and sometimes hind legs with dorsal protuberances (
Figs 43G
, 
45F
, 
49G
, 
51I
, 
53H
, 
55I
, 
61F
) ...................................................................................... 10

</p>
      <p>

10. Metasoma with only five tergites visible dorsally (following tergites hidden under fifth one); fifth tergite usually distinctly longer than previous (fourth) tergite (
Figs 48C
, 
50B
, 
52B
, 
54D
, 
56B
, 
58C
, 
60B
, 
62C
) .................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
Ruthe, 1854
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Metasoma with six or seven tergites visible dorsally; sixth tergite longer or not longer than previous (fifth) tergite (
Figs 44B
, 
46B
) ............................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotinus
Hedqvist, 1965
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

11. Acrosternite of first segment elongated, 0.4–0.6 times as long as first tergite (
Figs 10C– D
). Hind coxa without or with very small (almost invisible) basoventral tubercle (
Fig. 9F
). Second and third metasomal tergites with two lateral subparallel furrows (
Figs 9I
, 
10B
). Mesoscutum granulate or granulate-coriaceous (
Fig. 9G
). Propodeum without delineated areas (
Fig. 9G
) ............................... .................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hemispathius
Belokobylskij &amp; Quicke, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Acrosternite of first segment short, not elongated, 0.25–0.30 times as long as first tergite (
Figs 8C
, 
13D
). Hind coxa with distinct basoventral tubercle (
Figs 7K
, 
12G
). Second and third metasomal tergites usually without lateral furrows (
Figs 8B
, 
11G
, 
13C
) ......................................................... 12

</p>
      <p>

12. Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing arising distinctly before middle of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell (
Fig. 8A
). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing always present (
Fig. 8A
). Third segment of labial palpus long (
Fig. 7D
). Dorsal lobe of pronotum more or less distinctly convex (
Fig. 7I
). Posterior end of precoxal sulcus usually with rounded depression ........................ ........................................................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Doryctes
Haliday, 1836
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing arising from middle of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell (
Figs 11F
, 
13A–B
). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing absent (
Figs 13A–B
) or present (
Fig. 11F
). Third segment of labial palpus distinctly shortened. Dorsal lobe of pronotum absent (
Fig. 12J
). Posterior end of precoxal sulcus without rounded depression (
Fig. 12J
) ..................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mimodoryctes
Belokobylskij, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

13. First radiomedial vein (2-SR) of fore wing absent or largely unsclerotised (
Fig. 38F
). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing always present (
Fig. 38F
) ..................................................... 14

</p>
      <p>

– First radiomedial vein (2-SR) of fore wing present and mainly well sclerotised (
Figs 27A
, 
29A
, 
31A
, 
33A
, 
35A–B
; 
37A
). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing present (
Figs 35A– B
, 
37A
) or absent (
Figs 27A
, 
29A
, 
31A
, 
33A
) ............................................................................................. 15

</p>
      <p>

14. Apex of female vipositor transformed, upcurved, constricted subposteriorly, then widened and usually strongly narrowed towards apex; apex of ovipositor sheath distinctly widened. Second metasomal tergite often with basal area more or less distinctly delineated by furrow ....................... ................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neoheterospilus
Belokobylskij, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Apex of of female ovipositor not transformed, not upcurved and rather evenly narrowed towards apex; apex of ovipositor sheath not or sometimes only weakly widened (
Fig. 38A
). Second metasomal tergite always without basal area delineated by furrow (
Fig. 38H
) ........ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Heterospilus
Haliday, 1836
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

15. Hind coxa without basoventral tooth (
Fig. 36G
). Fore wing distinctly maculate (
Fig. 37A
). Nervulus (cu-a) of fore wing strongly postfurcal (
Fig. 37A
). – Vertex and mesopleuron densely granulate (
Fig. 36C, I
). Hind wing of male with large simple pterostigma-like sclerotisation at costal vein .... ..................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hemidoryctes
Belokobylskij, 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Hind coxa with distinct basoventral tooth (
Figs 27C
, 
32H
, 
34A
). Fore wing hyaline or only sometimes partly faintly infuscate (
Figs 27A
, 
29A
, 
31A
, 
33A
, 
35A–B
). Nervulus (cu-a) of fore wing more or less weakly postfurcal (
Figs 27A
, 
29A
, 
31A
, 
33A
, 
35A–B
) .......................................................... 16

</p>
      <p>

16. Vertex usually smooth, rarely with fine aciculation, always without granulation (
Fig. 34C, H
). Mesonotum without granulation, mainly smooth; mesopleuron smooth in lower half (
Fig. 34I, J
). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing always present (
Fig. 35A–B
). Recurrent vein (m-cu) of hind wing usually weakly curved towards apex of wing (
Fig. 35B
); if sometimes almost straight, then perpendicular to mediocubital vein (1-M). Propodeum with large areola delineated by distinct carinae (
Fig. 34I
). Hind wing of male without pterostigma-like sclerotisation ................................................. .................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Parallorhogas
Marsh, 1993
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Vertex granulate and usually with additional undulate transverse striae or reticulation (
Figs 26B
, 
28D
, 
30C
, 
32B
). Mesonotum granulate and often with additional rugosity; mesopleuron granulate in lower half (
Figs 26E–F
, 
28G–H
, 
30D–E
, 
32F–G
). Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing often absent (
Figs 27A
, 
29A
, 
31A
, 
33A
), but sometimes present. Recurrent vein (m-cu) of hind wing always curved towards base of wing (
Figs 27A
, 
29A
, 
31B
, 
33A
). Propodeum basically without areola delineated by carinae (
Figs 26E
, 
28G
, 
30E
, 
32G
). Hind wing of male with pterostigma-like sclerotisation ..........17

</p>
      <p>

17. Radial (marginal) cell or fore wing not or only weakly shortened; metacarpus (1-R1) usually not or only slightly shorter than pterostigma ......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leluthia
Cameron, 1887
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Radial (marginal) cell or fore wing distinctly shortened; metacarpus (1-R1) distinctly shorter than pterostigma (
Figs 27A
, 
29A
, 
31A
, 
33A
) ............................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hecabalodes
Wilkinson, 1929
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
