<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Rhaconotinus (Rhaconotinus)
                        albosetosus Belokobylskij 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5559932</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C731E358FFB2FFF7D6BDFC895264F853</uri>
                  <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae
                        (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and
                        Yemen</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Rhaconotinus ( Rhaconotinus ) albosetosus Belokobylskij </tp:taxon-name>
            sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 58BD9E91-59F6-47DD-B0FB-1150696C7D25 </p>
            <p> Figs 43–44 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Comparative diagnosis </p>
            <p> This species is similar to <tp:taxon-name> Rh. micholitzi (Belokobylskij, 2001)
                  </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. from Papua New Guinea ( Belokobylskij 2001b ), but
                  differs from latter in having the vertex entirely transversely striate (mainly
                  granulate and only laterally with short striation in <tp:taxon-name> Rh.
                        micholitzi </tp:taxon-name> ), frons entirely coarsely reticulaterugose
                  (mainly granulate in <tp:taxon-name> Rh. micholitzi </tp:taxon-name> ), precoxal
                  sulcus coarsely crenulate (smooth in <tp:taxon-name> Rh. micholitzi
                  </tp:taxon-name> ), pterostigma pale in basal third (entirely dark brown in
                        <tp:taxon-name> Rh. micholitzi </tp:taxon-name> ), mediocubital vein (M+CU1)
                  of fore wing distinctly curved in apical half (weakly curved in <tp:taxon-name>
                        Rh. micholitzi </tp:taxon-name> ), nervulus (cu-a) distinctly postfurcal
                  (almost interstitial in <tp:taxon-name> Rh. micholitzi </tp:taxon-name> ), hind
                  tarsus distinctly longer than hind tibia (almost equal to it in <tp:taxon-name>
                        Rh. micholitzi </tp:taxon-name> ), and the first metasomal tergite short
                  (long in <tp:taxon-name> Rh. micholitzi </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The name of this species refers to the Latin words ‘ albus ’ (white) and ‘ setosis ’
                  (pubescence), after the white body setosity of this species. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype YEMEN • ♀ ; “Yemen (6117), Al Kowd,
                        21–28.viii.2001 , light trap , A.v. Harten , S. Al Haruri , RMNH’02”; RMNH .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes YEMEN • 1 ♀ ; “ Yemen , Al Kowd, vii.2000 , light
                        tr. , no 4820, A.v. Harten &amp; S. Al Haruri , RMNH’01”; RMNH
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; “ Yemen (4054), Al Kowd ,
                        viii.1999 , light trap , A.v. Harten &amp; S. Al Haruri , RMNH’00”; RMNH
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 5.5–6.9 mm ; fore wing length 3.7–4.5 mm . </p>
            <p>HEAD. Head width 1.3–1.5 times its median length, 1.2–1.3 times width of mesoscutum.
                  Head behind eyes very convex anteriorly, than weakly roundly narrowed; transverse
                  diameter of eye 1.2–1.3 times larger than temple length. Ocelli medium-sized, in
                  triangle with base 1.2 times its sides; POL 1.0–1.4 times Od, 0.45–0.60 times OOL.
                  Eye glabrous, weakly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.2 times as high as
                  broad. Malar space height 0.40–0.45 times height of eye, 0.75–0.80 times basal
                  width of mandible. Malar suture fine but rather distinct, curved. Face width
                  almost equal to height of eye and 1.2–1.3 times height of face and clypeus
                  combined. Upper margin of clypeus situated almost on lower level of eyes.
                  Hypoclypeal depression round, its width 0.75–0.80 times distance from edge of
                  depression to eye, 0.40–0.45 times width of face. Occipital carina not fused with
                  hypostomal carina below being obliterated for rather long distance upper base of
                  mandible; below present several additional transverse carinae. Vertex convex.</p>
            <p>ANTENNA. Antenna slender, weakly setiform, 37–42-segmented, about as long as body.
                  Length of scape 1.7–1.9 times its maximum width. First flagellar segment 5.5–6.0
                  times longer than its apical width, 1.2 times longer than second segment.
                  Penultimate segment 4.5–4.7 times longer than wide, 0.4 times as long as first
                  segment, 0.7–0.8 times as long as apical segment; latter apically distinctly
                  pointed.</p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.1–2.2 times its height. Pronotum anteriorly weakly convex (dorsal
                  view), posteriorly strongly and widely convex dorsally (lateral view). Pronotal
                  carina rather distinct, widely separated from posterior margin of pronotum,
                  distances from carina to anterior and posterior margins of pronotum subequal.
                  Mesoscutum weakly and roundly elevated above pronotum. Notauli deep, complete and
                  crenulate. Mesoscutum without median longitudinal depression. Prescutellar
                  depression rather short, deep, its posterior sides straight and obliquely directed
                  posterolaterally, depression with distinct median carina, rather densely and
                  distinctly crenulate, about 0.3 times as long as convex scutellum. Precoxal sulcus
                  distinct, densely rugose-crenulate or crenulate, weakly S-shape, long, running
                  along entire lower part of mesopleuron. Prepectal carina rather strong, not
                  widened below, without lobes opposite fore coxae. Metanotum with distinct but not
                  high subpointed tooth (lateral view). Metapleural lobe rather short, narrow and
                  rounded distally.</p>
            <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 3.9–4.0 times its maximum width. Radial (marginal) cell
                  not or only weakly shortened. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.15–1.20 times longer than
                  pterostigma, almost 7.0 times longer than distance from apex of radial (marginal)
                  cell to apex of wing. Radial vein (r) arising weakly before middle of pterostigma,
                  from basal 0.45. First radial abscissa (r) forming distinct obtuse angle with
                  second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 2.6–2.7 times longer than
                  first abscissa (r), 0.5 times as long as third abscissa (SR1), 1.5 times longer
                  than first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell not
                  widened distally, its length 3.0–3.3 times maximum width, 0.85–1.00 times length
                  of the wide brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) distinctly
                  sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) weakly postfurcal. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) rather
                  distinctly curved to anal vein (1-1A) in distal half. Distance from nervulus
                  (cu-a) to basal vein (1-M) 0.6–0.7 times nervulus (cu- a) length. Brachial
                  (subdiscal) cell rather gently and almost roundly closed almost on level of
                  recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla on brachial vein (CU1b) present; posterior
                  abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) shortly present. Hind
                  wing not narrowed basally, 5.4–5.5 times longer than wide. First costal abscissa
                  (C+SC+R) 0.5–0.6 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). First abscissa of
                  mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.50–0.55 times as long as second abscissa (1-M).
                  Recurrent vein (m-cu) long and unsclerotised.</p>
            <p>LEGS. Hind femur with distinct wide baso-dorsal protuberance, its length 2.7–2.9
                  times maximum width. Hind tarsus 1.1–1.2 times longer than hind tibia. Hind tibia
                  distally with five–eight outside spines. Hind basitarsus 0.6 times combined length
                  of second-fifth segments. Second tarsal segment 0.4–0.5 times as long as
                  basitarsus, 2.6–3.0 times longer than fourth segment, 1.3–1.4 times longer than
                  fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
            <p> Fig. 43. <tp:taxon-name> Rhaconotinus ( Rh. ) albosetosus Belokobylskij
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♀ (RMNH). A . Habitus, lateral view. B .
                  Head, front view. C . Head, dorsal view. D . Head, lateral view. E . Basal
                  segments of antenna. F . Apical segments of antenna. G . Hind leg. H . Mesosoma,
                  dorsal view. I . Mesosoma, lateral view. J . Propodeum. K . Six metasomal tergite,
                  dorsal view. L . First to third metasomal tergites, dorsal view. </p>
            <p> Fig. 44. <tp:taxon-name> Rhaconotinus ( Rh. ) albosetosus Belokobylskij
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♀ (RMNH). A . Wings. B . Metasoma, dorsal
                  view. C . Metasoma, lateral view. </p>
            <p>METASOMA. Metasoma 1.1–1.2 times longer than head and mesosoma combined, with six
                  dorsally visible hard tergites. Posterior width of first tergite 1.8–2.1 times its
                  anterior width; its length 1.05–1.20 times posterior width. Second tergite without
                  anterior area, with distinct, narrow and weakly curved transverse submedian furrow
                  separated lenticular posterior area; this area 0.85–0.90 times as long as
                  remaining part of tergite. Median length of second tergite (with posterior area)
                  0.6–0.7 times its anterior width, 1.5–2.0 times length of third tergite. Second
                  suture distinct and rather narrow. Sixth tergite large, rounded in posterior
                  margin, with rather deep and more or less wide median emargination, without
                  posteroventral lobes. Sixth tergite 1.5–2.0 times longer than fifth tergite,
                  1.7–2.3 times longer than fourth tergite. Ovipositor sheath almost as long as
                  metasoma, 1.5 times longer than mesosoma, 0.8 times as long as fore wing.</p>
            <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex distinctly and densely transversely striate, partly
                  with rugulosity between striae; frons densely and coarsely rugose-reticulate;
                  temple rugose-striate, reticulate-coriaceous anteriorly along eye. Face densely
                  rugulose-reticulate, with curved striation in lower lateral parts. Mesoscutum
                  densely to very densely and finely granulate with rugulosity partly, with distinct
                  striation or rugosity along notauli, with two weakly convergent and undulate
                  striae in medio-posterior third. Scutellum densely reticulate-coriaceous.
                  Mesopleuron entirely densely reticulate-rugulose and partly with rugosity, smooth
                  or almost smooth below precoxal sulcus. Propodeum with basolateral areas
                  delineated by distinct carinae, with median carina in anterior 0.5–0.6, areola
                  short or not delineated, if present then pentagonal, rugose; basolateral areas
                  densely coriaceous-granulate to partly smooth entirely or at least in anterior
                  half, rugose-reticulate in posterior half, usually distinctly densely striate
                  along carinae. Hind legs densely and finely coriaceous, femur almost smooth in
                  lower half. First tergite with complete dorsal carinae, entirely with several
                  rather sparse longitudinal striae, densely rugulose-striate between striae. Second
                  to fifth tergites distinctly and densely striate, with distinct and dense
                  rugulosity or striation between striae; sixth tergite striate with very dense
                  reticulation in anterior two–thirds, striae more or less concentrically in
                  posterior third. Second-fifth tergites laterally with rather distinct striae and
                  very dense rugosity-reticulation between it. Vertex with long and rather dense
                  semi-erect white setae mainly directed backwards. Mesoscutum with dense semi-erect
                  white setae widely arranged along notauli and anteriorly and in usually single
                  line laterally. Mesopleuron almost entirely with sparse long and white setae.
                  Metasoma dorsally almost entirely with long and rather dense semi-erect white
                  setae directed backwards. Hind tibia dorsally with almost erect or semi-erect,
                  rather dense white setae; length of these setae 1.0–1.3 times maximum width of
                  hind tibia.</p>
            <p>COLOUR. Head reddish brown or dark reddish brown, faintly paler around eyes; mesosoma
                  and metasoma dark reddish brown to almost black partly. Scape reddish brown,
                  pedicel and flagellum in basal two– thirds or half yellowish brown to light
                  reddish brown, flagellum distinctly darkened in apical third or half. Palpi brown
                  to dark brown, sixth maxillary segment light brown or at least paler. All legs
                  reddish brown, fore coxae light reddish brown, all tibiae basally distinctly
                  paler, all tarsi yellowish brown to almost yellow. Ovipositor sheath black. Fore
                  wing faintly and almost evenly infuscate. Pterostigma black to dark brown, whitish
                  yellow or white in basal third or quarter and apically.</p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Yemen . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
