<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Spathius lahji Belokobylskij &amp;
                        Achterberg 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5559908</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C731E358FFFCFFA1D511FDB85264F9D2</uri>
                  <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae
                        (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and
                        Yemen</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Spathius lahji Belokobylskij </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 3E094E2E-9F85-48D1-9D8B-B58ED8226E0C </p>
            <p> Figs 20–21 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Comparative diagnosis </p>
            <p> According to Nixon’s (1943) key, this new species belongs to the <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        dissors Wilkinson </tp:taxon-name> species-group being similar to
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus Nixon, 1943 </tp:taxon-name> from Philippines .
                  However, <tp:taxon-name> S. lahji </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. distinctly differs
                  from <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus </tp:taxon-name> by having all maxillary palpal
                  segments entirely dark reddish brown (apical segment whitish in <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        zagreus </tp:taxon-name> ), fore and middle tibiae entirely black (pale at
                  apex in <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus </tp:taxon-name> ), vertex entirely and very
                  densely granulate reticulate (with distinct traces of transverse aciculation in
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus </tp:taxon-name> ), temple very densely
                  punctate-reticulate (virtually smooth in <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus
                  </tp:taxon-name> ), mesonotum with low but distinct longitudinal keel (without
                  keel and flat in <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus </tp:taxon-name> ), mesopleuron
                  entirely finely reticulate-coriaceous (with broad smooth shining area in
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus </tp:taxon-name> ), second-fourth metasomal
                  tergites with fine but distinct lateral margins (without such margins in
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus </tp:taxon-name> ), and ovipositor sheaths very
                  short, about 0.3 times as long as metasoma (long and 0.8–0.9 times as long as
                  metasoma in <tp:taxon-name> S. zagreus </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> Named after the type locality of the new species, Lahj in Yemen . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype YEMEN • ♀ ; “Yemen (6022), Lahj , vii–ix.2001 ,
                        Mal. trap , A.v. Harten &amp; A. Sallam , RMNH’02”; RMNH .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratype YEMEN • 1 ♂ ; same label data as for holotype;
                        RMNH </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 3.6 mm ; fore wing length 2.2 mm . </p>
            <p>HEAD. Head width (dorsal view) 1.6 times its median length, 1.2 times width of
                  mesoscutum. Vertex convex. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex anteriorly
                  and weakly evenly roundness decreased posteriorly. Transverse diameter of eye
                  (dorsal view) 1.4 times longer than temple. Ocelli small, in almost equilateral
                  triangle. POL 1.3 times Od, 0.5 times OOL. Eye with very short and sparse setae,
                  in lateral view oblique, its maximum diameter 1.2 times minimum diameter. Malar
                  space 0.4 times maximum diameter of eye, 0.85 times basal width of mandible. Face
                  weakly convex, its width 0.9 times maximum diameter of eye, 1.4 times height of
                  face and clypeus combined. Clypeal suture complete, distinct laterally but fine
                  mediodorsally. Ventral margin of clypeus with narrow flange. Hypoclypeal
                  depression medium-sized and rounded, its width 0.8 times shortest distance from
                  edge to eye, 0.4 times width of face. Occipital carina dorsally complete and
                  almost not broken toward ocellar triangle, not reaching below hypostomal carina
                  and obliterated short distance before mandible base. Hypostomal flange narrow.</p>
            <p> Fig. 20. <tp:taxon-name> Spathius lahji Belokobylskij </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ,
                  holotype, ♀ (RMNH). A . Habitus, lateral view. B . Head, front view. C . Head,
                  lateral view. D . Head, dorsal view. E . Basal segments of antenna. F . Apical
                  segments of antenna. G . Mesosoma, dorsal view. H . Mesosoma, lateral view. I .
                  Hind leg. J . Propodeum and petiole of metasoma, dorsal view. </p>
            <p> Fig. 21. <tp:taxon-name> Spathius lahji Belokobylskij </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ,
                  holotype, ♀ (RMNH). A . Wings. B . Petiole of metasoma, dorsal view. C . Metasoma
                  without petiole, dorsal view. D . Metasoma, lateral view. </p>
            <p>ANTENNA. Antenna rather slender, filiform, 22-segmented, 0.7 times as long as body.
                  Scape 1.6 times longer than its maximum width. First flagellar segment 3.5 times
                  longer than apical width, about as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 3.0
                  times longer than width, 0.7 times as long as first segment, 0.9 times as long as
                  apical segment; latter acuminate apically and without spine.</p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma high and short, its maximum length 1.6 times its maximum height.
                  Pronotal carina fine to very fine, its posterior fused medially with posterior
                  margin of pronotum. Pronotal lateral depression shallow and narrow,
                  reticulate-crenulate, delineated below by carina. Mesoscutum (lateral view) high,
                  roundly and curvedly elevated above pronotum, its median lobe (dorsal view)
                  distinctly convex anteriorly and without anterolateral corners, without
                  longitudinal median furrow; mesoscutum in dorsal view 0.9 times as long as maximum
                  width. Notauli incomplete, rather narrow, rather distinct and finely crenulate in
                  anterior half, very shallow or almost indistinct in posterior half. Prescutellar
                  depression distinct, narrow medially and widened laterally, with several rather
                  dense crenulation, 0.1 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum weakly convex,
                  without lateral carinae, almost as long as maximum basal width. Subalar depression
                  narrow, shallow, finely reticulate. Precoxal sulcus indistinct. Postpectal carina
                  absent. Metanotum with low, wide and distally not acuminate medio-dorsal tubercle
                  (lateral view). Metapleural flange (lobe) rather narrow, relatively long,
                  subrounded distally. Propodeum almost straight in anterior half and weakly rounded
                  in posterior half (lateral view), without lateral tubercles.</p>
            <p>WINGS. Fore wing 3.8 times longer than wide. Pterostigma wide, 3.0 times longer than
                  its maximum width. Radial vein (r) arising before middle of pterostigma, from its
                  basal 0.4. Radial (marginal) cell weakly shortened, metacarpus (1-R1) 1.5 times
                  longer than pterostigma. Second radial abscissa (3- SR) 4.8 times longer than
                  first abscissa (r) and forming with it straight angle, 0.8 times as long as the
                  evenly curved third abscissa (SR1), 2.1 times as long as straight first
                  radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell weakly narrowed
                  distally, its length 3.2 times maximum width, 1.7 times length of brachial
                  (subdiscal) cell. Second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M) long, 1.5 times longer
                  than recurrent vein (m-cu). Nervulus (cu-a) weakly postfurcal and oblique towards
                  base of wing. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) distinctly sinuate and strongly curved
                  medially to longitudinal anal vein (1-1A). Brachial (subdiscal) cell wide basally
                  and narrowed towards apex, evenly closed apically on the level of recurrent vein
                  (m-cu). Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial. Hind wing 4.7 times longer than its
                  maximum width. First costal abscissa (C+SC+R) 0.8 times as long as second abscissa
                  (1-SC+R). First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.55 times as long as second
                  and third abscissa (1-M) combined. Recurrent vein (m-cu) long, unsclerotised and
                  not pigmented, interstitial, distinctly and evenly curved towards base of
                  wing.</p>
            <p>LEGS. Fore tibia anterior margin with rather long and rather dense spines arranged in
                  long single line. Segments of middle tarsus rather short, weakly longer than their
                  width. Hind coxa rather short, without basoventral corner and tubercle, 1.4 times
                  longer than maximum width. Hind femur weakly thickened, elongate-oval, 3.5 times
                  longer than wide, with distinct antero-dorsal protuberance. Hind tibia with six
                  slender spines on outer distal margin. Hind tarsus 0.85 times as long as hind
                  tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.55 times as long as remaining segments combined. Second
                  segment of hind tarsus 0.6 times as long as basitarsus, 1.1 times longer than
                  fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
            <p>METASOMA. Petiole in lateral view, ventrally weakly curved, dorsally strongly arched
                  in anterior half and almost straight in posterior half, highest in anterior third;
                  in dorsal view, petiole rather broad, weakly evenly widening towards anterior
                  quarter (till distinct spiracular tubercles), and weakly widened to apex of
                  petiole, with very fine dorsope. Length of petiole 2.3 times its posterior width,
                  1.6 times length of propodeum; posterior width almost equal to its width at level
                  of spiracles, 1.5 times its minimum anterior width. Second to fifth tergites with
                  laterotergites separated; second and third lateral parts of tergites not fused.
                  Second suture present, but very shallow, weakly curved and reticulate with very
                  fine crenulation partly. Median length of second tergite 0.9 times its anterior
                  width, almost as long as third tergite. Median length of second and third tergites
                  combined 1.7 times anterior width of second tergite, 0.7 times their maximum
                  width. Ovipositor straight. Ovipositor sheath 1.2 times longer than petiole, 0.3
                  times as long as metasoma, 0.6 times as long as mesosoma, 0.3 times as long as
                  fore wing.</p>
            <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Head densely granulate, without aciculation; face medially
                  finely coriaceous in vertical stripe, temple below finely granulate-coriaceous.
                  Mesoscutum densely and small reticulateareolate, without carinae and rugulosity
                  medio-posteriorly; scutellum entirely finely reticulate. Meso- and metapleura
                  entirely densely and finely reticulate-coriaceous. Propodeum only with basolateral
                  areas delineated by rather distinct carinae, areola absent; propodeum almost
                  smooth in basomedial fifth, then medially reticulate-rugulose; transverse and
                  longitudinal striate with rugulosity in posterior third. Hind coxa almost entirely
                  areolate-coriaceous; hind femur mainly very finely reticulate. Petiole mainly
                  reticulate-rugulose, almost smooth medio-posteriorly, with short and subparallel
                  dorsal carinae in anterior 0.4. Second to sixth tergites entirely and very densely
                  small reticulate-areolate, sculpture becoming finer towards posterior; second
                  suture without crenulation. Vertex mainly glabrous, with short and sparse yellow
                  setae laterally. Mesoscutum widely glabrous, with short and sparse yellow setae
                  arranged along trace of notauli and laterally. Setae of hind tibia semi-erect,
                  short and rather sparse, their length on dorsal surface about 0.3 times maximum
                  width of tibia.</p>
            <p>COLOUR. Body mainly reddish brown to dark reddish brown, head mainly light reddish
                  brown but infuscate dorsally. Palpi dark brown. Antenna mainly yellow to brownish
                  yellow, two apical segments brown to dark brown. Legs mainly reddish brown with
                  dark spots, fore and middle coxae light reddish brown; fore femur anteriorly
                  partly brownish yellow; all tibiae almost black, tarsi yellow medially, dark
                  basally and apically. Ovipositor sheath almost black. Fore wing strongly
                  infuscate, paler distally, with hyaline vertical stripes wide basally, narrow on
                  level of maximum bend of mediocubital vein (M+CU) and under base of pterostigma.
                  Pterostigma mainly black, white in basal 0.4.</p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> Body length 4.3 mm ; fore wing length 2.2 mm . Antenna 22-segmented, with three dark
                  apical segments. Penultimate segment 2.4 times longer than width. Mesosoma maximum
                  length 1.7 times its maximum height. Hind femur 3.1 times longer than wide.
                  Otherwise very similar to female. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Yemen . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
