<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Rhaconotus (Rhaconotus) brevicellularis Belokobylskij &amp; Achterberg 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514689</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3B589B640E2EBFDF8053183A13D3F794</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and Yemen</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Rhaconotus
) 
brevicellularis

Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
95C2B19B-AD03-4EA3-B93A-75D8627B70A4
</p>
      <p>
Figs 49–50
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Comparative diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species is very similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus arabicus
Belokobylskij, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
, from the Arabian Peninsula (
Belokobylskij 2001a
), but differs from the latter by having the radial (marginal) and second radiomedial (submarginal) cells strongly shortened (both long in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. arabicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), metasoma densely and entirely sculptured (sparsely sculptured and with smooth areas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. arabicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), propodeum without basolateral areas (with such delineated arears in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. arabicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), first flagellar segment of antenna slender, 5.6 times longer than its posterior width (thick, about 4.0 longer than its posterior width in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. arabicus
</tp:taxon-name>
), ovipositor longer (shorter in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. arabicus
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus brevicellularis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resembles by the strongly shortened radial (marginal) cell of fore wing, the Central Asian 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. acmaeoderellae
Belokobylskij, 1990
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Belokobylskij 1990
), described from 
Uzbekistan
, but it distinctly differs in having the posterior area on the second metasomal tergite long and anteriorly distinctly delineated by a deep and narrow furrow (short posterior area delineated by a shallow and wide furrow in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. acmaeoderellae
</tp:taxon-name>
), presence of deep and coarsely crenulate curved transverse furrows on posterior third of the third and fourth tergites (absence of such furrows in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. acmaeoderellae
</tp:taxon-name>
), metasomal tergites long (short in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. acmaeoderellae
</tp:taxon-name>
), and fore wing faintly and evenly infuscate (distinctly maculate in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rh. acmaeoderellae
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Named after its strongly shortened radial (marginal) cell of the fore wing.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
• 
♀
; “United Arab Emirates, 
Wadi Safad
(5020), 
at light
, 

14–21.v.2006

, 
25º1′ N
, 
56º1′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
• 
1 ♀
; “United Arab Emirates, 
Wadi Safad
(5029), 
at light
, 

17–24.vi.2006

, 
25º1′ N
, 
56º1′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
ZISP
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “United Arab Emirates, 
Sharjah
Desert Park
(2049–2074), 
light tr.
, 

30.iv–31.v.2005

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Wadi Maidaq
(4003), 
white &amp; yellow pan tr.
, 

14–25.i.2006

, 
25º1′ N
, 
56º0′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Wadi Wurayah
(1368), 
Mal. &amp; water traps
, 

12–14.iv.2005

, 
25º2′ N
, 
56º1′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Hatta
(6398), 
at light
, 

17–24.viii.2006

, 
24º4′ N
, 
56º0′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♂♂
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharhah
x 
Khor Kalba
(6308–6311), 
light trap
, 

31.v–7.vi.2006

, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
3.6–4.8 mm
; fore wing length 
2.4–2.9 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width 1.4–1.5 times its median length, 1.2–1.3 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes distinctly evenly convex-roundly narrowed; transverse diameter of eye 1.6–1.8 times larger than temple length. Ocelli medium-sized, in triangle with base 1.2–1.3 times its sides; POL 1.1–1.5 times Od, 0.5–0.6 times OOL. Eye with short and very sparse setae, very weakly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.2 times as high as broad. Malar space height 0.45–0.50 times height of eye, 1.0–1.1 times basal width of mandible. Malar suture absent. Face width about 1.1 times height of eye and 1.2–1.3 times height of face and clypeus combined. Upper margin of clypeus situated weakly upper than lower level of eyes. Hypoclypeal depression subround, its width 0.7–0.8 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.35–0.40 times width of face. Occipital carina not fused with hypostomal carina below being obliterated for rather long distance upper base of mandible. Vertex convex.</p>
      <p>ANTENNA. Antenna long, slender, setiform, 29–35-segmented, about as long as body. Length of scape 1.7–1.8 times its maximum width. First flagellar segment 5.6–6.4 times longer than its apical width, 1.0–1.1 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 3.6–4.5 times longer than wide, 0.5 times as long as first segment, 0.8–0.9 times as long as apical segment; latter acuminate apically.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.2–2.3 times its height. Pronotum anteriorly almost straight (dorsal view), distinctly convex dorsally in posterior half (lateral view). Pronotal carina almost indistinct or fine. Mesoscutum not highly and gently-roundly elevated above pronotum. Notauli rather deep, wide, complete and crenulate. Mesoscutum without median longitudinal depression. Prescutellar depression rather long, shallow, its posterior side almost straight laterally or weakly curved, without median carina, densely and distinctly rugulose-granulate, 0.35–0.45 times as long as convex scutellum. Precoxal sulcus distinct, deep medially and shallow anteriorly and posteriorly, crenulate-reticulate, almost straight, long, running along entire lower part of mesopleuron. Prepectal carina distinct, not widened below, without lobes opposite fore coxae. Metanotum with short, obtuse wide tubercle (lateral view). Metapleural lobe rather long, narrow, rounded distally.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 3.8–4.0 times its maximum width. Radial (marginal) cell strongly shortened, 3.6–3.8 times longer than maximum width. Metacarpus (1-R1) 0.5–0.6 times as long as pterostigma, about 0.7 times as long as distance from apex of radial (marginal) cell to apex of wing. Radial vein (r) arising from middle of pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 1.4–1.7 times longer than first abscissa (r), 0.3 times as long as curved third abscissa (SR1), 0.65–0.80 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell short, not widened distally, its length 1.7–2.0 times maximum width, 0.6–0.8 times as long as narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) distinctly sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) postfurcal. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) distinctly curved to anal vein (1-1A) in distal half. Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal vein (1-M) 0.7–1.2 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Brachial (subdiscal) cell gently and roundly closed almost on level of recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla on brachial vein (m-cu) present; posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) absent. Hind wing not narrowed basally, 4.8–5.0 times longer than wide. First costal abscissa (C+SC+R) 0.7–0.8 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.4–0.5 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) rather long, unsclerotised, distinctly evenly curved to base of wing.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 49.
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Rh.
) 
brevicellularis
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head, front view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Head, lateral view. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Apical segments of antenna. 
G
. Hind leg. 
H
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
I
. Mesosoma, lateral view.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind femur with rather distinct basodorsal protuberance, its length 2.8–3.2 times maximum width. Hind tarsus as long as hind tibia. Hind tibia posteriorly with four-five outside spines. Hind basitarsus 0.5–0.6 times combined length of second-fifth segments. Second tarsal segment 0.60–0.65 times as long as basitarsus, 1.3–1.5 times longer than fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma 1.2–1.3 times longer than head and mesosoma combined, with five dorsally visible hard tergites. Maximum subposterior width of first tergite 2.4–2.7 times its anterior width; its length 1.15–1.20 times posterior width. Second tergite without basal area, with long posterior area separated anteriorly by deep curved crenulate transverse furrow. Median length of posterior area 0.7–0.8 times median length of the remaining part of second tergite. Median length of second tergite (with posterior area) 0.8–0.9 times its anterior width, 1.8–2.0 times length of third tergite. Second suture deep and twice curved. Third and fourth tergites with deep curved and densely crenulate transverse furrow on posterior half or third; fourth tergite with similar basal transverse furrow. Fifth tergite enlarged, on posterior margin distinctly curved, without processes, tubercles or incisure, without tubercles laterally. Fifth tergite 1.5–1.7 times longer than fourth tergite. Ovipositor sheath 0.70–0.85 times as long as metasoma, 1.2–1.4 times longer than mesosoma, 0.7 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex entirely densely curvedly transversely striate with very dense reticulation between striae and sometimes fine granulation between striae; frons distinct sinuate striate and densely reticulate-rugose; temple coarsely striate and densely reticulate-coriaceous in upper half, finely coriaceous to almost smooth in lower half. Face mainly densely reticulate-granulate in upper two– third, almost smooth to smooth medially and sometimes narrowly in lower parts. Mesoscutum entirely densely granulate, with reticulation along notauli, with two sinuate striae with rugosity in narrow medio-posterior third. Scutellum densely granulate. Mesopleuron entirely densely reticulate-coriaceous, finely coriaceous below precoxal sulcus. Propodeum without delineated areas, with several convergent posteriorly longitudinal carinae and dense rugulosity between striae; areola absent, but present here rugose area in medioposterior third. Hind coxa rugulose-coriaceous in upper half and finely coriaceous in lower half; hind femur mainly densely reticulate-coriaceous. First tergite without distinctly dorsal carinae. First to fifth tergites distinctly, densely and at least partly curvedly or divergently striate, with distinct and very dense rugulosity between striae; striae on posterior half of fifth tergite subparallel. Second-fifth tergites laterally with fine and dense striae and fine rugosity between it. Vertex with short and rather dense semi-erect white setae directed forwards. Mesoscutum almost entirely with rather dense and semi-erect white setae, its lateral lobes on narrow submedial parts and medial lobe narrow medially glabrous. Metasoma dorsally almost entirely with short and dense semi-erect white setae directed backwards. Hind tibia dorsally with semi-erect and rather dense short white setae, length of these setae 0.4–0.6 times maximum width of hind tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head light reddish brown to yellowish brown, reddish brown dorsally; mesosoma and metasoma dark reddish brown or reddish brown, metasoma below mainly pale brown. Scape of antenna light reddish brown, pedicel and basal four-fifth flagellum yellowish brown or light reddish brown, remaining apical part of flagellum brownish. Palpi brownish yellow to yellow. Fore and middle legs yellowish brown, coxa infuscate; hind coxa and femur reddish brown, hind tibia and tarsus yellow; all tibiae basally paler, fifth tarsal segments distally infuscate. Ovipositor sheath dark brown to black. Fore wing subhyaline, faintly infuscate along veins. Pterostigma dark brown, yellow to pale brown in basal third and shortly apically.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
Body length 3.0– 
4.3 mm
; fore wing length 
1.9–2.7 mm
. Antenna 25–31-segmented. Length of scape 1.4–1.5 times its maximum width. Hind femur thicker, its length 2.8 times maximum width. Metasoma narrow, with sixth tergite only shortly covered by previous (fifth) tergite. Length of first tergite 1.20– 1.35 times its posterior width. Median length of second tergite (with posterior area) equal to its anterior width. Fifth tergite 1.2–1.5 times longer than fourth tergite,1.6–2.0 times longer than sixth tergites. Otherwise similar to female.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 50.
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Rh.
) 
brevicellularis
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
C
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
UAE
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
