<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Cyrtodactylus chungi Ostrowski &amp;
                        Ngo &amp; Pham &amp; Phung &amp; Nguyen &amp; Ziegler 2021, sp.
                        nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4440079</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C94B87A2AE2E9E40FDF3784BDD86CB4A</uri>
                  <article-title>A new Cyrtodactylus (Squamata: Gekkonidae) from Binh Thuan
                        Province, southern Vietnam</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: C3B181E8-F9D3-4344-AD20-28765D1BA0B2 </p>
            <p> Figs 3–8 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> The new species can be distinguished from other members of the genus <tp:taxon-name>
                        Cyrtodactylus </tp:taxon-name> by a combination of the following characters
                  ( Table 1 ): relatively small body size (SVL up to 68.5 mm ); a continuous
                  neckband; 5 or 6 irregular transverse dorsal bands; 11 or 12 bands on original
                  tail; keeled tubercles present on dorsum, posterior limbs and tail; 17 or 18
                  irregular dorsal tubercle rows; 30 or 31 ventral scale rows; ventrolateral skin
                  folds indistinct; an angular series of seven precloacal pores in male and six
                  pitted, enlarged precloacal scales in female, each series separated by a diastema
                  of undifferentiated scales from 4–6 enlarged, poreless femoral scales; median
                  subcaudals slightly enlarged; 17–20 subdigital lamellae under the fourth toe. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> Specific epithet ‘ <tp:taxon-name> chungi </tp:taxon-name> ’ is in honor of Prof. Dr
                  Ngo Dac Chung, College of Education, Hue University, in recognition of his
                  outstanding contributions to training of many herpetologist generations from Hue
                  University. For the common names we suggest Chung’s Bent-toed Gecko (English) and
                  Thạch sùng ngón chứng (Vietnamese). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material ( Figs 3–8 ) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype VIETNAM • ♂; Southern Vietnam , Ham Thuan Nam
                        District , Binh Thuan Province , Ta Kou Nature Reserve ; 10 o 48.868′ N ,
                        107 o 53.523′ E ; 424 m a.s.l.; 20 Jun. 2017 ; T.M. Phung leg.; Field No.
                        BT2017.1; sequence with GenBank accession number MT576019 ; IEBR 4581 .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> VIETNAM • 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; Field
                        No. BT2017.2; sequence with GenBank accession number MT576020 ; IEBR 4582
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description of holotype </p>
            <p> Adult male, snout-vent length (SVL) 66.6 mm ; tail length (TL) 62.7 mm ( 45.1 mm
                  regenerated); head distinct from neck, relatively long (HL: 20.1 mm ; HL/SVL ratio
                  0.32), HW 13.3 mm (HW/ HL ratio 0.66), HH 7.8 mm (HH/HL ratio 0.4); loreal region
                  slightly bulged; snout elongated and rounded (SE: 7.6; SE/HL ratio 0.38); eye
                  diameter 4.4 mm , more than half of snout-eye distance (OD/SE ratio 0.58); median
                  snout scales small and rounded; eyes relatively small compared to head (OD/HL
                  ratio 0.22); anterior supraciliaries large and rounded, posterior supraciliaries
                  small and tapered; ear openings relatively small (ED: 0.75 mm ; ED/HL ratio 0.04),
                  vertical and oval in shape; eye to ear distance slightly longer than eye diameter
                  (EyeEar/ED ratio 1.39); rostral wider than high (RH: 1.65 mm ; RW: 3.3 mm ; RW/RH
                  ratio 2), with an inverse, Y-shaped median suture, surrounded by first
                  supralabial, two nostrils, two supranasals and internasal; lateral nostrils
                  elongated, oval and surrounded by rostral, first supralabial, three postnasals and
                  one supranasal; supranasals separated by one internasal; eye separated from
                  supralabials by 3 or 4 scale rows; mental triangular, wider than high (MW: 1.75 mm
                  ; MH 2.6 mm ; MW/MH ratio 1.49), surrounded by first two infralabials and
                  posteriomedially by postmentals; supralabials 10/9; infralabials 9/9; body slender
                  and short (AG/SVL ratio 0.41); ventrolateral skin folds not developed; dorsal
                  scales granular, heterogeneous in shape and size; dorsal tubercles present in
                  posterior part of head, extremities, dorsum and first third of tail; postocular
                  tubercles irregularly distributed, rounded, flat and about three times size of
                  surrounding granular scales; median dorsal tubercles about five times as large as
                  granular scales, oval, and not keeled; posterior dorsal tubercles keeled and on
                  sacral region very strongly keeled up to base of tail; 18 irregular transversal
                  dorsal tubercle rows; 24 paravertebral tubercles; each tubercle surrounded by 9 or
                  10 granular scales; ventrals smooth, oval and slightly imbricate, in 31
                  longitudinal rows; gular scales homogeneous; dorsal surfaces of upper and lower
                  arms without tubercles, but occasionally enlarged granular scales; left thigh with
                  series of 6 enlarged femoral scales separated by diastema of 6 smaller scales from
                  precloacal scales; right thigh with series of 3 enlarged femoral scales separated
                  by diastema of 8 smaller scales from precloacal scales and single enlarged femoral
                  scale distally; no femoral pores; 45 enlarged precloacal scales arranged in
                  diamond shape, with angled series of 7 pore-bearing scales (3 right, 1 angled, 3
                  left); 15 posteriorly enlarged scales and 21 anteriorly enlarged scales; two
                  postcloacal tubercles on each side; scales on palms and soles rounded to oval,
                  smooth and arched; fore- and hindlimbs moderately long (ForeaL/SVL ratio 0.15;
                  Tibia/SVL ratio 0.17) relatively narrow; toes and fingers narrow and curved at
                  interphalangeal joint; slightly transparent, pointed and curved claws, bordered
                  ventrally by large lamella and dorsally by small, narrow scale; subdigital
                  lamellae proximally larger, widened and merge basally into smaller scales of palm
                  and sole surfaces; distal lamellae smaller, more elongated and distally
                  increasingly imbricate; right fourth finger with 15 subdigital lamellae (6
                  proximal, 9 distal); left fourth finger with 16 subdigital lamellae (5 proximal,
                  11 distal); right and left fourth toe with 17 subdigital lamellae each (6
                  proximal, 11 distal); base of tail with small granular supracaudals and strongly
                  keeled, rounded tubercles; last two thirds of tail regenerated, scales
                  heterogeneously arranged and shaped; tubercles of original part arranged in 6
                  transverse rows (8/-/4/4/4/4) in a distance of 6–7 granular scale rows; tubercles
                  slightly keeled; subcaudals of original part oval, rounded and imbricate; median
                  subcaudals about two to three times larger than the lateral scales, but not
                  transversely enlarged, or arranged in definable rows. </p>
            <p> Table 1. Measurements (in mm) and morphological characters of type series of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. * =
                  regenerated or broken tail; bilateral meristic characters are given as left/right. </p>
            <p> characters IEBR 4581 (holotype) IEBR 4582 (paratype) Sex ♂ ♀ SVL 66.6 68.55 TL
                  62.75* (45.1*) 82.15* AG 27.5 28.8 ForeaL 10.2 10.2 TibiaL 11.2 11.2 HH 7.8 7.7 HL
                  20.1 20.4 HW 13.3 12.4 OD 4.4 4.4 EyeEar 6.1 5.8 SE 7.6 27.5 SnOrb 4.3 4.75
                  InterOrb 4.6 5.35 ED 0.75 0.75 RH 1.65 1.35 RW 3.3 3.4 MH 1.7 2.0 MW 2.6 2.7 SL
                  12/11 12/11 IL 9/9 8/9 N 4/5 4/4 IN 1 3 PM 2 2 DTR 18 17 ParaTub 24 27 GST 9–11
                  10–11 V 31 30 PPi/PP 0/7 6/0 EPS 45 41 FP 0 0 EFS 6/4 6/6 NSF 16/15 18/18 NST
                  17/17 20/20 </p>
            <p> Coloration in preservative ( Figs 5–8 ) </p>
            <p>Ground color of head, neck, limbs and tail grey to light brown; dorsal surface of
                  head brown with irregular, small, dark brown spots; two larger dark brown blotches
                  located in posterior interorbital area and two other dark brown blotches in
                  occiput area; skin above eyes dark grey, blue to black; rostral dark brown;
                  supralabials and infralabials also brown, turning to cream at adjacent areas; a
                  distinct dark brown stripe in loreal region, reaching to third supralabial; nuchal
                  loop dark brown, in V-shape, extending from posterior corner of eye to the neck,
                  edged in light grey; tubercles on head, limbs, dorsum and tail light to dark
                  brown; tubercles on lateral skin fold white to gray; dorsal surfaces of limbs with
                  small, irregularly distributed, dark brown spots; dorsal surface of toes and
                  fingers dark brown spotted with light grey; dorsum with 5 irregular transverse
                  dark brown bands; first band over the shoulder region, X-shaped; dark and light
                  brown spots present between transverse bands and on flanks; ventral scales of body
                  light grey to cream; lateral sides of head, below postocular stripe, and
                  ventrolateral margins of flanks slightly white to cream; anterior part of tail
                  with two transverse, dark brown bands dorsally with dark brown spots in
                  interspaces; dark, transverse dorsal bands separated from underside of tail by
                  light brown, whitish spotted sides of tail; tail light grey to cream ventrally and
                  marbled brown on the original part; regenerated part of tail grey to light brown,
                  marbled.</p>
            <p> Coloration in life </p>
            <p> Ground color of dorsal surface of head, limbs and dorsum bright-yellow; transverse
                  body and tail bands darker; lateral head and belly with bright-yellow spots;
                  marbling of surface of limbs darker; ventral surface white to light blue ( Figs
                  3–4 ). </p>
            <p> Sexual dimorphism and variation </p>
            <p> The morphological characteristics of the female IEBR 4582 correspond well with the
                  holotype (IEBR 4581) and differ only in a few details. The female has some
                  slightly keeled tubercles on the dorsal surface of the forelimbs. Dorsal tubercles
                  are keeled from the posterior insertion of the forelimbs. The two supranasals are
                  separated by two internasals. Another internasal is inserted between the rostral
                  and the two internasals. Two inverse sutures are X-shaped from the lower edges of
                  the internasal and do not form a median suture. The tail is original. The median
                  subcaudals are about twice as large as the supracaudals and extend to the tip of
                  the tail. The two dark brown spots of the occiput are longer and larger. The neck
                  band is also V-shaped but pointed posteriorly. The dorsal surfaces of the forearms
                  and hindlimbs with fine, irregular, transverse stripes. Dorsum with 6 transverse,
                  irregular bands. The first band, between the insertion of the forelimbs, is
                  clearly X-shaped over the shoulder region. Between the neck band and the first
                  body band is an oval, dark brown spot. The dorsal tubercles are clearly lighter.
                  The dorsal side of the tail bears 11–12 transverse, dark brown bands, which
                  completely enclose only the last third. Between these bands are irregular, fine,
                  light brown to brown stripes and dots. The first two thirds of the underside of
                  the tail are marbled light grey to brown. The last third resembles the dorsal
                  side. </p>
            <p> Comparison </p>
            <p> We compared the new species with its 19 congeners from the <tp:taxon-name>
                        Cyrtodactylus irregularis </tp:taxon-name> complex based on an examination
                  of specimens ( Table 2 ) and data obtained from the literature ( Smith 1921 a,
                  1921b ; Ziegler et al. 2002 , 2013 ; Heidrich et al. 2007 ; Orlov et al. 2007 ;
                  Nazarov et al. 2008 . 2012 ; Ngo &amp; Bauer 2008 ; Rösler et al. 2008 ; Geissler
                  et al. 2009 ; Ngo &amp; Chan 2010 ; Ngo 2013 ; Nguyen et al. 2013 ; Schneider et
                  al. 2014 ; Luu et al. 2017 ; Pauwels et al. 2018 ; Neang et al. 2020 ; Ostrowski
                  et al. 2020 ). The new species can be distinguished from all other <tp:taxon-name>
                        Cyrtodactylus </tp:taxon-name> species from Vietnam by morphological
                  characteristics (see Table 3 ). </p>
            <p> In comparison with the species from the <tp:taxon-name> C. irregularis
                  </tp:taxon-name> complex <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. is distinguished from <tp:taxon-name> C. caovansungi Orlov, Nguyen, Nazarov,
                        Ananjeva &amp; Nguyen, 2007 </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> C. kingsadai
                        Ziegler, Phung, Le &amp; Nguyen, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        takouensis Ngo &amp; Bauer, 2008 </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        yangbayensis Ngo &amp; Chan, 2010 </tp:taxon-name> by the absence of
                  transversely enlarged subcaudals. </p>
            <p> The new species can be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name> C. cryptus Heidrich,
                        Rösler, Vu, Böhme &amp; Ziegler, 2007 </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        gialaiensis Luu, Tran, Nguyen, Le &amp; Ziegler, 2017 </tp:taxon-name> ,
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. pseudoquadrivirgatus Rösler, Nguyen, Vu, Ngo &amp;
                        Ziegler 2008 </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> C. taynguyenensis Nguyen,
                        Le, Tran, Orlov, Lathrop Macculoch, Le, Jin, Nguyen, Nguyen, Hoang, Che,
                        Murphy &amp; Zhang, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> by the presence of enlarged
                  femoral scales. </p>
            <p> The new species can be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name> C. bidoupimontis Nazarov,
                        Poyarkov, Orlov, Phung, Nguyen, Hoang &amp; Ziegler, 2012 </tp:taxon-name>
                  by its smaller size (SVL of 66.6–68.5 vs 74.0– 86.3 mm ), fewer ventral scale rows
                  (30–31 vs 38–43) and enlarged femoral scales (4–6 vs 8–10), more precloacal pores
                  in the male (7 vs 4–6), the presence of 6 pitted precloacal scales in the female
                  (vs absence) and by the different dorsal color patter (irregular transversal bands
                  vs irregular transversal bands with light borders). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. bugiamapensis Nazarov, Poyarkov, Orlov, Phung, Nguyen,
                        Hoang &amp; Ziegler, 2012 </tp:taxon-name> by having fewer ventral scale
                  rows (30–31 vs 36–46) and enlarged femoral scales (4–6 vs 6–8), and by the
                  different dorsal color pattern (irregular transversal bands vs round spots forming
                  irregular transverse bands). </p>
            <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. in life. Top:
                  holotype, ♂ (IEBR 4581). Bottom: paratype, ♀ (IEBR 4582). Photos T.M. Phung. </p>
            <p> Table 2. Morphological comparisons between <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. and its congeners of the <tp:taxon-name> C. irregularis
                  </tp:taxon-name> complex (after Smith 1921 a, 1921b ; Ziegler et al. 2002 , 2013 ;
                  Heidrich et al. 2007 ; Orlov et al. 2007 ; Nazarov et al. 2008 , 2012 ; Ngo &amp;
                  Bauer 2008 ; Rösler et al. 2008 ; Geissler et al. 2009 ; Ngo &amp; Chan 2010 ; Ngo
                  2013 ; Nguyen et al. 2013 ; Schneider et al. 2014 ; Luu et al. 2017 ; Pauwels et
                  al. 2018 ; Neang et al. 2020 ; Ostrowski et al. 2020 ). Symbols: / = data not
                  available in literature; – = characteristic does not exist; + = characteristic
                  exists but is not uniquely determined; * = broken or regenerated tail. </p>
            <p> Species SVL (mm) TL (mm) V EFS FP PP (Ƌ) PP (♀) LT4 Color pattern of dorsum Enlarged
                  subcaudals <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  66.6–68.5 62.7*–82.1 30–31 4–6 – 7 6 (pitted) 17–20 banded absent <tp:taxon-name>
                        C. bidoupimontis </tp:taxon-name> 74.0–86.3 75.0–86.0 38–43 8–10 – 4–6 0
                  18–23 banded absent <tp:taxon-name> C. bugiamapensis </tp:taxon-name> 58.6–76.8
                  65.3–83.0 36–46 6–8 – 7–11 0–7 (pitted) 17–20 blotched absent <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        caovansungi </tp:taxon-name> 90.4–94.0 120.0 38–44 8 6 9 0 23–25 banded
                  transversally <tp:taxon-name> C. cattienensis </tp:taxon-name> 43.5–69.0 51.0–64.7
                  28–42 3–8 – 6–8 0 14–19 banded absent <tp:taxon-name> C. cryptus </tp:taxon-name>
                  62.5–90.8 63.5–88.4 47–50 – – 9–11 – 20–23 banded absent <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        cucdongensis </tp:taxon-name> 55.8–65.9 22.1–27.8 35–44 5–9 – 5–6 4–6
                  (pitted) 15–20 banded absent <tp:taxon-name> C. dati </tp:taxon-name> 57.3–77.6
                  50.3–78.1 42–48 2–7 0–7 0–6 / 14–20 blotched absent <tp:taxon-name> C. gialaiensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> 50.1–62.8 42.2–63.6* 38–45 – – 9–10 0–8 (pitted) 25–17 banded
                  absent <tp:taxon-name> C. huynhi </tp:taxon-name> 54.8–79.8 61.5–78.6 43–46 3–5
                  3–8 (♂) 7–9 0–8 (pitted) 17–21 banded absent <tp:taxon-name> C. irregularis
                  </tp:taxon-name> 72.0–86.0 66.0–74.0 38–45 7–8 – 5–7 0–6 18–20 blotched absent
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. kingsadai </tp:taxon-name> 83.0–94.0 117.0 39–46 9–12 0–7
                  7–9 4–8 21–25 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. phnomchiensis </tp:taxon-name>
                  76.1–80.7 56.9–79.1 45–54 0–8 – 4–5 1–7 (pitted) 20–23 banded absent
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. phumyensis </tp:taxon-name> 63.5–66.8 73.2*–74.6* 33–40
                  5–7 – 5–7 (1 pitted) 6 (pitted) 18–21 banded/ blotched absent <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        phuocbinhensis </tp:taxon-name> 46.0–60.4 76.1 43–47 5 – 7 – 17–19 banded
                  absent <tp:taxon-name> C. pseudoquadrivirgatus </tp:taxon-name> 48.6–83.3
                  55.7–82.3 41–57 – – 5–9 5–10 16–25 blotched absent <tp:taxon-name> C. sangi
                  </tp:taxon-name> 49.9–56.3 40.8–47.9* 37 4 – 7 4 (pitted) 18–22 banded absent
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. takouensis </tp:taxon-name> 74.7–81.1 77.7–91.0 39–40 3–5
                  0–2 3–4 – 18–20 banded transversally <tp:taxon-name> C. taynguyenensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> 60.0–85.0 66.0–94.0 42–49 – – 6 – 17–21 blotched absent
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. yangbayensis </tp:taxon-name> 78.5–92.3 91.3–109.1 39–46
                  5–16 0–2 V 6–8 – 15–17 banded variable/ not transversal <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        ziegleri </tp:taxon-name> 84.6–93.0 95.0–107.0 33–39 8–10 0–6 5–8 0–8 18–21
                  banded absent </p>
            <p> Table 3. Morphological comparisons between <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. and its other congeners from Vietnam (after S.N. Nguyen
                  et al. 2006 , 2014 , 2017 ; Ngo 2008a , 2008b ; Ngo et al. 2008 , 2010 , 2017 ;
                  Rösler et al. 2008 ; Ngo &amp; Grismer 2010 , 2012 ; Ziegler et al. 2010 ; Luu et
                  al. 2011 ; Ngo &amp; Chan 2011 ; Nazarov et al. 2012 ; Phung et al. 2014 ; Grismer
                  et al. 2015 , 2017 ; T.Q. Nguyen et al . 2015 , 2017 ; Le et al. 2016 ; Pauwels et
                  al. 2018 ; Murdoch et al. 2019 ; Pham et al. 2019 ). Symbols: / = data not
                  available in literature; – = characteristic does not exist; + = characteristic
                  exists but is not uniquely determined; * = broken or regenerated tail. </p>
            <p> Species SVL (mm) TL (mm) V EFS FP PP (Ƌ) PP (♀) LT4 Color pattern of dorsum Enlarged
                  subcaudals <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  66.6–68.5 62.75*–82.15 30–31 4–6 – 7 6 (pitted) 17–20 banded absent
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. badenensis </tp:taxon-name> 59.3–74.1 58.6–82.4 25–29 – –
                  0 0 18–22 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. bichnganae </tp:taxon-name>
                  95.3–99.9 96.3–115.6 30–31 11–13 18 (♂) 10 8 (pitted) 16–20 banded transversal
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. bobrovi </tp:taxon-name> 75.2–96.4 80.8–90.3 40–45 0 0 5
                  0 21–22 banded absent <tp:taxon-name> C. chauquangensis </tp:taxon-name> 90.9–99.3
                  97.0–108.3 36–38 – – 6–7 6–7 19–23 banded absent <tp:taxon-name> C. condorensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> 52.0–84.0 80.8–111.0 26–40 + – 4–7 – 17–23 blotched transversal
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. cucphuongensis </tp:taxon-name> 96.0 79.3* 42 14 – 0 / 24
                  banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. eisenmanae </tp:taxon-name> 76.8 91.0–103.8
                  44–45 4–6 – – – 17–18 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. grismeri
                  </tp:taxon-name> 68.3–95.0 111.3–115.1 33–38 – / – – 16–19 banded transversal
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. hontreensis </tp:taxon-name> 72.4–88.9 84.2–106.5 40–42 –
                  – 7–8 – 17–19 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. huongsonensis </tp:taxon-name>
                  73.4–89.8 90.5 41–48 7–9 15–17 6 8 20–23 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        intermedius </tp:taxon-name> 61.0–85.0 80.0–100.0 40–50 6–10 – 8–10 – 22
                  banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. leegrismeri </tp:taxon-name> 80.6–92.0
                  58.0–99.0 27–35 + – 4 0 18–20 blotched transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. martini
                  </tp:taxon-name> 64.4–96.2 76.0–101.2 39–43 14–8 – 4 – 22–24 banded present
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. nigriocularis </tp:taxon-name> 82.7–107.5 70.6–121.0
                  42–49 – – 0–2 – 17–21 uniform brown transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. otai
                  </tp:taxon-name> 85.2–90.6 89.7–97.6 38–43 – – 7–8 – 19–22 banded present
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. phongnhakebangensis </tp:taxon-name> 78.5–96.3 98.0–110.0
                  32–42 + + 32–42 (PP+PF) 0–41 (PP+FP) 18–26 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C.
                        phuquocensis </tp:taxon-name> 62.2–85.8 80.5–103.1 38–43 10–16 – 7–9 – 15–18
                  banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. puhuensis </tp:taxon-name> 79.2 82.59 36 + –
                  5 / 23 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. roesleri </tp:taxon-name> 51.1–75.3
                  63.4–101.0 34–40 7–10 + 20–28 (PP+FP) 17–22 (PP+FP) 17–19 banded transversal
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. septimontium </tp:taxon-name> 59.5–89.8 / 37–46 12–16 –
                  6–8 – 17–10 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. soni </tp:taxon-name> 88.7–103.0
                  70.6–113.0 41–45 8–11 6–8 (♂) 6–7 7–8 (pitted) 18–22 banded transversal
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. sonlaensis </tp:taxon-name> 63.1–83.2 33.3*–103.0 34–42
                  15–17 14–15 (♂) 8 – 18–21 banded transversal <tp:taxon-name> C. taybacensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> 77.6–97.5 97.1–104.1 30–38 11–13 – 11–13 5–15 (pitted) 16–20
                  banded transversal </p>
            <p> Fig. 4. <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , in life
                  paratype, ♀ (IEBR 4582). Photos T.M. Phung. </p>
            <p> Fig. 5. <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂
                  (IEBR 4581) and paratype, ♀ (IEBR 4582). Views in preservative. Top: dorsal view.
                  Bottom: ventral view. Photos T. Ziegler. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. cucdongensis Schneider, Phung, Le, Nguyen &amp; Ziegler,
                        2014 </tp:taxon-name> by its larger size (SVL 66.6–68.5 vs 55.8–65.9 mm ),
                  fewer ventral scale rows (30–31 vs 35–44) and enlarged femoral scales (4–6 vs
                  5–9). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. dati Ngo, 2013 </tp:taxon-name> by having fewer ventral
                  scale rows (30–31 vs 42–48) and by the different dorsal color pattern (irregular
                  transverse bands vs irregular dark blotches). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. huynhi Ngo &amp; Bauer, 2008 </tp:taxon-name> by having
                  fewer ventral scale rows (30–31 vs 43–46) and by the absence of femoral pores (vs
                  3–8). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. irregularis ( Smith, 1921 ) </tp:taxon-name> by its
                  smaller size (SVL of 66.6–68.5 vs 72.0–86.0 mm), having fewer ventral scale rows
                  (30–31 vs 38–45) and enlarged femoral scales (4–6 vs 7–8), and by the different
                  dorsal color pattern (irregular transverse bands vs transverse bands with uneven
                  margins in white binding, some bands can fall into separated spots). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. phnomchiensis Neang, Henson &amp; Stuart, 2020
                  </tp:taxon-name> by its smaller size (SVL 66.6–68.5 vs 76.1–80.7 mm ), having
                  fewer ventral scale rows (30–31 vs 45–54) enlarged femoral scales (4–6 vs 0–8),
                  precloacal pores in males (7 vs 4–5) and subdigital lamellae under the fourth to
                  (17–20 vs 20–23) and by the different dorsal color pattern (irregular transverse
                  brown bands vs dark brown body bands bordered by yellowish white or light brown
                  bands). </p>
            <p> Fig. 6. <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , holotype, ♂
                  (IEBR 4581). Cloacal region in preservative. Photo T. Ziegler. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. phumyensis Ostrowski, Do, Lee, Ngo, Pham, Nguyen, Nguyen
                        &amp; Ziegler, 2020 </tp:taxon-name> by having fewer ventral scale rows
                  (30–31 vs 33–40), the absence of pitted precloacal scales in the male (absent vs
                  1), more paravertebral tubercles (24–27 vs 20–23) and by the different dorsal
                  color pattern (irregular transverse bands vs anteriorly irregularly spotted and
                  posteriorly banded). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. phuocbinhensis Nguyen, Le, Tran, Orlov, Lathrop
                        Macculoch, Le, Jin, Nguyen, Nguyen, Hoang, Che, Murphy &amp; Zhang, 2013
                  </tp:taxon-name> by its larger size (SVL 66.6–68.5 mm vs 46.0– 60.4 mm ), having
                  fewer ventral scale rows (30–31 vs 43–47), the presence of 6 pitted precloacal
                  scales in the female (vs absence) and the different dorsal color pattern
                  (irregular transversal bands vs stripes). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. ziegleri Nazarov, Orlov, Nguyen &amp; Ho, 2008
                  </tp:taxon-name> by its smaller size (SVL of 66.6–68.5 vs 84.6–93.0 mm), having
                  fewer ventral scale rows (30–31 vs 33–39) and enlarged femoral scales (4–6 vs
                  8–10). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is most similar to
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. sangi Pauwels, Nazarov, Bobrov &amp; Poyarkov, 2018
                  </tp:taxon-name> . However, the new species can be distinguished from
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. sangi </tp:taxon-name> by its larger size (SVL 66.6–68.5
                  vs 49.9–56.3 mm ), having fewer ventral scale rows (30–31 vs 37) and by the
                  different dorsal color pattern (irregular transversal bands with a closed neck
                  band vs irregular transversal bands and pattern with an interrupted neck band).
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <p> Fig. 7. Head views in preservative of <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi
            </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. from Ta Kou Nature Reserve, Binh Thuan Province, Vietnam. On
            the left: holotype, ♂ (IEBR 4581); on the right: paratype, ♀ (IEBR 4582). Top: lateral
            view. Bottom left: dorsal view. Bottom right: ventral view. Photos T. Ziegler. </p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Cyrtodactylus chungi </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is currently known
                  only from the type locality in Ta Kou Nature Reserve, Binh Thuan Province ,
                  Vietnam ( Fig. 1 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Natural history </p>
            <p> Specimens were found at night between 20:00 and 22:00, on granite rock nearby a
                  forest path, about 0.5–1.0 m above the ground, at elevations between 400 and 500 m
                  a.s.l. The surrounding habitat was evergreen forest of medium and small hardwoods
                  mixed with shrubs and vines. The humidity was approximately 68–72% and the air
                  temperature ranged from 26.8 to 31.6 oC ( Fig. 9 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
