<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetides dilobosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
61431199-1286-4017-BFD8-DF2BC6C2727B
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetides peltates
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, but differs from it in male tenth abdominal tergite and genitalia.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new species refers to the morphology of the tenth abdominal tergite in males, the posterior part of which has a pair of lateral lobes. Greek ʻ 
di-
ʼ means with ʻtwoʼ and ʻ 
lobos
ʼ means ʻlobeʼ. The Chinese name of the species is 
ḋ叶ffi异ffl尾ễ
(Shuang Ye Ni Yi Shi Wei Zhong).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Guangxi
, 
Rongshui
, 
Yangmeiao
; 

9 Aug. 2015

; 
Bao-Jie Du
leg.; 
HBU
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS (mm). Body: 
♂
11.0; pronotum: 
♂
4.3; hind femur: 
♂
10.3.
</p>
      <p>BODY. Small.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Fastigium verticis conical, apex obtuse, furrowed dorsally. Apical segment of maxillary palpus longer than subapical one, apical area inflated, terminal truncate. Eyes spherical, protruded forwards.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Pronotum slightly elongated, reaching posterior margin of first abdominal tergite, anterior margin roughly straight, posterior margin rounded; hind transverse sulcus distinct; lateral lobe longer than high, with tapering posterior area, humeral sinus absent. Thoracic auditory spiracle exposed, small, pear-shaped.</p>
      <p>TEGMEN. Tegmina short, surpassing posterior margin of pronotum, apices rounded. Hind wings absent.</p>
      <p>LEGS. All femora unarmed on ventral surfaces. Fore coxa with a spine; fore tibia with 5 medium long spines on inner and outer sides of ventral surface, tibial tympana open and oval on both sides. Middle tibia with 5–6 spines on inner and outer margins of ventral surface. Hind tibia with 24–27 spines on each side of dorsal surface, bearing 2 pairs of ventral apical spurs and 1 pair of dorsal apical spurs.</p>
      <p>MALE ABDOMEN. Ninth abdominal tergite with lateral areas slightly expanded backwards. Tenth abdominal tergite extended backwards, with a U-shaped notch at the middle of posterior margin, divided into two lateral lobes, apices subacute. Genitalia sclerotized, base broad, other area very narrow, apex bifurcated. Cercus with base cylindrical, dorsal surface of middle area concave downwards, apical area upcurved, slightly twisted, inner margin ridge-shaped, apex rounded. Subgenital plate with base broad, terminal half conical, apex rounded. Styli long conical, apices obtuse, inserted on lateral margins near middle area of subgenital plate.</p>
      <p>FEMALE. Unknown.</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body yellowish brown. Dorsum of head brown, eyes brown, scapus and pedicel of antenna brown. Disc of pronotum with broad longitudinal brown stripe in prozona, splitting into two branches in metazona, most of which is light; ventral edge of lateral lobe with narrow brown stripe. Outer surface of hind femur with indistinctly light brown spots; knee area of hind femur brown, spines on all tibiae brown. Dorsum of abdomen brown, ventro-lateral surface of which dark brown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetides dilobosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (HBU). – 
A–B
. Pronotum. 
A
. Dorsal view. 
B
. Lateral view. – 
C–G
. Apex of abdomen. 
C
. Lateral view. 
D–E
. Dorsal view. 
F
. Apico-dorsal view. 
G
. Ventral view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Guangxi
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
