<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Neocyrtopsides Chang &amp; Wang &amp; Shi
            2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4923540</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D10D87ED4718D41CFC3DA890FBC00644</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera and five new species of the tribe Meconematini (Orthoptera:
            Tettigoniidae: Meconematinae) from Southwestern China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.751.1385</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature> Genus <tp:taxon-name> Neocyrtopsides </tp:taxon-name> gen. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: E3F4E5EA-C956-49E9-A282-DC69968F2B4B </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p> Type species </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Neocyrtopsides bispina </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> The new genus is similar to <tp:taxon-name> Neocyrtopsis Liu &amp; Zhang, 2007
         </tp:taxon-name> , but differs from it in the following characters: male tenth abdominal
         tergite extended backwards, divided into two lateral lobes with apices obtuse, which fuse
         with epiproct, with rectangular notch between lobes; genitalia sclerotized, long, exposed.
         Male subgenital plate with middle lobe; styli inserted on lateral margins near middle of
         subgenital plate. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> The name of the new genus is derived from the genus name <tp:taxon-name> Neocyrtopsis
         </tp:taxon-name> , and the Greek ʻ- ides ʼ, meaning ʻalikeʼ. The Chinese name of the genus
         is ffiùflḃễh (Ni Xin Ci Xi Zhong Shu). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Generic characters </p>
      <p>Body small, robust. Frons slightly sloping backwards, fastigium verticis conical, terminal
         obtuse, furrowed dorsally. Apical segment of maxillary palpus longer than subapical one,
         apical area inflated, apex truncate. Eyes globular, protruded forwards. Pronotum short,
         posterior area of lateral lobes tapering. Tibial tympana open and ovoid on both sides;
         genicular lobes of hind femora with apices rounded. Male tenth abdominal tergite elongated
         backwards and curved down, divided into 1 pair of lateral lobes with apices rounded;
         posterior margin fused with epiproct, after which with a rectangular notch; genitalia
         sclerotized, long, exposed; subgenital plate with basal area broad, terminal narrow, only
         with a middle lobe; styli inserted on lateral margins near the middle of subgenital
         plate.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
