<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Acosmetides Chang &amp; Wang &amp; Shi 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4923530</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D10D87ED4711D414FC0CA974FB6803E0</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera and five new species of the tribe Meconematini (Orthoptera: Tettigoniidae: Meconematinae) from Southwestern China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.751.1385</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetides
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
BF6B036C-62A0-4D4B-8D46-902BCF95D387
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetides peltates
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new genus resembles the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetura
Liu, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
, but differs from it in the following characters: male tenth abdominal tergite protruded backwards with posterior margin split or concave; subgenital plate with basal area broad, apical area narrow, with a median lobe.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new genus is derived from the genus name 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetura
</tp:taxon-name>
and the Greek ʻ 
-ides
ʼ, meaning ʻalikeʼ. The Chinese name of the genus is 
ffi异ffl尾ễh
(Ni Yi Shi Wei Zhong Shu).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Generic characters
</p>
      <p>Body small-sized, stout. Frons vertical, or sloping backwards. Fastigium verticis conical, apex obtuse, furrowed dorsally. Apical segment of maxillary palpus longer than subapical one. Male pronotum moderately extended backwards, shorter in female, lateral lobe longer than deep, posterior area tapering. Tegmina short, apices surpassing posterior margin of pronotum, or concealed beneath pronotum. Foretibial tympana open and oval on both sides. Genicular lobes of hind femur rounded, without spines. Male tenth abdominal tergite slightly elongated, posterior margin concave, or split; genitalia sclerotized, short; cercus medium long, usually dorsal surface of the middle area concave downwards, apex upcurved; subgenital plate with broad basal area, apical half narrow, only with a median lobe. Styli inserted on lateral margins of apical one third of subgenital plate. Ovipositor moderately upcurved.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
