<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Acosmetides peltates Chang &amp; Wang &amp;
            Shi 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4923532</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D10D87ED4712D411FC23AC4CFE25005C</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera and five new species of the tribe Meconematini (Orthoptera:
            Tettigoniidae: Meconematinae) from Southwestern China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.751.1385</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Acosmetides peltates </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: C687D6B4-CB1B-4E49-9471-37948C2C3815 </p>
      <p> Fig. 1 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>The new species is similar to its congeners in appearance, but differs from them in male
         genitalia, subgenital plate and tenth abdominal tergite.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> The name of the new species refers to the morphology of the male genitalia, the Greek ʻ
         peltate- ʼ meaning ʻshield-shapedʼ. The Chinese name of the species is ¶形ffi异ffl尾ễ (Dun
         Xing Ni Yi Shi Wei Zhong). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Holotype CHINA • ♂ ; Yunnan , Weixin , Daxueshan ; 20 Aug. 2012 ;
            Xun Bian leg.; HBU . </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Paratypes CHINA • 1 ♂ , 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype;
            HBU </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 8 ♂♂ , 2 ♀♀ ; same collection data
            as for holotype; Xun Bian and Guang-Lin Xie leg.; HBU </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 3 ♂♂ , 3 ♀♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; 19 Aug. 2012
            ; Xun Bian and Guang-Lin Xie leg.; HBU </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation>
            1 ♂ , 3 ♀♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; 21 Aug. 2012 ; Xun Bian leg.; HBU
         </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; Yunnan , Daguan , Mugan ; 27 Aug.
            2012 ; Xun Bian and Guang-Lin Xie leg.; HBU </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; Yunnan , Yiliang , Xiaocaoba ; 29 Jul. 2006 ; Long-Guan
            Chen leg.; HBU </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 2 ♂♂ , 1 ♀ ; Yunnan ,
            Weixin , Longtang ; 30 Jul. 2017 ; Ping Wang and Gang Wang leg.; HBU
         </tp:material-citation> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> MEASUREMENTS (mm). Body: ♂ 9.3–9.6, ♀ 10.5–11.2; pronotum: ♂ 4.0–4.2, ♀ 3.7–3.8; hind
         femora: ♂ 9.5–9.7, ♀ 9.8–10.3; ovipositor: 6.0–6.5. </p>
      <p>BODY. Small and stout.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Short; frons slightly sloping backwards. Fastigium verticis conical, with
         longitudinal sulcus on dorsum. Apical segment of maxillary palpus slightly longer than
         subapical one, apical area inflated, terminal truncated. Eyes globular, prominent.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Pronotum protruded backwards, reaching posterior margin of first abdominal tergite,
         or anterior margin of second abdominal tergite; anterior margin roughly straight, posterior
         margin rounded; hind transverse sulcus distinct; lateral lobe longer than deep, posterior
         margin tapering; humeral sinus absent. Thoracic auditory spiracle exposed, small and
         oval.</p>
      <p>TEGMEN. Tegmina short, most covered by pronotum, apices surpassing posterior margin of
         pronotum, obtusely rounded. Hind wings absent.</p>
      <p>LEGS. All femora unarmed on ventral surfaces. Fore coxa with a spine; fore tibia with 5
         medium long symmetrically arranged spines on both sides of ventral surface, tibial tympana
         open and oval on both sides. Middle tibia with 4–5 spines on inner and outer margins of
         ventral surface. Hind femur with apices of knees obtuse; hind tibia with 22–24 spines on
         inner and outer margins of dorsal surface, bearing 2 pairs of ventral apical spurs and 1
         pair of dorsal apical spurs.</p>
      <p>MALE ABDOMEN. Ninth abdominal tergite with lateral margin slightly broadened backwards.
         Tenth abdominal tergite narrow, posterior margin of middle area protruded backwards, apical
         area with median sulcus, which splits. Cercus with base cylindrical, middle area concave
         downwards, apex upcurved, twisted, inner edge ridge-shaped, apex indistinctly tooth-shaped.
         Genitalia sclerotized, shield-shaped, broad, terminal papillary. Subgenital plate with base
         broad, basal margin concave triangularly; apical half narrow, only with a median lobe,
         moderately upcurved, apex with small spine-shaped process on the middle. Styli short,
         conical, apices rounded, inserted on lateral margins near apical one third of subgenital
         plate.</p>
      <p> Fig. 1. <tp:taxon-name> Acosmetides peltates </tp:taxon-name> gen. et sp. nov. A–C, G–J .
         Holotype, ♂ (HBU). D–F, K–L . Paratype, ♀ (HBU). – A–B, D–E . Pronotum. A, D . Dorsal view.
         B , E . Lateral view. – C, F–L . Apex of abdomen. C . Lateral view. F, J . Dorsal view. H .
         Apico-dorsal view. I . Apical area of genitalia in ventral view. G, K . Subgenital plate in
         ventral view; a = apical area of subgenital plate. L . Ovipositor in lateral view. </p>
      <p>FEMALE. Pronotum shorter than in male. Tegmina short, most covered by pronotum. Cerci long
         conical, apices subacute. Subgenital plate with base broad, ventral surface of which with a
         colliculus process; lateral margins tapering, posterior margin slightly concave. Ovipositor
         moderately upcurved with finely serrated dorsal and ventral margins along entire length,
         apex acute.</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body yellowish brown, with admixed brown spots, some area light green when
         alive. Head with dorsum brown, eyes brown. Disc of pronotum with longitudinal brown stripe,
         which bifurcates in metazona, other area of which is light. All tarsi light brown, spines
         on all tibiae brown. Outer surface of hind femur with some parallel light brown spots, hind
         knees brown, apex of hind tibia brown. Lateral surface of abdomen brown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p>In some populations, lateral lobes of pronotum with ventral edge brown. The middle lobe of
         male subgenital plate with a pair of indistinct small spines on lateral sides of
         subapex.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> China ( Guizhou , Yunnan ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
