<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Neocyrtopsides bispina Chang &amp; Wang &amp; Shi 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4923870</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D10D87ED4719D41EFC52AFCEFE5C0737</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera and five new species of the tribe Meconematini (Orthoptera: Tettigoniidae: Meconematinae) from Southwestern China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.751.1385</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Neocyrtopsides bispina
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
AAC4C38A-F342-4144-BE5C-8435E2F0D5C2
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neocyrtopsides platycata
(
Shi &amp; Zheng, 1994
)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
, but differs from it in male genitalia and subgenital plate.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new species refers to the morphology of the male genitalia, the Latin ʻ 
bi
-ʼ meaning ʻa pairʼ and ʻ 
spin
-ʼ meaning ʻspine-shapedʼ. The Chinese name of the species is 
ḋflffiùflḃễ
(Shuang Ci Ni Xin Ci Xi Zhong).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Guizhou
, 
Leishan
, 
Leigongshan
, 
Lianhuaping
; 

15 Sep. 2005

; 
Fu-Ming Shi
leg.; 
HBU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
CHINA
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
HBU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS (mm). Body: 
♂
10.0, 
♀
10.7; pronotum: 
♂
3.6, 
♀
3.4; hind femora: 
♂
8.5, 
♀
9.6; ovipositor: 6.5.
</p>
      <p>BODY. Small and stout.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Frons slightly sloping backwards, fastigium verticis conical, apex rounded, furrowed dorsally. Apical segment of maxillary palpus longer than subapical one, apical area inflated, apex truncate. Eyes globular, protruded forwards.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Pronotum short, anterior margin roughly straight, posterior margin rounded; lateral lobes longer than deep, with posterior area tapering; humeral sinus absent. Thoracic auditory spiracle exposed, small, elliptic.</p>
      <p>TEGMEN. Tegmina short, mostly concealed beneath pronotum, only narrow edge visible. Hind wings absent.</p>
      <p>LEGS.All femora unarmed on ventral surfaces. Fore coxa with spine; fore tibia with 5 spines on inner side and 4 spines on outer side of ventral surface; tibial tympana open and oval on both sides. Middle tibia</p>
      <p>with 4 short spines on each side of ventral surface. Hind tibia with 15–17 spines on each side of dorsal surface, bearing 2 pairs of ventral apical spurs and 1 pair of dorsal apical spurs.</p>
      <p>
MALE ABDOMEN. Ninth abdominal tergite slightly protruded backwards. Tenth abdominal tergite extended backwards, posterior area divided into 2 lateral lobes, apices broadened, posterior area fused with epiproct, after which is a rectangular concavity. Cercus cylindrical, lightly incurved, base slightly stout, apex tooth- shaped. Genitalia sclerotized, dorsal branch narrow, near middle leaf-shaped expanded, lateral margins of apical half parallel, apex bispinose; ventral branch stout with apex thin (
Fig. 4D
). Subgenital plate with basal half broad, apical half narrow, lateral margins parallel, apex with a pair of spine-shaped processes, moderately upcurved. Styli long, inserted near base of middle lobe.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Neocyrtopsides bispina
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A–F
. Holotype, ♂ (HBU); 
G–I
. Paratype, ♀ (HBU). – 
A–B
. Pronotum. 
A
. Dorsal view. 
B
. Lateral view. – 
C–E, G
. Apex of abdomen. 
C
. Lateral. 
D
. Apico-lateral view. 
E, G
. Dorsal view. – 
F,H
. Subgenital plate. 
F
. Ventral view. 
H
. Ventro-lateral view. – 
I
. Ovipositor in lateral view. Abbreviations: c = cercus; e = epiproct; g = genitalia; ml = middle lobe of subgenital plate; su = subgenital plate; t = tenth abdominal tergite.
</p>
      <p>FEMALE. Body thinner; tegmina short, anterior edges exposed. Ninth abdominal tergite with lateral areas expanded backwards, tenth abdominal tergite narrow, its middle split at posterior margin. Cerci conical, apices acute. Ovipositor moderately upcurved, base stout, terminal acute, dorsal and ventral margins smooth. Subgenital plate bowl-shaped, posterior margin roughly truncate.</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body yellowish brown, with admixed brown spots. Dorsum of head brown. Pronotum with 1 pair of small brown spots on metazona, lateral lobes blackish brown. Ninth to tenth abdominal tergites dark brown. Cercus brown, apical area of subgenital plate and genitalia dark brown. Spines on all tibiae brown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Guizhou
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
