<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Macrocosmetura truncata Chang &amp; Wang &amp; Shi 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4923546</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/75A584D4717ED0A43F89F45FC936AD8E</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera and five new species of the tribe Meconematini (Orthoptera: Tettigoniidae: Meconematinae) from Southwestern China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.751.1385</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Macrocosmetura truncata
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
8752299A-3372-4DF9-AB26-D7341AF183E2
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Male tenth abdominal tergite observably extended backwards and genitalia sclerotized, posterior area broad, apex truncate.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new species refers to the morphology of the male genitalia, the word ʻ 
<tp:taxon-name>
truncata
</tp:taxon-name>
ʼ from the English ʻtruncateʼ. The Chinese name of the species is 
Ř形kffl尾ễ
(Jie Xing Da Shi Wei Zhong).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CHINA

• 
♂

; 
Guizhou
, 
Suiyang
, 
Chachang
; 

15 Aug. 2010

; 
Le-Hong Zhao
leg.; 
HBU
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
CHINA
•

1 
♀

; same collection data as for holotype; 
HBU
•
1 ♀
; 
Guizhou
, 
Suiyang
, 
Rangshui
; 

13 Aug. 2010

; 
Le-Hong Zhao
leg.; 
HBU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS (mm). Body: 
♂
10.3, 
♀
10.0 
–
10.5; pronotum: 
♂
4.5, 
♀
4.1 
–
4.4; hind femora: 
♂
8.7, 
♀
9.8 
–
10.5; ovipositor: 6.2 
–
6.3.
</p>
      <p>BODY. Small and stout.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Fastigium verticis conical, apex rounded, with median sulcus on dorsum. Eyes oval, protruded forwards.Apical segment of maxillary palpus longer than subapical one, apical area inflated, apex truncate.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Pronotum longer, posterior margin reaching anterior margin of third abdominal tergite; lateral lobe longer than deep, with posterior margin tapering. Thoracic auditory spiracle exposed, small, oval.</p>
      <p>TEGMEN. Tegmina short, reaching posterior margin of pronotum, apices widely rounded. Hind wings absent.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. All femora unarmed on ventral surfaces. Fore coxa with spine; fore tibia with 5 spines on inner margin and 5 spines on outer margin of ventral surface, tibial tympana open and oval on both sides. Middle tibia with 4 
–
5 spines on each side of ventral surface. Hind tibia with 20 
–
23 spines on each side of dorsal margin, 2 pairs of ventral apical spurs and 1 pair of dorsal apical spurs. Thoracic auditory spiracle exposed, small, elliptic.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrocosmetura truncata
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A–C, G–I, L
. Holotype, ♂ (HBU). 
D–F, J–K
. Paratype, ♀ (HBU). – 
A–B, D–E
. Pronotum. 
A, D
. Dorsal view. 
B, E
. Lateral view. – 
C, F–L
. Apex of abdomen. 
C, F
. Lateral view. 
G, J
. Dorsal view. 
H, K
. Ventral view. 
I
. Dorso-lateral view. 
L
. Ventro-apical view.
</p>
      <p>
MALE ABDOMEN. Ninth abdominal tergite expanded backwards, postero-lateral corner elongated, fingershaped, incurved, apical area curved backwards and outwards, apex rounded. Tenth abdominal tergite extended backwards, basal half broad, apical half narrow, with a median split, divided into 2 square lateral lobes. Cercus short, apical half downcurved, covered by tenth abdominal tergite, not visible in dorsal view. Genitalia sclerotized, posterior area broad, truncate (
Fig. 5I
). Subgenital plate with basal half broad, apical half with long middle lobe and 1 pair of short lateral lobes. Styli long inserted on inner margins of subapical areas of the lateral lobes.
</p>
      <p>FEMALE. Pronotum shorter than male; tegmina exposed narrow edge. Ninth abdominal tergite expanded backwards and ventrad, latero-anterior corner elongated, finger-shaped, overlapped, apices rounded. Tenth abdominal tergite with posterior tapering, middle with a small notch. Cerci long conical, apices subacute. Ovipositor moderately curved upwards, base stout, terminal acute, dorsal margin denticulate, ventral margin smooth.</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body light yellowish brown. Dorsum of head with 3 longitudinal brown stripes. Pronotum with disc light, and 1 pair of brown spots; lateral lobe with ventral edge brown. Outer surface of hind femur with some light brown spots, knee area brown, spines on all tibiae brown. Ninth to tenth abdominal tergites brown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Guizhou
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
