<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Acosmetides platycerca Chang &amp; Wang &amp; Shi 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4923536</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D10D87ED4716D41DFC53AF5FFEA80765</uri>
         <article-title>Three new genera and five new species of the tribe Meconematini (Orthoptera: Tettigoniidae: Meconematinae) from Southwestern China</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.751.1385</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetides platycerca
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
5C6A4228-2300-44D9-BCD7-22AA72A87175
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>The new species is similar to its congeners in appearance, but differs from them in male cerci and genitalia.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new species is derived from the Latin ʻ 
platy
-ʼ, meaning ʻbroadenedʼ, and ʻ 
cerc
-ʼ, meaning ʻcercusʼ. The Chinese name of the species is 
Î尾ffi异ffl尾ễ
(Kuang Wei Ni Yi Shi Wei Zhong).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Yunnan
, 
Weixin
, 
Daxueshan
; 

19 Aug. 2013

; 
Xun Bian
and 
Guang-Lin Xie
leg.; 
HBU
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratype
CHINA
• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 

21 Aug. 2013

; 
Xun Bian
leg.; 
HBU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
CHINA
• 
2 ♂♂
(in alcohol); 
Yunnan
, 
Weixin
, 
Longtang
; 

30 Jul. 2017

; 
Ping Wang
and 
Gang Wang
leg.; 
HBU
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS (mm). Body: 
♂
8.7–9.2; pronotum: 
♂
4.5–4.6; hind femora: 
♂
8.5–8.6.
</p>
      <p>BODY. Small and stout.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Frons slightly sloping backwards. Fastigium verticis conical, apex rounded with longitudinal sulcus on dorsum. Apical segment of maxillary palpus longer than subapical one, apical area inflated, apex truncate. Eyes globular, protruded forwards.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Pronotum elongated backwards, reaching posterior margin of first abdominal tergite; posterior transverse sulcus distinct; anterior margin roughly straight, posterior margin obtusely rounded; lateral lobes longer than deep, posterior margin tapering, humeral sinus absent. Thoracic auditory spiracle exposed, small, pear-shaped.</p>
      <p>TEGMEN. Tegmina short, slightly surpassing posterior margin of pronotum. Hind wings absent.</p>
      <p>LEGS.All femora unarmed on ventral surfaces. Fore coxa with spine; fore tibia with 5 medium long spines on each side of ventral surface, tibial tympana open and ovoid on both sides. Hind femur with genicular lobes rounded; hind tibia with 24–26 spines on each side of dorsal surface, bearing 2 pairs of ventral apical spurs and 1 pair of dorsal apical spurs.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Acosmetides platycerca
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (HBU). – 
A–B
. Pronotum 
A
. Dorsal view. 
B
. Lateral view. – 
C–G
. Apex of abdomen. 
C
. Lateral view. 
D
. Dorsal view. 
E
. Ventral view. 
F
. Dorsoapical view. 
G
. Apical view. – 
H–I
. Genitalia in ventral view. 
H
. Basal area. 
I
. Apical area.
</p>
      <p>MALE ABDOMEN. Ninth abdominal tergite with lateral surface slightly broadened backwards. Tenth abdominal tergite with base half broad, apical half tapering, with a triangular notch on the middle of posterior margin, divided into two lateral lobes with apices rounded. Cercus with base thin, middle area widened, with a semiglobular concavity; apical area thin, apices incurved. Genitalia sclerotized, base area with circular lateral process on each side; middle area broadened, lamellate, near apex shrunk, subapex slightly broadened, apex roughtly truncate. Subgenital plate with basal area rectangular, apical area triangular, apex rounded. Styli long with apices rounded, inserted on lateral margins near apical one third.</p>
      <p>FEMALE. Unknown.</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body light yellowish brown, with admixed brown spots. Dorsum of head brown, frons with 1 pair of longitudinal brown stripes, scapus and pedicel of antenna brown. Disc of pronotum with longitudinal brown stripe at prozona, which bifurcates into two branches at metazona, most of which is light; lateral lobe light, with brown stripe on ventral edge. All spines on tibiae brown. Abdomen brown, tenth abdominal tergite with apex light. Cerci brown, apices blackish brown. Styli light.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Yunnan
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
