<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Hamma spinellii Durante &amp; Loudit &amp; Susini 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4746575</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D32287A5FFD5FFA06A9068B0FD631041</uri>
         <article-title>On the genus Hamma Buckton, 1905 (Hemiptera: Auchenorrhyncha) in Equatorial Africa, with descriptions of three new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.748.1345</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Hamma spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
C19025BA-2C70-4CD0-BF61-68ED3716A5E0
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2
, 
4C
, 
5C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species belonging to the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hamma
</tp:taxon-name>
with thorax eminently brown, pronotum smooth and metopidium not densely tuberculate; suprahumeral horns with a laterally pointing thorn; a posterior process with four nodes, V-shaped in lateral view between the second and fourth nodes; last node roundish in dorsal view, ending in a well-developed terminal spine. Pterostigma almost three times longer than broad.
</p>
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The general light brown colour is diagnostic, 
<tp:taxon-name>
heimi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
being black, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
having a mosaic of russet brown and black.
</p>
      <p>
Other diagnostic characters with respect to 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
are:
</p>
      <p>
– the similarity of the width and height of the basal element of the suprahumeral horns (frontal view) (
Fig. 4C
): in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
the w/h ratio is 1; in 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
the w/h ratio is 0.66;
</p>
      <p>
– caudal node of the posterior process half the width of the head in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; ⅔ the width in 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(dorsal view);
</p>
      <p>
– anchor-like third node (
Fig. 5C
) thinner than in 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(dorsal view);
</p>
      <p>
– length of the posterior process clearly exceeding abdominal length in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; not exceeding the abdominal terminalia in 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(lateral view);
</p>
      <p>
– pterostigma (
Fig. 5C
) longer in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
: l/w ratio 
3.4 in
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; 
2.4 in
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
Other diagnostic characters with respect to 
<tp:taxon-name>
heimi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
include:
</p>
      <p>
– upper margin of the head roughly square (
Fig. 4C
);
</p>
      <p>
– metopidium (
Fig. 4C
) tuberculate;
</p>
      <p>
– suprahumeral horns (
Fig. 4C
) with a robust straight thorn, not curving upwards in frontal view;
</p>
      <p>
– anchor-like third node (
Fig. 5C
) posteriorly prolonged (dorsal view); rhomboidal or roughly circular in 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
heimi
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The species is dedicated to Dr Matteo Spinelli, Milano.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
GABON
• 
♀
; 
Ogooué Ivindo
, 
Mont Sassamongo
, 
Batouala
; 

30 Nov. 2012

; 
A. Susini
leg.; 
MSNS
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. 
Holotype
total length: 
3.8 mm
; pronotal length: 
4.4 mm
; tegminal length: 
4.3 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Black with brown suffusion along the margins and at the centre, convex, punctate, with small white setae; vertex width one and a half times the height; shallow concavity between the ocelli; carina present; upper margin arcuate but roughly square with two evident corners, one directly above each ocellus; ventral margin W-shaped with the lower parts not very pronounced; ocelli slightly above the centro-ocular line. Frontoclypeus pear-shaped, lateral lobes completely fused to frontoclypeus with margins barely distinguishable; rostrum and antennae light brown.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Light brown with one triangular black patch on the metopidium on each side of the carina, punctate, almost completely naked; metopidium tuberculate in its dorsal region, twice as wide as high, median carina percurrent, unpunctate, straight, with some swelling, supraocular callosities bean-like, slightly or not at all punctate, with a small club-shaped darker formation inside them, shallow and very finely punctate; humeral angles prominent and blunt; suprahumeral horns well developed, with a tower-shaped base, tuberculate, with a robust brown and black-tipped thorn pointing laterally? Posterior process light brown, punctate, emerging posteriorly from the pronotum and continuously from the posterior margin; sinuate in lateral view, with four nodes, the first of which (proximal) almost spherical; second node small, dome-shaped in lateral view (flattened in dorsal view) with seven-eight small spines latero-dorsally; third node anchor-like in dorsal view with one (left) or two (right) small spines at the end of the lateral arms; fourth node subspherical, almost one and a half times larger than the first, with many spines and a robust terminal spine at the caudal end; dorsal and ventral carinae continuous, of the same colour. A few spines along the dorsal carina, and dorsally and ventrally along the trunk of the posterior process between the third and fourth nodes. Each spine bears a very thin light apical seta.</p>
      <p>
SCUTELLUM (
Fig. 5
). Entirely brown, punctate, with the base longer than the height, emarginate with scutellar apices acute with a few translucent setae; base with a triangular swelling except at the corners; lateral corners of the swelling with a tuft of small shiny ochraceous setae.
</p>
      <p>FOREWING. Length about two and a half times width (l/w ratio 2.56), hyaline; basally sclerotized, punctate, grey-brown in colour with three to four brown stripes distally. Pterostigma sub-triangular with very rounded corners, blackish in colour; venation grey-brown; large brown shaded trapezoidal patch extending from costa to inner margin in the median area; I-shaped patch extending from costa to anal angle with light grey-brown anterior half and dark grey-brown posterior half.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Ochreous yellow, praetarsi brown.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Tergites grey-brown with black punctation and lighter caudal borders; sternites brown, as are the borders, and covered in translucent setae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
