<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Hamma caneparii Durante &amp; Loudit &amp; Susini 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4746577</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/237135B52B7F85598EDC742C73CBF52C</uri>
         <article-title>On the genus Hamma Buckton, 1905 (Hemiptera: Auchenorrhyncha) in Equatorial Africa, with descriptions of three new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.748.1345</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Hamma caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
CC05B142-B36F-4449-B12D-DE869B08470F
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3
, 
4D
, 
5D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species belonging to the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hamma
</tp:taxon-name>
with thorax a mosaic of russet brown and black, pronotum smooth and metopidium not densely tuberculate; suprahumeral horns with a laterally pointing thorn; a posterior process with four nodes, V-shaped in lateral view between the second and fourth nodes; last node roundish in dorsal view, ending in a well-developed terminal spine. Pterostigma twice as long as broad.
</p>
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The general colour (a mosaic of russet brown and black) is diagnostic, 
<tp:taxon-name>
heimi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
being black, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
n. sp being light brown.
</p>
      <p>
Other diagnostic characters with respect to 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
are:
</p>
      <p>
– the narrow width relative to height of the basal element of the suprahumeral horns (frontal view) (
Fig. 4D
): in 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
the w/h ratio is 0.66; in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
the w/h ratio is 1;
</p>
      <p>
– caudal node of the posterior process ⅔ of the head width in 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; half the head width in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(dorsal view);
</p>
      <p>
– anchor-like third node (
Fig. 5D
) broader than in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(dorsal view);
</p>
      <p>
– length of the posterior process not exceeding the abdominal terminalia in 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; clearly exceeding abdominal length in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(lateral view);
</p>
      <p>
– pterostigma (
Fig. 5D
) larger in 
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
: l/w ratio 
2.4 in
<tp:taxon-name>
caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; 
3.4 in
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
Other diagnostic characters with respect to 
<tp:taxon-name>
heimi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
are:
</p>
      <p>
– upper margin of the head (
Fig. 4D
) roughly square;
</p>
      <p>
– metopidium (
Fig. 4D
) tuberculate;
</p>
      <p>
– suprahumeral horns (
Fig. 4D
) with a robust straight thorn, not curving upwards in frontal view;
</p>
      <p>
– anchor-like third node posteriorly prolonged; rhomboidal or roughly circular in 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigrum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
heimi
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is dedicated to our friend Claudio Canepari, Milano, a specialist in 
<tp:taxon-name>Coccinellidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
GABON
• 
♀
; 
Ogooué Lolo
, 
Inzambò
(Iboundji); 
0.1°6′21.7″ S
, 
0.11°51′17.8″ E
; 

427 m
a.s.l.

; 

24 Nov. 2012

; 
A. Susini
leg.; 
MSNS
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. 
Holotype
total length: 
4.6 mm
; pronotal length: 
4.6 mm
; tegminal length: 
4.1 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Entirely black, convex, punctate; vertex almost twice as wide as high; carina not distinguishable; shallow concavity medially above the ocelli; upper margin sinuate; ventral margin W-shaped with lower parts not very pronounced; ocelli slightly above the centro-ocular line. Frontoclypeus russet and pear-</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hamma caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀, Gabon, Ogoouè Lolo, Inzambò (Iboundji), m 427, 0.1°6′21.7″ S, 0.11°51′17.8″ E, 24 Nov. 2012, A. Susini leg. (MSNS).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
Morphology. Left suprahumeral horn and left supraocular callosity, frontal view. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hamma heimi
Boulard, 1968
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hamma nigrum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hamma spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hamma caneparii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Figures are not to scale.
</p>
      <p>shaped, lateral lobes completely fused to frontoclypeus with margins not distinguishable; rostrum and antennae ochraceous.</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM. Mosaic of russet brown patches with one triangular black area at the base of the metopidium and black areas behind the suprahumeral horns; punctate, naked; ochraceous tuberculate areas at the dorsal border of the metopidium; metopidium one and a half times wider than high, median carina percurrent and unpunctate, straight; elongated supraocular callosities, slightly arcuate, not punctate; humeral angles prominent and blunt; suprahumeral horns well developed, with a tower-shaped base (shorter than in 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinellii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
), tuberculate, with a robust brown, black-tipped thorn pointing outwards. Posterior process patchy, black and russet in colour, punctate, emerging posteriorly from the pronotum and continuously from the posterior margin; sinuate in lateral view, with four nodes, the first of which (proximal) almost spherical, elongated posteriorly in dorsal view; second node small, dome-shaped in lateral view (flattened in dorsal view) with four small dorsal spines; third node anchor-like in dorsal view with two (left) or one (right) small spines at the end of the lateral arms; fourth node subspherical, slightly larger than the first, with many spines and a strong terminal spine at the caudal end; dorsal and ventral carinae continuous, of the same colour. A few spines along the dorsal carina and dorsally and ventrally along the trunk of the posterior process between the third and fourth nodes, some of which bearing a very thin light apical seta.
</p>
      <p>
SCUTELLUM (
Fig. 5
). Same colour as the pronotum, punctate, with the base longer than the height, emarginate with scutellar apices light, acute with a few translucent setae; base with a triangular swelling except at the corners; lateral corners of the swelling with a tuft of small brilliant whitish setae.
</p>
      <p>FOREWING. About two and a half times as long as wide (l/w ratio 2.57), hyaline; basally sclerotized, punctate, amber and brown in colour. Pterostigma trapezoidal with rounded corners, dark brown in colour; venation amber except for the median, cubital and anal veins in the median area, which are brown; large brown shaded trapezoidal patch extending from costa to inner margin in the median area; S-shaped patch extending from costa to anal angle with light grey-brown anterior half and brown posterior half. Presence in the right forewing of a small supplementary discoidal cell between the second apical cell and the first discoidal cell.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Ochreous yellow, praetarsi brown.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Tergites black and brown with punctation and lighter caudal borders; sternites brown with borders of the same colour covered by translucent setae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
