<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Cradoscrupocellaria severoi Reverter-Gil &amp; Souto 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5123028</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/DF223750FFE7CC3DFDCEFAD6156B0BA5</uri>
         <article-title>Two new species of cheilostomate Bryozoa from Iberian waters</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.760.1437</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
AF6D2F75-42FE-4AD5-A1A2-A8D587ECA7F7
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–2
; 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Scrupocellaria reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
– 


Templado 
et al.
2002: 203


.

</p>
      <p>

? 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scrupocellaria macrorhyncha
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Zabala 1986: 318

, fig. 88, pl. 3 figs a–d.

</p>
      <p>

? 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scrupocellaria reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Zabala &amp; Maluquer 1988: 97

, figs 159–160, pl. 5 figs a–b.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria
</tp:taxon-name>
with erect, branched colonies, with internodes comprising 5–10 alternating autozooids. Chitinous joints passing across proximal gymnocyst of outer and inner zooids. Large scutum, stout and flat, highly branched, completely covering the opesia. Two inner spines and 3 outer spines. Small distolateral avicularium frequent. Large monomorphic frontal avicularium in outer zooids oriented upwards on the branch. Ovicells globular, wider than long, perforated by 10–18 rounded pores; ovicelled zooids with 2 inner and 2 outer spines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is dedicated to Severo Ochoa de Albornoz (1905–1993), Spanish physician and biochemist, winner of the 1959 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine for the discovery of the mechanisms in the biological synthesis of nucleic acids.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
MEDITERRANEAN SPAIN
• colony; 
Columbretes Islands
; 
39º87.967´N
, 
0º66.817´E
; stn 277B15; depth 

3–40 m

; 1996; Fauna Ibérica IV exped.; 
MNCN 25.03/3059
(
Figs 1A, D
, 
2A, D
).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
MEDITERRANEAN SPAIN
• 
1 colony
; 
Columbretes Islands
; 
39º85.450´N
, 
0º67.617´E
; stn 285B1; depth 

42 m

; 1996; Fauna Ibérica IV exped.; 
MNCN 25.03/2999
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
several fragments
; 
Columbretes Islands
; 
39º87967´N
, 
0º66817´E
; stn 277B14; depth 

7.5 m

; 1996; Fauna Ibérica IV exped.; 
MNCN 25.03/3057
, 
25.03/4234
(
Figs 1C
, 
2C
)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
several fragments
; 
Columbretes Islands
; 
39º89.800´N
, 
0º68.883´E
; stn 275B5; depth 

35 m

; 1996; Fauna Ibérica IV exped.; 
MNCN 25.03/3200
(
Figs 1B
, 
2B
).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. View of the colony (MNCN 25.03/3059: holotype). 
B
. View of the colony (MNCN 25.03/3200: paratype). 
C
. Branching pattern (MNCN 25.03/4234: paratype). 
D
. Detail of a branch with large frontal avicularia, ovicells and scuta (MNCN 25.03/3059: holotype).
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
Paralectotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scrupocellaria macrorhyncha
Gautier, 1962
</tp:taxon-name>
(here designated, see explanation below):
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MEDITERRANEAN FRANCE
• 
several fragments
; 
Marseille
, 
SW Cap Caveaux
; stn 258; 

1 Dec. 1952

; 
Gautier
leg.; 
MNHN-IB-2008-11319
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
several fragments
; same collection data as for preceding; 
MNHN- IB-2008-11321
(
Fig. 3
).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Colony erect, up to 
1 cm
in height, branched, with internodes comprising 5–10 alternating autozooids. Internodes slender, almost straight, angled at axis, with acute bifurcating pattern; chitinous joints
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. Detail of branches with large frontal avicularia, ovicells, scuta and a lateral avicularium (centre left) (MNCN 25.03/3059: holotype). 
B
. Detail of a branch with large frontal avicularia, ovicells and a lateral avicularium (bottom left) (MNCN 25.03/3200: paratype). 
C
. Basal view of the branching pattern (MNCN 25.03/4234: paratype). 
D
. Single axial vibraculum (MNCN 25.03/3059: holotype).
</p>
      <p>
passing across proximal gymnocyst of outer (C and D) and inner zooids (F and G) at bifurcation. Autozooids cylindrical with straight sides. Oval opesia occupying two thirds of zooidal length; cryptocyst reduced to narrow rim around opesia. Large scutum inserted at midline of the inner edge of opesia, stout but relatively flat, its tips highly branched, fully developed and completely covering entire opesia. Distal spines short, unbranched; 2 inner and 3 outer spines, with outer distal spines closer to scutum; axial zooid with 5 spines. Small distolateral avicularium frequent and easily visible in frontal view. Monomorphic frontal avicularium often present in outer zooids of each internode; large but variable in size, with elongate rostrum 
0.22–0.28 mm
long, with fringed edges, proximally upright, with strongly hooked tip; mandible long, hooked distally. Vibracular chamber laterally placed on the basal surface of each zooid, visible in frontal view; chamber of vibraculum almost trapezoidal, with a proximal rhizoidal foramen; setal groove transverse to internode axis, straight, with smooth seta longer than one autozooid. Single axial vibraculum without rhizoidal foramen. Rhizoids tubular and smooth. Ovicells globular, wider than long, with an even, almost straight proximal rim; ectooecium perforated by 10–18 rounded pores; ovicelled zooids with 2 inner and 2 outer spines. Ancestrula unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria
</tp:taxon-name>
has been recently described by 

Vieira 
et al.
(2013)

. Nine already existing species were transferred to this genus, and the same authors described 18 new species.Among all these species, only 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gautieri
Vieira, Spencer Jones &amp; Winston, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. macrorhyncha
(
Gautier, 1962
)
</tp:taxon-name>
show similarities with 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, mainly regarding the very stout scutum with truncate tips and the large frontal avicularia. The description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gautieri
</tp:taxon-name>
is based on a single sample collected by 
Gautier (1962)
in 
Algeria
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria macrorhyncha
</tp:taxon-name>
was redescribed by 

Vieira 
et al.
(2013)

based on the only original sample of Gautier deposited at NHMUK, designated as 
lectotype
, and other Mediterranean samples by other authors. However, the MNHN collection includes two other original samples of Gautier from the same station as the 
lectotype
that seem to have been overlooked in the redescription of the species, perhaps because in the museum’s catalogue and in the external labels of the samples both are simply marked as “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scrupocellaria reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
”: sample MNHN-IB-2008-11319 contains a handwritten label by Gautier stating “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scrupocellaria reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
group? Dry specimen”; being written in English, it is highly probable that this sample together with the 
lectotype
were sent by Gautier to A. Hastings at the NHMUK, and later returned. Sample MNHN-IB-2008-11321 (
Fig. 3
) includes a label handwritten by Gautier indicating “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scrupocellaria reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
? grand avic.”. Since both samples actually correspond to 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. macrorhyncha
</tp:taxon-name>
and were collected by Gautier at the type locality of the species and studied by him, they should be considered as part of the type series and consequently considered as 
paralectotypes
of the species according to Arts 73.2.2 and 74.1.3 of the ICZN Code (
ICZN 1999
).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. macrorhyncha
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gautieri
</tp:taxon-name>
by several characters: the frontal avicularium is monomorphic in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
because the small columnar avicularium present in the other species is absent; this frontal avicularium is oriented upwards on the branch, not proximally (
Figs 2A–B
, 
3C
). The lateral avicularium is more frequent and more visible (
Fig. 2A–B
). In the bifurcations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, the chitinous joints pass through the gymnocyst of the external zooids (C and D) instead of through their opesiae (
Figs 1C
, 
3A
). The ovicell is wider than long in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, usually uniformly perforated by small pseudopores (
Figs 1D
, 
2A–B
), whilst in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. macrorhyncha
</tp:taxon-name>
the ovicell is more spherical and usually exhibits an imperforate flat frontal area (
Fig. 3B
) (in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gautieri
</tp:taxon-name>
the ovicell is unknown). The autozooids of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
are clearly smaller than those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. macrorhyncha
</tp:taxon-name>
, but similar in size to those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gautieri
</tp:taxon-name>
. Finally, the internodes are short in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, formed by 5–10 autozooids (
Fig. 1A–B
), as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. gautieri
</tp:taxon-name>
, but the scutum is flatter and not swollen as in that latter species.
</p>
      <p>
Table 1.
Measurements (in mm) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(holotype + paratypes). Abbreviations: SD = standard deviation, N = number of measurements.
</p>
      <p>
Mean
SD
Minimum
Maximum
N
Autozooid length
0.454
0.0480
0.370
0.565
29
Autozooid width
0.191
0.0154
0.161
0.232
29
Sutum length
0.289
0.0176
0.258
0.324
29
Scutum width
0.164
0.0206
0.121
0.207
29
Frontal avic. length
0.259
0.0283
0.218
0.281
4
Frontal avic. width
0.087
0.0037
0.082
0.093
6
Lateral avic. length
0.065
0.0080
0.055
0.073
6
Ovicell length
0.163
0.0160
0.134
0.186
18
Ovicell width
0.213
0.0187
0.170
0.245
18
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria macrorhyncha
(
Gautier, 1962
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNHN-IB-2008-11321: paralectotype), SW Cap Caveaux (Marseille, France), Gautier Coll. 
A
. Frontal view of the branching pattern. 
B
. Detail showing the scuta, ovicells, large frontal avicularia and a small frontal avicularium (bottom right). 
C
. Lateral view showing the large frontal avicularia and basal vibracula. 
D
. Basal view of the branching pattern.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Cradoscrupocellaria severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is known with certainty only from its 
type
localities at the Columbretes Islands (Mediterranean Spain) between 3 and 
42 m
depth. 
Zabala (1986)
reported 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scrupocellaria macrorhyncha
Gautier, 1962
</tp:taxon-name>
from several Catalonian localities, but these records were later reassigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. reptans
(
Linnaeus, 1758
)
</tp:taxon-name>
by 
Zabala &amp; Maluquer (1988)
. 

Vieira 
et al.
(2013)

, however, stated that these specimens are distinct from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. macrorhyncha
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
, as well as from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. ellisi
(
Vieira &amp; Spencer Jones, 2012
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, and that they may belong to a new undescribed species. Figures by 
Zabala (1986)
and 
Zabala &amp; Maluquer (1988)
are quite similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but the description given (actually an almost literal translation of the original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. macrorhyncha
</tp:taxon-name>
by Gautier) show several differences from the present description of the new species. A revision of the original material and collection of new material will be necessary to clarify which species was reported from 
Catalonia
, as well as to determine the possible presence of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. severoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
at other Iberian localities.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
