<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Setosella margaritae Reverter-Gil &amp; Souto 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5123030</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AC31C8F69EA265FE34DDC55A9D6E8F83</uri>
         <article-title>Two new species of cheilostomate Bryozoa from Iberian waters</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.760.1437</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Setosella margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E9976DD1-53EC-4547-A766-37B1DEE466DF
</p>
      <p>
Figs 4–5
, 
Table 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
– 


Reverter-Gil 
et al.
1992: 102


, fig. 2; 2016: 28, fig. 4d. — 


Barcia Leal 
et al.
1993: 251


. — 

Reverter-Gil 1995: 115

, fig. 7. — 

Hayward &amp; Ryland 1998: 298

, fig. 103. — 

Reverter-Gil &amp; Fernández-Pulpeiro 2001: 78

(shallow waters only). — 

De Blauwe 2006: 130

, fig. 9; 2009: 252, figs 257–258.

</p>
      <p>

Non 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Jullien 1882: 28

, pl. 17 fig. 66. — 

Calvet 1907: 394

. — 

d’Hondt 1973: 367

; 

1974: 38

. — 

Hayward 1979: 60

. — 

Reverter-Gil &amp; Fernández-Pulpeiro 2001: 78

(deep waters only). — 


Templado 
et al.
2006: 208


. — 


Reverter-Gil 
et al.
2014: 16


. — 


Souto 
et al.
2016: 416


, figs 33, 38. — 


Rosso 
et al.
2020: 403


, figs 1–2 [= 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
(
Busk, 1860
)
</tp:taxon-name>
].

</p>
      <p>

Non 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
– 


Templado 
et al.
2002: 203


. (= 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella cyclopensis
Rosso, Di Martino &amp; Gerovasileiou, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Setosella
</tp:taxon-name>
with small, encrusting colonies. Autozooids small, oval, with opesia D-shaped or irregularly rounded, and two oval to tear-shaped opesiules, positioned close to opesia and directly beside lateral walls of zooid. Small interzooidal vibracula oval, positioned distolateral to each autozooid, always on the right side and often without exceeding distal edge of autozooid, especially in ovicelled ones. Ectooecium with transversely oval membranous window and granular endooecial surface underneath, with a small, central pore. Ancestrula oval, with cryptocyst occupying slightly less than half of the frontal area; opesia semielliptical, with straight or slightly concave proximal border.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is dedicated to Margarita Salas Falgueras (1938–2019), Spanish scientist, medical researcher, and author in the fields of biochemistry and molecular genetics. She was a disciple of S. Ochoa (see above).</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype

ATLANTIC SPAIN • colony on shell fragment; 
Galicia
, 
Ría of Ferrol
; 
43º45.889´N
, 
08º293.33´W
; depth 

20 m

; 

13 Sep. 1989

; 
Reverter-Gil
leg.; 
MHNUSC 10120
; (

Fig. 4 
A
– 
B

).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes

ATLANTIC 
SPAIN
• several small juvenile colonies on shell fragment; same collection data as for 
holotype
; 
MHNUSC 10121
(

Fig. 4 
C

)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
colony on shell fragment; same collection data as for 
holotype
; 
MHNUSC 10122
(

Fig. 5 
C
– 
D

)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
small eroded colony on shell fragment; 
Galicia
, 
Ría of Ferrol
; 
43º45.500´N
, 
08º30.889´W
; depth 

12 m

; 

13 Sep. 1989

; 
Reverter-Gil
leg.; 
MHNUSC 10123
(

Figs 4 
D

, 

5 
B

)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. Holotype (MHNUSC 10120). 
B
. Same, optical photograph, together with a small, dead colony of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Callopora discreta
(
Hincks, 1862
)
</tp:taxon-name>
encrusting the inner part of a barnacle plate. 
C
. Ancestrula with reversed astogenetic pattern (note the short vibraculum positioned on the right side) (MHNUSC 10121: paratype). 
D
. Optical photograph of a damaged colony on a shell fragment (MHNUSC 10123: paratype).
</p>
      <p>
Table 2.
Measurements (in mm) of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(holotype + paratypes). SD = standard deviation, N = number of measurements.
</p>
      <p>
Mean
SD
Minimum
Maximum
N
Autozooid length
0.250
0.0604
0.174
0.350
9
Autozooid width
0.170
0.0436
0.120
0.227
9
Opesia length
0.055
0.0137
0.038
0.070
9
Opesia width
0.075
0.0213
0.050
0.096
9
Vibraculum length
0.091
0.0245
0.059
0.135
13
Vibraculum width
0.087
0.0231
0.055
0.131
13
Ooecium length
0.049
0.0164
0.038
0.073
4
Ooecium width
0.077
0.0200
0.062
0.105
4
Ancestrula length
0.239
0.0295
0.220
0.273
3
Ancestrula width
0.159
0.0366
0.124
0.197
3
Ancestr. opesia length
0.106
0.0061
0.099
0.110
3
Ancestr. opesia width
0.099
0.0068
0.091
0.104
3
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
ATLANTIC SPAIN
• 
colony on maërl
; 
Galicia
, 
Ría of Vigo
; 
42º23.889´N
, 
08º79.369´W
; depth 

16 m

; 

16 Sep. 1986

; 
Fernández-Pulpeiro
leg.; 
MHNUSC-Bry 93a
(together with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
) (
Fig. 5A
)
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
colony on shell fragment
; 
Galicia
, 
Ría of Vigo
; 
42º23.139´N
, 
08º76.389´W
; depth 

9 m

; 

16 Sep. 1986

; 
Fernández-Pulpeiro
leg.; 
MHNUSC-Bry 93b
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
colony on shell fragment
; 
Galicia
, 
Ría of Vigo
; 
42º22.944´N
, 
08º88.056´W
; depth 

23 m

; 

2 Aug. 1985

; 
Fernández-Pulpeiro
leg.; 
MHNUSC-Bry 93c
(together with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trypostega venusta
(
Norman, 1864
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microporella ciliata
(
Pallas, 1766
))
</tp:taxon-name>
         </tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
colony on shell fragment
; 
Galicia
, 
Ría of Ferrol
; 
43º46.389´N
, 
08º26.333´W
; depth 

8 m

; 

Jun. 2004

; 
Reverter- Gil
leg.; 
MHNUSC-Bry 656
(together with 12 spp. more).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
NORTH SEA • 
UK
, 
Shetland
; 
Busk
leg.; 
NHMUK 1899.7
.1.1487 (see also 

Souto 
et al.
2016

).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paralectotypes
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
NORTH SEA • several colonies; 
UK
, 

Shetland

; 
Busk
leg.; 
NHMUK 1911.10
.1.760 (see also 

Souto 
et al.
2016

)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>

Other material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MEDITERRANEAN SPAIN
• 
Alboran Island
; 
35º83.550´N
, 
03º23.667´W
; stn 313A; depth 

118 m

; 1996; Fauna Ibérica IV exped.; 
MNCN 25.03/3169
(
Fig. 6
).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>

Material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella cyclopensis
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MEDITERRANEAN SPAIN
• 
Columbretes Islands
; 
39º87.217´N
, 
0º63.400´E
; stn 283A; depth 

80– 85 m

; 1996; Fauna Ibérica IV exped.; 
MNCN 25.03/3149
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Colony encrusting, unilaminar, forming small discoidal patches of alternating autozooids and vibracula. Autozooids irregularly oval, with well-developed smooth gymnocyst proximally that narrows and steepens distally, lateral walls slightly raised, framing an evenly granular cryptocyst that is flat and depressed proximally, gently rising distally to the opesiules to form the proximal border of the opesia. Opesia D-shaped or irregularly rounded, wider than long, distal margin with some blunt, irregularly spaced denticles. Two oval to tear-shaped opesiules (ca 20 μm long by 10 μm-wide), located in distal depressed area of the cryptocyst, positioned close to the opesia (mean 36 μm) and directly beside the lateral walls of zooid, their inner edges sometimes with several sharp denticles; the size of both opesiules unequal, the left one slightly larger. Small interzooidal vibracula oval, positioned distolateral to each autozooid, always on the right side and often without exceeding the distal edge of the autozooid, especially in ovicelled ones. Wide oval opesia, sometimes slightly narrower in the middle; seta long and slender, curved, up to twice length of the autozooid. Communication of zooids via small uniporous septula. Some autozooids and vibracula show evidence of breakage and regeneration associated with the intramural budding (
Fig. 5C–D
). Ovicells terminal, with a brood cavity immersed within the distal part of the maternal zooid. Kenozooidal ooecium roughly level with the colony surface, forming shallow hood covering distal end of the maternal zooid from which it is budded. Proximal ooecial margin forming the distal part of the zooidal orifice; ectooecium with transversely oval membranous window and granular endooecial surface underneath, with a small, central pore. Ovicellate zooids dimorphic, slightly wider distally, with orifices distinctly broader and campanulate in outline. Distal budding of autozooids and vibracula in ooecium-producing zooid retained. Ancestrula oval, with cryptocyst relatively smooth, occupying slightly less than half of the frontal area; opesia semi elliptical, with straight or slightly concave proximal border. Astogenesis beginning with one distal and two lateral autozooids; later zooids more irregularly arranged. The ancestrula also buds the two typical caudate vibracula of the genus: one short caudate, budded mid-laterally on the left side, and the other long caudate, budded distally, and sometimes curved to the right. On one occasion, however, this pattern was reversed, with the short vibraculum budded on the right side (
Fig. 4C
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. A colony of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(left) together with the colony of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(right) (see text and 

Reverter-Gil 
et al.
2012

as 
<tp:taxon-name>
S.
aff. 
cavernicola
</tp:taxon-name>
) (MHNUSC-Bry 93a). 
B
. Damaged autozooids (one ovicelled, another with a developing ooecium) with three vibracula with setae (MHNUSC 10123: paratype). 
C
. A colony with a damaged periancestrular area; note the intramural budding in several zooids (MHNUSC 10122: paratype). 
D
. Same, detail showing two ovicelled zooids and a vibraculum with intramural budding.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella
</tp:taxon-name>
and all the species ascribed to it are at present well described under current standards. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
, the 
type
species of the genus, was redescribed by 

Souto 
et al.
(2016)

. 

Rosso 
et al.
(2020)

redefined the genus itself as well as two known species (
<tp:taxon-name>
S. cavernicola
Harmelin, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. spiralis
Silén, 1942
</tp:taxon-name>
) and three new species (
<tp:taxon-name>
S. alfioi
Rosso, Di Martino &amp; Gerovasileiou, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. cyclopensis
Rosso, Di Martino &amp; Gerovasileiou, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. rossanae
Rosso, Di Martino &amp; Gerovasileiou, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
). Another species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. folini
Jullien, 1882
</tp:taxon-name>
, was redescribed by 

Souto 
et al.
(2011)

. Finally, an undescribed species was reported from 
Galicia
(NW Iberian Peninsula) as 
<tp:taxon-name>
S.
aff. 
cavernicola
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

Reverter-Gil 
et al.
2012

; 

Rosso 
et al.
2020

).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Setosella margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
(see redescription by 

Souto 
et al.
2016

) as well as from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. cyclopensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, quite a similar species, by several characters: the vibracula of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
are much smaller, about half the size, and characteristically shifted laterally on the right side, often without exceeding the distal end of the autozooid (especially in ovicelled zooids), instead being distal or only slightly distolateral. The autozooids are oval and clearly smaller in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
The opesiules are shorter, oval to tear-shaped, instead slit-like or elongated; moreover, the opesiules are located closer to the opesia and directly beside the lateral walls of the zooid, instead of away from the opesia and the lateral walls. The window of the ectooecium in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is transversally oval, whilst in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. cyclopensis
</tp:taxon-name>
it is roughly circular, much smaller in the former species, much larger in the latter. Finally, the colonies of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
are very small, encrusting mainly shell fragments in shallow waters, as opposed to larger colonies encrusting mainly coarse sand, granules and fine pebbles in deeper waters in the other species.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
A colony of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
(
Busk, 1860
)
</tp:taxon-name>
collected at Alboran Island (Mediterranean Spain) (MNCN 25.03/3169). 
A
. General view of the colony. 
B
. The periancestrular area; note that the ancestrula was covered by a cryptocystal plate.
</p>
      <p>
At the same time, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella folini
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. alfioi
</tp:taxon-name>
differ from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
most obviously by their uniserial, free-living colonies. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella cavernicola
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. rossanae
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(as 
<tp:taxon-name>
S.
aff. 
cavernicola
</tp:taxon-name>
in 

Reverter-Gil 
et al.
2012

) differ by their circular opesiules, four or even up to five in the latter two species. Finally, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. spiralis
</tp:taxon-name>
differs by the much larger autozooids and vibracula, with opesiules located further away from the opesia, and by colonies with spirally arranged zooids typically in a single rightcoiled row.
</p>
      <p>
In the past, we have considered our own material to be similar to typical 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
. That is why we have cited deep material as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

Reverter-Gil 
et al.
2012

). But after the redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
by 

Souto 
et al.
(2016)

the situation has turned out to be just the opposite. Our previous records of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
from shallow waters of Galicia (NW Iberian Peninsula) are here assigned to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
: from the Ría of Ferrol at 
8–20 m
depth, and from the Ría of Vigo at 
9–23 m
depth, both on shell fragments (
Reverter-Gil &amp; Fernández-Pulpeiro 2001
and present data). These colonies are very small, formed by very few autozooids, but are fertile because ovicells are formed even in the first or second generations of periancestrular zooids (
Figs 4A, C
, 
5A
). Moreover, the material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
reported and figured by 
De Blauwe (2006
, 
2009
), collected on shells at 
10–25 m
depth in 
Belgium
(North Sea), also belongs to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
These colonies are larger than the Galician ones, but present the same characters, also including ovicells in the first or second generations of zooids (see 
De Blauwe 2009
: figs 257–258; accessible also through WoRMS 2020: http://www.marinespecies.org/photogallery.php?album=709&amp;pic=25695#photogallery and http://www.marinespecies.org/photogallery.php?album=709&amp;pic=25696#photogallery). Moreover, the description and figures of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Hayward &amp; Ryland (1998)
fit the present description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. margaritae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, at least the shallow-water material referred to there. Accordingly, the species is quite possibly distributed in shallow waters along the Atlantic coast of Europe, from the North Sea to at least the NW of the Iberian Peninsula. Its occurrence in other areas should be confirmed by reviewing previous citations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
. In a previous paper (

Reverter-Gil 
et al.
2012

), we already suggested that previous records of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
might correspond to several different species.
</p>
      <p>
Conversely, previous records of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
in Atlantic Iberian deep waters (Cachucho [= Le Danois Bank], Galicia, 
Portugal
and Gulf of Cadiz) actually belong to this species (see 
Jullien 1882
; 
Calvet 1907
; 
d’Hondt 1973
, 
1974
; 
Hayward 1979
; 
Harmelin &amp; d’Hondt 1992
; 
Reverter-Gil &amp; Fernández-Pulpeiro 2001
only deep waters; 

Reverter-Gil 
et al.
2014

; 

Souto 
et al.
2016

), as is also the case for records published as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
by 

Reverter-Gil 
et al.
(2012)

(see also 

Souto 
et al.
2016

; 

Rosso 
et al.
2020

).
</p>
      <p>
There are a few more previous records of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
in Iberian waters: the record from Alboran Island, at 
118 m
depth, made by 

Templado 
et al.
(2006)

actually corresponds to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
(see material examined and 
Fig. 6
) as well as the recent records published by 

Ramalho 
et al.
(2020)

in a nearby area between 95 and 
440 m
depth. However, the record from Columbretes Islands (Mediterranean Spain), at 
80 m
depth, made by 

Templado 
et al.
(2002)

actually belongs to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. cyclopensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(see material examined; unfortunately, this sample is currently unavailable for photography). Thus, this is the first Iberian record of this Mediterranean species. We have no further information about the records published by 

Zabala 
et al.
(1993)

from the Blanes Canyon at 
180–350 m
depth and by 

Madurell 
et al.
(2013)

from Cap de Creus at 
104–225 m
depth (
Catalonia
), but based on the given depths these records may belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
or to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. cyclopensis
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Following 

Souto 
et al.
(2016)

and 

Rosso 
et al.
(2020)

, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setosella vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
is distributed in the Northeast Atlantic and the Mediterranean, although several Atlantic and Mediterranean occurrences still need to be checked. As already stated by 

Rosso 
et al.
(2020)

it is likely that 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. vulnerata
</tp:taxon-name>
is actually restricted to deep habitats from the shelf break and the continental slope.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
