<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Merodon zebra Vujic &amp; Radenkovic 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5013408</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3BF9BE37E51CB336F03E2849B95EE0EF</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the Merodon bombiformis group (Diptera: Syrphidae) - rare and endemic African hoverflies</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1401</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Merodon zebra
Vujić &amp; Radenković
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
9B6ABB0D-7FF4-4217-9C23-FBD06F8D80F1
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1
, 
3D
, 
4D
, 
5D
, 
6D
, 
7A–C
, 
9D
, 
10D
, 
11D
, 
12D
, 
14C
, 
15C
, 
16C
, 
22D–F
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Large (
10–12 mm
), dark, striped species, with golden-yellow pile on the tip of abdomen (
Fig. 5C
). Scutum with conspicuous pollinose vittae (
Fig. 10D
); metafemur with medium sized apical dens on triangular lamina (
Figs 6D
, 
16D
); terga 3 and 4 with broad medial pollinose fasciae (
Fig. 5D
); male genitalia with S-shaped posterior lobe of surstyle, gradually narrowing toward tip (
Fig. 7A
: pl); anterior margin of surstyle rounded in lateral view (
Fig. 7A
: ams). Similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Merodon vittatus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. multifasciatus
</tp:taxon-name>
from which differs in less distinct dens on apicoventral triangular lamina of metafemur; shorter eye contiguity, about 10 ommatidia long, while in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. vittatus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is about 15, and in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. multifasciatus
</tp:taxon-name>
about 15–20; and shape of male genitalia (rounded anterior margin of surstyle (
Fig. 7A
: ams), in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. vittatus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
angular in lateral view (
Fig. 7D
: ams); narrow, S-shaped posterior lobe of surstyle, gradually narrowing toward tip (
Fig. 7A
: pl), in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. multifasciatus
</tp:taxon-name>
broad, slightly curved, with almost parallel and rounded apex (
Fig. 13D
: pl).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 18.
Male genitalia, aedeagus, lateral view. 
A.
<tp:taxon-name>
Merodon lotus
Vujić &amp; Radenković
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype (FSUNS; FSUNS ID ZA6_060). 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. multifasciatus
Curran, 1939
</tp:taxon-name>
(NBCN LML-05-3; FSUNS ID 03909). 
C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. vittatus
Vujić &amp; Likov
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype (NBCN; FSUNS ID 04085). 
D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. nasicus
Bezzi, 1915
</tp:taxon-name>
(TAUI; FSUNS ID 04972). Abbreviation: s = lateral sclerite of aedeagus. Scale bar = 0.25 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet ‘zebra’ was given as a reference to the African equine, zebra with a distinctive black and white striped coat, pattern like in this 
<tp:taxon-name>
Merodon
species.
</tp:taxon-name>
It is to be treated as a noun in apposition. The name ‘zebra’ was proposed by W. Hurkmans in an unpublished manuscript, but unfortunately the designated 
holotype
belongs to 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. multifasciatus
</tp:taxon-name>
. We decided to keep this descriptive name for this African endemic.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
1 ♂
; 
Lubumbashi
(former Elisabethville); 
11.589° S
, 
27.427° E
; 

4 Feb. 1923

; 
Dr M. Bequaert
leg.; 
FSUNS ID 25089
; 
RMCA
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; 
Lualaba River
; 
7.809° S
, 
26.919° E
; 

562 m
a.s.l.

; 

2500–4000 ft

; 

17 May 1907

; 
S.A. Neave
leg.; 
FSUNS ID 03314
, 
03911
; 
BMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 

30 May 1907

; 
FSUNS ID 03912
; 
NBCN AM-05-073
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
FSUNS ID 03316
, 
03910
; 
BMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 

31 May 1907

; 
FSUNS ID 03315
; 
BMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Kasongo
; 
4.45° S
, 
26.666° E
, 

661 m

a.s.l; 

7 Nov. 1912

; 
Dr M. Bequaert
leg.; 
FSUNS ID 25090
; 
RMCA
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 

16 Jan. 1921

; 
FSUNS ID 25091
; 
RMCA
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Lubumbashi
(former 
Elisabethville
), 
R. Kimilol
; 
11.589° S
, 
27.427° E
; 

Dec. 1928

; 
Dr M. Bequaert
leg.; 
FSUNS ID 05174
; 
NBCN
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
TANZANIA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Tanganyika Territory
(former), 
Ugano
, 
Matengo Highland
WSW of Songea
; 
10.949° S
, 
34.934° E
; 

1500–1700 m
a.s.l.

; 

11–20 Jan. 1936

; 
H. Zerny
leg.; 
FSUNS ID 05725
; 
NHMW
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Length: large species, body 
10–12 mm
, wing 
7–8 mm
(n = 4).
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 4D
, 
9D
, 
11D
, 
12D
). Antenna (
Fig. 4D
) reddish-brown; pedicel elongated, approximately as long as basoflagellomere (relation scape:pedicel: basoflagellomere =1.0: 2.5: 2.5); basoflagellomere concave dorsally, with acute apex; arista light brown to dark brown, thickened basally, 1.6 times as long as basoflagellomere. Face from black to dark brown, covered with gray pollinosity and whitish pile, except on bare medial vitta that occupies ¼ width of face. Oral margin protruded (
Fig. 9D
). Frons from black to reddish, inflated, covered with gray pollinosity and whitish pile. Vertical triangle isosceles (
Fig. 12D
), usually dark brown, predominantly covered with a long, yellow pile. Ocellar triangle equilateral. Eye pile dense, gray, slightly longer than scape. Eye contiguity about 10 ommatidia long. Occiput reddish, pollinose, covered with yellow pile.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Figs 6D
, 
10D
). Mesonotum black, except postpronotum and posterior margin of scutellum brown-reddish, covered with reddish-yellow pile; scutum with five pollinose longitudinal vittae (as on 
Fig. 10D
). Pleuron black to dark brown, covered with gray pollinosity and the following parts with whitish to yellow pile: anterior part of proepimeron, posterior part of anterior anepisternum, most of the posterior anepisternum except anterior end, antero-ventral and postero-dorsal part of katepisternum, anepimeron and metasternum. Wing hyaline, with dense microtrichia and yellow to brown veins. Calypter pale yellow. Halter with yellow pedicel and capitulum. All three femora dark brown to black; tibiae mostly reddish, medially black to dark brown; tarsi reddish, except darker apical two tarsomeres (
Fig. 6D
). Metatrochanter without calcar. Metafemur moderately thickened, with less developed apicoventral triangular lamina, more or less dentate, the apical dens is distinct (
Fig. 6D
). Pile on legs predominantly whitish to yellow.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Fig. 5D
). Black to dark brown. Tergum 1 black, usually with pollinosity, covered with short whitish to yellow pile; tergum 2 with pollinose posterior margin and narrow medial fascia, in some specimens interrupted in the middle, with whitish pile except posterior half between pollinose fasciae covered with short black pilosity; terga 3 and 4 with pollinose posterior margin and broad medial fasciae; anterior half of tergum 3 covered with short black pile; tergum 4 covered with long golden yellow pilosity. Sterna reddish-brown, covered with white or yellow pile.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
Figs 3D
, 
7A–C
). Posterior lobe of surstyle narrow, bent, S-shaped, gradually narrowing toward tip (
Fig. 7A
: pl); anterior lobe of surstyle undeveloped (
Fig. 7A
); anterior margin of surstyle rounded in lateral view (
Fig. 7A
: ams); cercus square like (
Fig. 7A
: c). Hypandrium with theca medially distinctly narrowed (
Fig. 7C
: marked with arrow). Lateral sclerite of aedeagus small (
Fig. 3D
: s).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 19.
Male genitalia. 
A–C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Merodon funestus
(Fabricius, 1794)
</tp:taxon-name>
(FSUNS; FSUNS ID F99). 
D–F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. nasicus
Bezzi, 1915
</tp:taxon-name>
(TAUI; FSUNS ID 04792). 
A, D
. Epandrium, lateral view. 
B, E
. Epandrium, ventral view. 
C, F
. Hypandrium, lateral view. Abbreviations: ams = anterior margin of surstyle; pl = posterior lobe of surstyle. Scale bar = 0.25 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
Figs 14C
, 
15C
, 
16C
)
</p>
      <p>
Similar to the male except for normal sexual dimorphism: metafemur usually with small apical dens on triangular lamina (
Fig. 16C
); frons with non pollinose medial vitta (
Fig. 15C
); vertex shiny, non pollinose, mostly covered with black pile.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Period of flight and distribution
(
Fig. 1
)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Merodon zebra
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
occurs in central parts of Africa (
Democratic Republic of the Congo
and 
Tanzania
); the flight period may extend over the whole year and probably depends on local circumstances. It appears in a deciduous forest-woodland savanna 
type
of vegetation (

Sayre 
et al.
2013

).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
