<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Merodon vittatus Vujic &amp; Likov
                        2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5013402</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E07B6D1EFFFE2B5EDA44FE14FC81FE6D</uri>
                  <article-title>Revision of the Merodon bombiformis group (Diptera: Syrphidae) -
                        rare and endemic African hoverflies</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1401</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Merodon vittatus Vujić &amp; Likov </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 591CEDD4-80E4-4978-B13E-3F66511C9026 </p>
            <p> Figs 1 , 4C , 5C , 6C , 7D–F , 8B , 9C , 10C , 11C , 12C , 18C , 21E </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Brown, large ( 12 mm ), striped species, with golden yellow pile on the tip of
                  abdomen ( Fig. 5C ); frons and postpronotum dark brown; scutum with five pollinose
                  vittae ( Fig. 10C ); metafemur with distinct apical thorn on triangular process (
                  Figs 6C , 8B ); terga 3 and 4 with broad medial pollinose fasciae ( Fig. 5C ).
                  Similar to <tp:taxon-name> Merodon multifasciatus </tp:taxon-name> from which
                  differs only in male genitalia with narrow, S-shaped posterior lobe of surstyle,
                  gradually narrowing toward tip ( Fig. 7D : pl) (in <tp:taxon-name> M.
                        multifasciatus </tp:taxon-name> broad, slightly curved, with almost parallel
                  sides and rounded apex ( Fig. 13D : pl). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The specific epithet ‘ <tp:taxon-name> vittatus </tp:taxon-name> ’ ‘wearing or
                  carrying a vitta’, an adjective, refering to the broad golden gray fasciae on the
                  terga 2–4. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype GHANA • 1 ♂ ; Transvolta Togoland , Amedzofe ;
                        6.853° N , 0.433° E ; 2 Nov. 1959 ; N.D. Jago leg.; FSUNS ID 04085 ; NBCN .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Length: large species, body 12 mm , wing 8.5 mm (n = 1). </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> HEAD ( Figs 4C , 9C , 11C , 12C ). Antenna ( Fig. 4C ) reddish-yellow; pedicel
                  elongated, approximately as long as basoflagellomere (relation scape:pedicel:
                  basoflagellomere =1.0: 2.5: 2.5); basoflagellomere concave dorsally, with acute
                  apex; arista yellow to reddish, thickened basally, 1.7 times as long as
                  basoflagellomere. Face dark brown, covered with gray pollinosity and whitish pile,
                  except on bare medial vitta that occupies ¼ width of face. Oral margin protruded (
                  Fig. 9C ). Frons dark brown, inflated, covered with gray pollinosity and whitish
                  pile. Vertical triangle isosceles ( Fig. 12C ), reddish, covered with a long,
                  whitish pile. Ocellar triangle equilateral. Eye pile dense, gray, slightly longer
                  than scape. Eye contiguity about 15 ommatidia long. Occiput reddish-brown,
                  pollinose, covered with a whitish pile. </p>
            <p> THORAX ( Figs 6C , 8B , 10C ). Mesonotum black, except lateral side of scutum
                  including postpronotum, postalar callus, and posterior margin of scutellum
                  red-brown; covered with grayish-yellow pile; scutum with five pollinose
                  longitudinal vittae ( Fig. 10C ). Pleuron black to dark brown, covered with gray
                  pollinosity and the following parts with whitish to yellow pile: anterior part of
                  proepimeron, posterior part of anterior anepisternum, most of the posterior
                  anepisternum except anterior end, antero-ventral and postero-dorsal part of
                  katepisternum and anepimeron. Wing hyaline, with dense microtrichia and yellow to
                  brown veins. Calypter pale yellow. Halter with pale yellow pedicel and capitulum.
                  All three femora dark brown; tibiae mostly reddish, medially dark brown; tarsi
                  reddish ( Figs 6C , 8B ). Metatrochanter without calcar. Metafemur moderately
                  thickened, with less developed apicoventral triangular lamina, more or less
                  dentate, the apical dens is distinct ( Figs 6C , 8B ). Pile on legs predominantly
                  whitish to yellow. </p>
            <p> ABDOMEN ( Fig. 5C ). Black to dark brown. Tergum 1 with gray pollinosity, covered
                  with black basal sockets of pile and with short pale yellow pile; tergum 2 with
                  pollinose posterior margin and narrow medial fascia, interrupted in the middle,
                  covered with pale yellow pile; terga 3 and 4 with pollinose posterior margin and
                  broad medial fasciae ( Fig. 5C ); tergum 3 covered with pale yellow pile except
                  anterior half with few short black pile; tergum 4 covered with long golden-yellow
                  pilosity ( Fig. 5C ). Sterna reddish-brown, covered with pale yellow pile. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA ( Figs 7D–F , 18C ). Posterior lobe of surstyle S-shaped, gradually
                  narrowing toward tip ( Fig. 7D : pl); anterior margin of surstyle angular ( Fig.
                  7D : ams); cercus elongated ( Fig. 7D : c). Hypandrium with theca medially
                  distinctly narrowed ( Fig. 7F ). Lateral sclerite of aedeagus small ( Fig. 18C :
                  s). </p>
            <p> Fig. 17. <tp:taxon-name> Merodon lotus Vujić &amp; Radenković </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. , male genitalia. Paratypes. A–C . Specimen FSUNS (FSUNS ID ZA6_066). D–F .
                  Specimen FSUNS (FSUNS ID ZA6_060). A, D . Epandrium, lateral view. B, E .
                  Epandrium, ventral view. C, F . Hypandrium, lateral view. Abbreviations: ams =
                  anterior margin of surstyle; c = cercus; pl = posterior lobe of surstyle. Scale
                  bar = 0.25 mm. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Period of flight and distribution ( Fig. 1 ) </p>
            <p> Only the holotype is known, which originated from Ghana and was collected in
                  November. It was found in a deciduous forest-woodland savanna type of vegetation.
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
