<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sibogasyrinx pagodiformis Kantor &amp; Puillandre 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536375</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E43BBB1DFFD4FFD826017EB47558F337</uri>
         <article-title>Rare, deep-water and similar: revision of Sibogasyrinx (Conoidea: Cochlespiridae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1509</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sibogasyrinx pagodiformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(= PSH 5)
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
DAA613D6-5AB6-4F89-A0AD-0C718A60307E
</p>
      <p>
Figs 8F
, 
12A–D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Shell small, reaching 
29 mm
in length, pagodiform, with strongly concave subsutural ramp bearing two low spiral cords and distinct subsutural nodules. Axial sculpture of distinct opisthocline ribs extending to shell base, 10–11 per whorl. Spiral sculpture of closely spaced cords on and below shoulder. Radula lacking central tooth, marginal teeth trough-shaped with thickened edges.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The name reflects the characteristic shell shape, resembling a pagoda.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
SOLOMON ISLANDS
• 
NW of Malaita I.
; 
08°28′ S
, 
160°32′ E
; depth 

1250–1402 m

; SALOMONBOA 3, stn CP2789; 
MNHN-IM-2009-16825
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Other material
(sequenced)
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
VANUATU
• 
1 lv
; 
E of Malekula I.
; 
16°00′ S
, 
167°38′ E
; depth 

1262–1285 m

; SANTO 2006, stn AT139; 
MNHN-IM-2009-11327
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS (
holotype
). SL 
28.8 mm
, AL (with canal) 
15.2 mm
, AL (without canal) 
9.9 mm
, SW 
11.9 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
SHELL (
holotype
). Moderately thick, except for fragile, partially chipped outer aperture lip; pagodiform, with moderately high spire and moderately long, narrow siphonal canal inclined to abaxially left. Protoconch missing (rendering exact an whorl count and protoconch measurements impossible), upper teleoconch whorls eroded. Teleoconch whorls rapidly increasing and strongly angled at shoulder, more than 8 remaining. Suture shallowly impressed, subsutural ramp broad, concave. A row of distinct, sharp, subsutural nodules on upper teleoconch whorls. Nodules less distinct on last three whorls and situated on short, slightly raised, prosocline axial ribs. Number of ribs on uppermost whorls indeterminate due to shell surface erosion, number of nodules per whorl increasing from 16–17 on first intact whorl to 22 on penultimate and 26 on last whorl. Subsutural ramp smooth except for nodules and two low, indistinct subsutural cords. Shoulder with pronounced, thickened, opisthocline axial ribs on all teleoconch whorls. Axial ribs on upper teleoconch whorls situated just above suture, extending to shell base on last whorl, number of ribs constant, 11–12 per whorl. Ribs intersected by closely spaced, rounded spiral cords, number increasing from 5 on uppermost remaining whorl to 10 on penultimate whorl. Last whorl with total of 38 cords, including 18 on canal. Cords narrow, their intervals 0.5–1.5 times cord width. Shell base rapidly narrowing towards narrow, moderately long siphonal canal. Aperture narrow, constricted posteriorly, with thin, moderately broad parietal callus, outer lip partially broken, convex on subsutural ramp, with rounded angle at shoulder, convex below shoulder and weakly concave at transition to canal. Anal sinus judging from growth lines shallow, subsutural, broadly arcuate. Shell flesh-coloured, with darker base, glossy. Periostracum thin, persisting in some cord intervals.
</p>
      <p>ANATOMY (n = 1; MNHN-IM-2009-11327). Female. Proboscis relatively short, straight, cylindrical. Proboscis retractors large, in two bundles attached at proboscis base. Buccal mass within proboscis, rather long, about half length of proboscis, radular sac opening on right. Venom gland very thick, not long, opening with very short constriction just posterior to nerve ring. Venom bulb moderately large, elongate.</p>
      <p>
RADULA (n = 2; MNHN-IM-2009-16825, AL 
9.9 mm
, IM-2009-11327, AL ca 
9 mm
). Relatively short, comprising 20–24 rows of teeth, 8–9 nascent. Radula length 
1.1–1.6 mm
(12–16% of AL without canal), tooth length 150 μm (1.7% of AL without canal). Central tooth absent. Marginal teeth trough-shaped when mature (
Fig. 8F
), with slightly thickened edges and sharp pointed tips. Teeth initially forming as a flat, elongate-oval plate, its edges gradually thickening along radular membrane and then by longitudinal folding of each tooth on 10–11 
th
row, counting from rear.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The second live collected specimen has a broken shell base. In sculpture pattern it is very similar to the 
holotype
.
</p>
      <p>
The species is distinct from all congeners in having a relatively broad, pagodiform shell with a shorter canal. Conchologically the species is quite similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Comitas paupera
(Watson, 1881)
</tp:taxon-name>
, a highly variable species of uncertain generic affinity, but differing in lacking distinct spiral cords on the subsutural ramp. The 
lectotype
and 
paralectotypes
of the latter were illustrated by 
Sysoev (1996
: figs 42–48). Superficially, the new species also strongly resembles a miniature copy of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leucosyrinx luzonica
(
Powell, 1969
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 

Kantor 
et al.
2018

: fig. 21), but differs in the shape of the marginal radular teeth and foregut anatomy. Another species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leucosyrinx
</tp:taxon-name>
from the 
Solomon Islands
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leucosyrinx
sp. D
</tp:taxon-name>
, is similar to the new species in shell outline (
Fig. 13F
), differing in radular morphology.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 12. A–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sibogasyrinx pagodiformis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–B
. Solomon Islands, holotype, MNHN- IM-2009-16825, SL 28.8 mm. 
C–D
. Vanuatu. MNHN-IM-2009-11327, SL 24.3 mm. 
E–H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sibogasyrinx elbakyanae
Kantor, Puillandre &amp; Bouchet
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, Solomon Islands, MNHN-IM-2009-16834, SL 27.3 mm. 
H
. Enlarged fragment of penultimate and antepenultimate whorls. A–G to same scale.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
This species was found in the 
Solomon Islands
and 
Vanuatu
at 
1250–1262 m
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
