<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sibogasyrinx subula Kantor &amp;
                        Puillandre 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536351</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E43BBB1DFFE4FFE826287F2373DFF4CA</uri>
                  <article-title>Rare, deep-water and similar: revision of Sibogasyrinx (Conoidea:
                        Cochlespiridae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1509</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx subula </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. (= PSH 3) </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 6A992BBF-7C62-4F15-BFCC-AD9F347ED379 </p>
            <p> Figs 4E–F , 6 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx sp. </tp:taxon-name> – Bouchet et al. 2011 : figs
                  11b, 12b–c. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Shell large, reaching 57 mm in length, narrowly fusiform, with concave, nearly
                  smooth subsutural ramp with darker subsutural band on posterior half of last whorl
                  and strong nodules on shoulder. Spiral sculpture of distinct, closely spaced cords
                  below subsutural ramp. Radula with central tooth and duplex marginal teeth. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> Latin ‘ <tp:taxon-name> subula </tp:taxon-name> ’ (noun in apposition), meaning
                  ‘awl’, with reference to the general appearance of the spire. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype SOLOMON ISLANDS • SE of Sta Isabel I.; 08°17′ S ,
                        160°00′ E ; depth 482–604 m ; SALOMON 2, stn CP2187; MNHN-IM-2007-42530 .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Other material (all sequenced) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> PAPUA NEW GUINEA • 1 lv ; 05°39′ S , 153°59′ E ; depth
                        654–660 m ; BIOPAPUA, stn CP3750; MNHN-IM-2009-17048 </tp:material-citation>
                  • <tp:material-citation> 1 lv ; New Ireland ; 02°13′ S , 150°12′ E ; depth 564–743
                        m ; KAVIENG 2014, stn CP4448; MNHN-IM-2013-58409 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SOLOMON ISLANDS • 2 lv ; SE of Sta Isabel I.; 08°17′ S ,
                        160°00′ E ; depth 464–523 m ; SALOMON 2, stn CP2184; MNHN-IM-2009-13567 ,
                        MNHN-IM-2009-13568 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 lv ;
                        SW of Sta Isabel I.; 08°25′ S , 159°27′ E ; depth 440–521 m ; SALOMON 2, stn
                        CP2194; MNHN-IM-2007-42533 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation>
                        1 lv ; 08°41′ S , 157°38′ E ; depth 814–980 m ; SALOMON 2, stn CP2276;
                        MNHN-IM-2007-42517 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> VANUATU • 4 lv ; 15°00′ S , 166°55′ E ; depth 630–705 m ;
                        BOA1, stn CP2432; MNHN-IM-2007-17701 to IM-2007-17704
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS ( holotype ). SL 55 mm , AL (with canal) 31 mm , AL (without canal)
                  17.5 mm , SW 15.6 mm . </p>
            <p> SHELL ( holotype ). Moderately thick, strong except for fragile outer lip of
                  aperture, fusiform, with high spire and long, narrow, straight siphonal canal.
                  Protoconch small, globose, of about 1.5 strongly convex, microshagreened whorls.
                  Protoconch/teleoconch transition marked by arcuate axial rib and appearance of
                  definitive sculpture. Protoconch diameter 1.0 mm, height 0.79 mm . Teleoconch
                  whorls angular at shoulder. Teleoconch comprising just under 10 whorls in total.
                  Suture shallowly impressed, subsutural ramp broad, strongly concave. Subsutural
                  region with a row of distinct sigmoidal nodules that correspond in shape to upper
                  parts of thickened growth lines, about 20 on first whorl, 17–19 on second–fourth
                  whorls, 32 on penultimate and 30 on last whorl. Subsutural ramp smooth except for
                  subsutural row of nodules, few thickened growth lines and 3–4 very weak spiral
                  threads on last and penultimate whorls. Shoulder with pronounced thickened and
                  rounded nodules, weakly opisthocline on upper whorls, but more strongly inclined
                  and confluent with growth lines on last whorl; 17 on penultimate and
                  antepenultimate whorls and 19 on last whorl. Spiral sculpture of 4–5 moderately
                  pronounced, narrow cords on shoulder, seen both on nodules and in their intervals,
                  and rather distinct, weakly rounded cords below shoulder, some flattened. Single
                  cord appears on 3rd whorl, two cords on other whorls, including penultimate one.
                  On last whorl cords occupy entire shell below shoulder, varying in width, their
                  intervals 1–2 times width of cords, in total 48 cords on last whorl, of which 28
                  on canal. Shell base gradually narrowing towards long, narrow, nearly straight
                  siphonal canal. Aperture narrow, constricted posteriorly, with very narrow and
                  thin parietal callus, outer lip partially broken, with rounded angle at shoulder,
                  weakly convex below shoulder and weakly concave at transition to canal. Anal sinus
                  moderately deep, subsutural, broadly arcuate, confluent with large forward
                  extension of outer lip. Shell off-white, with very light yellowish subsutural band
                  and darker subsutural band on posterior half of last whorl, protoconch light tan. </p>
            <p>ANATOMY (n = 1, MNHN-IM-2009-13568). Head with long cylindrical tentacles, rounded on
                  tips with closely spaced bases, eyes absent. Specimen male, with long penis with
                  obliquely truncated tip. Seminal papilla occupies entire tip and is surrounded by
                  circular fold. Proboscis conical, with broad base, but very narrow along most of
                  its length. Proboscis retractors large, arranged in two bundles attached to
                  proboscis base. Buccal mass very large and broad, nearly as long as proboscis,
                  oesophagus forming short loop before nerve ring. Venom gland thick, medium-long
                  and convoluted, opening dorsally into oesophagus just posterior to nerve ring.
                  Muscular bulb very large.</p>
            <p> Fig. 6. <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx subula </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. A–C . Solomon
                  Islands, holotype, MNHN-IM-2007-42530, SL 55 mm. D–F . Solomon Islands,
                  MNHN-IM-2007-42533, SL 53.6 mm. G . Papua New Guinea, MNHN- IM-2013-58409, SL 36.3
                  mm. H–I . Solomon Islands, MNHN-IM-2009-13568, SL 49.4 mm (radula seen on Fig.
                  4F). J–L . Vanuatu, MNHN-IM-2007-17704, SL 53 mm. M . Vanuatu, MNHN-IM-2007-17701,
                  SL 46.0 mm. N . Solomon Islands, MNHN-IM-2009-13567, SL 57.4 mm. All shells to
                  same scale. </p>
            <p> RADULA (n = 3; MNHN-IM-2007-17701, MNHN-IM-2007-17703, MNHN-IM-2009-13568). All
                  specimens with similar radular morphology, radula comprising 38–40 rows of teeth,
                  11–17 nascent, short, length ca 1.8 mm (11% of AL without canal). Radula width up
                  to 310 μm (1.9% of AL without canal). Central tooth with broad, subrectangular
                  basal plate, anteriorly overlapped by preceding tooth, borders distinct, with
                  narrow, sharply pointed cusp. Marginal teeth with strongly thickened posterior
                  edges, folded longitudinally ( Fig. 4E–F ), in all details similar to those of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx cf. pyramidalis </tp:taxon-name> 1. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Largest specimen attains an SL of 57.4 mm . </p>
            <p> The other specimens are rather similar to the holotype in shell shape and sculpture.
                  The entire subsutural ramp may be pale yellowish on the last whorl, but the
                  subsutural zone of the posterior part of last whorl in larger specimens is always
                  more darkly coloured than the rest of the shell. The subsutural ramp may be
                  completely smooth or with indistinct spiral threads, the shoulder angulation on
                  the last whorl is sometimes less distinct than in the holotype , as may be the
                  cords below the shoulder on the penultimate whorl (up to 4). </p>
            <p> In shell outline, the new species resembles its congener <tp:taxon-name>
                        Sibogasyrinx filosa </tp:taxon-name> , but differs in having much less
                  distinct spiral sculpture on the subsutural ramp, as well as in its larger size
                  (maximal SL 57.4 mm in <tp:taxon-name> S. subula </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. and 52
                  mm in <tp:taxon-name> S. filosa </tp:taxon-name> ) and radular morphology. The
                  shell shape of the new species also strongly resembles that of some species of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Leucosyrinx </tp:taxon-name> , particularly <tp:taxon-name>
                        L. verrillii (Dall, 1881) </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 13A–C ) and to a lesser
                  extent the smaller specimens of <tp:taxon-name> Leucosyrinx sp. B </tp:taxon-name>
                  and <tp:taxon-name> Leucosyrinx sp. G </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 13D and 13I ,
                  respectively). All these species of <tp:taxon-name> Leucosyrinx </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  however, have a different radular morphology, shorter siphonal canal and,
                  according to the molecular tree ( Fig. 1 ) and other published
                        <tp:taxon-name>Conoidea</tp:taxon-name> phylogenies ( Puillandre et al .
                  2011 ; Abdelkrim et al . 2018 ), belong to a different family. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> This species is known from the Solomon Islands , Papua New Guinea and Vanuatu , and
                  has a relatively broad bathymetric range, from 440 to 814 m . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
