<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sibogasyrinx lolae Kantor &amp;
                        Puillandre 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536363</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E43BBB1DFFECFFE0263C7E987079F418</uri>
                  <article-title>Rare, deep-water and similar: revision of Sibogasyrinx (Conoidea:
                        Cochlespiridae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1509</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx lolae </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. (= PSH 8) </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 73404289-ED57-4ABD-A0D0-05939F095C40 </p>
            <p> Figs 8D , 9I–Q </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Shell medium-sized, reaching 43 mm in length, fusiform, with weakly concave, nearly
                  smooth subsutural ramp and nodules on shoulder of upper teleoconch whorls, absent
                  on later whorls of large specimens. Spiral sculpture weak, of closely spaced cords
                  covering entire shell except subsutural ramp in some specimens. Radula with
                  central tooth and longitudinally folded marginal teeth with weakly thickened
                  edges. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>The species is named after Lola, the daughter of the second author.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype SOLOMON ISLANDS • W of San Cristobal I. ; 10°26′ S
                        , 161°20′ E ; depth 506–567 m ; SALOMONBOA 3, stn CP2839; MNHN-IM-2007-42537
                        . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Other material (all sequenced) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> NEW CALEDONIA • 1 lv ; Bank de L’Orne/Walpole ; 22°22′ S ,
                        168°57′ E ; depth 460–708 m ; EXBODI, stn CP3864; MNHN-IM-2009-29230
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 lv ; 21°58′ S , 167°07′ E ;
                        depth 511–1050 m ; TERRASSES, stn CP3098; MNHN-IM-2009-29311
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 lv ; Fairway Ridge ; 21°39′ S ,
                        162°42′ E ; depth 787 m ; KANADEEP, stn CP4923; MNHN-IM-2013-48156
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS ( holotype ). SL 37.3 mm , AL (with canal) 22.9 mm , AL (without canal)
                  14.5 mm , SW 11.3 mm . </p>
            <p> SHELL ( holotype ). Moderately thick, glossy, strong except for very fragile and
                  partially broken outer aperture lip, narrowly fusiform, with high spire and long,
                  narrow, straight siphonal canal. Protoconch small, globose, corroded, of about 1.5
                  whorls. Protoconch preserved in other juvenile specimen (MNHN-IM-2013-48156),
                  comprising just over 1.5 strongly convex, microshagreened whorls.
                  Protoconch/teleoconch transition indistinct, marked by appearance of axial ribs.
                  Protoconch diameter 1.0 mm, height 0.74 mm . Spire whorls angled at shoulder, last
                  whorl with less angular shoulder. Total teleoconch whorls just under 8. Suture
                  shallowly impressed on last whorl and rather deep on spire whorls, subsutural ramp
                  moderately broad, weakly concave on upper teleoconch whorls and nearly flat on
                  penultimate and last whorls. Subsutural ramp with distinct prosocline axial
                  wrinkles, extending from suture to upper ⅔ of ramp, 22–23 on first and second
                  whorls, 24 on penultimate and 31 on last whorl, and without spiral sculpture on
                  upper four whorls and later with indistinct spiral cords, three on last whorl.
                  Shoulder of teleoconch whorls (except last one) with a row of distinct,
                  opisthoclinely elongated nodules, intersected by weak spiral cords. Seventeen
                  nodules on first teleoconch whorl, 18 on antepenultimate and penultimate whorls.
                  Weak spiral cords on and below shoulder, starting from 3 rd teleoconch whorls,
                  about twice as wide below shoulder. Penultimate whorl with four cords on shoulder
                  and four below shoulder. Shoulder smooth on last whorl, but with about 55 cords
                  below shoulder, of which 25 on canal. Cords weak, slightly wavy and closely
                  spaced, their intervals about half the width of cords. Shell base gradually
                  narrowing towards long, narrow, nearly straight siphonal canal. Aperture narrow,
                  constricted posteriorly, with narrow, very thin parietal callus, outer lip badly
                  broken, distinctly impressed at shoulder, weakly convex below shoulder and
                  shallowly concave at transition to canal. Anal sinus judging from growth lines
                  shallow, subsutural, broadly arcuate, confluent with forward extension of outer
                  lip. Shell very light yellowish, protoconch very light tan (in holotype ) and
                  light brown in MNHN-IM-2013-48156. </p>
            <p>ANATOMY (n = 1; MNHN-IM-2009-29311). Male. Penis tip obliquely truncated, with long
                  and very narrow papilla, surrounded by circular fold, much larger in diameter than
                  papilla itself. Proboscis conical, moderately long, with broad base, anterior half
                  rapidly narrowing towards tip. Proboscis retractors distinct, arranged in two
                  symmetrical lateral bundles, attached to inner proboscis walls at border of its
                  posterior third. Buccal mass with small radular sac, odontophore situated within
                  proboscis in its broader posterior part; elongate oval, occupying slightly less
                  than half of proboscis length. Single small accessory salivary gland present.
                  Salivary glands separate, acinous, irregular in shape. Venom gland long,
                  moderately thick and convoluted, opening into oesophagus within the nerve
                  ring.</p>
            <p> Fig. 9. A–H . <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx filosa Ardovini, 2021 </tp:taxon-name> .
                  A–B . Holotype, Solomon Islands (MNHN- IM-2000-37629), SL 52 mm. C–D . Solomon
                  Islands, MNHN-IM-2007-42498, SL 49.9 mm. E–F . Solomon Islands,
                  MNHN-IM-2009-16831, SL 34.4 mm (radula seen on Fig. 8C). G–H . Papua New Guinea,
                  MNHN-IM-2013-59044, SL 29.9 mm. I–Q . <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx lolae
                  </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. I–J . Solomon Islands, holotype, MNHN-IM-42537, SL 37.3
                  mm. K–L . New Caledonia, MNHN-IM-2009-29230, SL 43.1 mm. M–N . New Caledonia,
                  MNHN-IM-2009-29311, SL 29.1 mm. O–Q . New Caledonia, MNHN-IM-2013-48156, SL 17.1
                  mm (O at the same scale as the other specimens, P–Q enlarged). All shells (except
                  P–Q) to same scale. </p>
            <p> RADULA (n = 1; MNHN-IM-2009-29311) ( Fig. 8D ). Short, comprising 28 rows of teeth,
                  13 nascent. Radula length 1.15 mm (7.9% of AL without canal), width up to 255 μm
                  (1.8% of AL without canal), tooth length 160 μm (1.10% of AL without canal).
                  Central tooth with subrectangular basal plate, having distinct borders and long,
                  narrow, sharp cusp. Anterior margin overlapped by preceding row, posterior margin
                  formed by two straight sections meeting at obtuse angle in midline. Marginal teeth
                  flat when formed, becoming trough-shaped with weakly thickened edges during
                  maturation, folded longitudinally when fully formed, with both margins overlapping
                  at tooth tip. Resulting folded tooth moderately broad, with sharp pointed tip,
                  anterior edge with a narrow slit between tooth margins. Tooth folding occurring
                  within 15 th row of teeth. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> The largest specimen attains 43.1 mm . </p>
            <p> Other specimens are similar to the holotype in shell shape, although some have much
                  more pronounced spiral sculpture, especially MNHN-IM-2009-29230, which also
                  retains spiral cords on the shoulder of the last whorl. </p>
            <p> In shell shape and sculpture the new species is most similar to <tp:taxon-name>
                        Sibogasyrinx filosa </tp:taxon-name> , some specimens being almost
                  indistinguishable (e.g., holotype of <tp:taxon-name> S. filosa </tp:taxon-name>
                  and MNHN-IM-2009-29230). <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx lolae </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. can be distinguished from <tp:taxon-name> S. filosa </tp:taxon-name> due to
                  its generally less distinct spiral sculpture and less concave, nearly flat
                  subsutural ramp. Other conchologically similar species are <tp:taxon-name> S. cf.
                        pyramidalis </tp:taxon-name> 1 and 2, but these differ in their radular
                  morphology. In both these species and <tp:taxon-name> S. lolae </tp:taxon-name>
                  sp. nov. , the nodules on the shoulder become less pronounced or disappear on
                  later whorls. Nevertheless, the nodules are still pronounced on the shoulder of
                  the last whorl in specimens of <tp:taxon-name> S. cf. pyramidalis </tp:taxon-name>
                  1 and 2 of the same size as specimens of <tp:taxon-name> S. lolae </tp:taxon-name>
                  sp. nov. which already lack nodules on the last whorl. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> This species is recorded from the Solomon Islands , the Coral Sea and southern New
                  Caledonia , at depths of 460– 787 m . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
