<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma quadrata
Machado &amp; Viecelli
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
6C2037C9-66B3-4B07-9102-E2BF009B8AC1
</p>
      <p>
Figs 12–13
, 18, 19B, 22B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The male of 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. quadrata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resembles that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. pentacantha
</tp:taxon-name>
by the shape and disposition of embolus (
Figs 13C, E
, 19B), however, it can be distinguished from that and other species of the genus by the rounded tegulum, which also presents a retrolateral reentrance, and by the squared-tipped RTA with remarkable grooved surface (
Figs 13D, F
, 19B). The females have an anterior longitudinal ruckle connected to a shallow and convex fold on the epigynal plate, with no median outgrowth, gutters or septum separating the copulatory openings (
Figs 12C, E
, 
22B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The epithet – a Latin feminine adjective that means squared – is a direct reference to the shape of the RTA tip, which ends abruptly.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Amazonas
, 
Coari
, 
Porto Urucu
, 
Base de Operações Geólogo Pedro de Moura
; 
4°53′42.5″ S
, 
65°11′18.2″ W
; 

28 Sep. 2006

; 
C.A.C. Santos Jr.
leg.; 
UFMG 22673
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MPEG 22669

• 

1 ♀
; same locality as for preceding; 
4°50′01″ S
, 
65°03′53″ W
; 

28 Sep. 2006

; 
D. Guimarães
leg.; 
UFMG 22673

• 

1 ♀
, same collection data as for preceding; 

Sep. 2006

; 
D. Candiani
leg.; 
MPEG 13297

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>None.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
paratype
, MPEG 13297)
</p>
      <p>
PROSOMA. Anterior eye row strongly recurved and posterior procurve, ocular mounds discrete, not as elevated as in other species, carapace predominantly yellow, black on the sides, MS well developed (
Fig. 12A–B
). Chelicerae yellow with two pairs of dark stains, sternum slightly longer than wide, brown with a large yellow stain, endites and labium truncated and totally brown.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Leg coloration pattern as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. gigas
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
OPISTHOSOMA. Concave anterior border, predominantly yellow, dark-brown on sides and on the back of the abdominal projections (
Fig. 12A
). Spermathecae rounded and smooth surfaced (
Fig. 12D, F
).
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Eye diameters and eye interdistances: AME 0.06, ALE 0.11, PME 0.08, PLE 0.08, AME–AME 0.12, AME–ALE 0.16, PME–PME 0.27, PME–PLE 0.09, MOQ length 0.48, MOQ width 0.51; leg formula: 1-2-4-3: leg I – femur 5.18/ patella 2.59/ tibiae 3.47/ metatarsus 2.07/ tarsus 1.39/ total 14.70; II – 4.14/ 2.33/ 2.84/ 1.81/ 1.29/ 9.57; III – 2.33/ 1.29/ 2.07/ 1.03/ 0.88/ 7.60; IV – 2.90/ 1.29/ 1.91/ 1.24/ 0.93/ 8.27. Total body length 7.25; carapace 3.50 length, 3.37 wide; opisthosoma</p>
      <p>
Fig. 12.
Female of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma quadrata
Machado &amp; Viecelli
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, paratype (MPEG 13297). 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B
. Front. 
C, E
. Epigynal plate, ventral view. 
D, F
. Spermathecae, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>length 3.75; clypeus 0.32 height; sternum 1.53 length, 1.29 width; endites 0.80 length, 0.40 width; labium 0.56 length, 0.58 width.</p>
      <p>
Male
(
holotype
, MPEG 22673)
</p>
      <p>
PROSOMA. Anterior eye row very recurved, posterior procurved, ALE with almost two times the size of AME; carapace knobby, predominantly light brown with its median region, clypeus and posterior slope scars yellowish; medial spire absent (
Fig. 13A–B
). Sternum scutiform, light brown with a median white stain.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Anterior legs light brown with some darker taints while legs III and IV are lighter, with extensive whitish areas; anterior femora enlarged, with dorsolateral setiferous tubercles randomly distributed and ventral region dark-brown; tibia I and II with four pairs of ventral macrosetae and anterior metatarsi with three pairs (
Fig. 13A
).
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Predominantly pale yellow with small white punctuations and posterior black spots; straight anterior border and five short spiniform projections.</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Eye diameters and eye interdistances: AME 0.06, ALE 0.08, PME 0.06, PLE 0.06, AME– AME 0.06, AME–ALE 0.08, PME–PME 0.16, PME–PLE 0.06, MOQ length 0.29, MOQ width 0.32; leg formula: 1-2-4-3: leg I – femur 2.23/ patella 1.24/ tibiae 1.33/ metatarsus 0.88/ tarsus 0.56/ total 6.24; II –</p>
      <p>
Fig. 13.
Male of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma quadrata
Machado &amp; Viecelli
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, 
holotype
(MPEG 22673). 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B
. Front. 
C–F
. Left male palp. 
C, E
. Ventral view. 
D, F
. Retrolateral view.
</p>
      <p>1.45/ 0.72/ 1.04/ 0.72/ 0.50/ 4.43; III – 0.87/ 0.48/ 0.80/ 0.45/ 0.37/ 2.97; IV – 1.12/ 0.48/ 0.80/ 0.56/ 0.40/ 3.36. Total body length 4.61; carapace 2.28 length, 2.18 width; opisthosoma length 2.33; clypeus 0.24 height; sternum 0.83 length, 0.72 width; endites 0.40 length, 0.24 width; labium 0.20 length, 0.32 width.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
(Amazonas) (
Fig. 18
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
