<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Elliptera mongolica Podeniene,
                        Podenas &amp; Gelhaus, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4557204</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EE2D1801FF94FFEFFE57FCFCE6FFF892</uri>
                  <article-title>Review of East Palaearctic Elliptera (Diptera, Limoniidae)
                        immatures with description of a new species</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature/>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 2–5 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Body length reaching up to 14.5 mm . Head capsule heavily sclerotized. Hypostoma
                  with nine teeth. Abdominal segments II–VII with dorsal and ventral creeping welts.
                  Spiracular disc surrounded by four lobes, with lateral pair of lobes almost
                  entirely sclerotized. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p>The specific epithet is a noun ‘mongol’ with Latin suffix ‘ica’, referring to the
                  distribution of the new species.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype MONGOLIA • larva (in alcohol); Tov Aimag ,
                        Mongonmorit Soum , Zuun Baydlag Gol , downstream , 15 km SW of Mongonmorit ;
                        48°06.49′ N , 108°22.04′ E ; 1475 m a.s.l.; 14 Jul. 2011 ; V . Podeniene
                        leg.; MAIS #2011071402; ANSP-ENT-146962 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes MONGOLIA • 22 larvae (in alcohol); same
                        collection data as for preceding; GenBank: MT233411 ; ANSP
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> CHINA • 11 larvae (in alcohol); Inner Mongolia , Chifeng ,
                        Bailin Youqi , Sai Hanwula Reserve ; 44°15.06′ N , 118°19.54′ E ; 1165 m
                        a.s.l. ; 10 Jul. 2018 ; V. Podeniene leg; Shenyang Agricultural University ;
                        GenBank: MT233412 ; ANSP </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Larva </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Length 11.6–14.5 mm , width 1.7–2.0 mm. </p>
            <p> BODY. Cylindrical, dark brown, hairs on dorsal and ventral sides darker than on
                  lateral side. Abdominal segments II–VII divided into anterior and posterior parts,
                  anterior part with dorsal and ventral creeping welts ( Fig. 2 A–C). Creeping welts
                  with dark brown spines, arranged into transverse rows. All thoracic and abdominal
                  segments I–II shorter than wider. Abdominal segments III–VIII approximately as
                  long as wide. Pale circular area present on dorsum of all segments except the
                  prothorax ( Fig. 2B ). </p>
            <p> HEAD. Length 1.20–1.25 mm , width 1.10–1.20 mm . Head capsule oval, heavily
                  sclerotized and slightly reduced ( Fig. 2D ). Frontal suture absent, dorsal suture
                  reaching to about the middle of head capsule ( Fig. 2D ), hypostoma complete (
                  Fig. 2I ). Labrum wide with numerous sensory structures: short seta, middle-long
                  seta and three sensory pegs in the middle of anterior part ( Fig. 2E ). A narrow
                  sclerotized band situated anterior to sensory structures. Anterior part and sides
                  of labrum as well as epipharynx covered with numerous short hairs. Clypeus fused
                  with labrum and bears wide sclerotized plate anteriorly ( Fig. 2E ). Frons
                  separated from clypeus and fused with internolateralia, which are considerably
                  shorter than externolateralia; four long setae located on each side of the
                  anterior margin of frons, one seta below the base of antenna, a pair of sensory
                  pits in the middle of anterior part, caudal end of fronsinternolateralia very wide
                  and arched ( Fig. 2 D–E). Basal antennomere cylindrical, more than twice as long
                  as wide, with two long setae and a few very short sensory structures apically;
                  apical segment short, cylindrical; sensory pit located at the base of basal
                  segment ( Fig. 2E ). Mandible conus-shaped, with two large apical teeth, both
                  similar in shape and size ( Fig. 2F ), first ventral tooth triangular, second
                  ventral and basal teeth blunt; single well developed sharp tooth on dorsal side;
                  two long setae at the base of mandible (on outer margin). Maxilla well developed (
                  Fig. 2G ); outer lobe (stipes) and inner lobe (galea fused with lacinia) large and
                  similar in size. Outer lobe: two-thirds sclerotized, apical part and outer margin
                  covered by long setae; button shaped apical papilla with sensory structures on the
                  apex and small papilla next to it. Inner lobe: basal part sclerotized; long and
                  short sensory papillae on apical part; apical part and inner margin covered with
                  short setae. Cardo large, wedge shaped with sensory pit near outer margin of
                  sclerite. Hypopharynx arched, sclerotized and toothless. Prementum dentated (four
                  large teeth in the middle and two small similar in size teeth on both sides) (
                  Fig. 2H ). Hypostoma with nine anterior teeth, the middle tooth most prominent (
                  Fig. 2I ). </p>
            <p> ANAL DIVISION. Spiracular field surrounded by four lobes, ventral lobe twice as long
                  as lateral lobe ( Fig. 3 A–B). Lateral lobe as long as wide, almost entirely
                  sclerotized except the middle part, three medium-long setae located along the
                  outer margin of lobe. Ventral lobe twice as long as wide at the base with dark
                  U–shaped sclerite, ventral branch of each lobe fused with its opposing sclerite to
                  form continuous line. Dark spot situated at base of each lobe below spiracle
                  (missing in some specimens). Two long setae and one medium-long seta located at
                  the apical part of lobe; one medium-long seta on the outer margin of lobe. A pair
                  of sensory pit located on dorsal margin of spiracular field. Spiracular field
                  fringed with long firm setae, longest around the apical part of each lobe.
                  Spiracles large, oblong, placed obliquely and inclined dorsally ( Fig. 3 A–B).
                  Anal field consists of two pairs of conical, white, fleshy anal papillae ( Fig. 2C
                  ). </p>
            <p>Pupal and adult stages unknown.</p>
            <p> Habitat </p>
            <p> Larvae were found on accumulated mud on river boulders in Mongolia ( Fig. 4 ).
                  Larvae in China were found on accumulated mud on spring boulders. Some of them (in
                  both localities) made cases from mosses ( Fig. 5 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Currently known only from Mongolia and Inner Mongolia ( China ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
