<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Caccothryptus brendelli Matsumoto
                        2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4623938</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F035D85E9904FFF6810DFC0FFC33565F</uri>
                  <article-title>Six new species of the genus Caccothryptus from the Himalayas
                        (Coleoptera: Limnichidae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1275</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Caccothryptus brendelli </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: F29031E6-E8C9-4235-A03F-A483EA581FD2 </p>
            <p> Figs 1 , 7A </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Caccothryptus brendelli </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is within
                        <tp:taxon-name> C. testudo </tp:taxon-name> group and can be distinguished
                  by several genital characters: (1) apex of median lobe narrow with tip slightly
                  pointed in ventral view; (2) concave structure between apical emargination
                  narrowly V-shaped with rounded end; (3) dorsal side of parameres bisinuate in
                  lateral view; (4) apical emargination of parameres V-shaped in ventral view. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> This species is named after Martin J.D. Brendell, who was the curator of the
                        <tp:taxon-name>Coleoptera</tp:taxon-name> Department of Entomology at the
                  Natural History Museum, London. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype NEPAL • ♂ ; “NEPAL 5600’ Kathmandu Dist. Godawari
                        25/v/1983 // UNDER BARK OF DEAD TREE // M.J.D.Brendell BMNH(E) 1983-222 //
                        NHMUK011225276 ”; BMNH . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> BODY. Elongate, oval, dorsum convex, EL: 3.36 mm , EW: 2.44 mm , PL: 0.94 mm , PW:
                  2.07 mm . Colour: dorsal side brown; venter brown, tibia reddish brown, tarsal
                  claws light brown. Dorsal surface densely covered with long setae with patches of
                  white setae forming a wavy pattern, ventral surface with relatively long setae. </p>
            <p> DORSUM. Head: partially retracted into pronotum; overall surface smooth, densely
                  punctured across surface. Antennae: 11 segmented, filiform, fully pubescent,
                  antennomeres long and slender, 1 st AS widest, 2 nd AS narrow and long, 3 rd AS
                  smallest, 4 th –11 th AS long, thin and obtusely angled on one side. Pronotum:
                  transverse, widest at posterior end, narrowest at anterior end, narrower than
                  elytra; anterior margin convex, posterior margin trisinuate, lateral margin
                  convex; surface covered with dense punctation, surface between punctures smooth
                  and shiny. Scutellum: subtriangular, large, lateral sides nearly straight. Elytra:
                  longer than wide; anterior margin slightly convex, sinuate; anterior lateral angle
                  nearly right angled, pointed; lateral margins strongly bordered; surface with
                  mixtures of small fine and medium sized punctuations; surface between punctures
                  smooth and shiny. </p>
            <p> VENTER. Prosternum: concave on anterior margin, outer lateral margin concave;
                  prosternal process as long as wide, lateral margin sinuated, posterior margin
                  rounded. Mesoventrite: wider than long, narrowed towards posterior; anterior end
                  concave where prosternal process fits, discrimen visible; laterally subparallel
                  and gently curved, posteriorly flat, anteriorly trisinuate. Metaventrite: long and
                  wide, flat on the middle; discrimen thin visible across each end. Abdomen: five
                  clearly visible ventrites. Intercoxal process with pointed apex. Posterior margin
                  of 1 st and 2 nd ventrites convex, 3 rd –4 th ventrites slightly concave around
                  the middle, 5 th ventrite curved. Surface covered with long, light yellow,
                  recumbent setae. LEGS. Tibia: protibia with outer and inner lateral ends curved.
                  Meso- and metatibia with outer lateral margin almost straight, inner lateral
                  margin straight. Tarsi: simple, segments increase in length towards the apex, 5 th
                  tarsal segment as long as 1 st –4 th tarsal segment combined. Tarsal claws: long,
                  narrow, symmetrical. </p>
            <p> Fig. 1. <tp:taxon-name> Caccothryptus brendelli </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , ♂,
                  holotype (NHMUK011225276). A . Dorsal habitus. B . Genitalia, dorsal. C .
                  Genitalia, lateral. D . Genitalia, ventral. </p>
            <p> GENITALIA. Aedeagus: elongate, strongly sclerotised. Base: asymmetrical, widest
                  around basal 0.2 from both lateral and ventral view. Median lobe: approximately 2
                  / 5 length of genitalia; longer than parameres; gently curved on dorsal side,
                  bisinuate on ventral side, widest at near apical end, narrowing towards apex, apex
                  with round point in lateral view; apex flat split into two on anterior half and
                  edge pointed, lower half of lateral end relatively straight in dorsal view;
                  triangular emarginate on one side towards the parameres and small emarginate
                  directing laterally in ventral view. Parameres: wider than median lobe in ventral
                  view; apical emargination V-shaped, concave structure between parameres elongated
                  narrow and deeply V-shaped with rounded end; bisinuate, lower half of sinuation
                  long and shallow, upper half short and slightly deep on dorsal side in lateral
                  view; gently curved on ventral side in lateral view; apex rounded and not
                  overlapping median lobe, majority of parameres not overlapping median lobe with
                  two spaces visible in lateral view. </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Caccothryptus brendelli </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is known only
                  from the type locality. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
