<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Caccothryptus arakawae Matsumoto 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4700558</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F035D85E9906FFF08106FBE4FC3C5559</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of the genus Caccothryptus from the Himalayas (Coleoptera: Limnichidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1275</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus arakawae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
FB863BA1-2C04-435A-869C-5C6A16C82964
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2
, 
7B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus arakawae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is within the 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. testudo
</tp:taxon-name>
group and can be distinguished by several genital characters: (1) apex of median lobe narrows with tip slightly pointed in ventral view; (2) concave structure between apical emargination narrow U-shaped with rounded end; (3) dorsal side of parameres bisinuate in lateral view; (4) apical emargination of parameres V-shaped in ventral view.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is named after Hiromi Arakawa, who is a Japanese manga artist.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
NEPAL
• 
♂
; “NEPAL: 5600’ 
Kathmandu Dist.
, 
Godawari
, 

24.v.-6.vi.1983

. // 
M.J.D.Brendell
BMNH(E) 1983-222 // 
At light
// 
NHMUK011225268
”; 
BMNH
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
NEPAL
• 
3 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype with additional label; “ 
NHMUK011225269
”, “ 
NHMUK011225270
”, “ 
NHMUK011225271
”; 
BMNH
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype with additional label; “ 
NHMUK011225272
”, “ 
NHMUK011225273
”; 
BMNH
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
BODY
. Elongate, oval, dorsum convex, EL: 
3.39 mm
, EW: 
2.36 mm
, PL: 
0.93 mm
, PW: 
2.03 mm
. Colour: dorsal side brown; venter brown, tibia reddish brown, tarsal claws light brown. Dorsal surface densely covered with long setae with patches of white setae forming a wavy pattern, ventral surface with relatively long setae.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus arakawae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (NHMUK011225268). 
A
. Dorsal habitus. 
B
. Genitalia, dorsal. 
C
. Genitalia, lateral. 
D
. Genitalia, ventral.
</p>
      <p>
DORSUM
. Head: partially retracted into pronotum; overall surface smooth, densely punctured across surface. Antennae: 11 segmented, filiform, fully pubescent, antennomeres long and slender, 1 
st
AS
widest, 2 
nd
AS
narrow and long, 3 
rd
AS
smallest, 4 
th
–11 
th
AS
long, thin and obtusely angled on one side. Pronotum: transverse, widest at posterior end, narrowest at anterior end, narrower than elytra; anterior margin convex, posterior margin trisinuate, lateral margin convex; surface covered with dense punctation, surface between punctures smooth and shiny. Scutellum: subtriangular, large, lateral sides nearly straight. Elytra: Longer than wide; anterior margin slightly convex, sinuate; anterior lateral angle nearly right angled, rounded; lateral margins strongly bordered; surface with mixtures of small fine and medium sized punctuations; surface between punctures smooth and shiny.
</p>
      <p>
VENTER
. Prosternum: concave on anterior margin, outer lateral margin concave; prosternal process as long as wide, lateral margin sinuated, posterior margin rounded. Mesoventrite: wider than long, narrowed towards posterior; anterior end concave where prosternal process fits, discrimen visible; laterally subparallel and gently curved, posteriorly flat, anteriorly trisinuate. Metaventrite: long and wide, flat on middle; discrimen not clearly visible. Abdomen: five clearly visible ventrites. Intercoxal process with pointed apex. Posterior margin of 1 
st
and 2 
nd
ventrites convex, 3 
rd
–4 
th
ventrites slightly concave around middle, 5 
th
ventrite curved. Surface covered with long, light yellow, recumbent setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS
. Tibia: protibia with outer and inner lateral ends curved. Meso- and metatibia with outer lateral margin almost straight, inner lateral margin straight. Tarsi: simple, segments increase in length towards apex, 5 
th
tarsal segment as long as 1 
st
–4 
th
tarsal segment combined. Tarsal claws: long, narrow, symmetrical.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Aedeagus: elongate, strongly sclerotised. Base: asymmetrical, widest around basal 0.2 from lateral, relatively consistent width in ventral view. Median lobe: approximately 
2
/ 
5
length of genitalia; longer than parameres; slightly bisinuate on dorsal side, bisinuate on ventral side, widest at near apical end, narrowing towards the apex, apex rounded in lateral view; apex flat split into two on anterior half and edge pointed, lower half of lateral end relatively straight in dorsal view; lower half narrows, upper half oval and tip slightly rounded in lateral view; apical end smooth and narrows inwards in ventral view. Parameres: wider than median lobe in ventral view; apical emargination V-shaped, concave structure between parameres elongated slightly narrow and deep U-shape with rounded end; bisinuate, lower half of sinuation long and shallow, upper half short and slightly deep on dorsal side in lateral view; gently curved on ventral side in lateral view; apex rounded and ever so slightly overlapping with median lobe, majority of parameres do not overlap median lobe with two spaces visible in lateral view.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
No morphological difference from male except for the longer 5 
th
abdominal ventrite. Ovipositor long, gonocoxites strongly tapering to a point.
</p>
      <p>
Morphological variation
</p>
      <p>
EL: 3.68‒ 
3.39 mm
, EW: 2.52‒ 
2.35 mm
, PL: 1.00‒ 
0.90 mm
, PW: 2.11‒ 
2.03 mm
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus arakawae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
