<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Caccothryptus larryi Matsumoto 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4620979</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/2B7D7993640689B34C5424F45C73BCB8</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of the genus Caccothryptus from the Himalayas (Coleoptera: Limnichidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1275</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus larryi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
C5571EBA-C47F-4375-AD03-7D11002761B1
</p>
      <p>
Figs 4
, 
7D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus larryi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is within 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. compactus
</tp:taxon-name>
group and can be distinguished by several genital characters: (1) apex of median lobe with two asymmetrical emarginations in ventral view; (2) concave structure between parameres an elongated narrow and deeply V-shaped with pointed end; (3) dorsal and ventral side of parameres smooth and elongate, narrowing towards apical end in lateral view; (4) apical emargination of parameres oval in ventral view. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. ripicola
</tp:taxon-name>
has semicircle shaped apical emargination of parameres, median lobe with symmetrical emarginations, overall genitalia long and thin, which differs significantly from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. larryi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is named after ʻLarryʼ the cat that lives at 10 Downing Street and the current ʻChief Mouserʼ to the Cabinet Office.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
INDIA
• 

♂

; “ 
AT LIGHT
// 
Haldwani
Divn
. 
Kumaon
, U.P. // 4017 // 
<tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus ripicola
Ch
</tp:taxon-name>
// 
<tp:taxon-name>Caccothryptus ripicola Champ.</tp:taxon-name>
// 
H.G. Champion
B.M. 1953-156 // 
NHMUK011225324
”; 
BMNH
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratype
INDIA
• 
1 ♀
; “AT LIGHT // Haldwani Divn. Kumaon, U.P. // 4017 // 
<tp:taxon-name>Caccothryptus ripicola Champ.</tp:taxon-name>
// 
H.G. Champion
B.M. 1953-156 // NHMUK011225325”; 
BMNH

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Elongate, oval, dorsum convex, EL: 
2.44 mm
, EW: 
2.09 mm
, PL: 
0.75 mm
, PW: 
1.68 mm
. Colour: dorsal side brown; venter brown, tibia brown, tarsal claws light brown. Dorsal surface densely covered with long setae with patches of white setae forming a wavy pattern, ventral surface with relatively long setae.
</p>
      <p>
DORSUM. Head: partially retracted into pronotum; overall surface smooth, densely punctured across surface. Antennae: 11 segmented, filiform, fully pubescent, antennomeres long and slender, 1 
st
AS
widest, 2 
nd
AS
narrow and long, 3 
rd
AS
smallest, 4 
th
–11 
th
AS
long, thin and obtusely angled on one side. Pronotum: transverse, widest at posterior end, narrowest at anterior end, narrower than elytra; anterior margin convex, posterior margin trisinuate, lateral margin convex; surface covered with dense punctation, surface between punctures smooth and shiny. Scutellum: subtriangular, large, lateral sides nearly straight. Elytra: longer than wide; anterior margin slightly convex, sinuate; anterior lateral angle nearly right angled, pointed; lateral margins strongly bordered; surface with mixtures of small fine and medium sized punctuations; elytral striae not clearly visible throughout; surface between punctures smooth and shiny.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus larryi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (NHMUK011225324). 
A
. Dorsal habitus. 
B
. Genitalia, dorsal. 
C
. Genitalia, lateral. 
D
. Genitalia, ventral.
</p>
      <p>
VENTER. Prosternum: concave on anterior margin, outer lateral margin concave; prosternal process as long as wide, lateral margin sinuated, posterior margin rounded. Mesoventrite: wider than long, narrowed towards posterior; anterior end concave where prosternal process fits, discrimen visible; laterally subparallel and gently curved, posteriorly flat, anteriorly trisinuate. Metaventrite: long and wide, flat on the middle; discrimen thin visible across each end. Abdomen: five clearly visible ventrites. Intercoxal process with pointed apex. Posterior margin of 1 
st
and 2 
nd
ventrites convex, 3 
rd
–4 
th
ventrites slightly concave around the middle, 5 
th
ventrite semioval. Surface covered with long, light yellow, recumbent setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia: protibia with narrowly oval. Meso- and metatibia with outer lateral margin almost straight, inner lateral margin straight. Tarsi: simple, segments increase in length towards the apex, 5 
th
tarsal segment as long as 1 
st
–4 
th
tarsal segment combined. Tarsal claws: Long, narrow, symmetrical.
</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Aedeagus: elongate, strongly sclerotised. Base: asymmetrical, width gently narrowed towards apical end. Median lobe: approximately ¼ length of genitalia; longer than parameres; consistent width on basal ¾, oval on apical half, maximum width of apical ¼ in lateral view; apex flat and edge rounded, lower half of lateral end gently concave in dorsal view; dorsal and ventral end curved, narrow near the apex, apex pointed, width relatively consistent in lateral view; triangular emarginate on one side towards parameres and small emarginate directing laterally in ventral view. Parameres: wider than median lobe in ventral view; apical emargination oval, concave structure between parameres an elongated U-shaped with rounded end; smooth and elongate, narrowed towards apical end, apex pointed and overlaps with median lobe, majority of parameres overlaps with median lobe with no visible spacing in lateral view.</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
No morphological difference from male except for the longer 5 
th
abdominal ventrite. Ovipositor long, gonocoxites strongly tapering to a point. EL: 
2.77 mm
, EW: 
2.18 mm
, PL: 
0.77 mm
, PW: 
1.71 mm
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus larryi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
