<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Andrena (Taeniandrena) levante Wood
                        &amp; Ghisbain &amp; Michez &amp; Praz 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5101749</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F12A87E8FFA0FFDCFE37FBBBFE7DFC45</uri>
                  <article-title>Revisions to the faunas of Andrena of the Iberian Peninsula and
                        Morocco with the descriptions of four new species (Hymenoptera:
                        Andrenidae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.758.1431</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Andrena ( Taeniandrena ) levante Wood &amp; Praz </tp:taxon-name> sp.
            nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 6B3F3AE1-AD7B-4A22-A351-04E8B4A6E911 </p>
            <p> Figs 3 , 10 , 12–19 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> Females of <tp:taxon-name> Andrena levante Wood &amp; Praz </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov.
                  are close to those of <tp:taxon-name> A. gelriae </tp:taxon-name> , with hair
                  bands that are not as dense, as wide, or as complete as in <tp:taxon-name> A.
                        gredana </tp:taxon-name> stat. nov. ( Figs 7 , 15 ). The clearest difference
                  can be seen on the scutum which is strongly and densely shagreened and dull ( Fig.
                  14 ), with dense punctures that are almost contiguous (except posteriorly), giving
                  the overall surface a duller appearance than in either <tp:taxon-name> A. gelriae
                  </tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name> A. gredana </tp:taxon-name> ( Fig. 6 ) that
                  have sparser punctation. The pubescence of the scutum and scutellum is also
                  denser, shorter, and thicker than either comparison species ( Figs 4 , 12 ). </p>
            <p> As for other similar species of <tp:taxon-name> Taeniandrena </tp:taxon-name> , male
                  identification is much easier. Males can be recognised as part of the group with
                  A3 equal to or slightly shorter than A4 (A3 1–1.03 times as long as A4). The
                  genitalia are distinctive, with the gonocoxa diverging from close to their base
                  (without their inner margins parallel for at least 50% of their length), the penis
                  valve uniformly wide (not constricted medially), and with the blades of the
                  gonostyli comparatively short, apically as wide as long ( Fig. 10 ).
                        <tp:taxon-name> Andrena levante </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. differs from
                        <tp:taxon-name> A. gelriae vocifera </tp:taxon-name> in numerous
                  morphological features; this taxon will be characterised elsewhere (Praz &amp;
                  Wood, in prep.). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The term ‘ El Levante ’ is the Spanish name for the eastern part of the Iberian
                  Peninsula that constitutes the majority of the known range of this species
                  (Almería, Granada , Málaga, Murcia, Valencia). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype SPAIN • ♂ ; 80 km SW of Valencia , Muela de Cortes
                        reserve ; [ 39.219° N , 0.957° W ]; 14 May 2003 ; J. Halada leg.; BOLD
                        accession number: HYMAA245-21; OÖLM (illustrated Figs 10 , 16–19 ).
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes SPAIN • 4 ♂♂ , 23 ♀♀ ; Murcia , Sierra de
                        Españula ; 14 May 2003 ; J. Halada leg.; OÖLM </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 2 ♂♂ , 4 ♀♀ ; same collection data as for preceding;
                        TJWC (illustrated Figs 12–15 ) </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 2 ♂♂ ; Málaga , between Mijas and Benalmadena ; 16
                        Apr. 1983 ; NMNL </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ;
                        Almería , E-Sierra Nevada , near Alboloduy ; 6–7 May 2003 ; J. Halada leg.;
                        CPC </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection
                        data as for preceding; OÖLM </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation>
                        1 ♂ ; Murcia , 25 km SW of Cartagena ; 12 May 2003 ; J. Halada leg.; OÖLM
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 7 ♂♂ , 2 ♀♀ ; Valencia , 80 km SW
                        of Valencia , Muela de Cortes reserve ; 14 May 2003 ; J. Halada leg.; OÖLM
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 3 ♂♂ , 1 ♀ ; same collection data
                        as for preceding; TJWC </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀
                        ; Granada , Maitena , 9 km E of Granada ; 1400 m a.s.l. ; 1 Jun. 1970 ; M.J.
                        and J.P. Duffels leg.; NMNL </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 11–12 mm ( Fig. 12 ). </p>
            <p> HEAD. 1.3 times as wide as long ( Fig. 13 ). Clypeus dark, flattened over most of
                  its area, densely and uniformly punctate with exception of raised central
                  impunctate line, punctures separated by &lt;0.5 puncture diameters, underlying
                  surface shagreened, weakly shining, particularly apically. Face, gena, vertex, and
                  scape with light brownish hair, longest not exceeding half of scape in length.
                  Antennae dark, A4–12 lightened to light brown below. Foveae broad, occupying
                  almost all area between lateral ocellus and top of compound eye, filled with short
                  brown hairs. </p>
            <p> MESOSOMA. Scutum densely punctate, punctures separated by &lt;0.5 puncture diameters
                  over majority of surface except becoming slightly sparser centrally and
                  posteriorly, underlying surface shagreened, weakly shining ( Fig. 14 ). Scutellum
                  with sparser punctures separated by 1 puncture diameter, shagreenation weaker,
                  generally shining. Episternum and propodeum with dense raised reticulation,
                  underlying surface dull, propodeal triangle weakly indicated by weak carina,
                  little differentiated from general reticulation. Scutum and scutellum with short,
                  orange-brown, semi-squamiform hairs, episternum with longer light brownish to
                  white hairs, becoming orange-brown on propodeum. Legs dark, hind tibiae and tarsi
                  of mid and hind legs orange, general pubescence light brown basally, becoming
                  orange apically, flocculus, femoral and tibial scopae light brown to golden. Wings
                  hyaline, venation dark orange, stigma orange, nervulus interstitial. </p>
            <p> METASOMA. Terga dark, finely shagreened and weakly shining, apical part of marginal
                  areas lightened semi-translucent brown ( Fig. 15 ). T1 very finely and subtly
                  punctured, punctures on disc scarcely visible against shagreenation, those on
                  margin more visible, separated by 1 puncture diameter. T2–4 more densely and
                  visibly punctate, punctures separated by 0.5 puncture diameters. Terga with
                  whitish hairbands, on T1 represented by two very widely separated spots (separated
                  by almost entire width of tergal margin), T2 widely interrupted, T3+4 complete.
                  Remaining tergal surface covered with short, fine brown to ferruginous hairs
                  visible when viewed obliquely or in profile. Terminal fringe of T5 and hairs
                  flanking pygidial plate golden, pygidial plate rounded, flat, without raised
                  margin. </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 10–11 mm ( Fig. 16 ). </p>
            <p> HEAD. 1.3 times as wide as long ( Fig. 17 ). Clypeus flattened and densely punctate,
                  punctures separated by &lt;0.5 puncture diameter, sculpturing as in female. Gena
                  and lower part of face with white hairs, becoming light brown on scape and vertex,
                  longest equalling length of scape. Antennae dark, A4–13 extensively lightened to
                  dark brown below. A3 as long as A4. </p>
            <p> Figs 12–19. <tp:taxon-name> Andrena levante Wood &amp; Praz </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. (TJWC). 12 . Female profile. 13 . Female face. 14 . Female scutum. 15 .
                  Female terga. 16 . Male profile. 17 . Male face. 18 . Male scutum. 19 . Male
                  terga. </p>
            <p> MESOSOMA. Scutum, scutellum, episternum, and propodeum structurally as in female (
                  Fig. 18 ). Scutum and scutellum with fine light brown to golden hairs that equal
                  length of scape, becoming light brown to whitish on propodeum and episternum. Legs
                  dark, apical tarsal segments lightened dark red, pubescence whitish to light
                  brownish. Wings hyaline, venation dark orange, nervulus slightly postfurcal. </p>
            <p> METASOMA. Terga dark, finely shagreened and weakly shining, apical part of marginal
                  areas lightened semi-translucent brown ( Fig. 19 ). Terga finely but clearly
                  punctate, puncture separated by 0.5– 1 puncture diameter. T2–5 with hairbands, on
                  T2 medially interrupted, complete on T3–5. S8 strap-like, slightly broadened
                  apically, uniformly hairy. Genitalia elongated oval-shaped in dorsal view,
                  gonocoxa with inner margins clearly diverging, not parallel, forming 90° angles
                  apically ( Fig. 10 ). Penis valve moderately broad, basally parallel sided before
                  tapering apically. Gonostyli comparatively short, apical blades as wide as long.
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Areas broadly near the coast in southeastern Spain , from Málaga to Valencia ( Fig.
                  3 ). All sites are mountainous (Sierra de Mijas, Sierra Nevada, Sierra de
                  Españula, Muela de Cortes, Sierra de la Muela, Cabo Tiñoso y Roldán). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
