<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Prostheceraeus crisostomum Cuadrado &amp; Rodríguez &amp; Moro &amp; Grande &amp; Noreña 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4700623</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8263D31E928F1996E82071879F6C895B</uri>
         <article-title>Polycladida (Platyhelminthes, Rhabditophora) from Cape Verde and related regions of Macaronesia</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Prostheceraeus crisostomum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
EC7A7E2B-99FD-447D-A189-676144875AC2
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1C
, 
3
A–D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Prostheceraeus crisostomum
</tp:taxon-name>
, is dedicated to the little cat, Crisostomo, roommate during the description of this species.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
CAPE VERDE
• 
Sal Island
, 
Calheta Funda
; 
16°39′03.34″ N
, 
22°56′42,94″ W
(
Fig. 1C V
3
); 

8 Jul. 2018

; 
Leopoldo Moro
leg.; 
MNCN 4.01/2684 to 2698
(15 slides). One sagittally sectioned specimen stained with AZAN.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Shape elongated. Length 
0.5 cm
. Smooth dorsal surface; background pigmentation ivory white, darker along the middle dorsal region of the body between the cerebral eyes and the posterior end of the body. In the posterior middle end it shows a large conspicuous black spot. Small black dots on the entire dorsal surface (
Fig. 3E
). Two marginal tentacles, separate. Tentacular eyes scarce and widely dispersed between the tentacles. Cerebral eyes arrow-shaped located by the central midline (
Fig. 3F
). Bell-shaped pharynx located in the first body half. Ventral sucker in the middle of the body. Male and female genital pores well separated and located after the pharynx (
Fig. 3
G–H).
</p>
      <p>
MALE REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM. Male copulatory organ oriented forward. The muscular prominent penis papilla houses a conical, elongated stylet of pseudosclerotized nature. The rounded and well developed prostatic vesicle joins transversally with the sperm duct and lies over the penis papilla (
Fig. 3H
). Muscular seminal vesicle oval, dorsally located and caudo-frontally oriented. The 
vasa deferentia
join at the ventro-caudal region of the vesicle and the sperm duct open ventro-frontally. Seminal and prostatic vesicles open together into the proximal region of the developed penis papillae. The male atrium surrounded the penis papillae and opens near the posterior end of the pharynx.
</p>
      <p>
FEMALE REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM. Atrium elongated and highly ciliated, continues dorsally into the long but not ciliated vagina externa. The vagina externa narrows into a non-ciliated small cavity that continues in the vagina interna. It presents a widened epithelium and ends with the entry of the oviducts (
Fig. 3H
). Cement and shell glands lie around the female atrium, vagina externa and distal region of the vagina interna, but opens into the small cavity (pouch) between both vaginas.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Prostheceraeus crisostomum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
belongs to the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Prostheceraeus
</tp:taxon-name>
due to the presence of cerebral, frontal and marginal eyes, true anterior tentacles, bell-shaped pharynx, the male copulatory system with prostatic vesicle, penis armed whit stylet and the presence of multiple uterine vesicles.
</p>
      <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Prostheceraeus
</tp:taxon-name>
comprises 10 species, mainly characterized by coloration pattern, with colorful pigmentations and dorsal longitudinal lines of different widths, as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. fuscolineatus
Dixit, Raghunathan &amp; Chandra, 2017
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. roseus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. pseudolimax
Lang, 1884
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. giesbrechtii
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. vittatus
(Montagu, 1815)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. zebra
(Hyman, 1955)
</tp:taxon-name>
or with fine, transversal lines as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. crozieri
(
Hyman, 1939
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3. A–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Prostheceraeus crisostomum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(MNCN 4.01/2684 to 2698). 
A
. Whole live animal, dorsal view. 
B
. Anterior region with cerebral eyes cluster and tentacles (black arrows). 
C
. Histological section of the reproductive system stained with AZAN. 
D
. Histological section of the whole animal stained with AZAN and sagittal reconstruction. – 
E–I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudoceros rawlinsonae
var. 
galaxy
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNCN 4.01/2729 to 2798). 
E
. Whole live animal, dorsal view. 
F
. Anterior region with eyes cluster and tentacles (white arrows). 
G
. Whole live animal, ventral view. 
H
. Histological sagittal section of male and female copulatory organ. 
I
. Sagittal reconstruction of the reproductive system. Abbreviations: see Material and methods.
</p>
      <p>
Three other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Prostheceraeus
</tp:taxon-name>
show a color pattern free of lines or bands: 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. albocinctus
Lang, 1883
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. moseleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rubropunctatus
Lang, 1884
</tp:taxon-name>
. These three species, together with 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. crisostomum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, have a dotted pattern, but the background colors are different in the four species: caramel brown background with white or whitish spots and white marginal line in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. albocinctus
</tp:taxon-name>
, blue-gray or cream background with black dots and yellow marginal band in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. moseleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
and finally 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rubropunctatus
</tp:taxon-name>
with a pink to reddish background color, white dots and without marginal band. The base coloration of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. crisostomum
</tp:taxon-name>
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. albocinctus
</tp:taxon-name>
, but much clearer and almost ivory; the dorsal points are black like in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. moseleyi
</tp:taxon-name>
and lacks a marginal line or band similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rubropunctatus
</tp:taxon-name>
. All these differences delimit 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. crisostomum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
as a new species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Prostheceraeus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
