<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Stylochus salis Cuadrado &amp;
                        Rodríguez &amp; Moro &amp; Grande &amp; Noreña 2021, sp.
                        nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4562033</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F13387D2FF8AC11CFBC2FC8BFB33364E</uri>
                  <article-title>Polycladida (Platyhelminthes, Rhabditophora) from Cape Verde and
                        related regions of Macaronesia</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Stylochus salis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 8A640FC8-D74C-4617-9766-F0FB9806BD4B </p>
            <p> Figs 1C , 5 A–D </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The name of the new species, <tp:taxon-name> Stylochus salis </tp:taxon-name> refers
                  to the type locality, Sal , a Cape Verdean Island. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined (2 specs) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype CAPE VERDE • Sal Island , Calheta Funda ;
                        16°39′03.34″ N , 22°56′42.94″ W ( Fig. 1C V 3 ); 12 Nov. 2018 ; Leopoldo
                        Moro leg.; MNCN 4.01/2719 to 2723 (5 slides). One sagittal sectioned
                        specimen stained with AZAN. </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Additional material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> CAPE VERDE • 1 spec. ; Sao Vicente Island , Mindelo ( Fig.
                        1C V1 ); 16°53′46.54″ N , 24°59′32.93″ W ; 6 May 2017 ; Leopoldo Moro leg.;
                        RCCN </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> BODY. Shape elongated. Length 0.4 cm . Smooth dorsal surface. Background
                  pigmentation cream white with an orange internal outline, sometimes interrupted,
                  along the body margin and bordered by a white/ creamy outer band ( Fig. 5A ). Few
                  cerebral and marginal eyes, scattered between the tentacles and anterior end (
                  Fig. 5C ). Two small nuchal tentacles with abundant basal eyes ( Fig. 5B ).
                  Ruffled pharynx in the middle of the body and the oral pore in the end of the
                  pharynx pouch and close to the gonopores. Male and female gonopores located close
                  together in the posterior end of the body. </p>
            <p> MALE REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM. Male copulatory organ backwards oriented and provided with
                  an inconspicuous unarmed penis papilla. Prostatic vesicle muscular with granular
                  lining (polyglandulartype after Bulnes et al . 2005 ) ( Fig. 5D ). Seminal vesicle
                  elongated, empties at the distal end of the prostatic vesicle. The short penis
                  papilla and ejaculatory duct emerge in a small male atrium ( Fig. 5D ). </p>
            <p>FEMALE REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM. Shows the characteristic configuration of the genus. A
                  tubiform canal with s-shaped ending in a small widening.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Stylochus salis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. belongs to the genus
                        <tp:taxon-name> Stylochus </tp:taxon-name> due to the presence of gonopores
                  separate and arranged in the second body half. With large and much ruffled
                  pharynx. Tentacular, cerebral, marginal, and often frontal eye-spots present. Male
                  copulatory apparatus with seminal vesicle and papillate penis. Lang’s vesicle
                  lacking (after Faubel 1983 ). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Stylochus salis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. clearly differs from
                  other known species of <tp:taxon-name> Stylochus Ehrenberg, 1831 </tp:taxon-name>
                  by its peculiar cream pigmentation bordered with the internal orange outline and
                  the white/creamy outer band. The color of the eastern Atlantic known species (
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. alexandrinus </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        castaneus Palombi, 1939 </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> S. neapolitanus
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> S. plessissii Lang, 1884 </tp:taxon-name> , and
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. suesensis Ehrenberg, 1831 </tp:taxon-name> ) varies
                  between brown, light brown, reddish or beige and spotted as in <tp:taxon-name> S.
                        neapolitanus </tp:taxon-name> . None of them present a continuous (or
                  discontinuous) marginal line. </p>
            <p> The most conspicuous anatomical feature is the location of the oral pore, very close
                  to the gonopore, clearly different from the central position of the oral pore in
                  this genus. The peculiar location of the oral and genital pores distinguishes
                        <tp:taxon-name> S. salis </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. from the remaining
                  species. Such a close location of the pores could only be found in the genus
                        <tp:taxon-name> Latocestus Plehn, 1896 </tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Latocestidae, Stylochoidea</tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
