<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Marcusia alba Cuadrado &amp;
                        Rodríguez &amp; Moro &amp; Grande &amp; Noreña 2021, sp.
                        nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4562021</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F13387D2FF92C105FBC3FD5AFC44363C</uri>
                  <article-title>Polycladida (Platyhelminthes, Rhabditophora) from Cape Verde and
                        related regions of Macaronesia</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia alba </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: DE4AF1C8-D784-4AB7-B536-A1E88524115B </p>
            <p> Figs 1C , 2 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
            <p> Etymology </p>
            <p> The name of the new species, <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia alba </tp:taxon-name> , comes
                  from the Latin ‘ albus ’ (white), and refers to the ivory white coloration this
                  species shows. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined (3 specs) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype CAPE VERDE • São Vicente Island , Mindelo ;
                        16°53′46.54″ N , 24°59′32.93″ W ( Fig. 1C V1 ); 6 May 2017 ; Leopoldo Moro
                        leg.; MNCN 4.01/2620 to 2683 (64 slides). One sagittally sectioned specimen
                        stained with AZAN. </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Additional material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> CAPE VERDE • 2 specs ; São Vicente Island , Baía das Gatas
                        ; 16°54′09.33″ N , 24°54′25.25″ W ( Fig. 1C V 2 ); 6 May 2017 ; Leopoldo
                        Moro leg.; RCCN </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> BODY. Shape oval. Length 2.6 cm . Smooth dorsal surface. Background pigmentation
                  ivory white, darker along the middle dorsal region of the body. Amber dots and
                  thin brushstroke-like lines garnish the dorsal surface. A thin, dark stripe,
                  sometimes interrupted, extends along the central dorsal line ( Fig. 2A ). Two
                  delicate marginal folds, separate and pointed, could be interpreted as
                  pseudotentacles. Tentacular eyes scarce and widely dispersed over the tentacles.
                  Cerebral eyes anterior drop-shaped and crossed by the central midline. Marginal
                  eyes only at the anterior part ( Fig. 2B ). Ruffled pharynx, in the middle of the
                  body with a central oral pore. Ventral sucker at the posterior part of the body.
                  Male and female genital pore lead in a common genital atrium ( Fig. 2 D–E) that
                  opens in the posterior body region after the pharynx ( Fig. 2C ). </p>
            <p> MALE REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM. Male copulatory organ backwards oriented, with a muscular
                  penis papilla, very muscular seminal vesicle ( Fig. 2C, E ) and without a
                  prostatic vesicle, instead a simple glandular epithelium leads into the penis
                  papilla ( Fig. 2 D–E). Seminal vesicle rounded, frontal oriented and with thick
                  muscular walls, opening into the ejaculatory duct. Short ejaculatory duct opens
                  into the penis papillae. The male atrium is small and thin, connected to the
                  common atrium. </p>
            <p> FEMALE REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM ( Fig. 2C, E ). The vagina runs from the common genital
                  atrium and continues dorsally into a narrowed duct that widens into a chamber, the
                  cement pouch. The vagina continues dorsally, then curves posteriorly and ventrally
                  and ends with the entry of the oviducts. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia alba </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. belongs to the genus
                        <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia </tp:taxon-name> due to the presence of cerebral,
                  frontal and marginal eyes, male copulatory organ enclosed in a muscular bulb, the
                  absence of prostatic vesicle and the common male and female atrium genital, as
                  well as the common gonopore. </p>
            <p> Fig. 2. <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia alba </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. (MNCN 4.01/2620 to
                  2683). A . Whole live animal, dorsal view. B . Anterior region with cerebral eyes
                  cluster and pseudotentacles (white arrows). C . Histological section of the male
                  copulatory organ stained with AZAN. D . Histological section of the female
                  copulatory organ stained with AZAN. E . Sagittal reconstruction of the
                  reproduction system. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. </p>
            <p> The genus <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia </tp:taxon-name> contained only one species,
                        <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia ernesti Hyman, 1953 </tp:taxon-name> , known from
                  the coast of the Gulf of California ( Hyman 1953 ). <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia
                        ernesti </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> M. alba </tp:taxon-name> sp.
                  nov. can be easily distinguished by their coloration patterns. <tp:taxon-name>
                        Marcusia ernesti </tp:taxon-name> is black or grey with darker splotches and
                  dotted with white spots, only visible in preserved individuals after Hyman (1953)
                  , <tp:taxon-name> M. alba </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. is ivory white with brownish
                  dots and stripes. The penis papilla is spherical in <tp:taxon-name> M. alba
                  </tp:taxon-name> and elongated in <tp:taxon-name> M. ernesti </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  with the male atrium being tube-like and longer in the Californian species. </p>
            <p> Another difference lies in the eyes’ presence and distribution. <tp:taxon-name>
                        Marcusia ernesti </tp:taxon-name> presents marginal, frontal and cerebral
                  eyes as well as two characteristic eye clusters with diagnostic value ( Hyman 1953
                  ). <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia alba </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. , on the other hand,
                  has cerebral, marginal and tentacular eyes, but not frontal eyes or eye clusters. </p>
            <p> The differences listed are enough to consider <tp:taxon-name> M. ernesti
                  </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> M. alba </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. as two
                  different species of the same genus. Furthermore, the molecular analyses show the
                  genus <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia </tp:taxon-name> (represented in this case by
                        <tp:taxon-name> Marcusia alba </tp:taxon-name> sp. nov. ) as a genus closely
                  related to <tp:taxon-name> Pericelis Laidlaw, 1902 </tp:taxon-name> within the
                  family <tp:taxon-name> Anonymidae Lang, 1884 </tp:taxon-name> , but as a clearly
                  independent genus. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
