<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Jurapecten dhondtae Gale &amp; Jagt 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5036874</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4F0D7F6FF824C1874CCEC48FABCA3B61</uri>
         <article-title>The fossil record of the family Benthopectinidae (Echinodermata, Asteroidea), a reappraisal</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1405</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Jurapecten dhondtae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3CEF9EA0-184A-4352-87FA-CC5F76FED11A
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8A–H, J–V
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>

benthopectinid sp. 1 (? spp.) – 

Jagt 2000: 393
, pl. 6 figs 1–4.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Cheiraster
</tp:taxon-name>
? sp. – 

Blake &amp; Jagt 2005: 190

, pl. 5 figs 1–7.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Jurapecten
</tp:taxon-name>
in which the marginal ossicles possess a coarsely rugose sculpture and the inferomarginals bear a single, large, laterally directed spine base.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Named after Annie V. Dhondt (1942–2006), specialist of Cretaceous bivalves and close friend.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>

The inferomarginal illustrated here (
Fig. 8F
) is the holotype (
NHMM JJ 10490a
), while the other figured ossicles in lot NHMM JJ 10490 are paratypes. Additional material includes around 50 isolated ossicles (lot 
NHMM JJ 9591
). All material is from the upper Maastrichtian (Maastricht Formation, Emael Member, Lava Horizon) at the CBR-Romontbos Quarry, Eben Emael (Liège, northeast Belgium).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Superomarginals (
Fig. 8A–D
) block-like, nearly equidimensional, elongating distally. Outer face with sculpture of dense rugosities of similar size and single, crater-rimmed spine base positioned towards abactinal-distal margin. Inferomarginals (
Fig. 8E–H, J–K
) asymmetrical, proximal margins broader than distal margins; inter-inferomarginal articulation facet close to actinal surface of plate (
Fig. 8J
), forming short projection. External face of inferomarginal with sculpture of coarse, rounded rugosities and single, large crater-rimmed spine base, positioned centrally, or slightly towards abactinal margin. Ambulacrals (
Fig. 8Q–V
) with elongated, bar-like 
ambh
, broad, flat 
ambb
, with large, flat surface for 
dadam
and 
ada3
, 
padam
on short wing.Abactinal ridge and inferomarginal articulation absent (
Fig. 8V
). Adambulacrals (
Fig. 8L–M
) with concave abactinal face, actinal face with single subambulacral spine base. Enlargement of 
dadam
(
Fig. 8P
) shows irregularly ridged region, similar to that seen on extant 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectinaster filholi
(Perrier, 1885)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 8I
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The marginal ossicles (
Fig. 8A–H, J–K
) are closely similar to those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pontaster tenuispinus
(von Düben &amp; Koren, 1846)
</tp:taxon-name>
(compare with 
Fig. 4J–M, O–Q
) in shape, sculpture and spine base development,
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8
(next page). 
A–H, J–V
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jurapecten dhondtae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–D
. Superomarginals in lateral view (NHMM JJ 10490b–e). 
E–H, J–K
. Inferomarginals (NHMM JJ 10490f–j), in lateral (E–H, K) and distal (J) views. 
E
. Original of 
Jagt (2000
: pl. 6 fig. 2; NHMM JJ 9591i). 
F
. 
Holotype
(NHMM JJ 10490a). 
L–P
. Adambulacrals, in actinal (M–N) and abactinal (L, O) views, with (P) enlargement to show ridges (lot NHMM JJ 9591). 
Q–V
. Ambulacrals, in actinal (Q, S, U), abactinal (R, T) and proximal/distal (V) views (lot NHMM JJ 9591). — 
I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectinaster filholi
(Perrier, 1885)
</tp:taxon-name>
(A.S. Gale collection, unregistered), enlargement of area on actinal surface of ambulacral. Provenance: A–H, J–V. Upper Maastrichtian, CBR Romontbos quarry, Eben Emael (Liège, NE 
Belgium
), Maastricht Formation, Emael Member (Lava Horizon). I. Recent, Rockall Trough, northeast Atlantic. Abbreviations: d = distal; p = proximal. See 
Fig. 3
for detailed morphological terminology. Scale bars: A–H, J–O, Q–V = 
1 mm
; I, P = 
0.2 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
but the ambulacrals (
Fig. 8Q–V
) possess elongated heads and lack abactinal ridges and inferomarginal articulation structures, and compare better with those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jurapecten hessi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. infrajurensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(see 
Figs 6J–M
, 
7M–O
).
</p>
      <p>
The partially preserved specimen (NHMM MD 4105), described and illustrated by 
Blake &amp; Jagt (2005)
, may be conspecific, but recrystallisation of all ossicle 
types
precludes detailed comparison of the sculpture of infero- and superomarginal ossicles and ambulacral ossicles are too poorly preserved. The 
type
material of 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. dhondtae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, from the middle Emael Member, is ca 200 000 years younger than NHMM MD 4105, from the basal Gronsveld Member (compare 
Keutgen 2018
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
