<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Nearchaster spinosus Gale &amp; Jagt
                        2021, comb. nov.</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5032980</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F160A367717DFFBEFE087324FAED2433</uri>
                  <article-title>The fossil record of the family Benthopectinidae (Echinodermata,
                        Asteroidea), a reappraisal</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1405</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Nearchaster spinosus ( Blake, 1973 ) </tp:taxon-name> comb. nov. </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Mistia spinosa Blake, 1973: 48 </tp:taxon-name> , pl. 16 figs
                  30–44, pl. 17 figs 1–21, 35–36. </p>
            <p> Brisingid (?) – Zullo et al . 1964: 334 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> UCMP A-5018 (holotype no. 10675) is the type and only
                        specimen; it exposes a partly disarticulated abactinal surface showing the
                        disc and proximal portions of four arms. Large marginal spines and smaller
                        abactinal ones are visible. Marginals, adambulacrals, ambulacrals and
                        abactinal ossicles of the holotype were figured individually by Blake (1973)
                        . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Occurrence </p>
            <p> Keasey Formation (Lower Oligocene) near Mist, Oregon ( USA ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> The abactinal surface of UCMP A-5018, embedded in matrix ( Blake 1973 : pl.16 fig.
                  44), shows part of the disc and four proximal arms. Although the outline is
                  retained, the ossicles are jumbled and largely dissociated, such that
                  adambulacrals and ambulacrals are visible on the actinal surface. The marginal
                  spines, largely in place, are elongated and tapering. The abactinal spines are
                  much smaller, perhaps one-fifth the size of those on the marginals. The
                  adambulacrals are well preserved, subrectangular, with 2–3 large subadambulacral
                  spine bases, and the concave inner (abactinal) surface and ridge bearing ada2 and
                  ada3 , characteristic of benthopectinids. The ambulacrals have the typical
                  hourglass shape of benthopectinids, and asymmetry of the interambulacral muscles
                  (P1 small, P2 large) is seen. The marginals are longer than broad with a convex,
                  mound-like outer surface which carries 1–2 large spine bases and a number of
                  sparsely scattered smaller ones. The inner surface of the marginals is flat. The
                  abactinal ossicles are parapaxillae, with centrally placed, single spine bases,
                  surrounded by a ring of smaller spines. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> As recognised by Blake (1973) , the distinctive characters of the ambulacral,
                  adambulacral and marginal ossicles place this form firmly in the
                        <tp:taxon-name>Benthopectinidae</tp:taxon-name> . Comparison with extant
                  benthopectinid species studied here indicates that <tp:taxon-name> Mistia spinosa
                  </tp:taxon-name> shares important characters with the Recent Pacific genus
                        <tp:taxon-name> Nearchaster </tp:taxon-name> , including the following: </p>
            <p> 1. Adambulacrals are nearly identical in shape to those of <tp:taxon-name>
                        Nearchaster aciculosus </tp:taxon-name> , and both carry 2–3 bases for
                  subambulacral spines. </p>
            <p> 2. Marginals are closely similar to those of <tp:taxon-name> N. aciculosus
                  </tp:taxon-name> in both shape and distribution of spine bases. </p>
            <p> The overall form of the body, with large marginal spines, and shorter abactinal
                  spines on the disc is broadly similar to the development in the genera
                        <tp:taxon-name> Benthopecten </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Nearchaster
                  </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Myonotus Fisher, 1911 </tp:taxon-name> (see
                  Fisher 1911 : pls 22–26). The proportionate sizes and distributions of spines in
                        <tp:taxon-name> Mistia spinosa </tp:taxon-name> are closest to those in
                        <tp:taxon-name> Benthopecten claviger Fisher, 1910 </tp:taxon-name> ,
                        <tp:taxon-name> Myonotus intermedius (Fisher, 1910) </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> Nearchaster aciculosus (Fisher, 1910) </tp:taxon-name> (see
                  Fig. 2E–F herein). </p>
            <p> The abactinal parapaxillae of <tp:taxon-name> Mistia spinosa </tp:taxon-name> are
                  very close in structure to those of <tp:taxon-name> N. aciculosus </tp:taxon-name>
                  , with a central spine base surrounded by a ring of smaller ones. </p>
            <p> In conclusion, <tp:taxon-name> Mistia spinosa </tp:taxon-name> is a benthopectinid
                  which has remarkably detailed similarities of ossicle morphology to the
                  present-day Pacific species <tp:taxon-name> Nearchaster aciculosus
                  </tp:taxon-name> and it is therefore provisionally placed in that genus. The genus
                  thus has a history in the Pacific Ocean of at least 33 million years. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
