<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D63466E2-7CA4-4896-BFD2-4D156A280AA8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Highly derived form in which the marginal ossicles are very elongated, proximal infero-and superomarginal pairs occasionally fused, and marginals may possess 1–2 large rounded bases for attachment of conical spines. Adambulacrals with deep rounded notch to allow extension of tube feet and very large furrow spines.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>From the similarity of the marginal spination to the 1980s punk hairdos.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
Assigned species
</p>
      <p>
In addition to the 
type
species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. ruegenensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(see below).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The highly unusual marginal ossicles of this new genus (
Fig. 9E, I–J, M, P
) have been known for over 60 years, but they remained undescribed and it has hitherto not been possible to assign them to any family. The new material includes ambulacral and adambulacral ossicles, which demonstrate a likely affinity with benthopectinids in the elongated, bar-like ambulacral heads and, especially, in the nature of the ambulacral/adambulacral articulation. This is typically benthopectinid, in the abradial position of 
ada3
, the position of 
padam
on a short wing-like process and the presence of 
ada2
on a steep ridge. The abactinal ossicles are closely similar to parapaxillae of modern benthopectinids. The presence of an abactinal ridge on the ambulacrals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
may indicate that the species possessed longitudinal muscles in the arms. The genus perhaps represents a highly specialised offshoot from the mainline benthopectinids.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
