<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Punkaster spinifera Gale &amp; Jagt 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5036878</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/42052952CEA7BBF023B30CB3E6210CB3</uri>
         <article-title>The fossil record of the family Benthopectinidae (Echinodermata, Asteroidea), a reappraisal</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1405</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
89D1989C-BB8C-459E-84D4-40874052C57C
</p>
      <p>
Figs 9–11, 12J–K
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>

Zwischenplatten QA, RA – 

Müller 1953: 45
, pl. 10 figs qa–ra.

</p>
      <p>

indeterminate “cryptozonid” – 
Jagt 1999
: pl. 2 figs 1–2, 4.

</p>
      <p>

benthopectinid sp. 2 – 

Jagt 2000: 394
, pl. 6 figs 5–6, 8, 10–12, pl.7 figs 1–2.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(holotype, NHMM JJ 11736). 
A–D
. Subadambulacral or suboral spines. 
E, I–J, M, P
. Marginal ossicles. 
F–G, S
. Abactinal ossicles. 
H, Q–R
. Ambulacrals, in actinal view. 
K
. Circumoral, in actinal view. 
L, N
. Odontophore, in abactinal and actinal views. 
O
. Oral ossicle, in radial view. Provenance: uppermost Maastrichtian, ca 12 m below K/Pg boundary, Kulsti Rende, Stevns Klint, eastern Denmark. Scale bars: A–D = 5 mm; E–S = 1 mm.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(holotype, NHMM JJ 11736). 
A–C, F–H
. Adambulacral ossicles, in actinal (A, C, H) and abactinal (B, F–G) views. 
D–E
. Abactinal or marginal spines. 
I
. Abactinal ossicle. 
J–M
. Ambulacral ossicles, in actinal (J 
–
L) and abactinal (M) views. 
N–P
. Oral ossicle, in radial (N), interradial (O) and actinal (P) views. 
Q–R
. Large spines of uncertain position. Provenance: uppermost Maastrichtian, ca 12 m below K/Pg boundary, Kulsti Rende, Stevns Klint, eastern Denmark. Scale bars: A–C, F–R = 1 mm; D–E = 0.5 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
in which the marginal ossicles carry 1–2 cylindrical spine bases, which bore conical spines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Derived from the Latin ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
’, meaning bearing spines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
A set of&gt;100 associated ossicles (marginals, a single terminal, abactinals, actinals, orals, circumorals, odontophores, adambulacrals, ambulacrals, marginal spines, adambulacral spines and oral spines) from ca 12 metres below the Cretaceous-Paleogene (K/Pg) boundary in the upper Maastrichtian Højerup Member (Tor Formation; 

Surlyk 
et al
. 2006

) at Kulsti Rende, Stevns Klint, eastern Denmark, is the holotype (
NHMM JJ 11736
). Additional material includes disarticulated, yet associated, ossicles of another individual from the same locality and stratigraphical unit, as well as isolated marginal ossicles from several localities exposing Cenomanian–Maastrichtian rocks in the United Kingdom (Kent, Hampshire), Belgium, Germany (Rügen, SNSB-BGSP collections; Aachen area) and the Czech Republic, including ossicles from the lower Campanian Chalk of Downend, Hampshire (
Gale 1980
).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 11.
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, reconstructions and interpretation. 
A
. Reconstruction of cross-section of arm. 
B
. Reconstruction of ambulacral groove, with large podial basins and furrow spines. 
C
. Ambulacral base, in actinal view. 
D
. Abactinal face of adambulacral. Abbreviations: see Material and methods, and Fig. 3 for detailed morphological terminology.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Marginals are highly distinctive plates; supero- and inferomarginals elongated, broadly rectangular in lateral-abactinal aspect, with a length-parallel central rounded ridge, single oninferomarginals, bifurcating towards distal and proximal margins of superomarginals. Central, raised part of ridge carrying 2–3 spine bases, borne on cylindrical protrusions projecting from surface of ossicles. Superomarginals (
Fig. 9E, I, P
) with thin, narrow abactinal portion and opposing inferomarginals. Inferomarginals (
Fig. 9J, M
) with distinctive facet on internal surface for contact with adambulacrals. External surface of supero- and inferomarginals with complex sculpture comprising numerous small, rounded rugosities interconnected by network of stereom. Marginal spines (
Fig. 10D–E
) conical, thorny.
</p>
      <p>
Adambulacrals boot-shaped in actinal and abactinal aspect, large 
adp
forming heel, narrow distal extension (
Fig. 10A, H
); adradial margin deeply concave to accommodate large tube feet. Three to four attachment sites for 
fs
, 
sads
not present; probable 
fs
large, lanceolate (
Fig. 9A–D
). Abactinal surface (
Fig. 11D
) of adambulacrals showing 
ada3
on abradial margin, poorly defined 
ada2
. Ambulacrals (
Figs 9H, Q–R
, 
10J–M
) in proximal position (
Fig. 10J
) short, broad, distal ambulacrals with elongated 
ambh
(
Fig. 10L
). Abactinal ridge present (
Fig. 10M
). Ambulacrals (
Figs 9Q–R
, 
10K
, 
11C
) with separate wing for 
padam
, 
ada3
on abradial margin, 
dadam
large, 
ada2
poorly defined, 
ada1
large. Oral ossicles robust, subtriangular, actinal surface trapezoidal, concave centrally (
Fig. 10P
). Proximal margin with three oral spine bases and two suboral spine bases on distal margin; 
apo
stout, with shallow 
rng
.
</p>
      <p>
Abactinal ossicles flattened parapaxillae, with irregular lobed outlines and bevelled rim (
Fig. 9F–G, S
). Raised central area with finely rugose stereom which probably carried small spines. Some abactinals with single, outwardly directed spine base.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster spinifer
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. ruegenensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(see below) in the unfused proximal supero- and inferomarginals and in the presence of large marginal spine bases. As seen in our reconstruction (
Fig. 11
), the marginals were paired, not alternating, and carried a transverse fan of 4–6 outwardly directed, large conical thorny spines (
Fig. 11A
). The species had very large tube feet, protected by large, lanceolate furrow spines (
Fig. 11B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
