<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Chrispaulia spinosa Gale &amp; Jagt 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5033000</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/16E0EFF2CB5F15F5D5D9B1D1194BF735</uri>
         <article-title>The fossil record of the family Benthopectinidae (Echinodermata, Asteroidea), a reappraisal</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1405</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Chrispaulia spinosa
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
4C003A9F-1F91-44BC-91AB-2910B8EA756A
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 13D–E, H–O
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Chrispaulia
</tp:taxon-name>
in which distal inferomarginals bear an oblique row of large, bifid spine attachment sites, which carried long, flattened spines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Latin for ‘bearing spines’, in reference to the row of spine attachment sites on distal inferomarginals.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>

A distal arm fragment (
Nds LH 105.107
), comprising five marginal pairs, with articulating spines preserved, is the holotype; it is from the lower Hauterivian (
<tp:taxon-name>
Endemoceras amblygonium
</tp:taxon-name>
ammonite Zone) at Engelbostel near Hannover (northern Germany). Paratypes (
NHMUK PI EE 17998–18004
) are 35 marginal ossicles and a single oral ossicle from the upper 3 metres of the Tealby Clay (Hauterivian) at Nettleton, Lincolnshire (United Kingdom).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Arms elongated, narrow, tapering slowly (
Fig. 13D–E
); proximal superomarginals tall, block-like, bearing a single, abactinally directed, crater-like spine base. Central region of external face narrow, poorly defined, lateral surfaces broad with small rugosities for attachment of tiny cribriform spines (
Fig. 13H–I, N
; spines still articulated in 
Fig. 13D
). Distal superomarginals with or without an abactinally situated, distally directed large spine base (
Fig. 13I–J
), rugose (
Fig. 13D
) or smooth (
Fig. 13I–J
). Distal infero- and superomarginals thin, imbricating proximally; distal inferomarginals with oblique row of large, bifid spine bases, which bore flattened, lanceolate spines (
Fig. 13D
). Sharply defined grooves for cribriform organs between each infero-/superomarginal pair. Oral ossicle (
Fig. 13O
) with broad actinal face, bearing large rugosities for attachment of 
sos
; large elongate 
oradm
, low, broad apophyse.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Chrispaulia spinosa
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
differs from its congeners in its possession of 3–4 bifid spine pits on distal inferomarginals.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
