<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Punkaster ruegenensis Gale &amp; Jagt 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5036846</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9E9801DF0D55CE8ABFC3E4E574A1CA7F</uri>
         <article-title>The fossil record of the family Benthopectinidae (Echinodermata, Asteroidea), a reappraisal</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1405</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster ruegenensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
9762A572-434A-4D16-86F8-644D05201BC4
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 12A–I, L–M
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
in which the proximal supero- and inferomarginals form fused pairs; distally, they are separate. Large marginal spine bases absent.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Named after the island of Rügen (northeast 
Germany
) in the Baltic Sea.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material studied
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
The interradial marginal pair (
Fig. 12A
) is the holotype (
SNSB-BGSP 2020 XLV 31
); the other eight ossicles illustrated here are paratypes (
SNSB-BGSP 2020 XLV 32–39
), all from the upper lower Maastrichtian Chalk of Rügen, northeast Germany. Additional material includes over 30 marginal ossicles and other ossicles from the same locality (lot 
SNSB-BGSP 2020 XLV 32
).
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 12. A–I, L–M
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster ruegenensis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A–E, H–I
. Fused marginal pairs, in lateral (A–C, E: SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 31–33, SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 35) views, at right angles to margin (D, H: SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 34, SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 38) views and internal view (I: SNSB- BGSP2020XLV 39). 
F–G
. Distal inferomarginals in lateral view (SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 36–37). 
A
. Holotype(SNSB-BGSP2020XLV31). 
B–I
. Paratypes(SNSB-BGSP2020XLV32–39). 
L–M
. Probable adambulacrals, actinal view (lot SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 32). — 
J–K
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, marginals (SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 40–41). — 
N–O
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
, sp. indet., abactinal ossicles (SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 42–43). — 
P
.? 
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
, sp. indet., oral ossicle, external view (SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 44). — 
Q
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
, sp. indet., adambulacral, actinal view (SNSB-BGSP2020XLV 45). All specimens are from the upper lower Maastrichtian of Rügen, NE Germany. Abbreviation:p = proximal. See Fig. 3 for detailed morphological terminology. Scale bars: A, C–Q = 0.5 mm; B = 0.2 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Proximal marginals fused, bilobed; actinal part formed by a low, elongated, concave inferomarginal, abactinal part a subrectangular flange, formed by superomarginal (
Fig. 12A–E, H–I
). Infero- and superomarginals separated by a notch of variable size. Proximal/distal profile L-shaped, articulation facets for adjacent marginal plates oval (
Fig. 12D
). External sculpture of coarse reticulate stereom network, with rugosities, and small cylindrical projections which carried spines. Distal inferomarginals (
Fig. 12F–G
) rectangular, elongated, with similar sculpture to proximal plates. Presumed adambulacral (
Fig. 12L–M
) boot-shaped, with deep podial notch and narrow distal portion. Large 
fs
bases present, central actinal face slightly inset, coarsely reticulate, rugose.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The marginal ossicles are most unusual in that supero- and inferomarginal pairs are fused, perhaps uniquely amongst asteroids. The overall shape and sculpture of the ossicles suggest affinity with the 
type
species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Punkaster spinifera
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(see above), but the present form differs in the fused proximal marginals and in the absence of large spine bases.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
