<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE tp:taxon-treatment
  PUBLIC "-//TaxPub//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v1.0 20180101//EN" "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/plazi/TaxPub/TaxPubJATS-blue/tax-treatment-NS0-v1.dtd">
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub"><tp:treatment-meta><mixed-citation>Drolshagen, Bastian &amp; Bäckstam, Christian M. Linothele Karsch 1879</mixed-citation></tp:treatment-meta>
<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>Genus Linothele Karsch, 1879<object-id/></tp:taxon-name><xref/></tp:nomenclature>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">

<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Linothele Karsch, 1879: 546</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
(
type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Linothele curvitarsis Karsch, 1879</tp:taxon-name>
, by monotypy). — 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref26091">Raven 1980: 254</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref26139">1985: 74</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
, 75.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Neodiplura F. O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1896: 755</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
(
type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Neodiplura jelskii F. O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1896</tp:taxon-name>
, by monotypy). — 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref26556">Simon 1903: 964</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
(first synonymized with 
<tp:taxon-name>Uruchus</tp:taxon-name>
by 
<xref rid="ref26556">Simon [1903: 964]</xref>
).
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Uruchus Simon, 1889a: 400</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
(
type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>Uruchus gaujoni Simon, 1889</tp:taxon-name>
, by monotypy). — 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref26139">Raven 1985: 74</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
, 75 (first synonymized with 
<tp:taxon-name>Linothele</tp:taxon-name>
by 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref26139">Raven [1985: 74</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
, 75]).
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>

</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
<p>
DISTRIBUTION. — 
Bahamas
and South America (for South American species see 
<xref rid="fig-8--131-142-1424-1442-">Fig. 4</xref>
).
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
<p>
DIAGNOSIS. — 
<tp:taxon-name>Linothele</tp:taxon-name>
can be distinguished from all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Diplurinae</tp:taxon-name>
by the absence of a maxillary lyra.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>DESCRIPTION</p>
<p>Small to large diplurid spiders. Eyes: present, on a common tubercle. Fovea: transverse, recurved. Labium: subquadrate, with few, or no cuspules. Sternum: three pairs of sigillae, all submarginal. Chelicerae: one row of ventral conical teeth on promargin. Maxillae: longer than wide with short anterior lobe bearing a serrula. Maxillary lyra: absent. Claws on pedipalp tarsi: with a single row of teeth in juveniles and females. Leg tarsi: aspinose; dorsally with a zig-zag row of trichobothria, metatarsi with one row of trichobothria, no trichobothria in proximal third of metatarsi; scopuliform setae present on anterior tarsi and metatarsi. Tarsal claws of legs: paired tarsal claws with a double row of teeth; unpaired claws of leg tarsi with teeth very short, or absent. Spinnerets: PLS elongated, with digitiform apical segment. Cymbium: equally bilobate, scopulate and aspinose. Palpal organ: pyriform with small subtegulum. Males with megaspine at retroventral apex of tibia I; metatarsus I with MP in 1:3B.</p>
<p>
Variability
</p>
<p>
See 
<xref>Table 1</xref>
. Examination of available material revealed variation of ± 5 CT and more than ± 30 MC between specimens of a single species. In single specimen we were able to observe variation from one side to the other of up to ± 3 CT and more than ± 30 MC.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
<p>REMARKS</p>
<p>
The collections of IBSP and MNRJ were destroyed in fires of 2010 and 2018, respectively. The MNRJ collection was reviewed by Silva-Moreira 
et al.
(2010), who were unable to locate many of the relevant 
types
at that time. Following 
<xref rid="ref25047">
Kury 
et al
. (2018)
</xref>
, material not located in MNRJ collection in 2010 might have survived the fire of 2018.
</p>
<p>
Unfortunately, the loan request on 
holotypes
to NHRS was rejected by QCAZ for all species described by 
<xref rid="ref24415">Dupérré &amp; Tapia (2015)</xref>
and, additionally, it was not possible to arrange a loan on any of the other types. N. Dupérré provided images and confirmed a “weak” scopula with “[…] two parallel lines” for all described species (pers. comm.).
</p>
<p>As mentioned by Ríos-Tamayo &amp; Goloboff (2012), it seems common for mygalomorphs with many spermathecal lobes, or processes to often show minor differences in the number or shape of lobes and processes of both sides. Presumably, lobes and processes with thin, weak ducts may easily get broken during moults, producing minor differences in successive moults of the adult female. Our research presented here suggests the same applies to vesicles.</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<ref-list><ref id="ref25891"><mixed-citation>PICKARD- CAMBRIDGE F. O. 1896. - On the Theraphosidae of the lower Amazons: being an account of the new genera and species of this group of spiders discovered during the expedition of the steamship Faraday up the river Amazons. Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London 1896: 716 - 766. https: // doi. org / 10.1111 / j. 1096 - 3642.1896. tb 03076. x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24415"><mixed-citation>DUPERRE N. &amp; TAPIA E. 2015. - Descriptions of four kleptoparasitic spiders of the genus Mysmenopsis (Araneae, Mysmenidae) and their potential host spider species in the genus Linothele (Araneae, Dipluridae) from Ecuador. Zootaxa 3972 (3): 343. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 3972.3.3</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24989"><mixed-citation>KARSCH F. 1879. - Arachnologische Beitrage. Zeitschrift fur die gesammten Naturwissenschaften 52: 534 - 562.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25047"><mixed-citation>KURY A. B., GIUPPONI A. P. L. &amp; MENDES A. C. 2018. - Immolation of Museu Nacional, Rio de Janeiro - unforgettable fire and irreplaceable loss. Journal of Arachnology 46 (3): 556 - 558. https: // doi. org / 10.1636 / JoA-S- 18 - 094.1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26091"><mixed-citation>RAVEN R. J. 1980. - The evolution and biogeography of the mygalomorph spider family Hexathelidae (Araneae, Chelicerata). Journal of Arachnology 8 (3): 251 - 266. https: // www. biodiversitylibrary. org / page / 53032632</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26139"><mixed-citation>RAVEN R. J. 1985. - The spider infraorder Mygalomorphae (Araneae): cladistics and systematics. Bulletin of the American Museum of natural History 182: 1 - 180.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26556"><mixed-citation>SIMON E. 1903. - Etudes arachnologiques. 34 e Memoire. LVI. Descriptions de deux especes nouvelles de la famille des Avicularides recueillis dans l'Ecuador par M. le Dr Rivet et faisant partie des collections du Museum de Paris. Annales de la Societe Entomologique de France 72: 314. https: // www. biodiversitylibrary. org / page / 8248189</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26423"><mixed-citation>SIMON E. 1889 a. - Revision des Aviculariidae de la Republique de l'Ecuador. Actes de la Societe Linneenne de Bordeaux 42: 399 - 404.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></tp:taxon-treatment>