<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE tp:taxon-treatment
  PUBLIC "-//TaxPub//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v1.0 20180101//EN" "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/plazi/TaxPub/TaxPubJATS-blue/tax-treatment-NS0-v1.dtd">
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub"><tp:treatment-meta><mixed-citation>Fabrizi, Silvia, Liu, Wan-Gang, Bai, Ming, Yang, Xing-Ke &amp; Ahrens, Dirk Maladera euphorbiae</mixed-citation></tp:treatment-meta>
<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>Maladera euphorbiae ( Burmeister, 1855 )<object-id/></tp:taxon-name><xref/></tp:nomenclature>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>
<xref rid="fig-24--151-250-1908-1932-">Figures 3</xref>
J–M, 85
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">

<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Serica euphorbiae Burmeister, 1855: 177</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref331423">Brenske 1897: 362</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Amaladera euphorbiae : Reitter 1896: 186</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref331602">Dalla Torre 1912: 19</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref333942">Medvedev 1952: 145</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Maladera ( Amaladera ) euphorbiae : Ahrens 2006b: 234</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref330155">2007b: 18</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Serica fusca Ballion, 1870: 339</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; syn by 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref335090">Reitter 1896: 186</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref331423">Brenske 1897: 362</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>

</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
<p>
Additional material examined.
<tp:material-citation>

<named-content content-type="named-content">China</named-content>
:

<named-content content-type="specimenCount">1 ♂</named-content>
“ 
<named-content content-type="location">Ining</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="collectingRegion">Xinjiang</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="date">
<named-content content-type="collectingDate">VI.1984</named-content>
</named-content>
” (
<named-content content-type="collectionCode">IZAS</named-content>
)
</tp:material-citation>
, 
<tp:material-citation>
<named-content content-type="specimenCount">2 ♂♂</named-content>
“ 
<named-content content-type="location">Yining</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="collectingRegion">Xinjiang</named-content>
, mid of 
<named-content content-type="date">
<named-content content-type="collectingDate">VI.1983</named-content>
</named-content>
, leg. 
<named-content content-type="collectorName">Wang Aijing</named-content>
” (
<named-content content-type="collectionCode">IZAS</named-content>
)
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>
Redescription.
Length: 
7.5 mm
, length of elytra: 
5.2 mm
, width: 
4.1 mm
. Body wide, oval, yellowish brown, dorsal surface dull, labroclypeus, tarsomeres, and tibiae shiny, glabrous.
</p>
<p>
Labroclypeus moderately wide, lateral margins straight and moderately convergent, lateral margins produce with ocular canthus a blunt angle, anterior angles moderately convex, anterior margin distinctly emarginate medially, margins weakly reflexed; surface flat and moderately shiny, coarsely and densely punctate, distance between punctures smaller their diameter, with numerous long erect setae; smooth area in front of eyes twice as wide as long; frontoclypeal suture finely incised, slightly elevated and bluntly angled medially; ocular canthus moderately wide and short (1/3 of ocular diameter), finely and densely punctate, with a short terminal seta. Eyes moderately large, ratio diameter/ interocular width: 0.65. Frons with fine and moderately dense punctures, with a few single setae beside eyes. Antenna with nine antennomeres, club with three antennomeres and straight, 1.2 times as long as remaining antennomeres combined. 
Mentum
convexly elevated and flattened anteriorly.
</p>
<p>Pronotum widest at base, lateral margins in basal half straight and weakly convergent anteriorly, in anterior half moderately convex and convergent anteriorly, anterior angles nearly blunt and weakly produced, posterior angles blunt; anterior margin convex, with complete and fine marginal line; basal margin without marginal line; surface finely and densely punctate, punctures with microscopic setae only, setae of lateral and anterior margin sparse; hypomeron carinate. Scutellum wide, triangular, punctation as in pronotum.</p>
<p>Elytra convex, widest at posterior third, striae finely impressed, finely punctate, intervals weakly convex, finely and densely punctate, punctures concentrated along striae, with minute setae in punctures, odd intervals with a few erect short setae; epipleura ending at strongly rounded external apical angle of elytra, sparsely setose; apex of elytra with a fine membraneous rim of short microtrichomes.</p>
<p>Ventral face coarsely and densely punctate, nearly glabrous, only metasternal plate and lateral metacoxa with a few robust setae. Distance between mesocoxae little less than width of mesofemur. Ratio of length of metepisternum/metacoxa: 1/1.3. Abdominal sternites finely and moderately densely punctate, each with a row of coarse punctures bearing each a robust seta; penultimate sternite medially retracted, ultimate sternite twice as long as penultimate. Pygidium moderately convex, coarsely and densely punctate, on apex with a few long setae.</p>
<p>Legs moderately long and wide; femora superficially and sparsely punctate, with two longitudinal rows of setae. Metafemur shiny, anterior margin acute, without adjacent serrated line, anterior longitudinal row of setae present; posterior ventral margin almost straight, little widened in apical half and smooth, and dorsal posterior margin also smooth, densely setose. Metatibia moderately long and wide, dorsal and ventral margin subparallel, ratio width/length: 1/3.6, sharply carinate dorsally, with two groups of spines, basal one at basal third, apical one at two thirds of metatibial length, basally with a few single fine and short setae; lateral face weakly longitudinally convex, with fine and sparse punctures; ventral margin with three widely separated spines, of which the distal one is more distant; medial face impunctate, apex shallowly and concavely emarginate interiorly near tarsal articulation. Tarsomeres dorsally very sparsely and finely punctate, neither laterally nor dorsally carinate, ventrally finely sparsely setose; metatarsomeres ventrally with a strongly serrated ridge, first metatarsomere slightly longer than following tarsomere and as long as dorsal tibial spur. Protibia moderately long, bidentate; anterior claws symmetrical, basal tooth of both claws bluntly truncate at apex.</p>
<p>
Aedeagus: 
<xref rid="fig-24--151-250-1908-1932-">Fig. 3</xref>
J–L. Habitus: 
<xref rid="fig-24--151-250-1908-1932-">
Fig. 
3M
</xref>
.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
<p>
Distribution.
See map (
<xref rid="fig-344--151-250-1053-1077-">Fig. 85</xref>
) and 
<xref>Table 1</xref>
.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<ref-list><ref id="ref329946"><mixed-citation>Ahrens, D. (2006 b) Sericinae. In: Lobl, I. &amp; Smetana, A. (Eds.), Catalogue of Palaearctic Coleoptera. Volume 3. Scarabaeoidea-Scirtoidea-Dascilloidea-Buprestoidea-Byrrhoidea. Apollo Books, Stenstrup, pp. 229 - 248.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref330155"><mixed-citation>Ahrens, D. (2007 b) Taxonomic changes and an updated Catalogue of Palearctic Sericini (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Melolonthinae). Zootaxa, 1504 (1), 1 - 51. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 1504.1.1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref331292"><mixed-citation>Ballion, E. (1870) Eine Centurie neuer Kafer aus der Fauna des russischen Reiches. Bulletin de la Societe Imperiale des Naturalistes de Moscou, 43, 320 - 353.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref331423"><mixed-citation>Brenske, E. (1897) Die Serica - Arten der Erde. Berliner Entomologische Zeitschrift, 42, 345 - 468. https: // doi. org / 10.1002 / mmnd. 18970420310</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref331559"><mixed-citation>Burmeister, H. (1855) Handbuch der Entomologie. Vierter Band. Besondere Entomologie. Fortsetzung. 2. Abteilung, Coleoptera Lamellicornia Phyllophaga chaenochela. T. C. F. Enslin, Berlin, x + 569 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref331602"><mixed-citation>Dalla Torre, K. W. (1912) Scarabaeidae: Melolonthinae I. In: Junk, W. &amp; Schenkling, S. (Eds.), Coleopterorum Catalogus, 45, pp. 1 - 84.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref333942"><mixed-citation>Medvedev, S. I. (1952) Fauna USSR: Coleoptera 10 Nr. 1: Lamellicornia (Scarabaeidae), subfam. Melolonthinae. Part 2. Izdatelstvo Akademii Nauk SSSR, Moskva, Leningrad, 276 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref335090"><mixed-citation>Reitter, E. (1896) Uebersicht der mir bekannten palaearktischen, mit der Coleopteren-Gattung Serica verwandten Gattungen und Arten. Wiener Entomologische Zeitung, 15, 180 - 188. https: // doi. org / 10.1002 / mmnd. 48018960133</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></tp:taxon-treatment>