<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE tp:taxon-treatment
  PUBLIC "-//TaxPub//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v1.0 20180101//EN" "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/plazi/TaxPub/TaxPubJATS-blue/tax-treatment-NS0-v1.dtd">
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub"><tp:treatment-meta><mixed-citation>Gill, Anthony C., Pogonoski, John J., Moore, Glenn I. &amp; Johnson, Jeffrey W. Plectranthias kamii Randall</mixed-citation></tp:treatment-meta>
<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>Plectranthias kamii Randall<object-id/></tp:taxon-name><xref/></tp:nomenclature>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>
<xref rid="fig-53--151-250-1930-1954-">Figures 18</xref>
, 
<xref rid="fig-">26–27</xref>
; 
<xref>Tables 1–16</xref>
, 
<xref>22</xref>
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="vernacular_names">
<p>Common name: Kami’s Perchlet</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">

<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:taxon-name>Plectranthias kamii Randall 1980: 141</tp:taxon-name>
, fig. 14, tab. 10 (
type
locality: 
Okinawa
, Ryukyu Islands, 
Japan
).— 

<tp:nomenclature-citation>Anderson 2018: 29</tp:nomenclature-citation>

(checklist).— 

<tp:nomenclature-citation>Parenti &amp; Randall 2020: 26</tp:nomenclature-citation>

(checklist).
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:taxon-name>Plectranthias yamakawai</tp:taxon-name>
[non 
<xref rid="ref76263">Yoshino 1972</xref>
].— 

<tp:nomenclature-citation>
Hobbs 
et al.
2014a: 194
</tp:nomenclature-citation>

, tab. 1 (list, 
Christmas Island
).
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>

</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
<p>
Diagnosis.
The following combination of characters distinguishes 
<tp:taxon-name>P. kamii</tp:taxon-name>
from congeners: dorsal rays X,17–18; third dorsal spine longest; pectoral rays 13; lateral line complete, with 32–38 tubed scales; scales below lateral line to origin of anal fin 16–20.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>
Description of Australian specimens.
Dorsal rays X,18, all or all but first segmented rays branched; anal rays III,7, all segmented rays branched; pectoral rays 13/13, all but upper ray branched; pelvic fin I,5, all segmented rays branched; upper procurrent caudal-fin rays 7–8; lower procurrent caudal-fin rays 6; principal caudal-fin rays 9+8; branched caudal fin rays 8+7; total caudal-fin rays 30–31; lateral line complete with 34–37 scales; scales above lateral line to origin of dorsal fin 4–5; scales above lateral line to base of fifth dorsal spine 3–4; scales below lateral line to origin of anal fin 16–20; diagonal rows of scales on cheek 9–10, including 2 overlying preopercular canal; predorsal scales 19–20, extending to anterior interorbital area, at about vertical through anterior edge of eye; circumpeduncular scales 16; gill rakers 5–6+11–12=17, the upper 4–5 and lower 3–4 rudiments; pseudobranchial filaments 19–22; branchiostegal rays 7.
</p>
<p>Vertebrae 10+16; supraneurals 3; predorsal formula 0/0+0/2/1+1; dorsal pterygiophores in interneural spaces 9–13 1/1/1+1/1+1/1+1; no trisegmental pterygiophores associated with dorsal fin; terminal dorsal pterygiophore in interneural space 18; no trisegmental pterygiophores associated with anal fin; terminal anal pterygiophore in interhaemal space 5; ribs present on vertebrae 3 through 10; epineurals present on vertebrae 1 through 10–11; parhypural and hypurals autogenous; well-developed hypurapophysis on parhypural; epurals 3; single uroneural (posterior uroneural absent); ventral tip of cleithrum with well-developed posteroventral process; proximal tip of first anal-fin pterygiophore near distal tips of parapophyses on vertebra 10.</p>
<p>Dorsal-fin spines with fleshy tabs on their distal tips, the tab on third spine longest; third dorsal spine longest; dorsal fin incised before first segmented-fin ray (tenth spine 57.3–58.1% length of first segmented ray); second anal-fin spine longest and stoutest; anal fin slightly pointed with second segmented ray longest; caudal fin emarginate; lower 6 pectoral fin rays thickened, with membranes between thickened rays deeply incised; eighth (counting from dorsal-most) pectoral ray longest, reaching vertical through base of second anal-fin spine; pelvic fins short, reaching about two-thirds way to anus, second segmented ray longest.</p>
<p>
Morphometric data are summarised in 
<xref>Table 22</xref>
.
</p>
<fig id="fig-68--151-250-1523-1547-" fig-type="figure" position="float"><caption>
<p>
FIGURE 26.
<tp:taxon-name>Plectranthias kamii</tp:taxon-name>
, photo from ROV 
SuBastian
, 471 m, Magdelaine Cay, Coral Sea, Australia. Photo courtesy of Schmidt Ocean Institute, Visioning Coral Sea Marine Park expedition.
</p>
</caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/record/4471979/files/figure.png"/></fig>
<p>Mouth large, slightly oblique, posterior margin of maxilla reaching vertical through posterior edge of pupil; maxilla expanded posteriorly, with long, low, lateral ridge running parallel to dorsal margin; small splint-like supramaxilla present; mouth terminal; upper jaw with 2 fixed, short stout outer canines on either side of symphysis, flanked internally by villiform band with about 7–8 rows of depressible, smaller, sharp-tipped teeth, with inner rows becoming progressively longer and caniniform near symphysis, band reducing to 4 rows posteriorly, the teeth on outer row subequal to other rows, but slightly stouter and fixed; lower jaw with 2–3 short, stout fixed canines at front of jaw, a villiform band of about 5–6 rows of small depressible teeth at symphysis, teeth becoming progressively longer and more caniniform on inner rows near symphysis, two enlarged, curved canines on middle of jaw, band narrows to 2–3 rows posteriorly, the inner row teeth larger and slightly curved; vomer with chevron of 2–3 rows of sharp-tipped conical teeth; palatine with a band of 2–3 rows of small, sharp-tipped conical teeth; ectopterygoid and mesopterygoid edentate; tongue narrow, pointed and edentate.</p>
<fig id="fig-69--151-250-1941-1965-" fig-type="figure" position="float"><caption>
<p>
FIGURE 27.
<tp:taxon-name>Plectranthias kamii</tp:taxon-name>
, Australian specimens: A) freshly dead specimen, approx. 280 mm SL, not retained, south of Lord Howe Island; B) WAM P.34014-001, 238 mm SL, freshly dead, Christmas Island; C) QM I.20683, 173 mm SL, preserved, east of Murray Isles, Coral Sea. Photos by (A) Scott Wilson, (B) S. Newman &amp; J.P. Hobbs, (C) A.C. Gill.
</p>
</caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/record/4471981/files/figure.png"/></fig>
<p>Opercle with 3 flat spines, middle spine longest, upper spine concealed by scales; preopercle with 26–30 serrations on posterior margin, and two enlarged antrorse spines ventrally; interopercle and subopercle smooth. Anterior nostril positioned at middle of snout, tubular with short posterior flap, barely reaching posterior nostril when appressed; posterior nostril at anterior border of orbit, with raised rim but no flap.</p>
<p>Scales ctenoid with peripheral cteni; lateral line broadly arched over pectoral fin following body contour to caudal-fin base; no scales on chin, branchiostegal membranes, maxilla, snout or infraorbital bones; no auxiliary scales on head or body; dorsal fin with low basal scale sheath of 2–4 scales along soft part of fin; anal fin with low basal scaly sheath posteriorly, with some small scales extending on to fin membranes; caudal fin with scaly basal sheath, with small scales extending on to basal third to half of fin membranes; pectoral fins with basal sheath and small scales extending on to fin membranes.</p>
<p>
Colour in life (based on photos of freshly dead and live fishes from the Coral Sea, Lord Howe Island and 
Christmas Island
; 
<xref rid="fig-">Figures 26–27</xref>
): Head and body reddish pink to white, paler ventrally, marked with following yellow-brown to bright yellow blotches and bars: several small blotches dorsally on head, nape and snout tip; a short stripe from anterior edge of eye to middle of jaws; a diffuse oblique bar from posteroventral part of eye to preopercle angle; a diffuse blotch covering most of operculum; a curved stripe from posterior edge of eye to posterior part of nape and dorsal origin; an oblique bar extending from bases of fourth through sixth dorsal spines to just behind posterior edge of opercle; an oblique bar extending from bases of seventh through ninth dorsal spines to upper third of body; an oblique bar extending from bases of first through third segmented dorsal rays to upper third of body; a pupil-sized spot or short bar beneath bases of eighth through tenth segmented dorsal rays; a similar spot beneath terminal three or four dorsal segmented rays; a median spot on mid-dorsal part of caudal peduncle, a bar over posterior edge of caudal peduncle; a large elongate blotch mid-laterally below bars from seven through ninth dorsal spines and first through third segmented dorsal rays; smaller elongate mid-lateral blotch beneath middle part of soft dorsal fin; and elongate blotch over middle part of caudal peduncle; adjacent yellow-brown to bright yellow markings sometimes coalescing, sometimes overlain with small blue-grey to dark grey spots and blotches; eye pale pink to white, yellow-brown to orange where adjacent to yellow-brown to yellow stripes on head, with dark blue-grey to black crescent in front of pupil; dorsal fin reddish pink to white, with yellow-brown to bright yellow markings from body extending on to fins; first dorsal spine with dark grey basal spot; anal fin pale pink or white to orange; caudal fin pink to white dorsally and ventrally, pinkish hyaline to orange centrally; distal margins of caudal, soft dorsal and soft anal fins of larger specimen dusky grey; pelvic fins white to pink or orange, paler on fin spine; pectoral fins whitish hyaline to pink.
</p>
<p>
Colour in preservative (
<xref rid="fig-69--151-250-1941-1965-">Figure 27C</xref>
): Head and body pale tan; yellow-brown to bright yellow markings remain, becoming dusky brown; first dorsal spine with dusky brown basal spot; yellow-brown markings on fin remain, becoming dusky brown; fins otherwise pale tan, with distal margins of caudal, soft dorsal and soft anal fins dusky brown.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
<p>
Remarks.
A very large 
<tp:taxon-name>Plectranthias</tp:taxon-name>
species (largest known specimen 
34 cm
total length, or approximately 
280 mm
SL; 
<xref rid="fig-69--151-250-1941-1965-">Figure 27A</xref>
), 
<tp:taxon-name>P. kamii</tp:taxon-name>
was originally described from Okinawa, Ryukyu Islands (
type
locality), 
Palau
and 
Guam
. It has since been recorded from 
Samoa
(
<xref rid="ref75876">Wass 1984</xref>
), Moorea (
<xref rid="ref74170">Randall 1996</xref>
), 
Taiwan
(
<xref rid="ref70570">Chen &amp; Shao 2002</xref>
), 
New Caledonia
(
<xref rid="ref70887">
Fricke 
et al.
2011
</xref>
) and 
Sulawesi
, 
Indonesia
(
<xref rid="ref73747">
Peristiwady 
et al.
2018
</xref>
). We newly record this species from 
Australia
on the basis of a specimen collected east of the Murray Islands, Coral Sea (
<xref rid="fig-69--151-250-1941-1965-">Figure 27C</xref>
), several individuals photographed from RV 
Falkor
ROV 
SuBastian
dives at Madgelaine Cays, Diamond Islet and Lihou Reef, Coral Sea (
<xref rid="fig-68--151-250-1523-1547-">Figure 26</xref>
), an individual collected and photographed (but not retained) from near Lord Howe Island (
<xref rid="fig-69--151-250-1941-1965-">Figure 27A</xref>
), and a specimen collected from 
Christmas Island
(
<xref rid="fig-69--151-250-1941-1965-">Figure 27B</xref>
). The last-mentioned was the basis for 
<xref rid="ref71758">
Hobbs 
et al.
(2014a)
</xref>
record of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. yamakawai</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Christmas Island
. Although the specimen resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>P. yamakawai</tp:taxon-name>
in having dark spots on the body, these are mostly arranged in and around yellow markings (versus evenly scattered over the upper body in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. yamakawai</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<xref rid="fig-71--151-250-963-987-">Figure 28</xref>
). Moreover, the third dorsal spine is longest (versus the fourth in 
<tp:taxon-name>P. yamakawai</tp:taxon-name>
), and the specimen lacks the large pink to red spot (grey-brown in preservative) beneath the posterior part of the dorsal fin that is characteristic of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. yamakawai</tp:taxon-name>
. The specimens and photographs agree well with published descriptions and photographs of 
<tp:taxon-name>P. kamii</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
<p>
Allen &amp; Walsh (2015) recorded a depth range of 
183–280 m
for 
<tp:taxon-name>P. kamii</tp:taxon-name>
. All of the Australian specimens and observations were from deeper than 
280 m
: 
350 m
for the Lord Howe individual, 
398 m
for the 
Christmas Island
specimen, 
480 m
for the Murray Islands specimen, and 
465–534 m
for the ROV 
SuBastian
observations.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
<p>
Material examined.
<tp:material-citation>
<named-content content-type="emphasis">
<named-content content-type="collectingCountry">Australia</named-content>
.
</named-content>
<named-content content-type="collectionCode">QM</named-content>
I. 
<named-content content-type="quantity">20683, 173 mm</named-content>
SL, 
<named-content content-type="collectingRegion">Queensland</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="collectingMunicipality">Coral Sea</named-content>
, east of 
<named-content content-type="location">Murray Islands</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="geoCoordinate">9°53′S</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="geoCoordinate">144°23′E</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="quantity">
<named-content content-type="elevation">480 m</named-content>
</named-content>
, trawl, 
<named-content content-type="collectorName">C. Jones</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="collectingRegion">Queensland</named-content>
<named-content content-type="collectorName">Fisheries Service</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="date">
<named-content content-type="collectingDate">28 May 1983</named-content>
</named-content>
</tp:material-citation>
; 
<tp:material-citation>
<named-content content-type="collectionCode">WAM</named-content>
P.34014-001, 238.0 mm SL, 
<named-content content-type="location">Christmas Island</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="geoCoordinate">10°29′S</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="geoCoordinate">105°37′E</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="quantity">
<named-content content-type="elevation">398 m</named-content>
</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="collectorName">S. Newman</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="date">
<named-content content-type="collectingDate">12 Mar 2014</named-content>
</named-content>
</tp:material-citation>
. 
<tp:material-citation>
<named-content content-type="emphasis">
<named-content content-type="collectingCountry">Taiwan</named-content>
.
</named-content>
<named-content content-type="collectionCode">ASIZP</named-content>
<named-content content-type="quantity">60270, 162 mm</named-content>
SL (radiograph), 
<named-content content-type="collectingRegion">Pingtung</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="collectorName">Hengchun, J.P</named-content>
. 
<named-content content-type="collectorName">Chen</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="date">
<named-content content-type="collectingDate">9 Apr 1999</named-content>
</named-content>
</tp:material-citation>
(radiograph from 
<xref rid="ref74699">Shao, 2020</xref>
).
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<ref-list><ref id="ref70044"><mixed-citation>Anderson, W. D. Jr (2018) Annotated checklist of anthiadine fishes (Percoidei: Serranidae). Zootaxa, 4475 (1), 1 - 62. https: // doi. org / 10.11646 / zootaxa. 4475.1.1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref70570"><mixed-citation>Chen, J. P. &amp; Shao, K. T. (2002) Plectranthias sheni, a new species and P. kamii, a new record of anthiine fishes (Perciformes: Serranidae) from Taiwan. Zoological Studies, 41, 63 - 68.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref70887"><mixed-citation>Fricke, R., Kulbicki, M. &amp; Wantiez, L. (2011) Checklist of the fishes of New Caledonia, and their distribution in the Southwest Pacific Ocean (Pisces). Stuttgarter Beitrage zur Naturkunde A, Neue Serie, 4, 341 - 463.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref71758"><mixed-citation>Hobbs, J. P., Newman, S. J., Mitsopoulos, G. E. A., Travers, M. J., Skepper, C. L., Gilligan, J. J., Allen, G. R., Choat, H. J. &amp; Ayling, A. M. (2014 a) Checklist and new records of Christmas Island fishes: the influence of isolation, biogeography and habitat availability on species abundance and community composition. Raffles Bulletin of Zoology, 30, 184 - 202.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref71758"><mixed-citation>Hobbs, J. P., Newman, S. J., Mitsopoulos, G. E. A., Travers, M. J., Skepper, C. L., Gilligan, J. J., Allen, G. R., Choat, H. J. &amp; Ayling, A. M. (2014 a) Checklist and new records of Christmas Island fishes: the influence of isolation, biogeography and habitat availability on species abundance and community composition. Raffles Bulletin of Zoology, 30, 184 - 202.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref73460"><mixed-citation>Parenti, P. &amp; Randall, J. E. (2020) An annotated checklist of the fishes of the family Serranidae of the world with description of two new related families of fishes. FishTaxa, 15, 1 - 170.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref73747"><mixed-citation>Peristiwady, T., Du, J., Hukom, F. D., Makatipu, P. C. &amp; Loh, K. H. (2018) Plectranthias kamii Randll, 1980 (Perciformes: Serranidae) collected from Bitung, North Sulawesi: first record from the Southwest Pacific Ocean. Acta Oceanologica Sinica, 37, 73 - 77. https: // doi. org / 10.1007 / s 13131 - 018 - 1289 - y</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref74170"><mixed-citation>Randall, J. E. (1996) Two new anthiine fishes of the genus Plectranthias (Perciformes: Serranidae), with a key to the species. Micronesica, 29, 113 - 131.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref74699"><mixed-citation>Shao, K. T. (2020) The Fish Datebase of Taiwan. WWW Web electronic publication: http: // fishdb. sinica. edu. tw (accessed 3 March 2020)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref75876"><mixed-citation>Wass, R. C. (1984) An annotated checklist of the fishes of Samoa. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Technical Reports, National Marine Fisheries Service, Special Scientific Report - Fisheries, 781, 1 - 43.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref76263"><mixed-citation>Yoshino, T. (1972) Plectranthias yamakawai, a new anthiine fish from Ryukyu Islands, with a revision of the genus Plectranthias. Japanese Journal of Ichthyology, 19, 49 - 56.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></tp:taxon-treatment>