<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE tp:taxon-treatment
  PUBLIC "-//TaxPub//DTD Taxonomic Treatment Publishing DTD v1.0 20180101//EN" "https://raw.githubusercontent.com/plazi/TaxPub/TaxPubJATS-blue/tax-treatment-NS0-v1.dtd">
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub"><tp:treatment-meta><mixed-citation>Arai, Mikihito &amp; Fujita, Toshihiko Fromia labeosa Arai &amp; Fujita 2021, sp. nov.</mixed-citation></tp:treatment-meta>
<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name>Fromia labeosa sp. nov.<object-id/></tp:taxon-name><xref/></tp:nomenclature>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="vernacular_names">
<p>[New Japanese name: Ogasawara-juzuberi-hitode]</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>
(
<xref rid="fig-2--822-853-1874-1896-">Figs 2C</xref>
, 
<xref rid="fig-7--157-188-1539-1561-">5</xref>
)
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">

<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
Fromia
sp.: 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref10506">Arai et al. 2018: 194</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
, 196.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>

</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
<p>
Material examined.
<tp:material-citation>
<named-content content-type="typeStatus">Holotype</named-content>
: 
<named-content content-type="collectionCode">NSMT</named-content>
E-9297, KY-16-14, 
<named-content content-type="location">East of Ototo-jima Island</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="quantity">
<named-content content-type="elevation">56.6–62.9 m</named-content>
</named-content>
</tp:material-citation>
. 
Paratypes
: 
NSMT
E-9293, KY-08-25, West of Nishi-jima Island, 
127–129 m
; 
NSMT
E-9294 and E-9295, KY-16-06, Northwest of Ototojima Island, 
135–137 m
; 
NSMT
E-9296, KY-16-09, East of Chichi-jima Island, 
90.5–94.6 m
; 1 individual each.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
<p>
Diagnosis.
A species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Fromia</tp:taxon-name>
with a small disc and slender, slightly arched arms. At R= 
31.3 mm
, abactinal plates arranged in five longitudinal rows at base of arms. Superomarginal plates only slightly convex, not alternating but regularly decreasing in size toward the tip of arms. Coarse granules enlarged at center of plates. Papulae single and confined on the abactinal surface. Adambulacral plates bear three (rarely two or four) furrow spines and five to nine thicker subambulacral granules graduating in size toward those on neighboring actinal/marginal plates. Oral plates bear five oral spines on the margin and four to six suboral spines on the rest of the plate. Large, elliptical pedicellariae on many actinal plates with their major axis oblique to the ambulacra.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>

Description of 
holotype
.

R= 
31.3 mm
, r= 
8.6 mm
, R/r= 3.6, width of arm is 9.0 mm at base, 
5.4 mm
at half of R, and 
2.9 mm
at 1/10 R from the tip. Body is slightly arched at both sides, and the abactinal interradial areas are sunken. Arms taper to blunt tips.
</p>
<p>
Abactinal plates are polygonal, weakly lobate, arranged in staggered longitudinal series where there are five rows at the base of arms (
<xref rid="fig-7--157-188-1539-1561-">Fig. 5C</xref>
). Hemispherical glassy bosses (crystal bodies) occur on the abactinal plates. Madreporite is single, circular, and about 
0.9 mm
in diameter, located at about one half r from the anal aperture. Gyri do not regularly radiate from the center of the madreporite. The anal aperture is single and surrounded by six slightly larger ossicles. Terminal plates are conical, truncated at the tip. Several tubercles encircle the top of terminal plates.
</p>
<fig id="fig-7--157-188-1539-1561-" fig-type="figure" position="float"><caption>
<p>
Fig. 5. 
<tp:taxon-name>Fromia labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, NSMT E-9297, holotype. A, actinal surface of the disc; B, abactinal surface of interradial area showing a madreporite (arrow); C, abactinal surface of a denuded arm; D, pedicellaria on the actinal plate; E, proximal portion of a partly denuded arm, actinal side. Arrows indicate pedicellariae; F, adambulacral armature on proximal adambulacral plates. Scale bars: 5 mm (A, C), 1 mm (B, E), 500µm (D, F). Abbreviations: fs, furrow spines; ss, subambulacral spines.
</p>
</caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/record/4585305/files/figure.png"/></fig>
<p>
Superomarginal and inferomarginal plates are block-like, rectangular, only slightly convex and not alternating but regularly decreasing in size toward the tip of arms. There are sixteen superomarginal and seventeen inferomarginal plates on one side of the ray when skin and granules are removed. The second to fourth superomarginal plates average 
1.7 mm
in length.
</p>
<p>Actinal plates are polygonal, without lobes, and leave no space in between. No glassy bosses occur on actinal plates. These are arranged in three longitudinal series at the base of a denuded arm with a few odd plates on the interradial area.</p>
<p>
Adambulacral plates bear three (exceptionally two or four), slender, flattened, cylindrical and bluntly pointed furrow spines and five to nine thicker, more sharply pointed subambulacral granules (
<xref rid="fig-7--157-188-1539-1561-">Fig. 5F</xref>
). The latter are not in regular rows parallel to the ambulacrum, and are grading in size to the granules on neighboring actinal or marginal plates. Tubefeet are biserial with a stout terminal disc.
</p>
<fig id="fig-" fig-type="figure" position="float"><caption>
<p>
Table 2. Variation in numerical characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>Fromia labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
sp.nov.
</p>
</caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href=""/></fig>
<p>
<table id="d3e295">
<tr>
<td>Catalogue Number</td>
<td>NSMT E-9297</td>
<td>NSMT E-9293</td>
<td>NSMT E-9294</td>
<td>NSMT E-9295</td>
<td>NSMT E-9296</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Holotype</td>
<td>Paratype</td>
<td>Paratype</td>
<td>Paratype</td>
<td>Paratype</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R (mm)</td>
<td>31.3</td>
<td>11.7</td>
<td>3.9</td>
<td>25.5</td>
<td>11.6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>R/r</td>
<td>3.6</td>
<td>3.5</td>
<td>1.9</td>
<td>4.4</td>
<td>2.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Furrow spines per plate</td>
<td>3 (rarely 2–4)</td>
<td>3–4</td>
<td>3–4</td>
<td>3 (rarely 2–4)</td>
<td>2–3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Subambulacral spines per plate</td>
<td>5–9</td>
<td>7–9</td>
<td>7–8</td>
<td>5–8</td>
<td>5–7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Granules/mm2 on abactinal plates</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>40</td>
<td>87</td>
<td>26</td>
<td>36</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Granules/mm2 on actinal plates</td>
<td>20</td>
<td>46</td>
<td>101</td>
<td>42</td>
<td>34</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Longitudinal rows of abactinal plates</td>
<td>5</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
<td>3</td>
</tr>
</table>
</p>
<p>Each oral plate bears five oral spines on the adoral margin and four to six suboral spines on the rest of the plate. Oral spines are conical or pyramidal, larger than furrow spines. Suboral spines are similar to oral spines in the adradial portion but abradially grading into actinal granules.</p>
<p>
The abactinal, marginal, and actinal plates are concealed with a skin which is covered coarsely with granules (
<xref rid="fig-7--157-188-1539-1561-">Fig. 5B</xref>
). These granules are domed at the top, polygonal in shape, and slightly enlarged at the center of plates, but never spinous. The diameter is ca. 
260–340µm
at center and ca. 
140–200µm
on periphery. There are 20 granules per square millimeter on abactinal plates at the base of arms and actinal interradial plates. The papular pores are isolated and confined around abactinal plates except on the interradial areas and tips of arms, where the pores are absent.
</p>
<p>
Many actinal plates possess a large elliptical pedicellaria (
<xref rid="fig-7--157-188-1539-1561-">Fig. 5D</xref>
). It is typically 
1 mm
in length and 
400 µm
in width. The pedicellariae are loosely arranged in a parallel series to an ambulacrum on arms, and their major axis is often oblique to the ambulacrum (
<xref rid="fig-7--157-188-1539-1561-">Fig. 5A, E</xref>
).
</p>
<p>
Color in life is vermilion with white granules and terminal plates (
<xref rid="fig-2--822-853-1874-1896-">Fig. 2C</xref>
).
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
<p>

Notes on 
paratypes
.

The difference in the numeric characters among type specimens is shown in 
<xref>Table 2. R</xref>
/r generally increases and the number of granules per square millimeter decreases as R increases. Other characters in the 
paratypes
are consistent with the description of 
holotype
.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="multiple">
<p>
DNA sequence.
A partial sequence of COI (655 bp) was obtained from NSMT E-9295 and deposited in DDBJ (Acc. No. 
LC427074
).
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
<p>
Remarks.
The present species is distinguished from its congeners by the following characters: superomarginal plates regularly decreasing in size toward the arm tip in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
while they are alternating large and small, or small superomarginal plates are occasionally intercalated between larger ones, in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. pacifica H. L. Clark, 1921</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>F. heffernani (Livingstone, 1931)</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>F. monilis (Perrier, 1869)</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>F. nodosa A. M. Clark, 1967</tp:taxon-name>
; there are five abactinal plates between first superomarginal plates on each side of arms in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
while there are more than seven such plates in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. hemiopla Fisher, 1913</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>F. milleporella (Lamarck, 1816)</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>F. polypora H. L. Clark, 1916</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>F. schultzei (Döderlein, 1910)</tp:taxon-name>
; abactinal plates are uniform in size in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
while several elliptical plates are larger than others in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. elegans H. L. Clark, 1921</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>F. indica (Perrier, 1869)</tp:taxon-name>
; abactinal granules are granular in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
while they are spinuous in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. armata Koehler, 1910</tp:taxon-name>
; they are also coarse (20/mm 
<sup>2</sup>
) in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
while they are fine (80–90/mm 
<sup>2</sup>
) in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. hadracantha H. L. Clark, 1921</tp:taxon-name>
; papulae are lacking on the actinal surface in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
while there are two rows of actinal papulae in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. balansae Perrier, 1875</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>F. ghardaqana Mortensen, 1938</tp:taxon-name>
. Five to nine subambulacral tubercles continuous in size and not arranged in definite rows in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
while subambulacral spines are conspicuously larger than outer granules on the adambulacral plate, and arranged in a straight row in 
<tp:taxon-name>F. eusticha</tp:taxon-name>
. In addition to these differences, large elliptical pedicellariae on actinal plates are specific to 
<tp:taxon-name>F. labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
<p>
Distribution.
<tp:taxon-name>Ogasawara Islands</tp:taxon-name>
, 
56.6–137 m
(this study).
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
<p>
Etymology.
The species epithet, 
<tp:taxon-name>labeosa</tp:taxon-name>
, is a Latin feminine adjective meaning having large lips and referring to the large pedicellariae on the actinal surface.
</p>
<p>
Japanese name.
<tp:taxon-name>Ogasawara</tp:taxon-name>
is taken from the 
type
locality and 
juzuberi-hitode
is a Japanese name for the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>Fromia</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:taxon-treatment><tp:treatment-meta><mixed-citation>Arai, Mikihito &amp; Fujita, Toshihiko Fromia labeosa Arai &amp; Fujita 2021, sp. nov.</mixed-citation></tp:treatment-meta>
<tp:nomenclature><tp:taxon-name><object-id/></tp:taxon-name><xref/></tp:nomenclature>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="vernacular_names">
<p>[Japanese name: Hadaka-akasuji-hitode]</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>
(
<xref rid="fig-2--822-853-1874-1896-">Figs 2D</xref>
, 
<xref rid="fig-9--156-187-1157-1179-">6</xref>
)
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">

<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Goniodiscus capella Müller and Troschel, 1842: 61</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Goniaster ( Ogmaster ) capella Martens, 1865: 359–360</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Ogmaster capella : Sladen 1889: 261</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref11315">Koehler 1910: 79</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; Fisher 1919: 262, 305; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref10801">Döderlein 1935: 101–102</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref11092">Guille and Jangoux 1978: 53</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; A. M. 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref10618">Clark 1993: 267</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; Liao and A. M. Clark 1995: 94; A. M. 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref10706">Clark and Mah 2001: 337</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
; 
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<xref rid="ref10506">Arai et al. 2018: 194</xref>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
, 196.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Dorigona reevesii Gray, 1866: 7</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>


<tp:nomenclature-citation-list>
<tp:nomenclature-citation>
<tp:taxon-name>Goniaster muelleri : Lütken 1871: 248–250</tp:taxon-name>
</tp:nomenclature-citation>
.
</tp:nomenclature-citation-list>

</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
<p>
Material examined.
<tp:material-citation>
<named-content content-type="collectionCode">NSMT</named-content>
E-9312, 1 individual, dry, KY-08-21, 
<named-content content-type="location">East of Chichi-jima Island</named-content>
, 
<named-content content-type="quantity">
<named-content content-type="elevation">
95– 
<named-content content-type="specimenCount">98 m</named-content>
</named-content>
</named-content>
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
<p>
Description.
R= 
16.5 mm
, r= 
6.9 mm
, R/r=2.4, width of arm is 
8.5 mm
at base, 
4.8 mm
at half of R, and 
1.9 mm
at 1/10 R from the tip. Abactinal and actinal surface are flat. Arms are five, tapering toward a pointed tip (
<xref rid="fig-9--156-187-1157-1179-">Fig. 6A</xref>
).
</p>
<p>
Abactinal plates are polygonal, mostly pentagonal to hexagonal, and arranged in a regular tessellate manner leaving only small spaces around the corners. The plates on the interradial area are larger than those on the median of arms, and those neighboring the superomarginal plates are smaller (
<xref rid="fig-9--156-187-1157-1179-">Fig. 6B</xref>
). The plates are covered with a very thin skin without any granules, thus giving a naked appearance. The surface of the plates is rough with numerous glassy bosses. Papulae are confined to the proximal portion of the abactinal radial area. They are isolated, and occur at the corners of abactinal plates. Madreporite is circular, domed, and about 1.0 mm in diameter; gyri radiate from the center. Anal aperture lies at the center of the disc, and is surrounded by five granular ossicles.
</p>
<fig id="fig-9--156-187-1157-1179-" fig-type="figure" position="float"><caption>
<p>
Fig. 6. 
<tp:taxon-name>Ogmaster capella , NSMT</tp:taxon-name>
E-9312. A, actinal side; B, abactinal surface of interradial area; C, arm tip, abactinal view; D, actinal, adambulacral and oral plates. Scale bars: 10mm (A), 1 mm (B–D).
</p>
</caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://zenodo.org/record/4585307/files/figure.png"/></fig>
<p>
Terminal plates are bell-shaped (
<xref rid="fig-9--156-187-1157-1179-">Fig. 6C</xref>
). They have a smooth surface and lack any appendages except two plates bearing a single cylindrical, blunt spine at either side of the tip, suggesting that each terminal plate should bear a pair of such spines.
</p>
<p>Marginal plates are block-like, and regularly decreasing in size from the interradius toward the arm tip. There are nine superomarginal plates on each side of arms. The distalmost four plates are in contact with their counterparts on the other side of the arm, though there are small rhomboidal abactinal plates inserted at the median of arms between sixth and seventh superomarginal plates (also between seventh and eighth on two arms). The inferomarginal plates correspond to the superomarginal plates in shape, size and number.</p>
<p>Actinal plates are polygonal, mostly quadrangular or pentagonal, and arranged in a regular tessellate manner leaving no space in between. The surface of the plates is smooth with a skin lacking granules. A few low, faint glassy bosses occur on some of the plates.</p>
<p>
Adambulacral plates bear four to five furrow spines and two to five subambulacral tubercles (
<xref rid="fig-9--156-187-1157-1179-">Fig. 6D</xref>
). Furrow spines are cylindrical or conical with a blunt tip, and arranged on the curved adradial margin of adambulacral plates. The most distal spine on each plate is about two times wider at the base than the others, and tapering more rapidly toward the tip with the same width as the others. The subambulacral spines are hemispherical, irregular in size, and mostly arranged in a straight line at the abradial side of the plate. On the distal plates corresponding to the final two to three inferomarginal plates, the number of furrow spines decreases to 1–3 including the larger distal spine, and the subambulacral ossicles disappear. Tubefeet are biserial and with a terminal disc. No pedicellariae occur on adambulacral plates or other plates.
</p>
<p>Oral plates have a semicircular and domed abactinal surface. Each oral plate bears six oral spines at the margin and six to eight suboral tubercles on the abactinal surface. Oral spines are conical, slightly depressed with flanking spines. The most adradial one is the largest and about two times larger than the most abradial one which is almost identical with the neighboring furrow spines.</p>
<p>
Color in life is dull pink with red lines between plates on the abactinal surface and white on the actinal surface (
<xref rid="fig-2--822-853-1874-1896-">Fig. 2D</xref>
).
</p>
<p>
DNA sequence.
A partial sequence of COI (655 bp) was obtained from NSMT E-9312 and deposited in DDBJ (Acc. No. 
LC427075
).
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
<p>
Remarks.
The specimen from the 
<tp:taxon-name>Ogasawara Islands</tp:taxon-name>
is small but generally agrees with all the past descriptions. Pedicellariae are lacking on adambulacral plates in the present specimen unlike larger specimens with R around 
30 mm
(
<xref rid="ref10801">Döderlein 1935</xref>
; 
<xref rid="ref11092">Guille and Jangoux 1978</xref>
). Additionally, the present specimen differs from the original description since none of its plates covered with granules. According to 
<xref rid="ref10801">Döderlein (1935)</xref>
, who examined the 
type
specimen, the original description by 
<xref rid="ref11779">Müller and Troschel (1842)</xref>
misinterpreted the crystal bodies (glassy bosses) as granules. In the present specimen, the surface of all the abactinal plates and some of the actinal plates shows numerous glassy bosses.
</p>
<p>
Liao and A. M. Clark (1995) suggested that 
<tp:taxon-name>Stellaster septemtrionalis Oguro, 1991</tp:taxon-name>
, which was described from 
105 m
deep in the East 
China
Sea (
<xref rid="ref11816">Oguro 1991</xref>
), may be a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>O. capella</tp:taxon-name>
although they did not give a detailed description or comparison of the two species. The two species are indeed very similar in having 5–6 furrow spines, 2–3 short subambulacral spines, and in lacking tubercles or spines on abactinal and marginal plates. However, 
<tp:taxon-name>O. capella</tp:taxon-name>
can be distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>S. septemtrionalis</tp:taxon-name>
by the absence of coarse granules on abactinal, marginal, and actinal plates and conical tubercles on actinal plates. We consider that these differences are sufficient to separate the two species and 
<tp:taxon-name>S. septemtrionalis</tp:taxon-name>
should be maintained as valid.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
<p>
Distribution.
Southern coast of 
China
, 
60–129 m
(Liao and A. M. Clark 1995). Kai Islands, 
Indonesia
, 
90 m
; Timor Island, 
112 m
; Small Sunda Islands, depth unknown (
<xref rid="ref10801">Döderlein 1935</xref>
). Seram Island, depth unknown (
<xref rid="ref11092">Guille and Jangoux 1978</xref>
). 
<tp:taxon-name>Ogasawara Islands</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Japan
, 
95–98 m
(this study).
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
<p>
Japanese name.
Hadaka-akasuji-hitode
means a bare red-lined sea star, referring to the body hardly covered with granular skin and conspicuous red lines bordering abactinal plates in life.
</p>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<ref-list><ref id="ref10506"><mixed-citation>Arai, M., Tanaka, Y., Miyazaki, T., and Fujita, T. 2018. Valvatida (Echinodermata: Asteroidea) of the Ogasawara Islands, Japan. Memoirs of the National Museum of Nature and Science 52: 191 - 203. [In Japanese]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10618"><mixed-citation>Clark, A. M. 1993. An index of names of recent Asteroidea-Part 2: Valvatida. Pp. 187 - 366. In: Jangoux, M. and Lawrence, J. M. (Eds) Echinoderm Studies 4. A. A. Balkema, Rotterdam.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10706"><mixed-citation>Clark, A. M. and Mah, C. 2001. An index of names of recent Asteroidea-Part 4: Forcipulatida and Brisingida. Pp. 229 - 347. In: Jangoux, M. and Lawrence, J. M. (Eds) Echinoderm Studies 6. A. A. Balkema, Lisse.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10766"><mixed-citation>Clark, H. L. 1921. The Echinoderm Fauna of Torres Strait: Its Composition and Its Origin. Carnegie Institution of Washington, viii + 223 pp., 38 pls.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10801"><mixed-citation>Doderlein, L. 1935. Die Asteriden der Siboga-Expedition. III. Oreasteridae. Siboga-Expeditie 46 (3): 71 - 110.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10891"><mixed-citation>Fisher, W. K. 1913. New starfishes from the Philippine Islands, Celebes, and Moluccas. Proceedings of the United States National Museum 46: 201 - 224</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11058"><mixed-citation>Gray, J. E. 1866. Synopsis of the Species of Starfish in the British Museum. John Van Voorst, London, iv + 18 pp., 16 pls.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11092"><mixed-citation>Guille, A. and Jangoux, M. 1978. Asterides et Ophiurides littorales de la region d'Amboine (Indonesie). Annales de l'Institut Oceanographique 54: 47 - 74.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11315"><mixed-citation>Koehler, R. 1910. An Account of the Shallow-water Asteroidea. Trustees of the Indian Museum, Calcutta, 191 pp., 20 pls.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11508"><mixed-citation>Lutken, C. F. 1871. Fortsatte kritiske og beskrivende Bidrag til Kundskab om Sostjernere (Asteriderne). Videnskabelige Meddelelser fra den naturhistoriske Forening i Kjobenhavn 1871: 227 - 304.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11757"><mixed-citation>Martens, E. 1865. Ueber ostasiatische echinodermen. Archiv fur Naturgeschichte 31 (1): 345 - 360.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11779"><mixed-citation>Muller, J. and Troschel, F. H. 1842. System der Asteriden. 1. Asteriae. 2. Ophiuridae. Friedrich Vieweg und Sohn, Braunschweig, xx + 134 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11816"><mixed-citation>Oguro, C. 1991. Asteroidea. Pp. 41 - 110. In: Imaoka, T., Irimura S., Okutani, T., Oguro, C., Oji, T., and Kanazawa, K. Echinoderms from Continental Shelf and Slope around Japan Vol. II. Japan Fisheries Resource Conservation Association, Tokyo.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12147"><mixed-citation>Sladen, W. P. 1889. The Asteroidea. Report on the scientific results of the voyage of H. M. S. Challenger during the years 1873 - 76. Zoology 30: 1 - 935.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></tp:taxon-treatment>
</tp:treatment-sec>
<ref-list><ref id="ref10506"><mixed-citation>Arai, M., Tanaka, Y., Miyazaki, T., and Fujita, T. 2018. Valvatida (Echinodermata: Asteroidea) of the Ogasawara Islands, Japan. Memoirs of the National Museum of Nature and Science 52: 191 - 203. [In Japanese]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10618"><mixed-citation>Clark, A. M. 1993. An index of names of recent Asteroidea-Part 2: Valvatida. Pp. 187 - 366. In: Jangoux, M. and Lawrence, J. M. (Eds) Echinoderm Studies 4. A. A. Balkema, Rotterdam.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10706"><mixed-citation>Clark, A. M. and Mah, C. 2001. An index of names of recent Asteroidea-Part 4: Forcipulatida and Brisingida. Pp. 229 - 347. In: Jangoux, M. and Lawrence, J. M. (Eds) Echinoderm Studies 6. A. A. Balkema, Lisse.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10766"><mixed-citation>Clark, H. L. 1921. The Echinoderm Fauna of Torres Strait: Its Composition and Its Origin. Carnegie Institution of Washington, viii + 223 pp., 38 pls.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10801"><mixed-citation>Doderlein, L. 1935. Die Asteriden der Siboga-Expedition. III. Oreasteridae. Siboga-Expeditie 46 (3): 71 - 110.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10891"><mixed-citation>Fisher, W. K. 1913. New starfishes from the Philippine Islands, Celebes, and Moluccas. Proceedings of the United States National Museum 46: 201 - 224</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11058"><mixed-citation>Gray, J. E. 1866. Synopsis of the Species of Starfish in the British Museum. John Van Voorst, London, iv + 18 pp., 16 pls.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11092"><mixed-citation>Guille, A. and Jangoux, M. 1978. Asterides et Ophiurides littorales de la region d'Amboine (Indonesie). Annales de l'Institut Oceanographique 54: 47 - 74.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11315"><mixed-citation>Koehler, R. 1910. An Account of the Shallow-water Asteroidea. Trustees of the Indian Museum, Calcutta, 191 pp., 20 pls.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11508"><mixed-citation>Lutken, C. F. 1871. Fortsatte kritiske og beskrivende Bidrag til Kundskab om Sostjernere (Asteriderne). Videnskabelige Meddelelser fra den naturhistoriske Forening i Kjobenhavn 1871: 227 - 304.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11757"><mixed-citation>Martens, E. 1865. Ueber ostasiatische echinodermen. Archiv fur Naturgeschichte 31 (1): 345 - 360.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11779"><mixed-citation>Muller, J. and Troschel, F. H. 1842. System der Asteriden. 1. Asteriae. 2. Ophiuridae. Friedrich Vieweg und Sohn, Braunschweig, xx + 134 pp.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11816"><mixed-citation>Oguro, C. 1991. Asteroidea. Pp. 41 - 110. In: Imaoka, T., Irimura S., Okutani, T., Oguro, C., Oji, T., and Kanazawa, K. Echinoderms from Continental Shelf and Slope around Japan Vol. II. Japan Fisheries Resource Conservation Association, Tokyo.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12147"><mixed-citation>Sladen, W. P. 1889. The Asteroidea. Report on the scientific results of the voyage of H. M. S. Challenger during the years 1873 - 76. Zoology 30: 1 - 935.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></tp:taxon-treatment>