<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
magatama
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
788D3C24-ECA9-471D-8F77-F4D688CD3C20
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–9
, 
86
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Nasus elongate, apex slightly expanded. Scape and pedicel of antenna yellow; flagellar segments 1–4 grayish yellow, other segments pale brown, except base darker. Prescutum almost wholly reddish brown with four olive-gray striped pruinescence, median stripe broadened apically and gradually narrowing to base. Posterior margin of gonocoxite with a sharp black spine. Tergite 9 separated medially, with a pair of angular arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9, with granulated margins, apex with a small inner projection, outer surface of arms with a pair of depressions (
Fig. 9
). Outer gonostylus slender, spoon-like. Lower beak of inner gonostylus absent.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named after the shape of inner gonostylus, it looks like a ‘Magatama’, a curved commashaped bead from prehistoric 
Japan
, called ‘勾玉’ in 
China
. The name is to be treated as a noun in apposition.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Bomi
, 
Yigong
(¼贡); 
30°16′19″ N
, 
94°48′28″ E
; 

2270 m
a.s.l.

; 

5–7 May 2017

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
light trap
; 
CAU
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
13 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
CAU

• 

4 ♂♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Motuo
, 
80K
; 
29°39′29″ N
, 
95°29′24″ E
; 

2020 m
a.s.l.

; 

8 May 2017

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
light trap
; 
CAU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Body length 16.5–20.0 mm, wing length 21.0–24.0 mm, antenna length 2.5–3.0 mm (n = 18).</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 1, 3
). Mainly brownish yellow. Occipital marking brown, elongated to vertex, broadened apically and gradually narrowing to base. Rostrum and nasus grayish yellow with brown setae, nasus elongate, apex slightly expanded. Setae on head dark brown. Antenna relatively short; scape and pedicel yellow; flagellar segments 1–4 grayish yellow, other segments pale brown, except base darker. Proboscis and palpus brown.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Figs 1, 3
). Mainly reddish brown, heavily grayish yellow pruinescence. Pronotum brown with yellow setae, middle black. Prescutum almost wholly reddish brown with four olive-gray striped pruinescence, median stripe broadened apically and gradually narrowing to base. Scutum brown with two olive-gray pruinose spots. Scutellum reddish brown with dark gray pruinescence. Mediotergite dark yellow with yellow pruinescence and olive-gray mid-longitudinally. Thoracic pleuron dark yellow with grayish yellow pruinescence. Anepisternum, katepisternum and anepimeron dark brown at antero-upper corners. Anatergite and katatergite yellow. Parascutellum yellow. Meron dark yellow. Setae on thorax yellow. Legs with coxae and femora yellow, femora with brownish black apexes; tibiae brownish yellow with black tips. Tarsi brownish black. Setae on legs dark brown. Wing variegated brown with numerous smaller pale areas; pterostigma pale black; petiole of cell m 
1
distinctly shorter than discal cell (
Fig. 2
). Halter with stem dark yellow, knob black.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
magatama
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ (CAU). 
1
. Habitus, lateral view. 
2
. Wing. 
3
. Head and thorax, dorsal view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 4–9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
magatama
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (CAU). 
4
. Hypopygium, lateral view. 
5
. Outer gonostylus, lateral external view. 
6–7
. Inner gonostylus, dorsal view and lateral external view. 
8
. Hypopygium, ventral view. 
9
. Tergite nine, dorsal view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars: 4, 8–9 = 0.5 mm; 5–7 = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Figs 1, 3
). Mainly dark yellow. Abdominal tergites each with three black stripes, middle stripe stout; lateral stripes relatively narrow. Abdominal segments 5–9 black. Setae on abdomen yellow.
</p>
      <p>
HYPOPYGIUM (
Figs 4–9
). Posterior margin of gonocoxite with a sharp black spine. Tergite 9 separated medially, with a pair of angular arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9, with granulated margins, apex with a small inner projection, outer surface arms with a pair of depressions. Sternite 9 with a median prominence. Apex of adminiculum slim. Outer gonostylus slender, spoon-like, apex circular (
Fig. 5
). Inner gonostylus with big concavity; inner margin black sclerotized; lower beak absent; reversed side with big concavity (
Figs 6–7
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown or unrecognized.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Tibet
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new species is similar to 
T
. (
V
.) 
yunnanensis
Alexander, 1942
from 
Yunnan
, 
China
, but the latter differs in the following characters: posterior margin of gonocoxite with a slightly twisted spine; outer gonostylus long and slender; lower beak of inner gonostylus sharp.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
