<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
zayulensis
Alexander, 1963
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 30–38
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
zayulensis
Alexander, 1963: 328
</tp:taxon-name>

. 
Type
locality: 
China
: 
Tibet
, Zayul.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Occipital stripe dark brown, middle wide, anterior part extended to vertex. All sterno-pleurites with dark brown margins. Tergite 9 longitudinally divided into two parts, posterior margin with long setae, and a bridge between them, a pair of angular arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9. Inner gonostylus with concavity at middle, concavity with many bristles, lower margin of concavity with bristled raise; base of inner gonostylus inward-rolled, enwrapped black and swollen lower beak; upper beak relatively obtuse, slightly recurved.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
1 ♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Chayu
, 
Longgucun
(AE古村); 
28°50′44″ N
, 
97°29′29″ E
; 

2640 m
a.s.l.

; 

7 Jul. 2015

; 
Shaolin Han
leg.; 
CAU

• 

2 ♂♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Chayu
, 
Shuidianqiao
(水ΨΚ); 
28°39′60″ N
, 
97°28′07″ E
; 

2640 m
a.s.l.

; 

12 Jun. 2019

; 
Qicheng Yang
leg.; 
sweeping net
; 
CAU

• 

1 ♂
; 
Tibet
, 
Chayu County
; 
28°39′49″ N
, 
97°27′52″ E
; 

2337 m
a.s.l.

; 

Jun. 2020

; 
Hui Wang
leg.; 
CAU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. Body length 18.5 mm, wing length 20.0 mm, antenna length 4.0 mm (n = 3).</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 30, 32
). Mainly yellow. Occipital stripe dark brown, middle wide, anterior part extended to vertex. Rostrum and nasus yellow, nasus long. Setae on head dark brown. Scape yellow, pedicel pale yellow, flagellum yellowish brown. Proboscis and palpus yellowish dark brown.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 30–32.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
zayulensis
Alexander, 1963
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CAU). 
30
. Habitus, lateral view. 
31
. Wing. 
32
. Habitus, dorsal view. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 33–38.
<tp:taxon-name>
Tipula
(
Vestiplex
) 
zayulensis
Alexander, 1963
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CAU). 
33
. Hypopygium, lateral view. 
34
. Outer gonostylus, lateral external view. 
35
.Appendages of sternite 9, lateral view. 
36
. Inner gonostylus, lateral external view. 
37
. Tergite nine, dorsal view. 
38
. Hypopygium, ventral view. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bars: 33, 37–38 = 0.5 mm; 34–36 = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX (
Figs 30, 32
). Mainly brownish yellow, heavily gray pruinescence. Pronotum yellowish brown, middle and both side each with brown spot. Prescutum yellowish brown with four brown stripes, all stripes with dark brown margins. Scutum yellowish brown with four dark brown spots. Scutellum yellowish brown with dark brown mid-longitudinal stripe. Mediotergite brown with dark brown midlongitudinal stripe. Thoracic pleuron brownish yellow. All sterno-pleurite with dark brown margins. Setae on thorax yellow. Legs with coxae yellow, femora with dark brown tips; tibiae and tarsi dark brown. Setae on legs dark brown. Wing variegated pale brown; pterostigma brown; petiole of cell m 
1
distinctly shorter than discal cell (
Fig. 31
). Halter with stem yellow, knob greyish black.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Figs 30, 32
). Mainly yellow. Abdominal tergites each with three stripes, middle stripe brown, bilateral stripes black. Abdominal segments 6–9 dark black. Setae on abdomen brownish yellow.
</p>
      <p>
HYPOPYGIUM (
Figs 33–38
). Gonocoxite slightly elongated, separated from sternite 9. Tergite 9 longitudinally divided into two parts, posterior margin with long setae, and a bridge between them, a pair of angular arms arising from ventral surface of tergite 9. Sternite 9 with a pair of very short appendages, as shown in figure, with a long seta (
Fig. 35
), covered by inner gonostylus and not visible in the lateral external view. Outer gonostylus relatively small, posterior margin basally slightly wide (
Fig. 34
). Inner gonostylus with concavity at middle, concavity with many bristles, lower margin with bristled raise; base of inner gonostylus inward-rolled, enwrapped black and swollen lower beak; upper beak relatively obtuse, slightly recurved (
Fig. 36
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
Described by 
Alexander (1963)
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
: 
Tibet
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
