<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Campoplex formosanae Horstmann 2012</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4638123</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03844338450E2F6DFDA3FCE6FE79FD8D</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the Campoplex difformis group (Ichneumonidae, Campopleginae), with particular reference to species of economic importance</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.740.1277</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Campoplex formosanae
Horstmann, 2012
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 7D
, 
8
, 
9D
, 
10D
, 
12C–E
, 14D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Campoplex formosanae
Horstmann, 2012: 108–109
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
GERMANY
• 
1 ♀
; 
ZSM
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
HUNGARY
• 
1 ♀
; 
ZSM
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
UNITED KINGDOM
• 
18 ♀♀
; 
NMS
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 6.5–7.0 mm; fore wing length 
4.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Face about 0.65–0.75 × as high as wide. Malar space 0.5–0.6 × width of mandibular base. Gena 0.5 × as long as eye (maximum width, seen laterally); temple about 0.6 × as long as eye (seen dorsally), weakly narrowed behind eye, imaginary lines connecting outer side of eye and temple intersect at the level of the scutellum. OOD 0.7 × distance between lateral ocelli. Mandibular teeth subequal. Clypeus 0.4 × as high as wide, not produced in profile medially, matt and coriaceous, its apical margin sharp and gently rounded. Face and frons granulate and matt. Vertex and temples coriaceous and subpolished. Flagellum in examined specimens with 32 segments, flagellomeres in apical quarter about 0.95–1.00 × as long as wide.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 13
(opposite page). Cocoons of species belonging to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Campoplex difformis
</tp:taxon-name>
species group. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Campoplex punctulatus
(Szépligeti, 1916)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
♀
(NMS), from 
UK
, Waulkmill, Glen 
Glasgow
, ex tortricid on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Centaurea
</tp:taxon-name>
L., R. Knill-Jones leg., K. Horstmann det. 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. punctulatus
(Szépligeti, 1916)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
♂
(NMS), from 
UK
, Hutton Roof, Cumbia, ex 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aphelia paleana
(Hübner, 1793)
</tp:taxon-name>
, J.R. Langmaid leg., K. Horstmann det. 
C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. restrictor
Aubert, 1960
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
♀
(NMS), from 
UK
, Bentley Wood, Wilts., ex 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pandemis cerasana
(Hübner, 1786)
</tp:taxon-name>
on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lonicera periclymenum
</tp:taxon-name>
L., B. Fox leg., K. Horstmann det. 
D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. restrictor
Aubert, 1960
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
♂
(NMS), from 
UK
, Trench Wood, Worcs., ex 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epinotia sordidana
(Hübner, [1824])
</tp:taxon-name>
, A.N.B. Simpson leg., K. Horstmann det. 
E
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. sulcatus
Horstmann, 1985
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
♀
(NMS), from 
UK
, 
Isle of Man
, Douglas Shoprite, ex 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lozotaenia forsterana
(Fabricius, 1781)
</tp:taxon-name>
on ivy, F.D. Bennett leg., K. Horstmann det. 
F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. melanostoma
(Strobl, 1904)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
♀
(NMS) from 
Portugal
, Alagarve, Carrapateira SW of Bordiera, ex 
<tp:taxon-name>
Agonopterix
Hübner, 1825
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Centaurea spaerocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
L., M.F.V. Cavley leg., K. Horstmann det.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 14.
Face, frontal view. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Campoplex capitator
Aubert, 1960
</tp:taxon-name>
, lectotype (MZL). 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. difformis
(
Gmelin, 1790
) (ZSM)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. dubitator
Horstmann, 1985
</tp:taxon-name>
(ZSM). 
D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. formosanae
Horstmann, 2012
</tp:taxon-name>
(ZSM). 
E
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. unicingulatus
(
Schmiedeknecht, 1909
) (ZSM)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. corsicator
Aubert, 1960
</tp:taxon-name>
, lectotype (MZL).
</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Pronotum medio-ventrally with longitudinal striae, dorsally coriaceous. Epomia indistinct. Mesoscutum and scutellum granulate and matt, scutellum without lateral carinae.Mesopleuron coriaceous and matt, with shallow and scattered punctures, especially on antero-ventral half; speculum smooth, anteriorly with fine longitudinal striae. Epicnemial carina only slightly sinuate subventrally, ventrally slightly raised, in middle without notch and not produced into lobes. Metapleuron coriaceous and matt. Fore wing with areolet small and petiolate, 2m-cu slightly beyond its middle; 1cu-a opposite M&amp;RS. Hind wing with proximal abscissa of CU 2.8–3.0 × as long as cu-a, distal abscissa of CU unpigmented. Hind femur 4.6 × as long as its maximum width, the longer inner tibial spur about 0.6 × as long as hind basitarsus. Propodeum with area basalis rectangular, about 0.4 × as wide as area superomedia; area superomedia about 1.9 × as wide as long, granulate and matt, slightly depressed and open posteriorly. Area petiolaris slightly depressed and with irregular transverse striae. Rim of propodeal spiracle and carina connecting propodeal spiracle to pleural carina normal.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 15.
<tp:taxon-name>
Campoplex capitator
Aubert, 1960
</tp:taxon-name>
,♀, lectotype (MZL). 
A
. Habitus and labels. 
B
. Mesopleuron and epicnemial carina, ventrolateral view. 
C
. Propodeum, dorsolateral view showing area superomedia and area petiolaris only slightly depressed and carina connecting propodeal spiracle to pleural carina thickened (DISAAA, specimen obtained from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lobesia botrana
(Denis &amp; Schiffermüller, 1775))
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 16.
<tp:taxon-name>
Campoplex difformis
(
Gmelin, 1790
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀ (ZSM). 
A
. Habitus and labels. 
B
. Head, lateral view. 
C
. Propodeum, dorsolateral view showing area superomedia and area petiolaris clearly depressed and carina connecting propodeal spiracle to pleural carina normal.
</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Postpetiole coriaceous. Metasomal tergite II 1.5 × as long as apically wide. Ovipositor ratio 1.4–1.5.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Black. Palps and tegulae yellowish-white. Mandibles (except black base and reddish teeth) and pedicel apically yellow. Scape and flagellum yellowish-brown, flagellum lighter distally. Pterostigma yellowish-brown. All coxae black, fore coxa yellow marked distally, all tibial spurs yellowish-white; fore and mid trochanters and trochantelli yellowish-red, fore and mid femora, tibiae and tarsi yellowishred. Hind trochanter and trochantellus brownish, hind femur red, hind tibia and tarsus yellowish-red, tibia with very small light spot at base, very slightly brownish subbasally and apically. Metasoma and ovipositor sheath black.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
