<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>

Diagnosis of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius
(
Luederwaldtinia
) 
agenor
</tp:taxon-name>
species group

</p>
      <p>
Within the subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Luederwaldtinia
Martínez, 1951
</tp:taxon-name>
, the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius agenor
</tp:taxon-name>
species group defined by 
Nunes &amp; Vaz-de-Mello (2013)
can easily be separated from other species groups by the following morphological characters: head of males bearing a transverse trituberculate carina, medial tubercle higher than lateral ones; in females head carina generally bituberculate or quadrituberculate, except in two species (
<tp:taxon-name>
D. fornicatus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius rafanunezi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
) where they are trituberculate; pronotum without ornamentation, displaying at most a truncate declivity or knob; pronotum convex in females.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Large to medium-sized species (length: 
11–28 mm
). Body in most cases shiny black to brownish, rarely copper coloured (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. subaeneus
</tp:taxon-name>
), dark blue (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. fornicatus
</tp:taxon-name>
) or dull green (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius rafanunezi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Wider than long, anterior clypeal margin emarginate (V-shaped when seen from above), producing short, rounded, subtriangular clypeal teeth, in some species clypeal teeth acute (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. inachoides
</tp:taxon-name>
) or reduced (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. belus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Male head process (over the front-clypeal suture) consisting of transverse trituberculate carina (here referred to as the cephalic carina), medial tubercle clearly higher than lateral ones (
Fig. 1
A–D) or very slightly higher (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. subaeneus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Clypeo-genal suture distinct and clypeogenal junction feebly emarginate. Genal border roundly expanded or even lobed posterior to clypeogenal suture.
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM. Generally presenting a truncate slope or declivity on anterior portion, except for 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. subaeneus
</tp:taxon-name>
which is convex. Hypomeral medial disc smooth (
Fig. 2E
as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
amplicollis
</tp:taxon-name>
) or punctate (
Fig. 2F
as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. tristis
</tp:taxon-name>
), lateral margins displaying single or multiple rows of long setae.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Metepisternum covered by ocellate setigerous punctures, upper posterior margin with subtriangular projection reaching the pseudoepipleuron. Metasternal medial disc smooth, lateral edges with dense pilosity (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. inachoides
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. deyrollei
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. validipilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. simplicicornis
</tp:taxon-name>
) or dispersed pilosity (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. belus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. subaeneus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Anterior portion near meso- and metasternal suture punctate, covered by long setae or not. Medial edges of sternites shiny, smooth or with single row of punctures; lateral portions exhibiting dense ocellate punctures. Male sixth sternite narrowed medially.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Metacoxa displaying single (as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. agenor
</tp:taxon-name>
) or two rows of setae. Protibia calcar generally spiniform except apically bifurcate in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. belus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. subaeneus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
SEXUAL DIMORPHISM. Smaller or less developed males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. agenor
</tp:taxon-name>
species group have cephalic carina less developed or, as in females, bearing two tubercles. Females have larger clypeal teeth with deeper emargination, denser and longer pilosity, pronotal disc bearing deeper and denser punctures. Female
</p>
      <p>
cephalic carina bi- or quadrituberculate (
Fig. 1
E–F), except for 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. fornicatus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. rafanunezi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, in which is trituberculate. Female sixth abdominal sternite twice as wide in the middle as in males and not narrowed medially.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
The distribution of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius
(
L.
) 
agenor
</tp:taxon-name>
species group is broad, from the north Pacific coast of 
Mexico
(
Sonora
desert) to the central region of South America (
Argentina
: 
Santiago del Estero
, 
Brazil
: 
Mato Grosso state
). Altitudinal range is variable, from nearly 3000 metres in the Andes mountain range to sea-level at the Atlantic or Pacific coast.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
