<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) validipilosus</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4545867</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/FD236B47DFC7BC6CCCA50FD5D251E725</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic review of the Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) agenor species group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus validipilosus
Luederwaldt, 1931: 103
</tp:taxon-name>

(original description).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus validipilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Blackwelder 1944: 208

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius validipilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Roze 1955: 44

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius validipilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
is separated from the other species in the group by the following combination of characters: head surface subrugose. Clypeus not rounded, clypeal margin displaying projection protruding on anterior portion of clypeo-genal suture. Cephalic carina conical, median tubercle apically emarginate, lateral tubercles slightly developed. Pronotal anterior disc with declivity, median edge deeper than lateral sides resembling two underdeveloped lobes. Pronotal median disc punctation fine. Anterior and lateral edges of metasternum with long and abundant setae. Elytral interstriae microsculpture shagreened. Sixth abdominal sternite marginally lower or depressed than other sternites.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
VENEZUELA
• 
1 ♂
; “Venézuela Caracas” [white, p]/ “Ex-Museo N. Van de Poil” [white, p]/ “MUSÉUM PARIS 1938 COLL. A. BOUCOMONT” [green, p]/ “ 
Typus
” [red with black margins, p]/ “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pinotus validipilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
n. sp.
Lueder. Det. 1931” [white, hw]; 
MNHN
.

</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
COLOMBIA
– 

La Guajira

• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; Cermanke, 
Rio Rancheria
; 

2800 m
a.s.l.

; 

Jun. 2008

; 
Andrea Esparza
leg.; 
CEMT

. – 

Magdalena

• 
1 ♀
; 

24 km
S of Sta. Marta

, 
Campana.
; 

3000 ft
a.s.l.

; 

14 May 1973

; 
Campbell
and 
Howden
leg.; 
CEMT

.
</p>
      <p>
VENEZUELA
– 

Aragua

• 
2 ♀♀
; 
Cuyagua
; 

50 m
a.s.l.

; 

6 Jul. 2004

; 
D. García
leg.; 
CEMT

. – 

Merida

• 
4 ♂♂
, 
2 ♀♀
; 
Arzobispo Chacón
, 
Mutucuy
; 

1380 m
a.s.l.

; 
8º14′18″ N
, 
71º17′12″ W
; 

13 Mar. 2015

; 
Racconcia
leg.; 
CEMT

. – 

Tachira

• 
2 ♂♂
; 
Palmira
, 
La Flautera
; 

15 Jul. 1985

; 
B. Joffre
leg.; 
CEMT

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
21.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Anterior surface subrugose (
Fig. 18C
), extending posteriorly not reaching base of cephalic carina. Clypeus not rounded, with large central emargination separating two rounded clypeal teeth, feebly angled upwards (
Fig. 18A, C
). Clypeal margin distinct, projection protruding on anterior portion of clypeo-genal suture. Cephalic carina, as wide as high, conical in shape. Median tubercle three times as high as lateral tubercles, apically emarginate. Lateral tubercles slightly developed. Ventral clypeal process truncate and broadened apically (see 
Fig. 2B
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 18.
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius validipilosus
(
Luederwaldt, 1931
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–B
. Dorsal habitus. 
A
. ♂. 
B
. ♀. 
C
. Lateral view of the aedeagus. 
D
. View from above of the head, basal third surface subrugose. 
E
. Ventral view of the aedeagus. 
F–G
. Lamella copulatrix. 
H
. Punctures along the anterior margin of the punctuated, sixth sternite marginally lower, depressed.
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM. Twice as wide as long and as wide as elytra. Pronotal median disc shiny and with fine punctures, ocellate punctures near posterior basal central margin. Anterior disc with sharp declivity, medial edge deeper than lateral sides, resembling two underdeveloped lobes (
Fig. 18A
). Hypomeron external margin bearing rows of disorganized setigerous punctures, median disc smooth and shiny (see 
Fig. 2E
).
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Mesosternum and metepisternum surface microsculpture shagreened, ocellate setigerous punctures separated by once diameter of a puncture. Metasternum anterior portion next to basal margin of mesosternum and margins of mesocoxa microsculpture shagreened, with dense pilosity surrounding margins of mesocoxa joining medial and lateral portions of metasternum (see 
Fig. 2G
, 
Fig. 18D
). Longitudinal sulcus distinctly sculpted, ending as shallow mid-fossa. Sternites ocellate punctures along anterior margins. Sixth abdominal sternite marginally lower or depressed than other sternites (
Fig. 18D
). Pygidium completely delimited by margin. Large punctation restricted to basal margin. Medial and apical surfaces finely punctate.
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA. Wider than long. Interstriae microsculpture shagreened (see 
Fig. 2J
) with fine shiny punctures arranged randomly. Striae with ocellate punctures separated by once diameter of a puncture on elytral disc.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Metacoxa surface microsculpture shagreened, posterior margin covered by row of dense setigerous punctures close together; setae dense, half the length of setae of metasternum.</p>
      <p>
PARAMERES AND LAMELLA COPULATRIX. 
Fig. 18
E–G.
</p>
      <p>
Morphological variation
</p>
      <p>
Females
(
Fig. 18B
)
</p>
      <p>As males except for the following characters:</p>
      <p>HEAD. Anterior surface rugose, less dense on interocular space. Cephalic carina quadrituberculate; two median tubercles higher than lateral ones.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Anterior disc declivity weak, not modified. Surface finely punctate, punctures firmly impressed, denser at anterolateral margins next to fossae. Medial sulcus conspicuous. Pygidium delimited by incomplete margin, faded apically.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The distribution of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. validipilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. deyrollei
</tp:taxon-name>
overlaps and, although males can easily be differentiated, the females are quite similar and can only be distinguished by the pronotal punctation, which is lacking in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. validipilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
, and the character of the sixth abdominal sternite, which is marginally lower in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. validipilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
