<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Handaoia mercedensis Bordera 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5056070</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E67DC3AC4B02CFE826F2D8E2489B1626</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Handaoia Seyrig, 1952 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Phygadeuontinae): the first to be described from the New World</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1415</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia mercedensis
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
80A6A583-DB23-43D9-AF4A-4D16A6270918
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1C
, 
4
, 
9B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia mercedensis
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be distinguished from all other New World species by the combination of the following characters: apophysis of propodeum conspicuously elevated, parallelsided with blunt tip (
Fig. 4G
, arrow); fore wing with well-defined transverse dark brown band (
Fig. 4A
); juxtacoxal carina strong, irregular, joining submetapleural carina at mid length (
Fig. 4F
, arrow); flagellum dark brown (except white band), with first and second flagellomeres light brown (
Fig. 4A–B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name refers to La Merced, municipality of Chanchamayo in the Department of 
Junin
(
Peru
), where the 
holotype
was collected.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
holotype
female.
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
PERU
• 
♀
; 
La Merced
, 
Fundo La Génova
; 
Trampa Malaise
3; 

3–17 Jan. 2009

; 
AECID 013484/07
; 
CEUA
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length (without ovipositor) 
4.3 mm
. Fore wing 
3.4 mm
long.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
Morphology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia mercedensis
Bordera
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (CEUA). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head, front view. 
C
. Head and mesoscutum, dorsal view. 
D
. Head and mesosoma, lateral view. 
E
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
F
. Metapleuron (arrow: juxtacoxal carina). 
G
. Propodeum (arrow: propodeal apophysis). Scale bars: A = 1 mm; B–E = 0.2 mm; F–G = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Finely granulate, matt, strongly narrowed behind eyes, occiput very concave centrally in dorsal view (
Fig. 4C
); gena 0.18 × length of eye in dorsal view; posterior ocellus separated from eye by 1.3× its own maximum diameter; distance between posterior ocelli 0.9 × maximum ocellar diameter (
Fig. 4C
); occipital carina gently V-shaped medially; malar space about 1.4× basal width of mandible; face slightly swollen medially; clypeus (
Fig. 4B
) quite convex, gently granulate, with scattered coarse punctures in apical half, apex slightly rounded, about 2.0× as wide as high; mandible quite tapered to apex, ventral tooth of mandible a little shorter than upper tooth; maxillary palp reaching mid coxa; flagellum widened in middle, tapered towards apex, flagellomeres 8–20 flattened ventrally (
Fig. 4A
); flagellum with 22 segments, length-thickness ratios: 1 
st
segment = 5.0, 2 
nd
= 5.38 and 10 
th
= 1.0.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA. Finely granulate and matt (
Fig. 4C–D
);mesoscutum slightly convex, notauli absent (
Fig. 4C
); scutellum moderately convex, without lateral carinae; sternaulus deep, exceeding half the length of mesopleuron (
Fig. 4D
); juxtacoxal carina strong, irregular, joining submetapleural carina at mid length (
Fig. 4F
, arrow); propodeum (
Fig. 1C
) with strong and conspicuous carinae; area superomedia confluent with area basalis and separated from area petiolaris; inner side of area externa about 4.7× as long as inner side of area dentipara; inner side of area dentipara about 0.3× length of outer side; area spiracularis confluent with area lateralis; posterior transverse carina strong, forming an elevate apophysis joining lateral longitudinal carina, apophysis parallel-sided with blut tip (
Fig. 4G
, arrow). Length of hind femur about 4.0× its height. Hind wing with vein 
cu-a
0.5 as long as abscissa of 
CU
between 
M
and 
cu-a
.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA. Tergite I (
Fig. 1C
) finely granulate, slightly shiny, 1.77 × as long as its maximum width; postpetiole laterally not finely strigose; lateromedian longitudinal carina moderately strong, reaching about 0.7× length of tergite; lateral longitudinal carina complete; tergite II (
Fig. 4E
) shiny, very slightly granulate anteriorly, glabrous, smooth posteriorly, with moderately dense short setae; remaining tergites (
Fig. 4E
) smooth and shiny with inconspicuous dense setiferous punctures. Ovipositor sheath 0.53 × as long as hind tibia.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR. Head (
Fig. 4A–D
) orange brown, vertical orbits and interocellar area dark brown; palpi dark brown; mandibular teeth black; antenna with scape, pedicel and flagellomeres 1–2 light brown, remaining flagellomeres dark brown, flagellomeres 4–7 and base of 8 dorsally white (
Fig. 4A
). Mesosoma (
Fig. 4A, C–D
) entirely orange-brown. Metasoma (
Fig. 4E
) except tergite I dark brown, tergite I light brown. Fore and mid legs (
Fig. 4A
) light brown, tarsi fuscous; hind leg dark brown, trochanter and base of tibia white. Wings slightly infuscate, fore wing with well-defined transverse dark brown band (
Fig. 4A
).
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
