<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Handaoia fritzi Bordera &amp; Broad 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5056068</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F6194818C7D2B1A92EF4AC625E1108C</uri>
         <article-title>Six new species of Handaoia Seyrig, 1952 (Hymenoptera, Ichneumonidae, Phygadeuontinae): the first to be described from the New World</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1415</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia fritzi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3FE16228-86F1-4A8C-8FA0-227999E65A4F
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1B
, 
3
, 
9B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia fritzi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be distinguished from all other New World species by the combination of the following characters: apophysis of propodeum as a low transverse rounded or slightly pointed triangular crest (
Fig. 3G
, arrow); juxtacoxal carina strong, irregular, joining submetapleural carina at anterior 0.3–0.4 (
Fig. 3F
, arrow); area externa of propodeum separated from area dentipara by strong carina (
Fig. 1B
); inner side of area externa 3.0–3.4 × as long as inner side of area dentipara (
Fig. 1B
); inner side of area dentipara 0.46–0.5 × the length of outer side (
Fig. 1B
); tergite II smooth and shiny (
Fig. 3B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This species is named in honour of Dr Fritz Plaumann, illustrious botanist and entomologist based in 
Brazil
, who collected the 
type
material. A noun in genitive case.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Known from 
five females
.
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Nova Teutonia
; 
27º11′ S
, 
52º23′ W
; 

26 Aug. 1937

; 
F. Plaumann
leg.; B.M. 1937-748; 
B.M. Type Hym
3b.2871; 
NHMUK010636381
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 

Aug.1935

;B.M. 1937-47; 
NHMUK010636388

• 

1♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 

28 May 1938

; B.M. 1938-458; 
NHMUK010636387

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 

11 Aug. 1938

; B.M. 1938-682; 
NHMUK010636396

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 

16 Sep. 1938

; B.M. 1938-682; 
NHMUK010636383

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length (without ovipositor) 
3.3–4.1 mm
. Fore wing 
2.7–3.3 mm
long.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Finely granulate, matt, distinctly narrowed behind eyes, occiput very concave centrally in dorsal view (
Fig. 3C
); gena 0.2–0.25 × length of eye in dorsal view; posterior ocellus separated from eye by 0.75–1.25 × its own maximum diameter; distance between posterior ocelli 0.75–1.0 × maximum ocellar diameter (
Fig. 3C
); occipital carina gently V-shaped medially (
Fig. 3B
); malar space 1.15–1.25 × basal width of mandible; face slightly swollen medially; clypeus (
Fig. 3E
) weakly convex, faintly granulate dorsally, smooth and shiny ventrally, with scattered punctures, its apex almost straight, 2.1–2.2× as wide as high; mandible slightly tapered to apex, ventral tooth of mandible approximately same length as upper tooth; maxillary palp relatively short, reaching at most ⅔ length of mesosternum; flagellum widened in middle, tapered towards apex, flagellomeres 8–17 flattened ventrally; flagellum with 19–20 segments, length-thickness ratios: 1 
st
segment = 4.74–5.0, 2 
nd
= 5.0–5.28 and 10 
th
= 1.0.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA. Finely granulate and matt (
Fig. 3B–D
); mesoscutum convex, notauli weak anteriorly, reaching about 0.3 distance to scuto-scutellar groove, sometimes inconspicuous (
Fig. 3C
); scutellum moderately convex, without lateral carinae; sternaulus moderately deep, reaching at least middle of mesopleuron (
Fig. 3D
); juxtacoxal carina strong, irregular, joining submetapleural carina at anterior 0.3–0.4 (
Fig. 3F
, arrow); propodeum (
Fig. 1B
) with strong and conspicuous carinae; area superomedia confluent with area basalis and separated from area petiolaris; inner side of area externa about 3.0– 4.0× as long as inner side of area dentipara; inner side of area dentipara 0.46–0.5× length of outer side; area spiracularis confluent with area lateralis; posterior transverse carina strong, forming a low and wide rounded or slightly subtriangular crest joining lateral longitudinal carina (
Fig. 3G
, arrow). Length of hind femur 4.0–4.7 × its height. Hind wing with vein 
cu-a
0.4–0.6 × as long as abscissa of 
CU
between 
M
and 
cu-a
.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
Morphology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Handaoia fritzi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (NHMUK010636396). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
C
. Head and mesoscutum, dorsal view. 
D
. Head and mesosoma, lateral view. 
E
. Head, front view. 
F
. Metapleuron (arrow: juxtacoxal carina). 
G
. Propodeum (arrow: propodeal apophysis). Scale bars: A–D = 0.5 mm; E–F = 0.2 mm; G = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA. Tergite I (
Figs 1B
, 
3B
), finely granulate, matt, 1.8–2.0 × as long as its maximum width; postpetiole laterally and posteriorly tending to fine strigosity; lateromedian longitudinal carina weak, reaching at least 0.6 × length of tergite; lateral longitudinal carina weak, complete or absent posterior to spiracles; tergite II (
Fig. 3B
) smooth and shiny, glabrous; remaining tergites (
Fig. 3B
) smooth and shiny with inconspicuous dense setiferous punctures. Ovipositor sheath 0.45–0.49 × as long as hind tibia.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR. Head (
Fig. 3A–E
) dark brown, clypeus and mandibles reddish brown; palpi light brown; antenna with scape, pedicel and flagellomeres 1–4 light brown, darker dorsally, remaining flagellomeres dark brown, flagellomeres 4–7 dorsally white (
Fig. 3A
). Mesosoma (
Fig. 3A–D
) mostly dark orange; mesoscutum with wide dark brown longitudinal bands on central and lateral lobes; dorsal anterior part of propodeum dark brown. Metasoma (
Fig. 3B
) mostly brown, tergite I sometimes centrally tinged dark brown. Legs (
Fig. 3A
) light brown, distal tarsomeres dark brown, fore and mid coxae, part of hind coxa and all trochanters and trochantelli lighter. Wings (
Fig. 3A
) slightly infuscate.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
