<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) enioi Montoya-Molina &amp; Vaz-De 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4545740</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BC08BA8C296BCAAD79FED858024B979D</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic review of the Dichotomius (Luederwaldtinia) agenor species group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Scarabaeinae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius
(
Luederwaldtinia
) 
enioi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E526BCF4-2B99-42E3-B18B-DC9FE1ED0D7B
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8
, Map 16
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius enioi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is separated from other species in the group by the following combination of characters: males interocular space microsculpture shagreened, with flat, well-defined punctures resembling rugosity. Median tubercle conical, twice as high as lateral, with fine apical emargination; lateral tubercles with acute apex. Row of dense uninterrupted ocellate punctures arrange along anterior and posterior margin of Pronotum.Anterior disc declivity with weak anteromedian lobe subemargination. Interstriae microsculpture shagreened.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius enioi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is an eponym after Enio Cano, a Guatemalan scientist who contributes to the study of 
<tp:taxon-name>Scarabaeoidea</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
GUATEMALA
• 
♂
; “ 
Petén
, 
Flores
, 
El Remate
, Biot. Cerro Cahuí; 

28-29 VII 1995

; 
Col. E.B. Cano
” /“Bosque guamil alto, Colecta nocturna, con heces humanas” / “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius agenor
(Harold)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Det. E. Cano
, 1996.” [white, p]; 
CEMT
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
COSTA RICA
– 

Guanacaste

• 
2 ♂♂
, 
2 ♀♀
; 
Pq. Nac. Santa Rosa. Parnaud.
; 
CEMT

– 

Puntarenas

• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; 
Est. Queb. Bonita
, 

50 m
.

Res. Biol. Carara
L-N-194500; 469850; 

Jun. 1993

; 
J.C. Saborío
leg.; 
CEMT
.

</p>
      <p>
GUATEMALA
– 

Petén

• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; Flores, El Remate, Biot. Cerro Cahuí; 

28–29 Jul. 1995

; 
E.B. Cano
leg.; 
CEMT

• 

1 ♀
; 
Parque Nac. Tikal
, área #1-B; 

5–6 Sep. 1995

; 
G. Orellana
leg.; 
CEMT
.

</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
– 

Campeche

• 
3 ♂♂
, 
2 ♀♀
; Xpujil; 

26 Jul. 1995

; 
J.L. Moreno
and 
T. Mestre
leg.; 
CEMT

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
21.47 mm
. Dorsal and ventral surface black.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius enioi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–B
. Dorsal habitus. 
A
. Holotype, ♂ (CEMT). 
B
. ♀. 
C
. Lateral view of the aedeagus. 
D
. Ocellate punctation of the posterior margin of the pronotum; elytral interstriae shagreened. 
E
. Ventral view of the aedeagus. 
F–G
. Lamella copulatrix. 
H
. Profemur covered with wellimpressed punctures, setigerous setae near the medial edge.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Anterior surface rugose. Interocular surface microsculpture shagreened, with flat, well-defined punctures. Clypeus with central emargination separating two short, rounded clypeal teeth. Cephalic carina wider than high. Median tubercle twice as high as lateral tubercles, conical in shape and with fine apical emargination, lateral tubercles apical acute. Ventral clypeal process truncate (see 
Fig. 2B
).
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM. Wider than long. Pronotal median disc shiny covered with simple well-impressed punctures, scattered dense uninterrupted ocellate punctures along anterior and posterior margins, absent in lateral margins (
Fig. 8A, C
). Anterior disc pronounced declivity with impressed longitudinal sulcus producing weak anteromedian lobe subemargination. Hypomeral disc smooth, external margin bearing multiple rows of disorganized long setae, approximately same length, (see 
Fig. 2E
).
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Prosternum surface microsculpture shagreened. Mesosternum and metepisternum surface covered by large ocellate setigerous punctures. Metasternum setigerous punctures restricted to anterior and lateral edges of mestasternal lobe. Setigerous punctures connecting antero-median edge with lateral through margin of mesocoxa (see 
Fig. 2G
); lateral edge of metasternum with ocellate setigerous punctures separated by diameter of a puncture, setae reaching metepisternum suture. Sternite with ocellate punctures along anterior margins of each sternite, denser in lateral areas. Pygidium microsculpture shagreened with scattered well-impressed simple punctures; basal margin bearing row of ocellate punctures.
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA. Interstriae microsculpture shagreened (
Fig. 8C
). Striae with ocellate punctures separated by diameter of a puncture on elytral disc.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Fore calcar spiniform, profemur surface covered by clearly impressed punctures (
Fig. 8D
); metacoxa posterior margin bearing row of organized ocellate setigerous punctures.
</p>
      <p>
PARAMERES AND LAMELLA COPULATRIX. As in 
Fig. 8
E–G.
</p>
      <p>
Morphological variation
</p>
      <p>
Females
(
Fig. 8B
)
</p>
      <p>As males except for the following characters:</p>
      <p>HEAD. Surface completely transversely rugose, denser on anterior portion. Cephalic carina quadridentate and greatly elevate, median tubercles higher than lateral.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Without medial declivity and sub-emargination, punctures dense and deeply impressed, separated between them by once the diameter of same.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Sternites lateral punctuation denser than in males. Pygidium surface punctation wider and denser than in males.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
It is possible that 
Kohlmann &amp; Solis (1997)
and 
López-Guerrero (2005)
reported this species for Central America as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichotomius agenor
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
