<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena biciliata
Saylor, 1946
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1E–I
, 
7A
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena biciliata
Saylor, 1946: 219
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena biciliata
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Frey 1973: 335

, 347 (identification key). — 

Evans 2003: 19

(checklist). — Evans &amp; 

Smith 2005: 5

(checklist); 2007: 5 (checklist); 2009: 5 (checklist).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
PERU
• 
♂
; “ 

ix-20-35

M. Sani Beni Lima Peru, 35 / L.W. Saylor Collection / California Academy of Sciences Type nº 7907 / Holotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astaena biciliata
L.W. Saylor
</tp:taxon-name>
”; 
CAS
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratype
PERU
• 
1 ♀
; “ 

ix-20-35

M. Sani Beni Lima Peru, 35 / L.W. Saylor Collection / Collection of the California Academy of Sciences, San Francisco, California / Allotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astaena biciliata
L.W. Saylor
</tp:taxon-name>
/ CASENT 8438128”; 
CAS
.

</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1. A–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astaena abaca
Saylor, 1946
</tp:taxon-name>
, holotype, ♀ (Type No. 7904; CAS). – 
E–I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. biciliata
Saylor, 1946
</tp:taxon-name>
, holotype, ♂ (Type No. 7907; CAS). – 
J–K
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. bogotana
Saylor, 1946
</tp:taxon-name>
, paratype, ♂ (CAS). – 
L–N
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. bogotana
</tp:taxon-name>
, holotype, ♂ (Type No. 7909; CAS). 
A
. Head and pronotum, dorsal view. 
B
, 
G
, 
L
. Labels. 
C, H, M
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
D, I, N
. Habitus, lateral view. 
E, J
. Parameres, dorsal view. 
F, K
. Aedeagus, lateral view. Scale bars: A, E–F, J–K = 0.5 mm; C–D, H–I, M–N = 1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
redescription

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
11 mm
. Width: 
5.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Reddish-brown, surface with upright setae. Labroclypeus, shape of anterior margin convex, posteriorly with sparse punctation. Ocular canthus with terminal setae, ratio to eye: 1/4. Eyes, ratio diameter/interocular width: 0.55. Antennae with eight antennomeres; antennal club with three antennomeres; ratio antennal club/remaining antennomeres: 1/1; ratio third vs fourth antennomere: 1/4; fourth antennomere, lateral projection absent; ratio fifth vs fourth antennomere: 1/5.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM AND ELYTRA. Surface of pronotum and elytra without setae. Pronotum unicolored, reddishbrown, widest at base, anterior marginal line present, posterior marginal line absent, lateral margin weakly convex and smooth (not serrated), antero-lateral angle dorso-ventrally not flattened, posterolateral angle dorso-ventrally not flattened, punctation on disc sparse, setae of lateral margin sparse, median longitudinal excavation absent. Scutellum, punctures absent medially. Elytra unicolored, reddishbrown, surface opaque, microsculpture absent, punctation on intervals present and dense, diameter of strial and interval punctation equal, posterior edge straight.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Lateral carina present. Second visible ventrite with row of setae in medial region. Apical visible ventrite without suture to apical tergite.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Ratio of length of metepisternum/metacoxa: 1/0.77. Metacoxa without longer lateral bristles, a laterally extended longitudinal shelf present. Metatibia, widest at apex, ratio of width/length: 1/2.69, dorsal margin not carinated, ventral margin not serrated, distal spines groups disposed at two thirds of metatibial length. First metatarsomere, ratio to dorsal metatibial spur 1/2. Dorsal surface of tarsi glabrous and without punctures. Metatarsi, length of first protarsomere smaller than second and third combined, ventral margin not serrated and setose. Protibia with three teeth. Protarsi, length of first protarsomere subequal to second and third combined, second protarsomere narrow, claws symmetrical, inner protarsal claw bifid, apex of basal tooth of inner protarsal claw acute.</p>
      <p>
AEDEAGUS. 
Fig. 1E–F
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
