<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena rugithorax
Saylor, 1946
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 4F–I
, 
7B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena rugithorax
Saylor, 1946: 222
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena rugithorax
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Frey 1973: 364

(identification key). — 

Evans 2003: 28

(checklist). — Evans &amp; 

Smith 2005: 13

(checklist); 2007: 13 (checklist); 2009: 13 (checklist).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
COLOMBIA
• 
♀
; “Colombia, S. A. / L.W. Saylor Collection / California Academy of Sciences Type nº 7918 / Holotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astaena rugithorax
L.W. Saylor
</tp:taxon-name>
”; 
CAS
.

</p>
      <p>
Holotype
redescription

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
14 mm
. Width: 
7 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Blackish-brown, surface with setae. Labroclypeus, shape of anterior margin straight, posteriorly with dense punctation. Ocular canthus without terminal setae, ratio to eye: 1/3. Ratio fifth vs fourth antennomere: 1/5.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM AND ELYTRA. Surface of pronotum and elytra without setae. Pronotum unicolored, blackishbrown, widest at middle, anterior marginal line present, posterior marginal line absent, lateral margin strong convex and serrated, antero-lateral angle dorso-ventrally flattened, postero-lateral angle dorsoventrally not flattened, punctation on disc dense, setae of lateral margin sparse, median longitudinal excavation absent. Scutellum, punctures absent medially. Elytra unicolored, blackish-brown, surface opaque, microsculpture absent, punctation on intervals present and sparse, diameter of strial and interval punctation equal.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Lateral carina absent. Second visible ventrite without row of setae in medial region. Apical visible ventrite without suture to apical tergite.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Metacoxa without longer lateral bristles, a laterally extended longitudinal shelf absent. Metatibia, widest at apex, distal spines groups disposed at half size of metatibial length. First metatarsomere, ratio to dorsal metatibial spur: 1/2. Dorsal surface of tarsi glabrous, without punctures. Metatarsi, length of first protarsomere subequal to second and third combined, ventral margin serrated and setose. Protibia with three teeth. Protarsi, length of first protarsomere subequal to second and third combined, second protarsomere narrow, claws symmetrical, inner protarsal claw bifid, apex of basal tooth of inner protarsal claw acute.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
