<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena abaca
Saylor, 1946
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1A–D
, 
7A
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena abaca
Saylor, 1946: 223
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena abaca
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Frey 1973: 354

(identification key). — 

Evans 2003: 19

(checklist). — Evans &amp; 

Smith 2005: 4

(checklist); 2007: 4 (checklist); 2009: 4 (checklist).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
COLOMBIA
• 
♀
; “Paine viii Colum. / Apolinar-Maria / L.W. Saylor Collection / California Academy of Sciences Type nº 7904 / Holotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astaena abaca
L.W. Saylor
</tp:taxon-name>
”; 
CAS
.

</p>
      <p>
Holotype
redescription

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
12 mm
. Width: 
5.8 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Reddish-brown, surface with simple setae. Labroclypeus convex, shape of anterior margin convex, posteriorly with sparse punctation. Ratio ocular canthus (measured just the process on the eye)/eye (measured along longitudinal axis): 1/4. Antennae with eight antennomeres; antennal club with three antennomeres; ratio antennal club/remaining antennomeres: 1/1.5; ratio third vs fourth antennomere: 1/2; fourth antennomere, lateral projection absent; ratio fifth vs fourth antennomere: 1/5.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM AND ELYTRA. Surface of pronotum and elytra with setae. Pronotum unicolored, reddishbrown, widest at middle, anterior marginal line present, lateral margin strongly convex and smooth (not serrated), antero-lateral angle dorso-ventrally flattened, postero-lateral angle dorso-ventrally not flattened, punctation on disc sparse, median longitudinal excavation absent. Scutellum, punctures absent medially. Elytra unicolored, reddish-brown, surface tegument opaque, microsculpture absent, punctation on intervals present, strial and interval punctation equal in size.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Lateral carina present. Second visible ventrite with row of setae in medial region. Apical visible ventrite without suture to apical tergite.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Metacoxa without longer lateral bristles, setae on basal surface present, a laterally extended longitudinal shelf present. Metatibia, widest at apex, dorsal margin carinate, ventral margin smooth (not serrated), distal spines groups disposed at two thirds of metatibial length. First metatarsomere, ratio to dorsal metatibial spur: 1/2. Dorsal surface of tarsi glabrous. Metatarsi, length of first protarsomere subequal to second and third combined, ventral margin serrated and setose. Protibia with three teeth. Protarsi, second protarsomere narrow, claws symmetrical, inner protarsal claw bifid, apex of basal tooth of inner protarsal claw acute.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
