<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena excisipes
Saylor, 1947
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 2A–D
, 
7A
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena excisipes
Saylor, 1947b: 433
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Astaena excisipes
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Frey 1973: 347

(identification key). — 

Evans 2003: 22

(checklist). — Evans &amp; 

Smith 2005: 7

(checklist); 2007: 7 (checklist); 2009: 7 (checklist).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
ECUADOR
• 
♀
; “Ecuador Baron / 
Coll. Kraatz
/ L.W. Saylor Collection / California Academy of Sciences Type nº 7910 / 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astaena producta
Bates
</tp:taxon-name>
? / Moser det. / Holotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Astaena excisipes
L.W. Saylor
</tp:taxon-name>
”; 
CAS
.

</p>
      <p>
Holotype
redescription

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length: 
9.5 mm
. Width: 
4.7 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Reddish-brown. Labroclypeus, shape of anterior margin weakly sinuated medially. Ocular canthus with terminal setae, ratio to eye: 1/4. Ratio third vs fourth antennomere: 1/4. Fourth antennomere, lateral projection absent. Ratio fifth vs fourth antennomere: 1/5.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM AND ELYTRA. Surface of pronotum and elytra without setae. Pronotum unicolored, reddishbrown, widest at middle, anterior marginal line present, posterior marginal line absent, lateral margin straight and not serrated, two angles on postero-lateral margin present, antero-lateral angle dorsoventrally not flattened, postero-lateral angle dorso-ventrally not flattened, punctation on disc dense, median longitudinal excavation absent. Scutellum, punctures absent medially. Elytra unicolored, reddishbrown, surface opaque, microsculpture absent, punctation on intervals present and dense, diameter of strial and interval punctation equal.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Lateral carina present. Second visible ventrite without row of setae in medial region. Apical visible ventrite without suture to apical tergite.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Metacoxa without longer lateral bristles, a laterally extended longitudinal shelf present. Metatibia, widest at apex, dorsal margin not carinated, ventral margin serrated, distal spines groups disposed at two thirds of metatibial length. First metatarsomere, ratio to dorsal metatibial spur: 1/2. Dorsal surface of tarsi glabrous, without punctures. Metatarsi, length of first protarsomere smaller than second and third combined, ventral margin serrated and setose. Protibia with three teeth. Protarsi, length of first protarsomere subequal to second and third combined, second protarsomere narrow, claws symmetrical, inner protarsal claw bifid.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The 
holotype
specimen is a female; 
Saylor (1946)
incorrectly stated that the 
holotype
as a male.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
