<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus brunnerianus
Saussure, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 5
, 
7A
, 
8A–B
, 
10A
, 
11A
, 
12A
, 
13A
, 
14A
, 
15B
, 
16A
, 
17A–B
, 18; 
Tables 1–3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus brunnerianus
Saussure, 1878: 516
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Nisitra brunnerianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Kirby 1906: 87

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus brunnerianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Chopard 1968: 353

. — 

Cigliano 
et al.
2020

(
<tp:taxon-name>Orthoptera</tp:taxon-name>
Species File online). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus
aff. 
brunnerianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Vicente 2017: 2203

(phylogeny, historical biogeography).

</p>
      <p>

non 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus brunnerianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Robillard &amp; Desutter-Grandcolas 2004a: 276

(morphological phylogeny).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species differs from all known congeners by the following characters: head nearly completely black (sometimes with yellow patch beneath scapes and eyes). Pronotum lateral lobe either black with small brown spot on postero-ventral corner, or black in dorsal half and yellow in ventral half. Male FW with basal area brown with tint of black, otherwise mostly hyaline; veins mostly yellow. Female FW with dorsal field mostly infumated black, with veins dark brown and lighten towards lateral field and apical areas. Legs red brown; FIII black dorso-basally without bands or stripes on external surface; with a distinct black ring before hind knee; hind knee black.Abdomen with tergites black, sternites mostly black. This species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. crucius
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. rindu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
but differs by the combination of these characters: frons nearly completely black (without black cross marking as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. crucius
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
), dorsum of head completely black (vs with yellow margins in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. crucius
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
or pale with dark patterns in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. rindu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
) and lateral lobe either with ventral half yellow or with an oval yellow spot at the anterior end (vs with a characteristic dorsal yellow band that extends ventrally in 
<tp:taxon-name>
N. rindu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated)
</p>
      <p>

NO COUNTRY • 
♀
; “Boncard ded.”; 
Brunner von Wattenwyl
leg.; 
NMW
.

</p>
      <p>
Paralectotype

(here designated)
</p>
      <p>

NO COUNTRY • 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for lectotype; 
NMW

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional specimens
</p>
      <p>
INDONESIA
– 

Kalimantan

• 
1 ♀
; [East Kalimantan] 
“West Borneo, Marah”
, [
near border of Koetai and Beraoe
]; 
1°42′28″ N
, 
116°15′40″ E
; 

10 Aug. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♂
; [
East Kalimantan
] “ 
West Borneo, Marah
”; 
0°58′31″ N
, 
116°33′14.8″ E
; 

10–28 Nov. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN-EO- ENSIF1734

• 

7 ♀♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
MNHN

• 

2 ♀♀
; 
“West Borneo, Midden”
, [
near border of Koetai and Beraoe
]; 
1°47′35″ N
, 
116°12′22″ E
; 

12 Sep. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♂
; 
“West Borneo, Midden”
, [
near border of Koetai and Beraoe
]; 
1°50′14″ N
, 
116°12′34″ E
; 

26 Sep. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF1726

• 

1 ♂
; 
“West Borneo, Midden”
, [near Beraoe?]; 
1°58′53″ N
, 
116°7′56″ E
; 

1 Oct. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN-ENSIF1752

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♂
; 
“West Borneo, Midden”
, [
near border of Koetai and Beraoe
]; 
1°54′44″ N
, 
116°11′27″ E
; 

6 Nov. 1925

; 
H.C. Siebers
leg.; 
MNHN-ENSIF1715

• 

2 ♀♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
; [
Melawi Regency
] 
“West Borneo, Melawi”
; 
0°35′43″ S
, 
0°0′46″ E
; 

Nov.– Dec. 1924

; 
Blanchemanche
leg.; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
West Borneo
”; 1924; 
Blanchemanche
leg.; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
Lebang Hara
”; 

25 Nov.–5 Dec. 1924

; 
H. Winkler
leg.; 
ZMH

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
Samarinda
”; 
0°29′47″ S
, 
117°8′23″ E
; 
M.-E. Walsh
leg.; 
ZMLU

• 

1 ♀
; 
Kayan Basin
, 
Bahau
; 
2°55′23.2″ N
, 
117°33′13.1″ E
; 

13 Nov. 1999

; 
H.H. Tan
and 
D. Wowor
leg.; 
ZRC

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
ZRC

• 

1 ♀
; “O. 
Borneo Pelawan
”; 

May 1937

; 
M.-E. Walsh
leg.; 
ZMLU

• 

4 ♀♀
; 
Penda Siroen
, 
Soengai Maroewai
[Sungai Maruwai]; 
0°34′1.9″ S
, 
114°44′0.5″ E
; 

13 May 1932

; 
Prince Leopold
leg.; 
RBINS

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
RBINS

• 

1 ♀
; 
Kumai
, 
West Kotawaringin Regency
, 
Central Kalimantan
; 
2°55′17.9″ S
, 
111°54′16.4″ E
; 

24 Jun. 2014

; 
G. Cahyadi
leg.; iNaturalist.org/observations/41219515

. – 

Java

• 
2 ♂♂
; “ 
Bibidjilan Djampang
, Tengah VI.”; 
7°20′8.2″ S
, 
107°38′21.2″ E
; 
M.-E. Walsh
leg.; 
ZMLU

.
</p>
      <p>
MALAYSIA
– 

Sarawak

• 
1 ♀
; 
Balleh River
, 
Kapit jungle
; 
1°45′14.51″ N
, 
113°45′59.00″ E
; 

15Apr. 1979

; PII: N53; 
MNHN-EO-ENSIF11260

• 

2 ♀♀
; 
Balleh River
, 
Kapit jungle
; 
1°45′14.51″ N
, 
113°45′59.00″ E
; 

15 Apr. 1979

; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
; 

10 miles
south of Kuching

; 
1°15′12.94″ N
, 
110°19′36.71″ E
; 

14 Jun. 1910

; 
Beebe
leg.; 
MZB

• 

1 juvenile
; “ 
Gunung Mulu
NP, Camp 4, 
Summit Trail
”; 
4°2′40.6″ N
, 
114°54′50.8″ E
; 

5950 ft
a.s.l.

; 

19 Jan. 2009

; 
G.J. Svenson
leg.; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
; 
Sarawak
; 1909; 
C.J. Brooks
leg.; 
NHMUK 012497567

• 

1 ♀
; [
Semongoh
] “ 
Semongok, on oil palm
”; 
1°23′51″ N
, 
110°18′43″ E
; 

19 Dec. 1966

; “Salin Iuses” leg.; 
NHMUK 012497569

.
</p>
      <p>
NO COUNTRY • 
1 ♀
; “Borneo”; [19]32; “Weir” leg.; AMS-K393086 • 
1 ♀
; “Borneo”; 1891; Chopard leg.; 
MNHN
• 
1 ♀
; “Federal Malay States”; 1909; C.J. Brooks leg.; NHMUK 012497568.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Relatively large and slender (
Figs 7A
, 
18
). Vertex completely black (
Fig. 11A
). Fastigium velvety black, with anterior margins yellow. Scapes black, posterior end red brown. Antennae red brown with some segments black and with wide whitish rings. Eyes dark green when alive and red brown when dried. Frons generally black, sometimes with yellow to cream-coloured bands above and beneath antennal cavity and along ventral margins of eyes (
Fig. 10A
). Mouthparts dark red brown to black. Maxillary palpi creamcoloured; apical segment black apically (
Fig. 10A
). Head lateral side black (
Fig. 12A
). Pronotum generally black, covered with white setae; dorsal disk trapezoidal, posterior margin bisinuated (
Fig. 11A
). Lateral lobes of pronotum with two variants: (1) in 
lectotype
, completely black except for a cream-coloured oblong spot near anterior margin (
Fig. 12A
); (2) dorsal third black, otherwise completely yellow. Legs red brown. FIIIs dark red brown, sometimes with a dorsal black longitudinal stripe; knees dark brown to black; TIIIs brown with black spines and spurs, dark brown to black near distal end; tarsomeres dark brown to black. Hindwings hyaline brown, with a rounded transparent window near internal-basal area; longer than FWs, the dark brown tail exceeding FWs more than twice as long as pronotum. Tergites black, in some segments with cream-coloured transverse stripe at anterior end and/or with pale band laterally; sternites pale, their median area red brown. Cerci cream-coloured, short and conical.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
FOREWINGS. FW colouration (
Fig. 13A
): dorsal field cells mostly transparent to pale yellow, veins mostly dark brown to black. Basal area brown with tint of black. R brown, Sc projections brown basally, transparent apically. Lateral field yellow brown, apex more transparent. FW venation (
Fig. 13A
): 1A somewhat straight. Harp slightly longer than wide, with 3 oblique veins, posterior-most vein bifurcated at base. c1 long and wide, c2 diamond-shaped; mirror (d1) longer than wide, not rounded, generally separated into two parts by a distinct, roundly bent transverse vein, the posterior part hexagonal, shorter than anterior part. Cell d2 narrower than d1. Apical field short and rounded, with 2 wide cell alignments posterior to mirror and a narrow apical alignment; veins yellow. Lateral field with 5–6 projections of Sc. Epiproct black. Subgenital plate pale cream, its median area and anterior and posterior margins black.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
Fig. 16A
). Pseudepiphallus sclerotized, relatively large and broad compared to congeners, anterior margin somewhat broad and straight, posterior margin also straight, lateral margins faintly converging posteriorly. Posterior apex with paired lophi longer than wide (at base), subacute at apex, sclerotized laterally only and covered with strong short setae; spaced apart from one another. Rami swollen preapically, anterior apex somewhat truncated. Pseudepiphallic parameres narrow, divergent posteriorly, their basis membranous, with a sclerotized lobe on anterior apex. Ectophallic arc transverse, complete, with anterior and posterior margins straight. Ectophallic fold strong rounded lateral sclerites appearing bean-shaped. Ectophallic apodemes long and thin, straight and slightly divergent basally. Endophallic sclerite large and sclerotized, its posterior apex with divergent lateral arms and with a short median expansion curved dorsally. Endophallic apodeme with lateral lamellae stout.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
FOREWINGS. FW colouration (
Fig. 14A
): cells on dorsal field mostly infumated black, gradually becoming yellow near CuA, M and R veins; veins generally black or dark brown, also gradually becoming yellow towards CuA, M and R veins; veins near apical area also yellow. Sc projections cream-coloured basally, black apically. Lateral field dark. FW venation: 6–7 strong longitudinal veins on dorsal field, sometimes not smooth; lateral field with 6 projections of Sc.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 18.
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus brunnerianus
Saussure, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A
. In its natural environment. 
B
. In an oil palm plantation. Photograph source and credits: iNaturalist; James Steamer (A), Ganjar Cahyadi (B).
</p>
      <p>
Table 3.
Measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nisitrus brunnerianus
Saussure, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
(in mm, means in brackets).
</p>
      <p>
PronL
PronW
FWL
FWW
HWT
FIIIL
FIIIW
TIIIL
Males (n = 4)
2.1–2.3 (2.2)
3.6–3.8 (3.7)
10.8–11.7 (11.2)
4.1–4.8 (4.4)
5.1–8.3 (6.8)
13.8–14.7 (14.3)
2.0–2.6 (2.4)
14.3–15.3 (14.8)
Females (n = 5)
1.9–2.6 (2.2)
3.3–3.8 (3.5)
11.8–14.6 (13)
3.7–4.1 (3.9)
7.1–8.4 (7.7)
13.8–17.5 (15.9)
2.6–3.2 (2.8)
12.3–18.7 (15.4)
Dorsal spines of TIII
Ias
Ibs
Oas
Obs
TaIIIs
OL
Males (n = 4)
15–16 (15)
2–4
23–26 (25)
2–5
2–4
–
Females (n = 5)
11–15 (14)
2–6
19–26 (22)
2–5
2
14.7–19.9 (17.5)
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Ovipositor: on average longer than FIII; apex thin with both dorsal and ventral edges smooth. Copulatory papilla conical, slender, more elongated than congeners; apex folded ventrally, long and slender, pointed; dorsal face with a sclerotized area; ventro-anterior end forming a somewhat triangular rim (
Fig. 17A–B
).
</p>
      <p>
Juvenile
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 3
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Borneo (Kalimantan, 
Sarawak
), West Java.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Calling song
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
