<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Micronecta (Micronecta) cultellata Tran 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5033080</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/54D43C1F5599826295A801F8A332C58F</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomy of Micronectidae (Heteroptera: Nepomorpha) from Vietnam, with descriptions of 11 new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.756.1407</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta
(
Micronecta
) 
cultellata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
A59D915E-EEA7-4278-B2B0-4C0707189B6F
</p>
      <p>
Figs 5E
, 
8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Body length 1.6–2.2. Pronotum slightly shorter than median head length, lateral margin of pronotum short. Hemelytron punctate, orangish (
Fig. 5E
).
</p>
      <p>
Males: fore femur with a pair of spines on proximal third ventrally, one spine in distal third, three spines distally, and one long seta dorsodistally; fore tibia without spine; palar claw broad, apex rounded (
Fig. 8A
). Median lobe of sternite VII short and broad, with an angular apex and four long setae (
Fig. 8C
). Free lobe long, mesial angle obtuse, lateral angle square, with ca 20 long setae (
Fig. 8D
). Left paramere: shaft broad, flattened, apex narrowly rounded; basal lobe sub-rectangular (
Fig. 8F
). Right paramere: shaft evenly curved, distal half parallel sided, apex rounded; pars stridens processus with ca 30 ridges (
Fig. 8E
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The species epithet refers to the shape of the left paramere’s shaft, which resembles the blade of a knife.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
♂
; 
Lao Cai Prov.
, 
Sa Pa
, 
Trung Chai
, 
km 119 Nat. Road
#4D; 

28 Oct. 2013

; 
Q.H. Ngo
et al.
leg.; 
TAD1370
; 
ZVNU
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
– 

Lao Cai Prov.

• 
3 ♂♂
, 
3 ♀♀
; same locality data as for holotype; 
ZVNU

• 

2 ♂♂
, 
2 ♀♀
; same locality data as for holotype; 
NHMW

• 

4 ♂♂
; 
Sa Pa
, 
Nam Cang
, 
Nam Cang
stream; 

23 Oct. 2012

; 
N.H. Dinh
et al.
leg.; 
DNH12.08
; 
ZVNU

• 

3 ♂♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
ZRC

• 

1 ♀
; 
Sa Pa
, 

waterfall by roadside from Nui Xe to Sa Pa town, ca 
13 km
from Sa Pa

; 

25 Oct. 2013

; 
A.D. Tran
et al.
leg.; 
TAD1358b
; 
ZVNU

• 

1 ♀
; 
Sa Pa
, 
Thanh Phú
, N 
ậm Cang stream
; 

26 Oct. 2013

; 
A.D. Tran
et al.
leg.; 
TAD1359
; 
ZVNU

• 

1 ♀
; 
Sa Pa
, 
Cat Cat
, 
Ho
stream (tributary of 
Muong Hoa
stream); 

27 Oct. 2013

; 
A.D. Tran
et al.
leg.; 
TAD1366
; 
ZVNU

. – 

Ha Giang Prov.

• 
1 ♂
; 
Vi Xuyen
, 
Xin Chai
commune, 
Da stream by the road from Thanh Thuy to Lao Chai
; 

9 May 2014

; 
A.D. Tran
et al.
leg.; 
TAD1405
; 
ZVNU

• 

1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; 
Xin Man
, 
Nam Dan
commune, 
Thac Tien-Deo Gio
, 

stream 
100 m
below waterfall

; 

11 May 2014

; 
A.D. Tran
et al.
leg.; 
TAD1413
; 
ZVNU

. – 

Cao Bang Prov.

• 
2 ♀♀
; 
Quang Uyen
, 
road 207
, 
Doc Lap
commune, stream #2; 

18 Dec. 2013

; 
A.D. Tran
et al.
leg.; 
TAD1374
; 
ZVNU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 8.
Morphological features of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta cultellata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, paratype (ZVNU). 
A
. Fore leg. 
B
. Prestrigilar flap. 
C
. Sternite VII and median lobe. 
D
. Free lobe. 
E
. Right paramere. 
F
. Left paramere.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR (
Fig. 5E
). Dorsum generally light orangish. Frons and vertex pale yellowish, eyes reddish brown. Pronotum light greyish brown. Hemelytron light orangish, without distinct mark. Suture between clavus and corium brownish, a band with minute red dots along anterior margin of clavus. Membrane translucent apically. Venter of thorax and abdomen, and legs brownish yellow.
</p>
      <p>
Structural characteristics
</p>
      <p>
MACROPTEROUS MALES. Body length 1.78–2.16 (
holotype
: 1.93), width 1.0–1.16 (
holotype
: 1.13). Head width 0.75–0.78 (
holotype
: 0.70), slightly wider than pronotum. Pronotum about four times as wide as long, width 0.71, length 0.18. Synthlipsis about twice the posterior width of an eye (0.35: 0.18). Lengths of leg segments: fore leg: femur 0.30, tibia 0.17, pala 0.14; middle leg: femur 0.65, tibia 0.20, tarsus 0.34, claw 0.16; hind leg: femur 0.45, tibia 0.36, tarsus I 0.36, tarsus II 0.18, claw 0.05. Prestrigilar flap on segment V elongated, with weakly acute apex (
Fig. 8B
). Strigil present. Median lobe of sternite VII, free lobe, and parameres as in diagnosis.
</p>
      <p>MACROPTEROUS FEMALES. Body length 1.63–2.09, width 0.9–1.19. Head width 0.74–0.80, slightly wider than pronotum. Pronotum about four times as wide as long, width 0.75, length 0.19. Synthlipsis about twice the posterior width of an eye (0.36: 0.19). Lengths of leg segments: fore leg: femur 0.27, tibiotarsus0.21; middle leg: femur 0.76, tibia 0.27, tarsus 0.32, claw 0.20; hind leg: femur 0.41, tibia 0.32, tarsus I 0.36, tarsus II 0.16, claw 0.09.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Vietnam
: northern area (
Cao Bang
, 
Ha Giang
, 
Lao Cai
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta cultellata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. drepani
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. erythra
</tp:taxon-name>
in the general form of the right paramere, with the evenly curved shaft, and in the shape of the free lobe. These three species can be separated from each other by the characteristics as follows. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta erythra
</tp:taxon-name>
has a distinct colour pattern on the hemelytra and a distinct triangular projection on the lateral side of the left paramere. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta drepani
</tp:taxon-name>
has dark marks on the hemelytra, but they do not form a distinct pattern. The left paramere of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. drepani
</tp:taxon-name>
has a short ridge running onto the lateral margin of the shaft, and the apex of the shaft is broad. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta cultellata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
has a light orangish dorsum, without dark markings, and its left paramere lacks modifications on the lateral margin, with the apex narrow. The right paramere of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. drepani
</tp:taxon-name>
differs from that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. erythra
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. cultellata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
by having a thicker, swollen basal part of the shaft (on the mesial side). This structure is not swollen in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. erythra
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. cultellata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but gradually tapering to the distal part instead.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
