<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta
(
Micronecta
) 
erythra
Nieser, Chen &amp; Yang, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 5D
, 
7D–F
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta erythra
Nieser, Chen &amp; Yang, 2005: 191–192
</tp:taxon-name>

, 194, figs 1–11 (
type
locality: 
Yunnan
, 
China
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Body length 1.5–1.6 (brachypterous). Pronotum slightly shorter than median head length, lateral margins of pronotum short. Hemelytron light brown with scattered small red dots and distally with a transverse irregularly-shaped dark mark (
Fig. 5D
).
</p>
      <p>
Males: fore femur with a pair of spines on distal third, one spine on dorsal margin of distal third and two spines dorsodistally; fore tibia with one spine on distal third; palar claw broadened distally, apex rounded. Median lobe of sternite VII short and broad, with four long setae and an angular apex. Free lobe slightly expanded at middle part, then tapering posteriorly, mesial angle rounded, lateral angle square, with ca 17 long setae (
Fig. 7D
). Left paramere: shaft broad, flattened, lateral side with a distinct triangular projection, apex rounded; basal lobe length greater than its width, sub-trapezoid (
Fig. 7F
). Right paramere: shaft evenly curved, distal half parallel sided, apex rounded (
Fig. 7E
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
– 

Phu Tho Prov.

• 
2 ♂♂
(brachypterous); 
Xuan Son N.P.
, Coi stream, site 1, 
by the road to Tan Son
; 
21°09.204′ N
, 
104°56.927′ E
; 

8 May 2016

; 
T.S. Nguyen
leg.; 
TS1617
; 
ZVNU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Previously only known from 
China
(
Yunnan
). First records for 
Vietnam
(
Phu Tho
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
According to the description by 

Nieser 
et al.
(2005)

, the hemelytron of this species is marked with small red dots, but our specimens do not exhibit this characteristic. However, our sample is too small to determine whether intra-populational variations in colouration may be present. Other morphological characteristics of our specimens totally match the original description. Also see Remarks under 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. cultellata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
