<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta
(
Dichaetonecta
) 
johorensis
Fernando, 1964
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 3G–I
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta johorensis
Fernando, 1964: 17–18
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1–9 (
type
locality: 
Johor
, Peninsular 
Malaysia
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta johorensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Nieser 2000: 287

(key); 2002b: 265, 267–268 (diagnosis, key).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Body small, ovate, length 1.5–1.8 (brachypterous). Pronotum shorter than median head length. Dorsum colour pale yellowish. Pronotum with a pair of transverse brown marks. Dark patterns on hemelytra reticulate; embolium with five dark patches; membrane reduced.</p>
      <p>
Males: fore femur with a pair of spines in proximal third ventrally, a large and two small spines in distal third, and a pair of spines distally; fore tibia with one spine on middle third, and a pair of spines on distal margin; palar claw narrow, parallel sided, apically bent (
Fig. 3G
). Median lobe of sternite VII with two long setae and a serrated triangular apex. Free lobe: mesial angle broadly rounded, lateral angle produced, posterior margin straight, two long setae restricted to lateral angle. Left paramere: shaft relatively short and flattened, on mesial side near the middle with a large triangular tooth, apex of shaft narrowly rounded; basal part with a prominent projection on opposite side of large subovate basal lobe (
Fig. 3I
). Right paramere: shaft stout, longitudinally striated, apex rounded (
Fig. 3H
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
– 

Phu Tho Prov.

• 
1 ♂
(brachypterous); 
Xuan Son N.P.
, 
Coi stream
, site 1, 
by the road to Tan Son
; 
21°09.204′ N
, 
104°56.927′ E
; 

8 May 2016

; 
T.S. Nguyen
leg.; 
TS1617
; 
ZVNU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
First record for 
Vietnam
. Other countries: 
Malaysia
, 
Singapore
(
Nieser 2002a
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Nieser (2002a)
already noted the similarities and differences between three closely related species 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. johorensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. dentifera
Nieser, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. eucosmeta
Hutchinson, 1940
</tp:taxon-name>
. These three species can be placed in the subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichaetonecta
</tp:taxon-name>
as they possess a rather narrow palar claw, and the median lobe of sternite VII bears two long setae. The longitudinally striated shaft of the right paramere is a unique diagnostic characteristic for 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. johorensis
</tp:taxon-name>
. Also see Remarks under 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. sahlbergi
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
