<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta pocsi
Wróblewski, 1967
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta pocsi
Wróblewski, 1967: 232–235
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1–5 (
type
locality: 
Ha Tinh
, 
Vietnam
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Micronecta pocsi
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Wróblewski 1968: 775

(checklist). — 

Nieser 2000: 287

, fig. 37 (key).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Body length 1.6–1.8. Pronotum longer than median head length. Dorsum generally brown. Hemelytron with brown markings, weakly contrasting with greyish background.</p>
      <p>
Males: fore femur with two stout spines on middle part; tibia without spine; palar claw widened distally, apex rounded. Median lobe of sternite VII narrow, with four long setae and a pointed apex. Free lobe expanded distally, mesial angle produced and rounded, posterior margin concave. Left paramere: shaft broad, flat, with a triangular projection nearer to base, distal part parallel sided, apex of paramere rounded; basal lobe large, tongue-shaped. Right paramere: shaft slender proximally and pre-apically with a small notch in upper margin, apical part widened, flap-like (based on description by 
Wróblewski 1967
: figs 1–5).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>No material available.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Currently only known from 
Vietnam
, and possibly endemic to the country. Records from 
Vietnam
: 
Ninh Binh
(Cuc Phuong), 
Nghe An
, 
Ha Tinh
(
Wróblewski 1967
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This species was reported from various localities in 
Vietnam
, and we conducted samplings in some of those areas. Unfortunately, we have not yet obtained any fresh specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. pocsi
</tp:taxon-name>
. This suggests that it is a rare species. If encountered, this species can easily be recognised by the unique structure of the right paramere (see 
Wróblewski 1967
: fig. 1). See also Remarks under 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. clavata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
