<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amythas membranifera Benham 1921</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4531811</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/A072FCB458D8EDD72EC56F911F8809EE</uri>
         <article-title>Contribution to the taxonomic knowledge of Ampharetidae (Annelida) from Antarctica with the description of Amage giacomobovei sp. nov.</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amythas membranifera
Benham, 1921
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 4
, 
5
A–E, J
–L
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amythas membranifera
Benham, 1921: 102–105
</tp:taxon-name>
, pl. 10, figs 124–132.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amythas membranifera
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Monro 1939: 141–142

, fig. 24.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
ANTARCTICA
•
1 ♂
(BL = 
55 mm
, 20 AU); 
Terra Nova Bay
; 
-74.67597º S
, 
164.24592º E
; depth 

400 m

; 

30 Jan. 2014

; 
Schiaparelli
leg.; station: DR5; XXIX PNRA expedition (2013-2014); 
MNA- 07940
•
1 ♂
(BL = 
55 mm
, 19 AU); same collection data as for preceding; 
MNA-07939
•
1 ♂
(BL = 
13 mm
, 17 AU); same collection data as for preceding; 
MNA-07935
•
1 ♂
(BL = 
45 mm
, 18 AU); same collection data as for preceding; 
MNA-07934

• 

1 spec.
, undetermined sex; 
Princess Elizabeth Land
; 
-67.05000º
, 
74.48333º
; depth 

437 m

; station: 103; 
BMNH
1941.3.3.126–127

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Body (
Fig. 4
A–C) short and thick. Length 
13–55 mm
, width 
9–20 mm
; girth of body spindleshaped, increasing to the middle of thorax, decreasing thereafter.
</p>
      <p>PROSTOMIUM. Prostomium trilobed, middle lobe anteriorly broadly rounded; any additional structures (nuchal organs, ridges, horns etc.) absent.</p>
      <p>BUCCAL TENTACLES. Buccal tentacles numerous, short, smooth, attached behind a large-folded membrane. Lower lip broad, embracing mouth laterally and slightly latero-dorsally, covered by warts. Paleae totally absent.</p>
      <p>
BRANCHIAE. Three pairs of branchiae, the outermost one originating from TC1, the innermost one from TC2, and the middle one from S2 (
Fig. 5C
). Branchostyles cirriform, short, organized in a straight line and showing a wide middle gap. Branchostyles and branchophores covered with warts. There are no visible nephridial papillae or nephropores.
</p>
      <p>NOTOPODIA AND NEUROPODIA. 17 TC, notopodia with capillary chaetae from S3; anterior notopodia small, increasing in size from first to third pair; elevated or modified notopodia absent; 14 TU, all thoracic neuropodia well developed, with almost equal size, middle ones slightly bigger than anterior and posterior ones. Ventral shields distinct anteriorly and completely disappearing before the end of thorax. Subdivision of thorax absent. 17–20 AU; shape of neuropodia gradually changing throughout in most specimens, from tori to pinnula with marked size reduction on the thorax/abdomen transition; uncini at the margin of neuropodia. All neuropodia without cirri; typically rudimental abdominal notopodia absent.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amythas membranifera
Benham, 1921
</tp:taxon-name>
, morphology (MNA-07940). 
A–C
. Lateral, ventral and dorsal views. 
D
. Dorsal anterior end with a close-up view of the branchiae. 
E
. Ventral view of the anterior end showing the mouth. 
F
. External surface of the tube wall. 
G
. Living specimen still embedded in the tube, partially cut with scissors before the extraction of the specimen. Scale bars = 10 mm.
</p>
      <p>
UNCINI. Uncini pectinate (
Fig. 5
J–L) with 4 teeth in double row, similar from TU1 to last AU; prow absent.
</p>
      <p>PYGIDIUM. Anal cirri absent.</p>
      <p>
TUBE (
Fig. 4
F–G). Tubes of this species appear to be formed by progressive additions of small quantities of homogeneous fine-grained sediment to form an irregular banded pattern (
Fig. 4F
). The interior part of
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amythas membranifera
Benham, 1921
</tp:taxon-name>
and some other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ampharetidae 
Malmgren, 1866
</tp:taxon-name>
, morphological features. 
A
. Lateral view of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. membranifera
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNA-07490). 
B
. Antero-ventral view of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. membranifera
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNA-07939). 
C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. membranifera
</tp:taxon-name>
, dorsal view, showing places of branchostyles attachments and their origin (MNA-07935). 
D–I
. Lateral view of last TC and anterior AU, showing change of neuropodial shape at thorax/abdomen border in different species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Ampharetidae</tp:taxon-name>
. 
D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. membranifera
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNA-07935). 
E
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. membranifera
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNA-07940). 
F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phyllocomus sovjeticus
(Annenkova, 1937)
</tp:taxon-name>
, Aniva Bay, Japan Sea. 
G
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Samythella elongata
Verrill, 1873
</tp:taxon-name>
, R/V “Vitjaz”, station 5624, 45º26′ N, 154º12′ E, depth 5200 m. 
H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ampharete finmarchica
(M. Sars, 1865)
</tp:taxon-name>
, R/V “Schmidt”, station 26.9301, 69.91667° N, 41.98333° E, depth 107 m. 
I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amage auricula
Malmgren, 1866
</tp:taxon-name>
, Ice station SP-22, st. 74, 74.633° N, -164.500° E, depth 465 m. 
J–L
. Uncini of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. membranifera
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
J
. From TU1. 
K
. From AU1. 
L
. From AU2 (last). Abbreviations: p = pinnuli; t = tori.
</p>
      <p>
the tube has a homogeneous and transparent membranous lining that isolates the body of the worm from the outer layer and that can easily be peeled off from it (
Fig. 4G
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
This species was reported from fjords along the West Antarctic Peninsula (WAP) (
Grange &amp; Smith 2013
) and in several stations from the Ross Sea (
NZ
NIWA “IPY-CAML” Voyage TAN0802; records retrieved from GBIF, last accession 
2020 Feb. 20
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Benham in the description of the new genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amythas
</tp:taxon-name>
, stated that there were no buccal tentacles and that these were replaced by a folded membrane (
Benham 1921
). 
Hartman (1966)
and 
Fauchald (1977)
followed Benham.As it has already been stated by 
Monro (1939)
, buccal tentacles are present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amythas
</tp:taxon-name>
as in all other 
<tp:taxon-name>Ampharetidae</tp:taxon-name>
. The whole construction of buccal tentacles shows perfect resemblance to 
<tp:taxon-name>Terebellidae Johnston, 1846</tp:taxon-name>
and, at the same time, to 
<tp:taxon-name>Ampharetidae</tp:taxon-name>
with an everted pharynx (see 
Jirkov 2016
: fig. 3) which provides an indication of their homology and prostomial origin. The position of the uncini at the margin of the neuropodia was found to vary according to the individuals (e.g., 
Fig. 5
D–E). The smallest specimen examined (MNA-07935) has small rudimental abdominal notopodia and AU neuropodia more pinnuli-like (
Fig. 5D
). The morphology of the tube of this species was documented and described to occur in extant 
<tp:taxon-name>Sabellidae</tp:taxon-name>
as well as in the ichnofossil 
<tp:taxon-name>
Caprascolex antarcticus

Schweitzer 
et al.
, 2005

</tp:taxon-name>
from the Antarctic Eocene of La Meseta formation (Seymour Island, 
Antarctica
) (

Schweitzer 
et al
. 2005

: figs 3b, 4). 
In situ
images of tubes of this species are available in 
Grange &amp; Smith (2013
: fig. 2c).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
