<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Onychelmis whiteheadi Spangler &amp; Santiago
            1991</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4602497</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B187D7E832FFDAFE48FA2FFD39FD40</uri>
         <article-title>A revision of Onychelmis Hinton, 1941 (Coleoptera: Elmidae), with
            description of new species, DNA barcoding and notes on the geography of the
            genus</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1263</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis whiteheadi Spangler &amp; Santiago, 1991 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Figs 2 C–D, 6H, 7A–B, 12B </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis whiteheadi Spangler &amp; Santiago, 1991: 495 </tp:taxon-name> ,
         figs 1–2. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Differential diagnosis </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Onychelmis whiteheadi </tp:taxon-name> can be distinguished from other
         species of the genus by the combination of the following characters: 1) larger size (CL:
         1.65–1.66 mm ); 2) pro- and mesofemora with tomentum at base ( Fig. 6H ); 3) humeri
         produced; 4) prominent carina on sixth interval present; 5) elytral punctures shallowly
         impressed; 6) apeX of aedeagus trilobate ( Fig. 7 A–B). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Holotype COLOMBIA • ♂ ; “ COLOMBIA : [CUND.]: Río Cachéta near
            Bogota , 26 Feb 1984 , Maria T. Szauer // [red] HOLOTYPE <tp:taxon-name>Onychelmis
               whiteheadi Spangler</tp:taxon-name> &amp; Santiago.”; NMNH . </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Paratype COLOMBIA • 1 ♂ ; “ COLOMBIA : [CUND.]: Río Cachéta near
            Bogota , 26 Feb 1984 , Maria T. Szauer // [blue] PARATYPE <tp:taxon-name>Onychelmis
               whiteheadi Spangler</tp:taxon-name> &amp; Santiago.”; NMNH </tp:material-citation> .
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Redescription </p>
      <p> Male </p>
      <p> BODY. Obovate, black ( Fig. 2 C–D); length 1.65–1.66 mm ; width 0.79–0.81 mm ; dorsum
         conveX, glabrous, with sparse, light yellowish setae. Hairy or scale-like tomentum
         distributed on following areas: genae, sides of prosternum, mesoventrite, metaventrite and
         abdomen, epipleura, and medial and lateral portions on bases of femora. </p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head, pronotum and elytra black; venter dark brown to black; coxae, femora and
         tarsi dark brown with reddish tinge; trochanters and tibiae brown; basal segments of
         antennae and tarsal claws pale brown.</p>
      <p> HEAD. Partly retractable into prothoraX, dorsally shiny. Antennae filiform, 11-segmented;
         pedicel about twice as long as scape; remaining segments about 4 times as long as scape and
         pedicel combined, segments 3–10 subrectangular, subequal in length; terminal segment
         longest, suboval, with pointed apex. Labrum with anterior margin very slightly emarginate
         medially; anterolateral angles broadly arcuate with numerous golden, recumbent hair-like
         setae; clypeus shorter and wider than labrum, about 3.5 times as wide as long, anterior
         margin slightly concave, anterolateral angles rounded; frontoclypeal suture almost
         straight. Eyes well developed, HW: 0.31–0.32 mm , ID: 0.15–0.16 mm , suboval in lateral
         view, protruding from head outline in dorsal view, circumocular surface raised. Frons
         convex between eyes. </p>
      <p> THORAX. Pronotum widest behind middle, PW: 0.47–0.48 mm , PL: 0.51–0.54 mm ; surface
         shiny, with narrow reticulation along basal margin and posterolateral angles, with dense
         tiny punctures; sublateral carinae never well-developed, but a short, very fine raised line
         in basal ¼ present; disc conveX, divided by a broad, deep transverse impression before
         middle; two prescutellar foveae separated by a raised line extending from base to apical
         discal half, connecting both halves and merging into them; anterior margin arcuate;
         posterior margin bisinuate; sides of pronotum convex before and after transverse
         constriction; lateral margins narrowly rimmed; posterolateral angles orthogonal;
         anterolateral angles slightly produced. Hypomeron finely microreticulate, widest in middle.
         Prosternum moderately long in front of procoxae, with anterior margin concave; sides raised
         around procoxae, forming carinae, not reaching anterior margin, prosternal process long,
         moderately broad and with posterior margin broadly rounded. Mesoventrite coarse, short and
         wide, with deep triangular groove for reception of prosternal process; posterior margin
         around mesocoxae raised. Metaventrite slightly wider than long, wrinkled, more or less
         shiny with setigerous punctures; disc convex with deep, medial, triangular depression in
         posterior half; discrimen in basal ¾; in males with one prebasal fovea on each side. Elytra
         (EL: 0.12–0.15 mm , EW: 0.79–0.81 mm ) conveX, widest in anterior ¾; sides strongly
         declivous; surface shiny, with dense tiny punctures; elytral margin narrowly rimmed; humeri
         protruding from outline; epipleuron tapering posteriorly. Prominent carina on siXth
         interval in ⅘ of elytron. Elytra with ten rows of small, shallowly impressed punctures,
         separated by 2–4 times puncture diameter, diminishing toward lateral margins and elytral
         apeX. Scutellum subovate, flat. Legs moderately long; femora clavate; tibiae longest.
         Protibiae with anterior cleaning fringe on apical ⅓; mesotibiae with two cleaning fringes –
         anterior on apical ⅕ and posterior on apical ⅓; metatibiae with posterior cleaning fringe
         on apical ⅓. Tarsi 5-segmented, first four segments each with one fine pale, recumbent
         seta, fifth segment slightly shorter than remaining segments combined; claws with a large
         subbasal and smaller basal teeth. </p>
      <p> ABDOMEN. With 5 ventrites. First ventrite with basal margin broadly rounded, fifth
         ventrite longest, apically setose, with posterior margin broadly arcuate. Aedeagus ( Fig. 7
         A–B) elongate. Penis without fibula; corona below apeX, well developed; in ventral view
         concave, from apical half widening toward laterally projected, apically nearly acute sides,
         apical margin medially with wide arcuate projection; in lateral view thick, evenly narrowed
         from base to curved apex, with apical sides pointing backwards. Parameres absent.
         Phallobase about 1.5 times as long as penis, subparallel, distal portion markedly narrowed,
         in ventral view straight, curved in lateral view. </p>
      <p> Female </p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Known only from the type locality in Cundinamarca , Colombia ( Fig. 12B ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
