<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba obscura
Itoh, 1995
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba obscura
Itoh, 1995: 199
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba tuberculipennis obscura
Itoh, 1995: 199
</tp:taxon-name>

(
type
loc.: Doi Suthep, 
Thailand
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba obscura
</tp:taxon-name>
– 


Gao 
et al
2018: 14


, figs 5a–c, 6 (combination; 
type
material); 2019: 461 (species list; in key).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Itoh 1995
; 

Gao 
et al
. 2018

). Dorsal surface glabrous. Clypeus with anterior edge arcuate. Frontal carina sharp and developed. Pronotum densely punctate; anterior margin widely flanged; lateral margins smooth, elevated laterally at anterior third. Scutellum densely punctate. Elytral surface glabrous and punctate; epipleuron with setae at basal half. Meso- and metatibia with transverse carina interrupted at middle, inner margin of metatibial dorsal surface with spines. Pygidium irregularly punctate with scattered punctures dorsally, conspicuous setae on apex; apical margin moderately raised. Ventrite 5 depressed at posterior half. Male genitalia: parameres without pubescence, dorsal branches starting slightly below collum, long, thin and curved downwards; ventral branches widened, apices bent outwards ninety degrees.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Itoh (1995)
described the subspecies 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba tuberculipennis obscura
</tp:taxon-name>
base on a male 
holotype
, a female 
allotype
and thirteen 
paratypes
(
three males
and 
ten females
) from 
Thailand
and 
Laos
. According to 
Itoh (1995)
, the subspecies is distinguishable by robust and shorter parameres branches of male genitalia and variability in intensity of coloration of elytral tubercles. After studying 
two paratypes
deposited in MFNB and additional non-type specimen from 
China
, 

Gao 
et al
. (2018)

elevated this subspecies to species rank as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba obscura
</tp:taxon-name>
according to parameres and clypeus shape (

Gao 
et al
. 2018

: fig. 5). Male genitalia indicates that this species is characteristic of the morphotype I “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trichophora
</tp:taxon-name>
”. Hence, this species is included in this genital morphotype.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Yunnan
), 
Thailand
(
Chiang Mai
, Kanchanoburi, 
Chaiyaphum
), 
Laos
(
Xiangkhouang
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
