<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba thai Keith 2010</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773257</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B56743A61C0600FD7AFC6CFE31E643</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae,
            Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba thai Keith, 2010 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Figs 57–59 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba thai Keith, 2010: 235 </tp:taxon-name> , figs 4–6 ( Chiang Mai ,
         Thailand ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> External morphology of adult ( Fig. 57 ). Body size 20.5 mm . Dorsal surface glabrous, at
         most, with tiny setae in each puncture hardly visible. Clypeus shorter than frons, concave,
         oblique sides, with anterior edge emarginate at middle. Frons with strong carina. Pronotal
         anterior margin widely flanged, with a perpendicular anterior face glabrous, with concavity
         at each lateral end; posterior margin, glabrous, finely flanged except at middle; lateral
         margins smooth and glabrous, elevated at fore half; anterior angles acute, not projected
         forward; posterior angles obtuse and rounded. Prosternal process coneshaped. Scutellum with
         dense punctures except at lateral sides. Elytra with dense punctures except on sutural
         costae; epipleuron with pubescence on basal half. Foretibia with develop dorsal carina.
         Meso- and metatibia with complete transverse carina moderately developed; inner margin of
         dorsal surface with sparse but conspicuous spines. Prepygidium regularly punctate and with
         short pubescence. Pygidium irregularly punctate, with conspicuous pubescence longer on
         apex. Ventrite 5 moderately depressed at posterior half, with pubescence on surface, longer
         on depressed part. Ventrite 6 with anterior margin bulky and without punctures, posterior
         half moderately concave with long pubescence. Male genitalia: parameres ( Fig. 58 ) without
         pubescence; dorsal branches and collum continuous, apices convergent; ventral branches with
         apices moderately bent outwards. Endophallus ( Fig. 59 ) arising from middle of temones
         apophysis, short, thin and with spines at distal end. Apophysis of temones ( Fig. 59 ) very
         long and strongly sclerotized separated from each other at distal end, with a distal
         membrane at apices armed with spines. Female genitalia not studied. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p> Holotype </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> THAILAND • ♂ ; “THAILANDE N” [ Northern Thailand ], “ Chiang Dao
            Hill resort ” [in Chiang Dao District , Chiang Mai ]; 7–10 Jun. 2008 ; Murzin leg.; “
            HOLOTYPE ”; “ <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba thai </tp:taxon-name> nov. sp. Det. D. KEITH
            &amp; G. SABATINELLI 2009”; DKC . </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> Keith (2010) described <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba thai </tp:taxon-name> based on three
         specimens , two males and one female , and designated a holotype , a paratype and an
         allotype , respectively. We have studied the holotype and verified that this species shows
         features of external morphology that characterize <tp:taxon-name> Miridiba </tp:taxon-name>
         . Besides, the parameres show two dorsal and two ventral branches separated from each other
         (Keith 2010: figs 5–6) and antenna 9-segmented (not 10-segmented as was specified in the
         original description of Keith 2010), which characterize morphotype I “ <tp:taxon-name>
            Trichophora </tp:taxon-name> ”. Hence, this species is included in this genital
         morphotype. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Thailand ( Chiang Mai ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
