<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba gressitti
(
Frey, 1970
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 5–7
, 
65
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia gressitti
Frey, 1970: 249
</tp:taxon-name>

, 263 (
type
loc.: 
Vientiane
, 
Laos
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Fig. 65
). Body size 
18.6 mm
. Dorsal surface glabrous, shiny appearance. Clypeus shorter than frons, flat, oblique sides, anterior edge strongly emarginate at middle. Frons with carina moderately developed. Pronotal anterior margin glabrous, moderately wavy forward just behind eyes; posterior margin glabrous, finely flanged with a row of punctures except at middle; lateral margins moderately serrated almost smooth with a few short setae; anterior and posterior angles obtuse, anterior angle not projected forward. Prosternal process cone-shaped. Scutellum glabrous, with scattered punctures and sides without punctures. Elytra with punctures bigger than those of pronotum, epipleuron with a few short setae at basal part. Foretibia with dorsal carina moderately developed; insertion of inner spur closer to third outer tooth than second one. Meso- and metatibia with transverse carina interrupted at middle and complete, respectively; inner margin of dorsal surface with few spines. Prepygidium and pygidium with scattered punctures and glabrous, pygidium with apical margin pubescent, widened and moderately raised. Ventrites 3 and 4 with inconspicuous punctures and glabrous. Ventrite 5 not depressed at posterior half, with pubescence of different length, with conspicuous scattered punctures. Ventrite 6 moderately bulging at anterior margin, with long pubescence near posterior margin. Male and female genitalia as described above (genital morphotype II “ 
Gressitti
”). Male genitalia: parameres (
Fig. 5
) with all branches of dorsal complex shorter than ventral branches. Endophallus (
Fig. 6
) with a strong raspulae with numerous setae. Female genitalia (
Fig. 7
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Paratype
</p>
      <p>
LAOS
• 
1 ♀
; 
Vientiane
; 

15 Jun. 1965

; 
Ban Van Eue
leg.; 
G. Frey
1969 det.; 
NHMB

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Frey (1970)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia gressitti
</tp:taxon-name>
based on 
three female
specimens designated as a 
holotype
and 
two paratypes
, remaining the male unknown. We have studied 
one paratype
(NHMB) which shows external morphology characteristic of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. Moreover, female genitalia has features not shared with species of other genital morphotypes. Hence, the female genitalia of morphotype II “ 
Gressitti
” was described based on this species (
Fig. 7
). Moreover, the male genitalia of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. gressitti
</tp:taxon-name>
is described based on a 
paratype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba herteli
</tp:taxon-name>
(see remarks under 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. herteli
</tp:taxon-name>
), which is described in morphotype II “ 
Gressitti
” (
Figs 5–6
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Laos
(
Vientiane
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
