<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba saigonensis</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773293</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/6A98D95CF8101A139F8D9FF1746A6956</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba saigonensis
(
Moser, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 11
, 
74–76
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia saigonensis
Moser, 1912: 440
</tp:taxon-name>

(
type
loc.: 
Ho Chi Minh City
, 
Vietnam
). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Frey 1970: 249

(in key).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Keith 2006: 45

(combination). — 

Coca-Abia 2008: 682

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Fig. 74
). Body size 
22–25 mm
. Dorsal surface glabrous. Clypeus with conspicuous punctures, concave, shorter than frons, arcuate laterally, anterior edge strongly emarginate at middle. Frons with punctures similar to those of clypeus; surface depressed laterally, depressions without punctures; frontal carina sharp. Anterior pronotal margin glabrous, strongly flanged, narrowed at middle and at lateral ends; posterior margin glabrous, moderately flanged except at middle; lateral margins glabrous, moderately elevated, sinuate and smooth at anterior half, posterior half moderately serrated; anterior angles sharp, not projected forward, posterior angles obtuse and rounded. Pronotal surface with strong and deep punctures, each one with a tiny bulge hardly visible. Prosternal process pentagonshaped. Scutellum without punctures at middle line. Elytral surface with punctures regularly distributed, each one with a tiny bulge hardly visible; apical callus well definite; epipleuron with sparse setae at basal part and membrane. Foretibia with moderate dorsal carina. Meso- and metatibia with transverse carina interrupted and complete respectively; inner margin of dorsal surface with few spines. Prepygidium with pubescence short but conspicuous; punctures irregularly distributed, posterior area with strong punctures bearing short setae, anterior area with punctures thinner than those on posterior one. Pygidium irregularly punctate; punctures thinner at anterior and posterior margins than at middle; surface without conspicuous pubescence, at most with short setae in each puncture, apical margin with long pubescence. Ventrites 1 and 2 with conspicuous short pubescence reclined and regularly distributed. Ventrites 3 and 4 with inconspicuous pubescence. Ventrite 5 moderately depressed at posterior half where shows punctures irregularly distributed and sparse long pubescence; anterior half with thin and dense punctures uniformly distributed and without conspicuous pubescence. Ventrite 6 moderately bulging anteriorly; strong and deep punctures; wrinkled appearance; conspicuous pubescence irregularly distributed. Male genitalia: dorsal branch (
Fig. 75
) of parameres symmetrical, narrowing towards distal end, with a rounded tip curving downward; sutural scar completely fused. Ventral branches with elevations as waves at outer margin, apices expanded. Phallobase shorter than parameres. Endophallus (
Fig. 76
) strongly armed with long spines at distal end; proximal end with smaller spines. Temones short, T-shaped, with distal ends of apophysis extended laterally surrounding endophallus partially, (
Fig. 76
). Female genitalia as described for morphotype IV “ 
Bidentata
” (
Fig. 11
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated) 
VIETNAM
• 
♂
; “ 
Saigon
” [
Ho Chi Minh City
]; “ 
Donckier
leg.”; “Coll. Brenske”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
Type ♀ Mos”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. saigonensis
Mos.
</tp:taxon-name>
”; “Syntype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia saigonensis
Moser 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by 
MFNB 2017
”; “♂”; “Lectotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba saigonensis
(
Moser, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao
&amp; 
Coca- Abia
det. 2017”; 
MFNB
.

</p>
      <p>
Paralectotype

(here indicated) 
VIETNAM
• 
♂
; “ 
Cochinchina
” [southern of current 
Vietnam
]; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia
saigonensis

</tp:taxon-name>
Type ♂ Mos”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. saigonensis
Mos.
</tp:taxon-name>
”; “SYNTYPE 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia saigonensis
Moser 1912
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by 
MFNB 2017
”; “Paralectotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba saigonensis
(
Moser, 1912
)
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao
&amp; 
Coca-Abia
det. 2017. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba behrensi
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao
&amp; 
Coca-Abia
det. 2017”; 
MFNB
.

</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
2 ♂♂
, 
6 ♀♀
(identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. behrensi
</tp:taxon-name>
herein); 
Cochinchina
; 
MFNB

• 

3 ♂♂
(identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. behrensi
</tp:taxon-name>
herein); 
Saigon
; 
Donckier
leg.; 
MFNB

• 

3 ♂♂
(identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
herein); 
Saigon
; 
Donckier
leg; 
Gao
and 
Coca-Abia
det.; 
MFNB

• 

1 ♂
(identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
herein); 
Cochinchina
; 
Gao
and 
Coca-Abia
det.; 
MFNB

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Moser (1912)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
with a series of specimens from 
Cochinchina
. 
Keith (2006)
transferred this species without studying the types nor giving any justification. After studying seventeen specimens (MFNB) including 
two types
, we agree with the transfer of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. Features of external morphology and genitalia prove that this species belongs to this genus. Moreover, the parameres with one dorsal and two ventral branches allowing us include this species in genital morphotype IV “ 
Bidentata
”. On the other hand, we have designated 
two syntypes
as 
lectotype
and 
paralectotype
. After comparing these 
two types
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, we have noted that they differ from each other. The differences between them lie in the clypeus (more concave and deeply emarginate in 
lectotype
than in 
paralectotype
), frons (surface depressed laterally in 
lectotype
and without depressions in 
paralectotype
), and parameres (dorsal branch flat and wider in the 
lectotype
, in the 
paralectotype
narrower and with a dorsal depression). In addition to that, we have compared the 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
with types of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. behrensi
</tp:taxon-name>
and they are very similar to each other. Currently, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. behrensi
</tp:taxon-name>
is a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. bidentata
(
Matsumoto 2016
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, but it is not possible to compare the 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
with 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. bidentata
</tp:taxon-name>
until types are studied. Then, we only can assert that the 
paralectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is very similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. behrensi
</tp:taxon-name>
. Moreover, four other specimens, of seventeen studied, differ from the 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
, and are also identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. behrensi
</tp:taxon-name>
in this study. Male and female genitalia of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. saigonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
shows features that characterize morphotype IV “ 
Bidentata
”. Hence, this species is included in this genital morphotype.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Vietnam
(
Ho Chi Minh City
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
