<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba ciliatipennis
(Moser, 1913)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 23
, 
98
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia ciliatipennis
Moser, 1913b: 344
</tp:taxon-name>

(
type
loc.: 
Vietnam
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia ciliatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Chang 1964: 146

, 149–150, figs 54–55 (species list; in key). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neodontocnema ciliatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Frey 1970: 245

, figs 1–2 (combination).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Figs 98–99. 98
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba ciliatipennis
(Moser, 1903)
</tp:taxon-name>
, lectotype, ♂ (MFNB), habitus in dorsal view. 
99
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. brunneipennis
(
Moser, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, lectotype, ♂ (MFNB), habitus in dorsal view. Scale bars = 5.0 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Fig. 98
). Dorsal surface glabrous and densely punctate. Clypeus with anterior edge widely emarginate at middle and oblique laterally. Frontal carina developed and sharp. Anterior pronotal margin flanged, with a concavity moderately developed at each lateral end; posterior margin glabrous; lateral margins smooth, elevated laterally at anterior third; anterior angle acute; posterior angle obtuse and rounded. Scutellum densely punctate. Elytral surface with punctures more scattered than those on pronotum; epipleuron with long yellow setae along all its length. Foretibia with dorsal carina moderately developed. Meso- and metatibia with transverse carina interrupted at middle; inner margin of metatibial dorsal surface with two strong spines. Pygidium dense punctate and conspicuously pubescent; apex with long pubescence. Ventrites punctate and conspicuously pubescent. Ventrite 2 with short pubescence decumbent. Ventrites 3 and 4 with scattered pubescence at middle. Ventrite 5 with long pubescence on posterior half, irregularly distributed. Ventrite 6 with long pubescence along posterior margin. Male genitalia: parameres (
Fig. 23
) with dorsal branches of dorsal tubular complex sharp apically and with a tendency to converge (
Fig. 23A
), apices of ventral branches of dorsal tubular complex convergent (
Fig. 23B
) and curved ventrally (
Fig. 23C
); in lateral view, dorsal and ventral branches of dorsal tubular complex forming a semi-circular concavity (
Fig. 23C
). Ventral branches reduced. Phallobase longer than parameres. Endophallus, temones and female genitalia not studied.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated)
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
♂
; “ 
Annam
” [Centre of Vietnam]; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba ciliatipennis
(Moser, 1913) 
CH. Bu Gao
</tp:taxon-name>
det. 2017”; 
MFNB
.

</p>
      <p>
Paralectotype

(here indicated)
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for the lectotype; 
MFNB

.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
VIETNAM
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; 
Frey
det.; 
MFNB

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Moser (1913b)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia ciliatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
without indicating how many species he studied. 
Frey (1970)
transferred this species to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neodontocnema
Arrow, 1948
</tp:taxon-name>
and illustrated the parameres only in dorsal view.The first author of the present paper has examined 
four specimens
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. ciliatipennis
(MFNB)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
3 males
and 
1 female
, including 
two types
), which show external and genital features that characterize 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. However, male genitalia show features not shared with species belonging to other genital morphotypes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. Hence, we transfer 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. ciliatipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
and describe the male genitalia morphotype IX “ 
Ciliatipennis
” based on this species. Moreover, we designate 
lectotype
and 
paralectotype
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Vietnam
, 
Thailand
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
