<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba schoolmeesteri Keith 2010</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4773342</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03B56743A6790667FDC4FD24FDBCE642</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba schoolmeesteri
Keith, 2010
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 95–97
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba schoolmeesteri
Keith, 2010: 239
</tp:taxon-name>
, figs 12–14 (
type
loc.: Mt Phu Tha Ca, 
Ha Giang
, 
Vietnam
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Fig. 95
). Body size 
17.7 mm
. Dorsal surface glabrous. Clypeus with conspicuous punctures, wrinkled appearance, flat, shorter than frons, arcuate laterally, anterior edge emarginate at middle. Frons flat, with punctures similar to those of clypeus; frontal carina moderately developed, blunt. Pronotal surface bulky with strong punctures irregularly distributed; anterior pronotal margin flanged, glabrous; posterior margin glabrous; lateral margins serrated with a few short setae, moderately elevated at anterior quarter, posterior half hidden beneath pronotal surface; anterior angles almost right, not projected forward, posterior angles obtuse and marked. Prosternal process with two-pointed ends. Scutellum sparsely punctate. Elytral surface with punctures regularly distributed, epipleuron glabrous. Foretibia with a dorsal carina moderately developed; insertion of inner spur closer to third outer tooth than second one. Meso- and metatibiae with transverse carina moderately developed, interrupted and complete respectively; inner margin of dorsal surface without spines. Prepygidium with punctures regularly distributed; each puncture with a tiny seta. Pygidium regularly punctate, umbilicate punctures; surface glabrous, at most with a tiny seta placed at anterior margin of each puncture, apex with long pubescence. Ventrites 2, 3 and 4 with pubescence hardly visible, decumbent and regularly distributed. Ventrite 5 with punctures uniformly distributed and sparse long pubescence. Ventrite 6 with punctures irregularly distributed and conspicuous pubescence on posterior margin. Male genitalia: it seems that parameres have one dorsal branch and two ventral branches short; a membranous area at distal part connects ventral branches with phallobase (
Fig. 96
). Endophallus (
Fig. 97
) with proximal end covered with conspicuous punctiform sensillae; distal part covered with delicate filiform sensillae; between proximal and distal parts an accumulation of spines. Apophysis of temones (
Fig. 97
) long and separated from each other. Female genitalia unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
VIETNAM
• 
♂
; “ 
Ha Giang
, 
Mt Phu Tha Ca
; 

1400 m
a.s.l.

; 

May 2004

; 
Lassalle
leg. 
Viet Nam
sept”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba schoolmeesteri
</tp:taxon-name>
sp nov. 
Keith
det. 2009”; “ 
Holotype
”; 
DKC
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Keith (2010) described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba schoolmeesteri
</tp:taxon-name>
based on a male 
holotype
from 
Vietnam
.After studying the 
holotype
(DKC), we consider that features of external morphology and genitalia confirm that this species belongs to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. Although the aedeagus is damaged, the parameres seem to have one dorsal and two ventral branches, the ventral ones partially fused, and endophallus with raspulae at distal end and spines
</p>
      <p>
isolated at middle, similar to that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. scutata
</tp:taxon-name>
. These characteristics could suggest that 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. schoolmeesteri
</tp:taxon-name>
belongs to morphotype VIII “ 
Scutata
”. Hence, we include 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. schoolmeesteri
</tp:taxon-name>
in the morphotype VIII.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Vietnam
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Species included in Morphotype IX “Ciliatipennis”
</p>
      <p>The group is composed of three species, which are characterized by antenna 9-segmented, pronotal surface densely punctate (distance between punctures shorter than diameter of puncture), and male and female genitalia as specified above.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
