<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba pseudosinensis Keith 2010</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4770386</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/427E84C09F42986AD4AC3318A41BC0B0</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba pseudosinensis
Keith, 2010
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 84–86
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba pseudosinensis
Keith, 2010: 232
</tp:taxon-name>
, figs 1–3 (
type
loc.: 
Champassak
, 
Laos
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Fig. 84
). Body size 19.0 mm. Dorsal surface glabrous. Clypeus with conspicuous punctures, flat, shorter than frons, oblique laterally, anterior edge strongly emarginate at middle. Frons with punctures similar to those of clypeus; frontal carina developed. Anterior pronotal margin glabrous, regularly flanged; posterior margin not flanged, glabrous; lateral margins with anterior third elevated; anterior angles almost right and elevated, posterior angles obtuse and rounded. Prosternal process with two-pointed ends. Scutellum densely punctate and glabrous. Elytral surface with punctures regularly distributed, glabrous; epipleuron with setae at basal half. Foretibia with strong dorsal carina. Meso- and metatibia with transverse carina complete and inner margin of dorsal surface with spines. Pygidium irregularly punctate; punctures dense and deep; surface glabrous, at most with a tiny seta on each puncture hardly visible, apex with conspicuous pubescence. Ventrites 1 and 2 with decumbent conspicuous pubescence regularly distributed. Ventrites 3 and 4 with scattered thin punctures, glabrous. Ventrite 5 with strong punctures and long pubescence irregularly distributed on posterior half. Ventrite 6 with anterior margin moderately sharped; punctures and pubescence (long and short) irregularly distributed. Male genitalia: paramere (
Fig. 85
) with two dorsal branches bilaterally symmetrical. Phallobase shorter than paramere. Endophallus (
Fig. 86
) without raspulae, with acicular soft setae. Apophysis of temones separated from each other at distal end (
Fig. 86
). Female unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
LAOS
• 
♂
; 
Champassak Prov.
, 
Dong Hua Xiao
NBCA, 

2 km
S of Ban Nong Luang bank of Touay-Guai stream

; 15º4′ N, 106º13′ E; 

800 m
a.s.l.

; 

1–5 Apr. 1998

; 
O. Merkl
and 
G. Csorba
leg.; 
light trap
No. 24; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba Pseudosinensis
sp. nov.
</tp:taxon-name>
Det D. Keith
and 
G. Sabatinelli
det. 2009”; 
DKC
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
LAOS
• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
DKC
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Keith (2010) described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba pseudosinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
with 
two specimens
designated as 
holotype
and 
paratype
. This species shows features of external morphology, which characterize 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. Besides, male genitalia shows features that characterize the morphotype V “ 
Sinensis
”. Hence, this species is included in this genital morphotype.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Laos
(
Champassak
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
