<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba siamensis Keith 2004</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4770402</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E4D4938D7F42A2DE5EF5AC1C57865EE3</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba siamensis
Keith, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba siamensis
Keith, 2004: 11
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 2–3 (
type
loc.: Na Haeo, 
Loei
, 
Thailand
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba siamensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Coca-Abia 2008: 682

, 684 (in key).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
See 
Keith (2004)
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Keith (2004)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba siamensis
</tp:taxon-name>
from only 
one male
specimen. Unfortunately, we were unable to study the 
holotype
. However, according to the original description, this species shows features of the external morphology that characterize the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
, such as labrum strongly depressed at middle, frons with developed carina, foretibia with a row of longitudinal pubescence and apices of first-four segments of fore- and mesotarsi with a tuft of setae ventrally. On the other hand, the author illustrated the male genitalia in lateral and dorsal views (
Keith 2004
: figs 2–3). According to the illustrations (
Keith 2004
: fig. 2), the parameres in lateral view could have the dorsal tubular complex characteristic of morphotype IX. The upper part shows divergent branches in dorsal view (
Keith 2004
: fig. 3), and the lower part shows short ventral branches pubescent with apical ends curved ventrally (
Keith 2004
: fig. 2). Besides, dorsal tubular complex forms a soft concavity, typical of this genital morphotype at distal end. Unfortunately, 
Keith (2004)
did not illustrate the parameres in ventral view, and it is not possible to tell whether the ventral branches under the dorsal tubular complex are present, or not. In our opinion, the morphology of the parameres shows features that characterize the genital morphotype IX “ 
Ciliatipennis
”. Hence, we consider 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba siamensis
</tp:taxon-name>
should be included in this genital morphotype. Nevertheless, the 
holotype
must be studied to confirm this consideration.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Thailand
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
