<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba brunneipennis Gao &amp; Coca-Abia 2021, comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4770415</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/809ADA9C1CB494F2302DADE453DEC25C</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba brunneipennis
(
Moser, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 99
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia brunneipennis
Moser, 1916: 186
</tp:taxon-name>

(
type
loc.: Juranda, 
India
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Fig. 99
). Antenna 10-segmented. Dorsal surface glabrous, densely punctate. Clypeus shorter than frons, with conspicuous punctures, oblique laterally, anterior edge strongly emarginate at middle. Frons with punctures similar to those of clypeus; strong frontal carina. Pronotal surface densely punctate (distance between punctures smaller than diameter of puncture); anterior pronotal margin glabrous, regularly flanged; posterior margin glabrous; lateral margins smooth, moderately elevated at anterior half; anterior angles sharp and not projected forward, posterior angles obtuse and rounded. Prosternal process with two-pointed ends. Scutellum densely punctate, glabrous. Elytral surface glabrous and punctate, without striations defined, epipleuron with short pubescence on basal half. Foretibia with strong dorsal carina. Meso- and metatibia with transverse carina interrupted, and inner margin of dorsal surface with sharp spines. Pygidium glabrous, with deep punctures irregularly distributed, apex with short pubescence. Ventrites 1 and 2 densely punctate, with conspicuous decumbent pubescence regularly distributed. Ventrites 3 and 4 with a transversal row of short and robust pubescence arranged at middle of sternites. Ventrite 5 with strong punctures and long pubescence irregularly distributed on posterior half. Ventrite 6 concave moderately bulging anteriorly, punctures unevenly distributed and with long pubescence on posterior margin. Female unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated)
</p>
      <p>
INDIA
• 
♂
; “Juranda; Ind. or” [India]; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia brunneipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
Type Mos”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
brunneipennis
Mos
</tp:taxon-name>
”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
BRUNNEIPENNIS
Mos
</tp:taxon-name>
”; “Typus”; “Lectotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba brunneipennis
(
Moser, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao
and 
Coca-Abia
2017”; 
MFNB
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Moser (1916)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia brunneipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
from Juranda (
India
). We have studied a male type specimen conserved in MFNB, which shows external features that characterize the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. Hence, we have transferred 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. brunneipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. Unfortunately, we were unable to study the male genitalia because this type specimen only conserves the ninth genital segment, which does not allow us to assign it to any genital morphotype. Therefore, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. brunneipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
is considered as species incertae sedis within the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
. The 
syntype
specimen is designated as 
lectotype
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
India
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
