<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Miridiba rugaticollis Gao &amp; Coca-Abia 2021, comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4770394</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/06EE76A2E4403F4A53EC75AA55E0EBD4</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of the genus Miridiba Reitter, 1902 (Coleoptera, Scarabaeidae, Melolonthinae): genital morphotypes and new taxonomic data</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.749.1355</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba rugaticollis
(Moser, 1913)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 18–19
, 
90
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia rugaticollis
Moser, 1913a: 53
</tp:taxon-name>

(
type
loc.: Kanara, 
India
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia rugaticollis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Frey 1971: 220–221

, fig. 29a (in key).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
External morphology of adult (
Fig. 90
). Body size 
14.7 mm
. Dorsal surface shiny, glabrous. Male antennal club longer than funiculus and scape. Clypeus longer than frons, almost flat, arcuate laterally, anterior edge emarginate at middle; surface with conspicuous and deep punctures. Frons with punctures similar to those of clypeus, wrinkled appearance; frontal carina blunt. Pronotal surface with strong and deep punctures, wrinkled appearance; anterior margin glabrous, widely flanged; posterior margin glabrous; lateral margins widely serrated with short setae, moderately elevated at anterior half; anterior angles almost right, posterior angles obtuse and marked. Prosternal process slender, apex spade-shaped. Scutellum glabrous, with punctures uniformly distributed. Elytral surface with punctures evenly distributed and softer than those of pronotum; glabrous, at most with short setae in each puncture hardly visible; epipleuron glabrous, with a few short setae at basal part. Foretibia with a dorsal carina moderately developed. Meso- and metatibia with transverse carina complete, inner margin of dorsal surface with a few spines. Prepygidium with punctures regularly distributed. Pygidium with punctures irregularly distributed, glabrous; apex with sparse and short pubescence. Ventrites 1 and 2 with conspicuous short pubescence reclined and regularly distributed. Ventrites 3 and 4 glabrous. Ventrite 5 moderately depressed at posterior half, with sparse long pubescence irregularly distributed. Ventrite 6 moderately bulging at anterior margin, with strong and deep punctures, wrinkled appearance; long pubescence on posterior margin. Male genitalia fits into morphotype VII “ 
Rugaticollis
”. Parameres (
Fig. 18
) with notch of dorsal branch well developed and circular-shaped. Endophallus (
Fig. 19
) with an area of soft sensillae at distal half. Apophysis of temones (
Fig. 19
) separated from each other at both ends. Female genitalia unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Figs 90–93. 90
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba rugaticollis
(Moser, 1913)
</tp:taxon-name>
, lectotype, ♂ (MFNB). Habitus in dorsal view. 
91–93
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. nigrescens
(
Moser, 1916
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, lectotype, ♂ (MFNB). 
91
. Habitus in dorsal view. 
92
. Parameres in dorsal (A) and lateral (B) views. 
93
. Endophallus and temones in lateral view. Scale bars: 90–91 = 5.0 mm; 92–93 = 1.0 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Lectotype

(here designated)
</p>
      <p>
INDIA
• 
♂
; “Kanara”; “ 
Rugaticollis
Brensk”; “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia rugaticollis
</tp:taxon-name>
Type Mos”; “Syntypus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia rugaticollis
Moser, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by 
MNHUB 2016
”; “Lectotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba rugaticollis
(Moser, 1913)
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao
&amp; 
Coca-Abia
det. 2017”; 
MFNB
.

</p>
      <p>
Paralectotype

(here indicated)
</p>
      <p>
INDIA
• 
1 ♂
; “Kanara”; “ 
Rugaticollis
” [in red]; “Syntypus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia rugaticollis
Moser, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
labelled by MNHUB 2016”; “Paralectotype 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba rugaticollis
(Moser, 1913)
</tp:taxon-name>
Chuan-bu Gao
&amp; 
Coca-Abia
det. 2017”; 
MFNB

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Moser (1913a)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Holotrichia rugaticollis
</tp:taxon-name>
from a series of specimens from 
Bombay
(Kanara). We have studied 
two male
type specimens (MFNB) (one of them heavily damaged), which show the external features that characterize the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
and the morphotype VII “ 
Rugaticollis
”. Hence, we transfer 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. rugaticollis
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Miridiba
</tp:taxon-name>
and to this genital morphotype. Moreover, we designate 
lectotype
and 
paralectotype
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
India
(Kanara).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
