<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Evippomma simoni Alderweireldt 1992</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4509060</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/466E5E4E8ED17AA4493FE527BF56CCF3</uri>
         <article-title>Synopsis of the Evippinae (Araneae, Lycosidae) of Israel, with description of a new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Evippomma simoni
Alderweireldt, 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

Figs 1– 
2

, 
4E
, 
5E
, 
6E
, 
7E
, 
8E
, 
10E
, 
11E
, 
13B, D
, 
14B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Evippomma simoni
Alderweireldt, 1992: 161
</tp:taxon-name>
, fig. 3a–c (♂, 
Sudan
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Recognized by a combination of genital characters. Male palp: tegular apophysis small, translucent, oriented distad, parallel to plane of bulb, laterally barb-shaped (
Figs 6E
, 
7E
, 
8E
). Tegulum presents single sinus shape curve of sperm duct (in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa
</tp:taxon-name>
: two) (
Fig. 6E
). Epigyne: rounded or hat-shaped, wider than long, septum wide. Atria narrow, shallow, greatly constricted distally (in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa
</tp:taxon-name>
: width approximately equal throughout), similar to epigyne of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. squamulatum
</tp:taxon-name>
, but proximal portion of atrium wide (in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. squamulatum
</tp:taxon-name>
proximal portion of atrium slit-shaped) (
Figs 10E
, 
13B, D
). It is the only 
<tp:taxon-name>Evippinae</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Israel
covered in flat, leaf-shaped setae and without annulations on the legs.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
ISRAEL
– 

Dead Sea Area

• 
1 ♂
; 
Near Sedom
; [
31.01° N
, 
35.35° E
]; 

10 Apr. 1967

; 
P. Amitai
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16537
</tp:material-citation>
. – 
<tp:material-citation>
Negev

• 
1 ♀
; 
Be’er Mash’abbim
; [
31.01° N
, 
34.76° E
]; 

18 Sep. 1990

; 
Y. Lubin
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16544
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 ♂♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 

11 Apr. 1991

; 
Y. Lubin
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16541
, 
16568 to 16569
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 

27 May 1992

; 
Y. Lubin
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16540
, 
16570
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
3 ♀♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 

25 Jun. 1992

; 
Y. Lubin
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16050
, 
16571 to 16572
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
4 ♂♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 

30 Apr. 1993

; 
Y. Lubin
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16049
, 
16573 to 16575
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 

30 Apr. 1993

; 
Y. Lubin
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16042
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Holot Agur
; [
30.97° N
, 
34.40° E
]; 

1 Apr. 2012

; 
I. Renan
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16536
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 subadult
♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 

26 Feb. 2013

; 
I. Renan
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16576
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 juv.
; same collection data as for preceding; 

14 Mar. 2013

; 
I. Renan
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16545
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Mash’abbim sands
; 
31.002° N
, 
34.754° E
; 

16 Jun. 2020

; 
S. Aharon
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 20421
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Mash’abbim sands
; [
31.00° N
, 
34.75° E
]; 

28 Jun. 2020

; 
S. Aharon
leg.; 
HUJ INV- Ar 20422
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
4 ♂♂
; 
Nahal Sekher
; [
31.09° N
, 
34.82° E
]; 

5 May 1967

; 
P. Amitai
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16538 to 16539
, 
16577 to 16578
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Nizzana
; [
30.89° N
, 
34.41° E
]; 

29 Aug. 1991

; 
J. Henschel
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16543
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Mamshit
; [
31.02° N
, 
35.06° E
]; 

10 Apr. 2018

; 
A. Uzan
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 16579
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS (n =12). AME diameter: 0.13–0.2; PME diameter: 0.27–0.4; carapace length: 2.8–3.99; carapace width: 2.1–2.8; abdomen length: 2.7–4.17; leg I (Fe, Pa, Ti, Mt, Tr): 2.77–4.7, 0.98–1.6, 2.39– 5.96, 2.8–4.86, 1.7–2.3; leg II: 3.38–4.46, 1.2–1.57, 2.8–3.7, 3.57–4.5, 1.7–2.2; leg III: 3.2–4.3, 1.08– 1.5, 2.27–2.9, 3.5–4.5, 1.78–2.25; leg IV: 3.8–5.26, 1.3–1.68, 3.9–5.1, 4.6–6.0, 2.14–2.58.</p>
      <p>
COLOR. Carapace yellow to orange and brown, lighter around fovea and in patches behind PME; lateral bands brown to grey, radiated, fused posteriorly; ocular area black; cephalic and thoracic regions separated by sharp, black V-shaped line; perimeter with spots of white setae. Clypeus black near AME, light laterally, with white setae on margin. Chelicerae proximally yellow to orange with grey or brown reticulation connecting to oblique brown band in middle, retrolateral margin white. Legs yellow, proximal part of femur and coxa usually grey. Palps yellow to brownish (femur and tarsus darker). Sternum grey to brown, margin black, sometimes with light radiation. Abdomen dorsum yellow to whitish, sometimes with white spots. Cardiac mark yellow to brown, outlined with black spots, surrounded by posteriorly extending broken light band, outlined with dark spots, not reaching spinnerets. Abdominal venter margins yellow to whitish, center irregularly bordered, grey to black with yellow spots. Book lungs white. Spinnerets yellow (
Fig. 4E
).
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Ocular area elevated. Fovea area slightly elevated.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAL TEETH. 3 promarginal, 2 retromarginal.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Palpal organs weakly sclerotized. Tegulum keel-shaped. Part of sperm duct visible through tegulum bent at 90°. Tegular apophysis small, translucent, oriented distad, with subapical process oriented ventrad; slightly elevated over tegulum (
Figs 6E
, 
7E
, 
8E
).
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tarsus without pseudoarticulation, but in some specimens tarsi bent. Metatarsus I ventral spination: 2 pairs of long spines (pair I not reaching pair II) + short apical triplet; tibia I ventral spination: 5 pairs (all long except 5 
th
pair) + short apical pair. Distance between pairs 2–3 greatest.
</p>
      <p>
Female
MEASUREMENTS (n=6). AME diameter: 0.1–0.19; PME diameter: 0.33–0.42; carapace length: 3.28–4;
</p>
      <p>carapace width: 2.3–3.07; abdomen length: 3.57–5.1; leg I (Fe, Pa, Ti, Mt, Tr): 2.95–3.6, 1.24–1.56, 2.5– 3.09, 1.84–2.31, 1.22–1.5; leg II: 2.64–3.18, 1.22–1.3, 2.15–2.47, 1.69–2.2, 1.1–1.3; leg III: 2.46–3.14, 1.1–1.26, 1.5–2.9, 1.9–3.1, 1.37–1.6; leg IV: 2.99–3.86, 1.28–1.58, 2.79–3.8, 2.69–3.25, 1.48–1.78.</p>
      <p>
COLOR. Carapace yellow to brownish-orange, covered with white setae, lighter around fovea and in patches behind PME; lateral bands grey, radiated, fused posteriorly; cephalic and thoracic regions separated by sharp, black V-shaped line. Clypeus yellow to brown, covered with leaf-like setae, with dark lateral bar. Chelicerae orange, with leaf-like setae on proximal half, sometimes with grey reticulation and oblique grey band. Legs yellow, usually, greyish on proximal side of segment, sometimes with grey line on dorsal side. Palps yellow, with some grey on femur and tarsus. Sternum brown.Abdomen dorsum yellow to whitish. Cardiac mark grey, usually with two lines of gray spots, connecting above spinnerets. Abdomen venter yellow, grey or white, darker on center. Book lungs white. Spinnerets yellow (
Fig. 5E
). CARAPACE. Ocular area elevated. Due to the females’ strongly raised cephalic region and short legs they resemble a juvenile 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lycosa
</tp:taxon-name>
rather than an 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAL TEETH. 3 promarginal, 2 retromarginal.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Epigyne wider than long, septum wide, atria distinct, shallow, narrow, widening proximally. Spermathecae longer than atria, bent retrolaterally, shaped like a crookneck squash (
Figs 10E
, 
11E
, 
13B, D
).
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. No pseudoarticulation of the tarsus. Metatarsus I ventral spination: 2 long pairs (pair I reaching base of pair II); tibia I ventral spination: 5 pairs (long, except 5 
th
) + short apical pair.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
Adult 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippomma simoni
</tp:taxon-name>
were collected April through June, August and September (
Table 3
) and may have a yearly cycle similar to what was suggested for 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. arenaria
</tp:taxon-name>
, with a period of lowered activity in the colder months of the year (see Discussion). A female with eggs (HUJ INV-Ar 20422) was collected in June. The species mostly inhabits sandy desert habitats (
Fig. 15B
). An anecdotal report raises the possibility that the species also exists along the coastal dune strip, similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa arenaria
</tp:taxon-name>
(Y. Salaviz, pers. com.). Specimen HUJ INV-Ar 20421 was found by S. Aharon in a silk-lined burrow (
Fig. 2
), similar to what has been reported for 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. rechenbergi
(

Bayer 
et al.
2017

)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Sudan
(Alderweireldt 1992), 
Israel
.
</p>
      <p>
Israel
: Negev (Be’er Mash’abbim, Holot Agur, Nahal Sekher, Mamshit), Dead Sea area (Near Sedom) (
Fig. 16
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This is the first record of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippomma
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Israel
, and may also be the first record outside of Africa (depending on the dubious report of the species from 
India
(
Roewer 1955
)). If there is a continuous distribution with the 
type
locality at the northern Sudanese border, this species is to be present in the sandy desert of northern 
Sinai
and in eastern 
Egypt
. It may be distributed in other hot desert environments in the region, such as the sandy deserts of 
Jordan
.
</p>
      <p>Most of the specimens were collected in dune areas, but a specimen from the Sedom area, with a clayrich substrate, suggests that this species is not an obligate psammophile.</p>
      <p>

Phylogenetic relationships of 
<tp:taxon-name>Evippinae</tp:taxon-name>
based on COI and NADH

</p>
      <p>
The ML tree topology recovered the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa
</tp:taxon-name>
as monophyletic (bootstrap support [BS]= 89%). 
<tp:taxon-name>Evippinae</tp:taxon-name>
was only moderately supported in our tree (
Fig. 17
; BS =63%), yet the topology in our tree accords with the tree topology for 
<tp:taxon-name>Lycosidae</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Piacentini &amp; Ramírez 2019
and with the composition of 
<tp:taxon-name>Evippinae</tp:taxon-name>
sensu 
Alderweireldt 1991
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
