<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Evippa onager
Simon, 1895
sensu 
Šternbergs 1979
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 3
C–D, 4C, 5C, 6C, 7C, 8C, 10C, 11C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Evippa onager
Simon, 1895: 341
</tp:taxon-name>

(
♀
, 
China
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Evippa caucasica

Zamani 
et al.
, 2016: 107

</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 28–30 (♂, 
Iran
). (misidentification corrected by 

Zamani 
et al
. 2017

)

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Evippa? onager
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Šternbergs 1979: 67

, fig. 1 (misidentified fide Marusik 
et al.
2003: 50) (♂ 
♀
, 
Turkmenistan
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Evippa?
onager
sensu 
Šternbergs 1979
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Marusik 
et al.
2003: 50, figs 19–22, 28–29 (♂ 
♀
, 
Turkmenistan
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Recognized by short, robust legs (carapace longer than ¼ of leg I), coloration and its genital morphology. Prosoma of preserved specimens dark brown (other 
<tp:taxon-name>Evippinae</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Israel
are yellow after preservation). Male palp: tegular apophysis parallel to cymbium, with single, small, subapical process oriented ventrad (
Figs 6C
, 
7C
, 
8C
). It is the only 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa
</tp:taxon-name>
in 
Israel
with a subapical process directed ventrad at 90° to the tegular apophysis. In the similar 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa caucasica
Marusik, Guseinov &amp; Koponen, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
, the base of the subapical process reaches the tip of the tegular apophysis, whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. onager
</tp:taxon-name>
, the tip and the process are distinct. Epigyne: atria distinct, widest in middle. Septum narrow, slightly constricted in middle, broadened distally (
Figs 10C
, 
11C
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
ISRAEL
– 

Dead Sea Area

• 
1 ♂
; 
Qalya
; [
31.74° N
, 
35.46° E
]; 

15 Feb. 1941

; 
A. Shulov
leg.; 
HUJ INV- Ar 16510

. – 

Negev

• 
1 subadult
♀
; 
Nahal Hiyyon
; [
30.191° N
, 
35.008° E
]; 

30 Jul. 2019

; 
HUJ INV-Ar 20315

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 

30 Jul. 2019

; 
HUJ INV-Ar 20316

• 

1 ♀
; 
Biq’at ‘Uvda
(‘ 
Uvda valley
); [
29.998° N
, 
34.973° E
]; 

18 Mar. 2018

; 
E. Gavish-Regev
leg.; 
HUJ INV-Ar 20314

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS (n =2, specimen HUJ INV-Ar 20316 (the smaller of the two) was raised in the laboratory and might not be representative of sizes found in wild populations). AME diameter: 0.24–0.2; PME diameter: 0.51–0.4; carapace length: 3.97–3.58; carapace width: 2.94–2.67; abdomen length: 2.81–3.4; leg I (Fe, Pa, Ti, Mt, Tr): 2.99–2.74 (rest missing in specimen HUJ INV-Ar 16510), 1.26, 2.38, 2.3, 1.27; leg II: 2.91–2.44, 1.27–1.17, 3.04–2.3, 2.91–2.4 (rest missing in specimen HUJ INV-Ar 16510), 1.19; leg III: 2.29–2.6, 1.38–1.22, 2.59–2.22, 3.51–2.86, 1.51–1.34; leg IV: 3.83–3.34, 1.64–1.37, 3.43–2.9, 5.13–4.13, 1.99–1.61.</p>
      <p>
COLOR. Carapace brown, darker on margins and in ocular area, sparsely radiated. Clypeus center dark, margins white. Chelicerae dark yellow, striated brown. Legs yellow, dorsum with wide brown annulations. Palps yellow, tarsus darkest. Sternum brown to black. Abdomen dorsum brown to black with white setae. Abdomen venter black to brown, with sparse white setae. Spinnerets yellow (
Fig. 4C
). Live specimens dark yellow; legs with faint annulations.
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Transverse depression posterior to ocular area.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAL TEETH. 2 promarginal, 2 retromarginal.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Palpal organs weakly sclerotized. Tegulum flat. Part of sperm duct visible through tegulum makes two sinoid curves. Tegular apophysis large, somewhat transparent, oriented distad, with subapical process oriented ventrad. Subapical process sharp, distinct from sharp tip of tegular apophysis (
Figs 6C
, 
7C
, 
8C
).
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Pseudoarticulation of tarsi not evident, but tarsi curved. Metatarsus I ventral spination: 3 pairs + apical triplet; tibia I ventral spination: 5 pairs + apical pair.</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS. AME diameter: 0.2; PME diameter: 0.56; carapace length: 3.88; carapace width: 2.8; abdomen length: 4.44; leg I (Fe, Pa, Ti, Mt, Tr): 2.54, 1.37, 2.35, 1.94, 1.03; leg II: 2.55, 1.36, 2.26, 1.96, 0.96; leg III: 2.58, 1.31, 2.22, 2.39, 1.1; leg IV: 3.31, 1.47, 2.93, 3.9, 1.41.</p>
      <p>
COLOR. Carapace blackish, with some orange setae and orange fringe of setae. Clypeus blackish. Chelicerae reddish brown. Legs yellow, dorsum annulated grey. Palps yellow. Sternum black. Abdomen dorsum dark brown. Abdomen venter grey, spotted yellow. Spinnerets yellow (
Fig. 4C
). Live specimens yellow, legs mildly annulated (
Figs 3
C–D).
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Transverse depression posterior to ocular area.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAL TEETH. 3 promarginal, 2 retromarginal.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Epigyne septum wider posteriorly, margins with small tooth or terrace in middle. Atria distinct (
Fig. 10C
), width variable (compare 
Šternbergs 1979
). Spermathecae round, unbent, distinct from sperm ducts (
Fig. 11C
).
</p>
      <p>LEGS. No clear pseudoarticulation on tarsi. Metatarsus I ventral spination: 3 pairs + apical triplet; tibia I ventral spination: 6 pairs + apical pair.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
Outside 
Israel
inhabits steppes. In 
Israel
inhabits hyperarid deserts. Specimens were found at night, on and in the cracks of fine-grained floodplain deposits (
Fig. 15C
). Adult female collected in March, adult male collected in February, juveniles collected in July (
Table 3
). The short legs, not typical of 
<tp:taxon-name>Evippinae</tp:taxon-name>
, may be an adaptation for a somewhat fossorial lifestyle.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Turkmenistan
(
Šternbergs 1979
), 
Iran
(

Zamani 
et al.
2016

), 
Israel
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Records
</p>
      <p>
Israel
: Dead Sea area (Qalya), Negev (Biq’at ‘Uvda, Nahal Hiyyon) (
Fig. 16
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The female of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa onager
</tp:taxon-name>
was originally described from 
China
by 
Simon (1895)
, and redescribed from both sexes by 
Šternbergs (1979)
from 
Turkmenistan
. It is very unlikely that these later specimens are conspecific with the 
holotype
(fide Marusik 
et al.
2003). As we have not examined Simon’s type specimen, we avoided describing a new species and instead have chosen to treat the species as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Evippa onager
sensu Šternbergs
</tp:taxon-name>
, following Marusik 
et al.
(2003).
</p>
      <p>
The species’ population in 
Israel
is by far the southernmost and westernmost of the three known localities, and the only one not in a steppe habitat. Nevertheless, cool steppe habitats are found in 
Israel
and it would be helpfull to search them for 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. onager
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
See Phylogenetic relationships of 
<tp:taxon-name>Evippinae</tp:taxon-name>
based on COI and NADH for a partial molecular phylogeny and a discussion of the placement of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. onager
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
