<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus nigriceps
(
Wittmer, 1955
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1D
, 
4A‒C
, 
6D
, 
8D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Podabrinus nigriceps
Wittmer, 1955: 39
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 1.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudoabsidia nigriceps
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Wittmer 1969: 128

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Athemellus nigriceps
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Wittmer 1972: 124

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Lycocerus nigriceps
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Kazantsev &amp; Brancucci 2007: 252

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
♂
; [p] “ 
Kwangtung. S. China.
// Kau- lin San. 900-1.450// Mt. Lien-p’ing Distr.// 

April 21. 1940

. // 
J. Linsley Gressitt
”, [h-p] “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Podabrinus
</tp:taxon-name>
// 
<tp:taxon-name>
nigriceps
</tp:taxon-name>
//Wittm.// det. 
W. Wittmer
”, [p] “ 
Holotypus
”, [p-h] “California Academy // of Sciences //Type // NO.7786”; 
CAS
.

</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
– 

Hong Kong

• 
1 ♀
; “Taipokan, 

2011.III.11

, coll. 
Paul Aston
”; 
MHBU

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
Taipokan
, 

2014. II.13

, coll. 
Paul Aston
”; 
MHBU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length (both sexes): 8.5‒11.0 mm; width: 2.0‒ 
2.4 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 1D
)
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body yellow, head and apices of elytra black, antennae, tarsi and bases of tibiae dark brown. Body densely covered with short, recumbent yellow pubescence, mixed with slightly longer semi-erect pubescence on elytra.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Subquadrate, surface densely and finely punctuate, each side with smooth rectangular impression behind antennal socket; eyes strongly protruding, head width across eyes about 1.2 times as wide as pronotum; terminal maxillary palpomeres long-triangular, widest in middle; antennae filiform, extending to two-thirds length of elytra; antennomeres II about 2.5 times as long as wide at apices, III about twice as long as II, IV longest, XI slightly longer than X, pointed at apex.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
Aedeagus (A, D, G = ventral view; B, E, H = dorsal view; C, F, I = lateral view). 
A‒C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus nigriceps
(
Wittmer, 1955
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(MHBU). 
D‒F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. flavus
Y. Yang &amp; X. Yang
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(IZAS, IOZ(E)1123159). 
G‒I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. longicornis
Y. Yang &amp; H. Liu
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(MHBU, HBU(E)410001). Scale bars: 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Subquadrate, about 1.2 times as long as wide, anterior margin nearly arcuate, anterior angles widely rounded, lateral margins nearly parallel, posterior margin straight, posterior angles moderately sharp, protruding, disc distinctly convex on posterolateral parts, surface finely and densely punctate.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Parallel-sided, about 4.0 times as long as humeral width, 4.2 times as long as pronotum, surface densely and finely punctate, with hardly indicated longitudinal costae.</p>
      <p>
AEDEAGUS (
Fig. 4A‒C
). Weakly swollen dorsally in basal part, weakly contracted in diameter basally; basal piece obviously shorter than dorsal plate of each paramere, each with triangular protuberance but without conjoint middle nodule at base of ventral side; ventral processes of parameres approaching to each other, long and slightly widened at apices, bent dorsally in lateral view; dorsal plate slightly longer than ventral process, strongly narrowed apically, narrow-triangularly protuberant in middle, apex acute and approaching to each other; apical part of laterophyses compressed and next to each other in middle, apex hooked and directed laterally, slightly exceeding middle emargination between dorsal plates.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Similar to male, but body stouter, eyes less protruding, head width across eyes slightly wider than anterior margin of pronotum; antennae narrower and shorter, extending to elytral mid-length; pronotum wider, nearly as long as wide; elytra slightly dilated posteriorly, about 3.1 times as long as humeral width.</p>
      <p>
ABDOMINAL STERNITE VIII (
Fig. 8D
). Obliquely narrowed posteriorly, latero-apical angles widely triangular, posterior margin deeply and roundly emarginate in middle and nearly straight on both sides (membrane missing behind notch).
</p>
      <p>
INTERNAL ORGAN OF REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM (
Fig. 6D
). Vagina moderately elongate, with median oviduct situated at ventro-apical part, diverticulum and spermathecal duct arising from apex; diverticulum moderately long, about 0.16 times body length, evenly thinned apically, slender tube-shaped and spiral; spermathecal duct much shorter than diverticulum; spermatheca slender tube-shaped and spiral, obviously thinner than spermathecal duct and shorter than diverticulum, with basal part extended into short tube, where accessory gland opening. Accessory gland thin and shorter than spermatheca.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>In this study, the structure of abdominal sternite VIII of the female is incomplete. Because there is only one female specimen, the structural description of abdominal sternite VIII needs to be improved.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Guangdong
, 
Hong Kong
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
