<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Stenothemus pallicolor Yang &amp; Yang &amp; Liu 2021, comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4694509</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/313E6AEE8E57DF6C2C9A7C7876713456</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the species of Stenothemus from Southeast China (Coleoptera, Cantharidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.744.1307</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus pallicolor
(
Wittmer, 1951
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1B
, 
3D‒F
, 
6B
, 
8B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Podabrinus pallicolor
Wittmer, 1951: 98
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudoabsidia pallicolor
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Wittmer 1969: 128

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Athemellus pallicolor
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Wittmer 1972: 124

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Lycocerus pallicolor
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Kazantsev &amp; Brancucci 2007: 252

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
♂
; [p] “ 
Kuatun
(

2300m

) 27, 40n. Br.//117. 40ö. 
L. J. Klapperich
// 

1. 3. 1938

(Fukien)”, [h] “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Podabrus
</tp:taxon-name>
// 
<tp:taxon-name>
pallicolor
</tp:taxon-name>
//Wittm.”, [h-p] “ 
Holotypus
// 
<tp:taxon-name>
Podabrinus
</tp:taxon-name>
// 
<tp:taxon-name>
pallicolor
</tp:taxon-name>
// n. sp. //Wittmer, 1949”; 
ZFMK
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratype
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
1 ♂
; [p] “ 
Kuatun
(

2300m

) 27, 40n. Br.// 117. 40ö. 
L. J. Klapperich
// 

4. 3. 1938

(Fukien)”, [p] “Paratypus”,[h]“ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Podabrinus
</tp:taxon-name>
// 
<tp:taxon-name>
pallicolor
</tp:taxon-name>
// Wittm.”,[h-p]“ 
A
. // 
<tp:taxon-name>
pallicolor
</tp:taxon-name>
// (Wittmer.) // det. 
W.Wittmer
”, [p]“Naturhistorisches// Museum Basel // Coll.W.Wittmer”,[p]“ 
<tp:taxon-name>CANTHARIDAE</tp:taxon-name>
// CANTH00001839”; 
NHMB
.

</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
Aedeagus (A, D, G = ventral view; B, E, H = dorsal view; C, F, I = lateral view). 
A‒C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus biimpressiceps
(
Pic, 1930
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(IZAS). 
D‒F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. pallicolor
(
Wittmer, 1951
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(IZAS). 
G‒I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. limbatipennis
(Pic, 1926)
</tp:taxon-name>
stat. rev. et comb. nov.
(MHBU). Scale bars: 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
– 

Fujian

• 
2 ♂♂
; 
Wuping
, 
Liangyeshan
, 
Kongxia
; 

627 m
a.s.l.

; 

17 Nov. 2008

; 
G.Y. Yang
leg.; 
IZAS

• 

2 ♂♂
, 
3 ♀♀
; Chong’an, San’gang; 

1 Dec. 1980

; 
L.Z. Hua
leg.; 
SYSU

• 

1 ♀
; 
Kuatun
; 

8 Apr. 1946

; 
Tschung Sen
leg.; 
NHMB

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length (both sexes): 7.2‒10.0 mm; width: 
1.3‒2.2 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 1B
)
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body dark brown, head, prothorax and scutellum testaceous, pronotum orange at anterior angles, elytra light brown, with irregular brown markings. Body mixed with short, recumbent and slightly long, semi-erect light yellow pubescence.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Subquadrate, surface sparsely and finely punctate, each side with smooth and rectangular impression behind antennal socket; eyes strongly protruding, head width across eyes 1.2 times as wide as pronotum; terminal maxillary palpomeres long-triangular, widest in basal third; antennae filiform, extending to two-thirds length of elytra; antennomere II about twice as long as wide at apices, III about 2.5 times as long as II, IV longest, XI slightly longer than X, pointed at apex.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Subquadrate, about 1.1 times as long as wide, anterior margin nearly straight, anterior angles roundly truncate, lateral margins slightly sinuate, posterior margin straight and narrowly bordered, posterior angles nearly rectangular and slightly protruding, disc distinctly convex on posterolateral parts, surface finely and sparsely punctate.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Slightly dilated posteriorly, about 4.3 times as long as humeral width, 6.0 times as long as pronotum, surface densely and finely punctate, present with hardly visible longitudinal costae.</p>
      <p>
AEDEAGUS (
Fig. 3D‒F
). Strongly swollen dorsally at basal part, nearly parallel-sided in apical part; basal piece obviously as long as dorsal plate of each paramere, with a large, bifurcate conjoint middle nodule at base of ventral side; ventral process of each paramere nearly parallel to each another, long and slightly thickened apically, bent dorsally in lateral view; dorsal plate nearly as long as ventral process, strongly narrowed and even in width along the whole length, acute at apex and folded ventrally; apical parts of laterophyses depressed and separate from each other, apex acute and almost reaching middle emargination between dorsal plates.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Similar to male, but body stouter, eyes less protruding, head width across eyes slightly wider than anterior margin of pronotum; antennae shorter, extending to elytral mid-length; elytra about 4.0 times as long as humeral width.</p>
      <p>
ABDOMINAL STERNITE VIII (
Fig. 8B
). Strongly narrowed posteriorly, latero-apical angles obtusely widetriangular, posterior margin deeply and rectangularly emarginate in middle and hardly emarginate on both sides, behind notch with membrane which presents small traverse-triangular sclerite at center.
</p>
      <p>
INTERNAL ORGAN OF REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM (
Fig. 6B
).Vagina stout, with median oviduct situated at ventroapical part, diverticulum and spermathecal duct arising from apex; diverticulum moderately long, about 0.12 times body length, evenly thinned apically, slender tube-shaped and spiral; spermathecal duct long but shorter than diverticulum; spermatheca slender tube-shaped and spiral, slightly thinner than spermathecal duct and shorter than diverticulum, with basal part extended into short tube, where accessory gland opening. Accessory gland thin, and shorter than spermatheca.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The morphological characters, including the aedeagus, indicate that this species should belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Fujian
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
