<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ophryotrocha geoffreadi, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4570311</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/CB2A8DAE0959C348F995AA375A5C2DD3</uri>
         <article-title>Four new species and further records of Dorvilleidae (Annelida, Polychaeta) from deep-sea organic substrata, NE Atlantic</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Ophryotrocha geoffreadi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
F5023AAF-791B-47A3-90A2-824D50CC4826
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named after Dr Geoffrey Read, the chief taxonomic editor of 
<tp:taxon-name>Polychaeta</tp:taxon-name>
at the World Register of Marine species (WoRMS) and founder of the Annelida mailing list. His tireless work in both these initiatives is an immense and invaluable aid to all polychaetologists.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MOROCCO
• 
complete spec
. (ethanol), 
0.94 mm
long, 
0.17 mm
wide, 16 chaetigers; GoC, Meknès MV; 
34°59.091′ N
, 
07°04.424′ W
; 

698 m
depth

; 

20 May 2009

; Stn B09-14b_03W; 
wood substrata
; 
NHMUK 2020.1512
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
MOROCCO
• 
31 specs
(formalin); same collection data as for holotype; 
NHMUK 2020.1513

• 

1 spec.
(ethanol), 
2 specs
(slide preparation); same collection data as for holotype; 
DBUA0002286.02

.
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
MOROCCO
• 
5 specs
(ethanol); same locality as for holotype; 

20 May 2009

; Stn B09-14b_03A; 
alfalfa substrata
; 
DBUA0002286.03
(1 hologenophore, 4 paragenophores)

• 

2 specs
(ethanol), 
13 specs
(formalin); GoC Darwin MV; 
35°23.523′ N
, 
07°11.513′ W
; 

1100 m
depth

; 

19 May 2009

; Stn B09- 14b_02A; 
alfalfa substrata
; 
DBUA0002286.04

• 

9 specs
(ethanol), 
1 spec.
(slide preparation), 
5 specs
(formalin); same collection data as for preceding; 

19 May 2009

; Stn B09-14b_02W; 
wood substrata
; 
DBUA0002286.05

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Relatively small specimens compared to most species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophryotrocha
</tp:taxon-name>
. Most of the larger specimens are damaged or incomplete and were not measured. Measured specimens 
0.73 to 1.46 mm
long and 
0.19 mm
wide, for 17 to 25 chaetigers (
Fig. 3
). Body dorso-ventrally flattened, wider anteriorly and tapering posteriorly. Prostomium broadly rounded (
Fig. 7A
), without eyes. Antennae and palps short, cirriform; antennae inserted mid-dorsally on the prostomium; palps inserted laterally. Peristomium achaetous, with two rings of length similar to the following segments. Jaw apparatus brown, well visible through the specimen body. Mandibles rod-like, with straight, serrated cutting edge (with around 8 teeth in smaller specimens, 
Fig. 7B
) and weakly sclerotized apophyses, shorter than cutting edges. In larger specimens, the cutting edge teeth are usually worn and the apohyses are enlarged longitudinally (
Fig. 7E
). Maxillae of P-type (also after moulting) with asymmetric forceps; left forceps narrow and finely toothed (up to 35? teeth), right forceps wider and coarsely toothed (~15 teeth) (
Fig. 7F
); seven free denticles (D1–7; 
Fig. 7C, F
), D1 comb-like coarsely toothed, similar to right forceps, D2 shovellike with an outer larger tooth and coarse teeth, D4–6 shovel-like with smaller teeth slightly increasing in number anteriorly, D7 shovel-like, much broader than the others; carrier-like structure with a toothed ridge on each side at the base of the bifurcation (
Fig. 7F
) and a posteriorly fimbriate handle (
Fig. 7C
). Parapodia uniramous, with conical acicular lobes, inconspicuous pre-chaetal lamellae, long sub-acicular lobes and conical dorsal cirri inserted sub-distally on the parapodia (
Fig. 7D
); ventral cirri absent. Subacicular lobes with a short needle-like protruding acicula (
Fig. 7H
). Chaetae relatively short and stiff; supra-acicular chaetae simple, tapering distally, smooth or very finely serrated, up to 7 per fascicle (
Fig. 7I
); sub-acicular chaetae compound with sub-distally serrated shafts and falcate, lightly serrated blades (
Fig. 7G
), up to 7 per fascicle. Pygidium with terminal anus, a pair of short cirriform anal cirri (spherical and almost inconspicuous in smaller specimens) and a median papilla.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
According to the phylogenetic analysis (
Fig. 2
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. geoffreadi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is close to the species 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. langstrumpae

Wiklund 
et al
., 2012

</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. sadina
Ravara, Marçal, Wiklund &amp; Hilário, 2015
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. cantabrica
Nuñez, Riera &amp; Maggio, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. scutellus
Wiklund, Glover &amp; Dahlgren, 2009
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. lusa
Ravara, Marçal, Wiklund &amp; Hilário, 2015
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. batillus

Wiklund 
et al
., 2012

</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. chemecoli
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(

Wiklund 
et al
. 2009

, 
2012
; 

Nuñez 
et al
. 2014

; 

Ravara 
et al
. 2015

). However, unlike 
<tp:taxon-name>
O
. 
geoffreadi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, all those species have well-developed parapodial lobes and cirri, and only two of them (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. langstrumpae
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. cantabrica
</tp:taxon-name>
) have mandibulae with a straight cutting edge but without membranous apophyses. Three other species that are not included in the phylogenetic analysis have mandibulae with a straight, serrated cutting edge: 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. pachysoma
Hilbig &amp; Blake, 1991
</tp:taxon-name>
from the W Atlantic (
604–2065 m
depth), 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. natans
Pfannenstiel, 1975
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Red Sea (intertidal) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. kagoshimaensis
Miura, 1997
</tp:taxon-name>
from the W Pacific (
197 m
depth) (
Pfannenstiel 1975
; 
Hilbig &amp; Blake 1991
; 
Miura 1997
). Nevertheless, the presence of a membranous apophyse below the cutting edge is not clear for the two latter species, and the cutting edge of the mandibulae of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. pachysoma
</tp:taxon-name>
is much wider and also serrated on its internal border. Furthermore, the maxillary, parapodial and chaetal morphology of all these species is different from that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. geoffreadi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophryotrocha geoffreadi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Stereo (A) and compound (B–I) microscope images. A–D: DBUA0002286.02; E–I: DBUA0002286.05. 
A
. Anterior region, ventral view. 
B
. Mandibulae of a smaller specimen, ventral view. 
C
. Maxillae of the same specimen with moulting pieces, ventral view. 
D
. Median parapodia, anterior view. 
E
. Mandibulae of a larger specimen, ventral view. 
F
. Maxillae of the same specimen, dorsal view. 
G
. Sub-acicular chaetae of mid-body parapodia. 
H
. Simple chaeta protruding from the sub-acicular lobe of a mid-body parapodium. 
I
. Supra-acicular chaetae, mid-body parapodium. Numbers refer to free denticles.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology and distribution
</p>
      <p>
NE Atlantic: Gulf of Cadiz (Moroccan Margin). Found in experimentally deployed wood and alfalfa substrata, at 
698–1100 m
depth (this study).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
