<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes pacificus
Schmidt, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 8A, D, G
; 
Tables 7–8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Emended diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes
</tp:taxon-name>
with middorsal spines on segments 4 to 8, and lateroventral spines on segments 6 to 9; middorsal spines on segments 5 to 8 extend well beyond the posterior margin of their respective segments. Tubes present in lateroventral positions on segments 2 and 5, and in midlateral positions on 10; tubes on segment 10 short and stout. Minute glandular cell outlets 
type
2 in
laterodorsal positions on segment 8. Tergal extensions of segment 11 triangular, pointed, well-spaced. Females with female papillae with crescentic and tubular substructure in ventrolateral positions on segment 7 and ventromedial on segment 8. Lateral terminal spines thick in proximal 
⅓
, but tapered abruptly into very thin distal 
⅔
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
GALAPAGOS
• 
1 ♂
; 
Santa Cruz
; 
00°45′ S
, 
090°19′ W
; &lt;

1 m
b.s.l.

; 

Jul.–Sep. 1972

; 
P. Schmidt
leg.; heterogeneous sediment, rich in organic matter; 
USNM-53335
. Specimen mounted for LM.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
GALAPAGOS
• 
5 ♀♀
, 
4 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
USNM-53336
. Specimens mounted for LM

.
</p>
      <p>
Most of the 
paratypes
were in surprisingly good condition, whereas the mounting medium around the 
holotype
was dried out. SEM specimens were not available. See 
Table 1
for an overview.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
The appearance of the species generally follows the original description by 
Schmidt (1974)
, and in particular the redescription by 
Higgins (1977a)
, hence the following notes only provide additional information not included in the two previous descriptions. For complete overview of measurements and dimensions, see 
Table 7
. Distribution of cuticular structures, i.e., sensory spots, glandular cell outlets, spines and tubes, is summarized in 
Table 8
.
</p>
      <p>
Table 7.
Measurements from light microscopy for holotype and nine paratypes of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes pacificus
Schmidt, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
from Galapagos Islands (in µm), including number of measured specimens (
n
) and standard deviation (SD).
</p>
      <p>
Character
n
Range
Mean
SD
TL MSW-8 MSW-8/TL SW–10 SW–10/TL S1 S2 S3 S4 S5 S6 S7 S8 S9 S10 S11
10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10 10
359–393 69–75 18.7–20.1% 64–72 17.7–18.7% 35–39 32–39 33–41 38–43 40–46 43–50 45–52 48–53 50–59 46–54 34–39
378 73 19.3% 68 18.1% 37 35 38 40 43 45 48 52 53 49 36
10.46 2.31 0.44% 2.16% 0.34% 1.41 2.18 2.28 1.75 2.16 2.45 2.42 1.55 2.81 2.82 1.93
MD4 (ac) MD5 (ac) MD6 (ac) MD7 (ac) MD8 (ac)
9 7 8 9 9
27–33 31–44 41–54 56–71 77–89
28 35 51 65 83
1.94 4.50 4.21 5.30 4.43
LV2 (tu) LV5 (tu) LV6 (ac) LV7 (ac) LV8 (ac) LV9 (ac) ML10 (tu)
10 9 10 10 10 9 10
16–23 17–21 19–27 27–34 31–38 35–43 12–17
19 18 25 31 36 38 14
2.21 1.20 2.36 2.13 2.08 2.50 1.97
LTS LTS/TL LTAS
10 10 5
96–130 26.5–33.5% 36–40
108 28.5% 37
9.38 2.23% 1.67
</p>
      <p>
Table 8.
Summary of nature and location of sensory spots, glandular cell outlets, tubes and spines arranged by series in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes pacificus
Schmidt, 1974
</tp:taxon-name>
. Note that mapping of sensory spots might be incomplete.
</p>
      <p>
Position Segment
MD
PD
SD
LD
ML
SL
LA
LV
VL
VM
1
gco1
ss
ss
gco1
ss
2
gco1, ss
ss,ss
tu
ss, gco1
3
gco1
ss
ss
gco1
4
ac
gco1, ss
ss
ss, gco1
5
ac
gco1, ss
ss
tu
ss, gco1
6
ac
ss
gco1, ss
ss
ac
ss,gco1
7
ac
ss
gco1, ss
ss
ac
fpa (♀)
ss,gco1
8
ac
ss
gco1, ss
gco2
ss
ac
ss
gco1, fpa (♀)
9
ss
gco1, ss
ss
si
ac
ss
gco1
10
gco1, gco1
ss
tu
ss
gco1
11
gco1, gco1
ss
3xpe (♂)
ltas (♀)
lts
</p>
      <p>
Spines and tubes are as described by 
Higgins (1977a)
, and middorsal spines on segments 5 to 8 extend well beyond the posterior margins of segments from which they originate (
Fig. 8A
). The line art illustrations provided with the redescription also summarize and show the distribution of glandular cell outlets 
type
1 correctly (white open circles in 
Higgins 1977a
: figs 26–27), even though the nature of these structures are misinterpreted, mostly as sensory spots in the text. Same illustrations also picture laterodorsal glandular cell outlets 
type
2 on segment 8, and female papillae with a crescentic substructure in ventrolateral positions on segment 7 and ventromedial positions on segment 8. Our observations confirm the presence of these structures (
Fig. 8D
). The substructure of the female papillae is crescentic, as reported by 
Higgins (1977a)
, and in addition they also have a relatively strong tubular substructure.
</p>
      <p>
Higgins (1977a)
furthermore noted the short, curved midlateral tubes on segment 10 (described as “lateral spine of segment 12”, following the old terminology). We can confirm the distinct appearance of these tubes, and add that they, besides being curved, are conspicuously short and stout, and somewhat truncate (
Fig. 8G
), which make them differ from segment 10 tubes in other species examined for the present study. Another highly characteristic feature regards the shape of the lateral terminal spines. The proximal parts of the spines are conspicuously thick, or swollen, but around 
⅓
from the proximal end the spines taper abruptly, and become very thin and nearly seta-like (
Fig. 8G
). Tergal extensions are triangular and well-spaced; sternal extensions are short with ventrolateral seta-like tuft of extended fringe tips.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
