<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Stenothemus jindraimimus Y. Yang &amp; X. Yang 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5038620</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C0930FF075823D0D7D964CA2E90518D5</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the species of Stenothemus from Southwest China (Coleoptera, Cantharidae), with the descriptions of five new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1409</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Stenothemus jindraimimus
Y. Yang &amp; X. Yang
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3BA9E362-3F39-4413-B04B-FF1CB6549998
</p>
      <p>
Figs 9D
, 
10G‒I
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jindrai
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 5A
), but differs in the following characters: pronotum and elytra uniformly light yellow, while pronotum dark brown, lightened at anterior angles, elytra honey yellow, sienna at humeri and outer part in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jindrai
</tp:taxon-name>
; aedeagus:apex of dorsal plate slightly narrowed, middle emargination between dorsal plates moderately deep, nearly as long as half its length, apical parts of laterophyses reaching middle emargination between dorsal plates, while dorsal plate strongly narrowed, middle emargination much longer than half length, laterophyses clearly exceeding middle emargination in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jindrai
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Švihla 2004
: figs 155‒156).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific name is derived from the Latin ‘ 
mimus
’ (‘imitate’), and the name of the similar species 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. jindrai
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Sichuan
, 
Emei Shan
, 
Xixiangchi
; 

1800‒2000 m
a.s.l.

; 

11‒12 May 1957

; 
F.X. Zhu
leg.; 
IZAS
IOZ(E) 
1389239
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Body length: 
♂
6.6 mm
; width: 
1.5 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 9D
)
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. Body light yellow, head, mouthparts, antennae and tarsi light brown. Body densely covered with short, semi-recumbent yellow pubescence.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Subquadrate, surface sparsely and finely punctate, each side with a smooth and rectangular impression behind antennal socket; eyes strongly protruding, head width across eyes 1.5 times wider than pronotum; terminal maxillary palpomeres long-triangular, widest in middle; antennae filiform, extending ¾ of the length of elytra, antennomeres II about 1.7 times as long as wide at apices, III about 1.9 times longer than II, IV longest, XI slightly longer than X, pointed at apex.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Subrounded, about 0.9 times as long as wide, anterior margin nearly straight, anterior angles roundly truncate, lateral margins slightly sinuate, posterior margin nearly straight and narrowly bordered, posterior angles sharp, protruding, disc distinctly convex on posterolateral parts, surface finely and densely punctate.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Nearly parallel-sided, about 3.7 times as long as humeral width, 6.1 times as long as pronotum, surface finely and densely punctate, with hardly visible longitudinal costae.</p>
      <p>
AEDEAGUS (
Figs 10G‒I
). Weakly swollen dorsally in basal part, reduced basally in diameter; basal piece slightly shorter than dorsal plate of each paramere, with a large, bifurcate conjoined middle nodule at base of ventral side; ventral processes of parameres approaching each other, long and slightly narrowed apically, bent ventrally in lateral view; dorsal plates slightly longer than ventral processes, evenly narrowed apically, apex slightly acute and bent ventrally, outer margins of dorsal plates folded ventrally; apical parts of laterophyses depressed and next to each other in middle, apex acute, reaching middle emargination between dorsal plates.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Sichuan
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
