<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Echinoderes lanceolatus Chang &amp; Song 2002</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4420021</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03C79270FF9A572BB14DFBC61941FE26</uri>
         <article-title>Description, redescription and revision of sixteen putatively closely related species of Echinoderes (Kinorhyncha: Cyclorhagida), with the proposition of a new species group - the Echinoderes dujardinii group</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes lanceolatus
Chang &amp; Song, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 18
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
REPUBLIC OF KOREA
• 
♀
; 
Jeju Island
, 
Boemseom Islet
; 
33°11′53″ N
, 
126°30′58″ E
; 

25 m
b.s.l.

; 

3 Mar. 2000

; 
J. Lee
and 
Y.H. Song
leg.; muddy sand; 
EWNHM60268
. Specimen mounted for LM.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
Additional examined material included all specimens listed as “additional material examined” in 
Chang &amp; Song (2002: 206)
. This material was collected from other islands in the Korean East Sea, along the south coast of the Korean Peninsula, and around 
Jeju
Island (see further details in 
Table 1
and below under description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes songae
Sørensen &amp; Chang
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

Morphological notes on female 
holotype
</p>
      <p>
Specimen with slender middorsal spines on segments 4 to 8, and lateroventral spines on segments 6 to 9; middorsal spine on segment 6 reaches posterior segment margin, whereas middorsal spines on segments 7 and 8 reach well beyond their respective posterior margins (
Fig. 18B
). Tubes present in ventrolateral positions on segment 2 (
Fig. 18D
) and lateroventral positions on 5, and in midlateral positions on 10. An incomplete midventral, intracuticular fissure is present on anterior half of segment 2 (
Fig. 18D
). Complete overview of glandular cell outlets 
type
1 distribution could not be obtained, but we see indications of paradorsal outlets on segment 6. Glandular cell outlets 
type
2 are not present on any segment (
Fig. 18E
). Female lateral terminal accessory spines are short, with stout bases. Female papillae were difficult to examine, but indications of ventrolateral papillae with a tubular substructure were observed on segment 7 (
Fig. 18C
). All characters that could be observed fit the emended diagnosis of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. aureus
</tp:taxon-name>
, which suggest that 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. lanceolatus
</tp:taxon-name>
is a junior synonym of this species.
</p>
      <p>
Morphological notes on additional material
</p>
      <p>
All examined 
paratypes
and non-types supposed to represent the morphology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. lanceolatus
</tp:taxon-name>
were similar, but differed from the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. lanceolatus
</tp:taxon-name>
. The specimens have short middorsal spines on segments 4 to 8, and lateroventral spines on segments 6 to 9; middorsal spines never reach the pectinate fringes of the posterior margins of their segments – not even middorsal spines on more posterior segments. Tubes are present in lateroventral positions on segments 2 and 5, and in laterodorsal positions on 10. Minute glandular cell outlets type 2 are present in laterodorsal positions on segments 8, but lacking on segment 9. Tergal extensions of segment 11 are short, pointed and well-spaced, whereas sternal extensions are short and triangular, but not as pointed as the tergal ones. Seta-like, ventrolateral tufts of extended fringe tips project from the sternal extensions. Females have slender lateral terminal accessory spines, and female papillae with tubular intracuticular substructure in ventrolateral positions on segments 7 and in ventromedial positions on segment 8. These traits suggest that the specimens are not conspecific with the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. lanceolatus
</tp:taxon-name>
, but represent a new species (see following description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. songae
Sørensen &amp; Chang
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
