<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Echinoderes worthingi Zelinka 1928</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4419047</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/34B50AA8B28603595D92204D015FAFBE</uri>
         <article-title>Description, redescription and revision of sixteen putatively closely related species of Echinoderes (Kinorhyncha: Cyclorhagida), with the proposition of a new species group - the Echinoderes dujardinii group</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes worthingi
Zelinka, 1928
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 16–17
; 
Table 13
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Emended diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes
</tp:taxon-name>
with middorsal spines on segments 4 to 8, and lateroventral spines on segments 6 to 9; middorsal spines on segments 4 to 6 are barely reaching posterior segment margins of respective segments, whereas middorsal spine on segment 8 is more than twice as long as any other middorsal spine, extending to the posterior margin of segment 9 or onto segment 10. Tubes present in lateroventral positions on segments 2 and 5, and in laterodorsal positions on 10. Glandular cell outlets 
type
2 not present. Paradorsal glandular cell outlets 
type
1 on segment 11. Primary pectinate fringe on ventral sides of segments 1 to 3 very well-developed, in particular on segment 1. Tergal extensions of segment 11 pointed, with tips extending into long, seta-like fringe. Females with ventromedial female papillae formed by conspicuously strong spatulate tubular substructures on segments 7 and 8.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
FRANCE
• 
1 ♀
; 
Roscoff
; 
48°43′ N
, 
003°59′ W
; &lt;

1 m
b.s.l.

; 

19 Oct. 1973

; 
E. Kozloff
leg.; sandy mud (see 
Higgins 1985
); 
USNM-96034
. Specimen mounted for LM

.
</p>
      <p>
UNITED KINGDOM
• 
1 ♂
; 
Plymouth
; 
50°20′ N
, 
004°07′ W
; 

8 m
b.s.l.

; 

10 July 1978

; 
R.P. Higgins
leg.; sandy mud (see 
Higgins 1985
); 
USNM-67282
. Specimen mounted for LM

.
</p>
      <p>
SWEDEN
• 
2 ♀♀
; 
Kungshamn
; 
58°20′ N
, 
011°14′ E
; 
SMNH-155944A
, 
SMNH-155944B

• 

1 ♀
; 
Tjärnö
; 
58°51′ N
, 
011°09′ E
; 
2004
; 
G. Giribet
leg.; 
NHMD-644455
. Specimens mounted for LM

.
</p>
      <p>
DENMARK
• 
1 ♀
; 
Hirsholmene
; 
57°29′17″ N
, 
010°38′01″ E
; &lt;

10 m
b.s.l.

; 

28 Jan. 2001

; 
M.V. Sørensen
leg.; shell gravel; 
NHMD-644454
. Specimen mounted for LM

.
</p>
      <p>
SPAIN
• 
3 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Huelva
, 
El Portil
; 
37°07′37″ N
, 
006°48′54″ W
; &lt;

1 m
b.s.l.

; 

6 May 2012

; 
M. Herranz
, 
N. Sánchez
and 
F. Pardos
leg.; rocks and stones; personal reference collection of M. Herranz. Specimens mounted for SEM

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
No 
type
material was available. See 
Table 1
for an overview.
</p>
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
The appearance of the species generally follows the redescription provided by 
Higgins (1985)
, hence the following notes only provide additional information not included in the original description. We could confirm the lack of glandular cell outlets 
type
2 in
this species. Spines and tubes as described by 
Higgins (1985)
, with the conspicuously long middorsal spine on segment 8 that extends to the posterior margin of segment 9, or onto segment 10 (
Figs 16F
, 
17B
). Pectinate fringes on the posterior segment margins on segments 1 to 3 are differentiated into a dorsal half with very minute fringe tips, and a ventral half with long and well-developed fringe tips; especially on segment 1 (
Fig. 17
C–D). On segment 4, all fringe tips are well-developed, except in the laterodorsal parts of the margin, and fringes are well-developed all around the segment margins from segments 5 to 10. Glandular cell outlets 
type
1 present in middorsal positions on segments 1 to 3 (
Fig. 16B
) and 10 (
Fig. 16I
) (two longitudinally aligned), in subdorsal positions on segments 4 to 9 (
Fig. 16
D–F), in sublateral positions on segment 1 (
Fig. 16C
), and ventromedial positions on segments 2 to 10 (most of these structures are also included in the original description, but generally referred to as ‘subcuticular scars’). An additional, not previously reported pair of paradorsal glandular cell outlets 
type
1 is present on segment 11 (
Fig. 16I
). Sensory spots were easily observed in most specimens (
Figs 16B, D, F, I
, 
17A
, C–F, H). Their positions are summarized in 
Table 13
. Female papillae are present in ventromedial positions on segments 7 (more lateral) and 8 (more midventral) (
Figs 16E
, 
17E
). They consist of circular openings, resembling glandular cell outlets 
type
2 (
Fig. 17E
), and rather strong oblique, spatulate tubular intracuticular substructures (
Fig. 16
G–H). The female from Roscoff (USNM-96034) is a preadult with a very thin cuticle, which explains why 
Higgins (1985)
missed these structures. They are, however, very distinct in the Kattegat specimens (
Fig. 16
G–H). Hair-patterns are as described by 
Higgins (1985)
, but opposite to this redescription, perforation sites are usually distinct (expect for the preadult from Roscoff). Laterodorsal tubes on segment 10 are quite long and slender (
Figs 16
I–J, 17G–H). Tergal extensions of segment 11 pointed, and extending into long, flexible seta-like tips, formed by a terminal fringe (
Figs 16
I–J, 17G–H). Sternal extensions rounded, without any particular fringe differentiation (
Figs 16K
, 
17H
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
