<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Echinoderes sublicarum Higgins 1977</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4419035</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/3C3E9ABC3924DFE1453305E69E66ECD3</uri>
         <article-title>Description, redescription and revision of sixteen putatively closely related species of Echinoderes (Kinorhyncha: Cyclorhagida), with the proposition of a new species group - the Echinoderes dujardinii group</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes sublicarum
Higgins, 1977
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 8C, F, I
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Emended diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Echinoderes
</tp:taxon-name>
with middorsal spines on segments 4 to 8, and lateroventral spines on segments 6 to 9; middorsal spines on segments 5 to 8 extend well beyond the posterior margin of their respective segments. Tubes present in lateroventral positions on segments 2 and 5, and in laterodorsal positions on 10; tubes on segment 10 are long and slender. Minute glandular cell outlets 
type
2 in
laterodorsal positions on segment 8. Tergal extensions of segment 11 pointed, with additional tooth on inferior margin. Females with ventromedial female papillae formed by crescentic substructure and a tube on segment 8; similar ventrolateral female papillae might also be present on segment 7.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
SOUTH CAROLINA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Georgetown
, 
North Inlet Estuary
, 
Clambank docks
; 
33°20′ N
, 
079°11′ W
; &lt;

1 m
b.s.l.

; 

19 Mar. 1975

; 
W. Sikora
leg.; from the hydroid 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eudendrium
</tp:taxon-name>
sp.; 
USNM-54397
. Specimen mounted for LM.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
SOUTH CAROLINA
• 
4 ♀♀
, 
4 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
USNM-54399
to 
54400
. Specimens mounted for LM
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Most of the 
types
were in good condition, although the mounting medium was partly or fully dried out. While it was easy to see spines and tubes, it was very difficult or impossible to see the mostly subcuticular structures, such as glandular cell out 
type
1, female papillae and sensory spots. SEM specimens were not available. See 
Table 1
for an overview.
</p>
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
The appearance of the species generally follows the description provided by 
Higgins (1977b)
, hence the following notes only provide additional information not included in the original description.
</p>
      <p>
Males and females with minute laterodorsal glandular cell outlets 
type
2 on segment 8 (
Fig. 8C
). Spines and tubes as described by 
Higgins (1977b)
. Glandular cell outlets 
type
1 present in middorsal positions on segments 1 to 3, 10 (two longitudinally aligned) and 11, in subdorsal positions on segments 4 to 9, in sublateral positions on segment 1, and ventromedial positions on segments 2 to 10 (most of these structures are also included in the original description, but generally referred to as ‘sensory spots’).Actual sensory spots were only observed in paradorsal positions on segments 6 to 8, but more sensory spots are most likely present. Female papillae are present in ventromedial positions on segment 8 (
Fig. 8F
). The intracuticular substructures indicate the presence of a very weak crescentic line, and a more distinct tube extending from the centre of this line. 
Higgins (1977b)
also reports these structures but refers to them as “bracket-shaped muscle scars”. He does not mention that they are restricted to females, but we can confirm that this is the case. 
Higgins (1977b)
furthermore reports the present of “bracket-shaped muscle scars” in ventrolateral positions of segment 7. This suggests that female papillae also could be present on this segment. We cannot confirm their presence, but this is most likely due to the age and condition of the 
type
specimens. Hence, based on own observations and information provided by 
Higgins (1977b)
we find it likely that female papillae are present in ventrolateral positions of segment 7 and ventromedial positions of segment 8. Laterodorsal tubes on segment 10 are quite long and slender (
Fig. 8I
). Tergal extensions of segment 11 are well-spaced and pointed (
Fig. 8I
). Lateral terminal spines are regular acicular, and gradually tapered towards tips.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
