<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Echinoderes pilosus Lang
                        1949</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4420027</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03C79270FFB0573AB111F93E19DBFCC7</uri>
                  <article-title>Description, redescription and revision of sixteen putatively
                        closely related species of Echinoderes (Kinorhyncha: Cyclorhagida), with the
                        proposition of a new species group - the Echinoderes dujardinii
                        group</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes pilosus Lang, 1949 </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 9–10 ; Tables 9–10 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Emended diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes </tp:taxon-name> with middorsal spines on segments 4
                  to 8, and lateroventral spines on segments 6 to 9; all middorsal spines slender
                  and flexible and projecting well beyond the posterior margin of their respective
                  segments. Long and slender tubes present in ventrolateral positions on segment 2,
                  lateroventral positions on segment 5, and in laterodorsal positions on 10.
                  Incomplete midventral, intracuticular fissure present on anterior half of segment
                  2. Two middorsal, longitudinally aligned glandular cell outlets type on segment 1.
                  Minute glandular cell outlets type 2 in subdorsal positions on segment 2, and in
                  laterodorsal positions on segments 8 and 9. Tergal extensions of segment 11 short
                  and pointed; margin of sternal extensions straight, with ventrolateral seta-like
                  tuft of extended fringe tips. Females with female papillae with tubular
                  substructure in ventrolateral positions on segment 7 and ventromedial positions on
                  segment 8; males with ventrolateral sensory spots on segment 10. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Lectotype (here designated) </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SOUTH GEORGIA ISLANDS • ♀ ; Grytviken ; 54°16′59″ S ,
                        36°30′29″ W ; 22–23 May 1902 ; collected during the Swedish Antarctic
                        Expedition in Grytviken; SMNH 3930 . Specimen mounted for LM.
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paralectotypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> SOUTH GEORGE ISLANDS • 15 ♀♀ , 18 ♂♂ , 3 uncertain sex;
                        same collection data as for lectotype; SMNH-1007 , SMNH-9256 to 9282 .
                        SMNH-1007 , SMNH-9256 to 9282 . 9 ♀♀ , 13 ♂♂ and 3 uncertain sex mounted for
                        LM; 6 ♀♀, 5 ♂♂ mounted for SEM </tp:material-citation> ; </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Higgins (1986) mentions that he accessed the type material of <tp:taxon-name> E.
                        pilosus in SMNH </tp:taxon-name> , mounted and observed two paratypic
                  specimens. However, such mounted specimens were found in neither the SMNH nor the
                  USNM. </p>
            <p> After examining the syntypes and providing the present redescription we choose, in
                  the interest of assuring future taxonomic stability, to designate one of the
                  female syntype as lectotype for <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes pilosus
                  </tp:taxon-name> with the catalogue number SMNH-3930, and consequently designate
                  the remaining specimens as paralectotypes (SMNH-1007, 9256–9282). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> The species was described by Lang (1949) , and more recently redescribed by Higgins
                  (1986) . However, since information from SEM not previously has been available for
                  the species, and since the present examinations with LM and SEM resulted in
                  substantial new information about the morphology of the species, we are here
                  providing a full redescription. </p>
            <p> Adults with head, neck and eleven trunk segments. The anterior part of the trunk is
                  relatively stout, and maximum width is reached around segments 6 and 7 ( Fig. 9
                  A–B). From segment 8 the segments taper significantly, giving the species an
                  appearance of a pointed hind end ( Fig. 9 A–B). The trunk cuticle appears thin in
                  SEM specimens ( Fig. 10A ), and tends to collapse posterior to the stronger
                  pachycycli. Secondary pectinate fringe present near anterior segment margin on
                  segments 2 to 10. For complete overview of measurements and dimensions, see Table
                  9 . Distribution of cuticular structures, i.e., sensory spots, glandular cell
                  outlets, spines and tubes, is summarized in Table 10 . </p>
            <p>The head consists of a retractable mouth cone and an introvert. Inner oral styles
                  could not be examined. Nine outer oral styles are present; nine tufts with ca. six
                  long, rigid and distally bifurcated tips in each, attach basally on the mouth
                  cone, posterior to each outer oral style. The exact arrangement of scalids could
                  not be examined.</p>
            <p> The neck has 16 placids, measuring 19 µm in length. The midventral placid is
                  broadest, measuring 17 µm in width at its base, whereas all other are narrower,
                  measuring 10 µm in width at their bases. </p>
            <p> Fig. 9. Light micrographs showing overviews and details of <tp:taxon-name>
                        Echinoderes pilosus Lang, 1949 </tp:taxon-name> . A–B, G–L . Lectotype, ♀
                  (SMNH-3930a). C–F, M . Paralectotype, ♂ (SMNH-3930b). A . Dorsal overview. B .
                  Ventral overview. C . Segments 1 to 2, dorsal view. D . Segments 1 to 2, ventral
                  view. E . Segments 1 to 3, dorsal view. F . Segments 2 to 4, ventral view. G .
                  Segments 6 to 7, ventral view, showing female sexual dimorphism. H . Segments 3 to
                  5, dorsal view. I . Segments 8 to 9, dorsal view. J . Segments 7 to 8, ventral
                  view, showing female sexual dimorphism. K . Segments 10 to 11, ventrolateral view,
                  showing female sexual dimorphism. L . Segments 8 to 9, dorsal view but deeper
                  focal plane than (I). M . Segments 10 to 11, ventral view, showing male sexual
                  dimorphism. </p>
            <p> Fig. 10. Scanning electron micrographs showing overviews and details of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes pilosus Lang, 1949 </tp:taxon-name> . A–J, L . ♀
                  (SMNH-9262, SMNH-9281). K .♂ (SMNH-9262). A . Lateral overview. B . Segments 1 to
                  2, dorsal view. C . Segments 1 to 2, ventral view. D . Segments 3 to 4, dorsal
                  view. E . Segments 5 to 6, lateral view. F . Segments 6 to 7, ventral view,
                  showing female sexual dimorphism; inset shows ventrolateral female papilla on
                  segment 6, scale on inset = 1 µm. G . Segments 8 to 9, dorsal view. H . Segments 8
                  to 9, laterodorsal view. I . Segments 7 to 8, ventral view, showing female sexual
                  dimorphism; inset shows ventromedial female papilla on segment 8, scale on inset =
                  2 µm. J . Segments 10 to 11 dorsal view, showing female sexual dimorphism. K .
                  Segments 10 to 11 ventral view, showing male sexual dimorphism. L . Segments 10 to
                  11 ventral view, showing female sexual dimorphism. </p>
            <p> Table 9. Measurements from light microscopy for lectotype and nine paralectotypes of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes pilosus Lang, 1949 </tp:taxon-name> from
                  Grytviken, South Georgia Island (in µm), including number of measured specimens (
                  n ) and standard deviation (SD). </p>
            <p> Character n Range Mean SD TL MSW-8 MSW-8/TL SW-10 SW-10/TL S1 S2 S3 S4 S5 S6 S7 S8
                  S9 S10 S11 14 14 11 15 11 14 14 15 15 15 17 18 17 16 15 15 343–440 79–90
                  19.0–25.1% 65–78 15.4–20.0% 36–54 27–41 26–33 27–37 31–38 33–43 35–49 40–52 42–55
                  51–61 30–40 389 86 22.5% 71 18.6% 44 34 30 33 35 38 42 46 49 55 34 28.83 3.09
                  1.86% 4.24% 1.44% 5,70 4,43 1,99 2,93 1,93 2,76 3,60 3,46 3,07 3,70 3,40 MD4 (ac)
                  MD5 (ac) MD6 (ac) MD7 (ac) MD8 (ac) 20 19 19 22 22 29–47 33–48 38–57 42–61 60–80
                  35 39 44 49 70 3,66 4,00 4,22 4,65 5,65 LV2 (tu) LV5 (tu) LV6 (ac) LV7 (ac) LV8
                  (ac) LV9 (ac) ML10 (tu) 21 23 24 25 23 22 23 24–44 24–34 26–37 28–42 36–43 38–54
                  28–38 31 30 31 37 41 44 32 4,00 2,97 2,83 3,08 1,75 3,33 2,80 LTS LTS/TL LTAS 20
                  12 9 163–205 39.9–56.4% 46–48 186 48.0% 52 9,80 4.58% 3.91 </p>
            <p>The trichoscalid plates are well-developed, subdorsal and laterodorsal ones narrow
                  and elongated, and ventromedial ones broadly oval.</p>
            <p> Segment 1 consists of a complete cuticular ring. Sensory spots are located on the
                  anterior segment half in subdorsal, laterodorsal, and sublateral positions, and
                  medially on segment, in ventromedial positions ( Figs 9C , 10 B–C); sensory spots
                  on this all following segments are small, and rounded, with numerous
                  micropapillae. Two longitudinally arranged glandular cell outlets type 1 are
                  present in middorsal position ( Figs 9C , 10B ); anteriormost outlet appears
                  narrower and more elongate than the posterior one; an additional pair of glandular
                  cell outlets type 1 is present in ventrolateral positions ( Fig. 10C ). Dorsal and
                  lateral sides, with scattered cuticular hairs emerging through rounded perforation
                  sites; posterior half of ventral side with similar hair covering, but anterior
                  part with large, W-shaped hairless area ( Fig. 10 B–C). The posterior segment
                  margin is straight along the dorsal and lateral sides, and slightly convex
                  ventrally, terminating into a pectinate fringe with short and very flexible fringe
                  tips. Pachycyclus thin to medium thickness, and not interrupted. </p>
            <p> Segment 2 consists of a complete cuticular ring, but with indication of an
                  intracuticular, partial, midventral fissure ( Figs 9F , 10C ). Sensory spots are
                  located in middorsal (but slightly laterally displaced), laterodorsal (twin pair)
                  ( Figs 9E , 10B ) and ventromedial positions ( Fig. 10C ). Minute glandular cell
                  outlets type 2 present in subdorsal positions ( Figs 9C , 10B ), and tubes present
                  in ventrolateral positions ( Figs 9D , 10C ). Glandular cell outlets type 1
                  present in middorsal and ventromedial positions ( Figs 9 C– D, 10B). The segment
                  is densely covered with bracteate hairs, but interrupted by hairless areas
                  posterior to ventrolateral tubes, and in paraventral areas. Pachycyclus of the
                  anterior segment margin is of medium thickness and not interrupted. The posterior
                  segment margin is straight along dorsal and lateral sides, and extend into
                  V-shaped flap on the ventral side; pectinate fringe from middorsal to midlateral
                  positions with short fringe tips, as on segment 1; fringe tips from midlateral to
                  ventromedial positions longer and very flexible, and then very short between
                  ventromedial positions. </p>
            <p> Segment 3, and remaining segments, consisting of one tergal and two sternal plates.
                  Pachycyclus of the anterior segment margin of medium thickness, and interrupted
                  only at tergosternal junctions. Sensory spots present in subdorsal, laterodorsal (
                  Figs 9E , 10D ) and sublateral positions. Glandular cell outlets type 1 present in
                  middorsal ( Fig. 9E, H ) and ventromedial positions. Bracteate cuticular hairs are
                  densely covering the segment from middorsal to ventromedial positions (except in
                  V-shaped areas in laterodorsal positions anterior on segment); paraventral areas
                  that are devoid of any hair-like structures. Pectinate fringe of posterior margin
                  as on preceding segment, but with ventromedial fringe tips being slightly longer. </p>
            <p> Segment 4 with acicular spine in middorsal position, reaching attachment point of
                  middorsal spine on following segment ( Fig. 10D ); this and all other spines on
                  following five segments are slender and flexible. Sensory spots present in
                  subdorsal ( Figs 9H , 10D ), midlateral and ventromedial positions; midlateral and
                  ventromedial sensory spots considerably smaller than most other sensory spots in
                  the species, but they occur consistently in all examined specimens. Glandular cell
                  outlets type 1 present in subdorsal ( Fig. 9H ) and ventromedial positions.
                  Pectinate fringe of posterior segment margin, pachycycli and cuticular hairs as on
                  preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 5 with acicular spine in middorsal position, reaching attachment point of
                  middorsal spine on following segment, and long, slender tubes in lateroventral
                  positions ( Fig. 10E ). Sensory spots present in subdorsal, midlateral ( Figs 9H ,
                  10E ) and ventromedial positions; ventromedial sensory spots considerably smaller
                  than most other sensory spots in the species. Glandular cell outlets type 1,
                  pachycycli, pectinate fringe of posterior margin and cuticular hairs as on
                  preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 6 with acicular spine in middorsal position, reaching attachment point of
                  middorsal spine on following segment, and in lateroventral positions ( Fig. 10
                  E–F), reaching beyond the posterior margin of the segment. Females with female
                  papillae in ventrolateral positions; openings of papillae with fine fringes around
                  their margins ( Fig. 10F inset); intracuticular substructures each form an
                  indistinct tubular structure ( Fig. 9G ). Sensory spots present in paradorsal,
                  midlateral and ventromedial ( Fig. 10F ) positions. Pectinate fringe of posterior
                  segment margin with uniform long fringe tips on tergal plate and on most lateral
                  halves of sternal plates; fringe tips shorter between ventromedial positions.
                  Glandular cell outlets type 1, pachycycli and cuticular hairs as on preceding
                  segment. </p>
            <p> Table 10. Summary of nature and location of sensory spots, glandular cell outlets,
                  tubes and spines arranged by series in <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes pilosus Lang,
                        1949 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
            <p> Position Segment MD PD SD LD ML SL LA LV VL VM 1 gco1, gco1 ss ss ss gco1 ss 2 gco1,
                  ss gco2 ss, ss tu gco1, ss 3 gco1 ss ss ss gco1 4 ac gco1, ss ss* ss*, gco1 5 ac
                  gco1, ss ss tu ss*, gco1 6 ac ss gco1 ss ac fpa (♀) ss, gco1 7 ac ss gco1 ss ac
                  fpa (♀) ss, gco1 8 ac ss gco1 gco2, ss ac ss gco1, fpa (♀) 9 ss gco1, ss gco2, ss
                  si ac ss gco1 10 gco1, gco1 ss tu ss (Ƌ) gco1 11 gco1, gco1 ss 3xpe (Ƌ) ltas (♀)
                  lts </p>
            <p> Segment 7 with acicular spine in middorsal position, extending about halfway over
                  the following segment, and in lateroventral positions, reaching beyond the
                  posterior margin of the segment. Female papillae ( Figs 9G, J , 10F, I ), sensory
                  spots, glandular cell outlets type 1, pachycycli, pectinate fringe of posterior
                  margin and cuticular hairs as on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 8 with acicular spine in middorsal position, extending more than halfway
                  over the following segment ( Fig. 10G ), and in lateroventral positions ( Fig. 9J
                  ), reaching beyond the posterior margin of the segment ( Fig. 10I ). Minute
                  glandular cell outlets type 2 present in laterodorsal positions ( Figs 9L , 10H ).
                  Sensory spots present in paradorsal, laterodorsal (posterior to glandular cell
                  outlets) and ventrolateral positions ( Fig. 10 G–I). Females with female papillae
                  in ventromedial positions ( Figs 9J , 10I ); openings of papillae with fine
                  fringes around their margins ( Fig. 10I inset); intracuticular substructures each
                  form an indistinct tubular structure. Glandular cell outlets type 1 as on
                  preceding segment, but subdorsal ones are situated slightly closer to each other (
                  Fig. 9I ). Pachycycli, pectinate fringe of posterior margin and cuticular hairs as
                  on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 9 with acicular spines in lateroventral positions, extending about halfway
                  over the following segment. Minute glandular cell outlets type 2 present in
                  laterodorsal positions ( Figs 9L , 10H ). Sensory spots present in paradorsal,
                  subdorsal, laterodorsal ( Fig. 10 G–H), and ventrolateral positions. Female
                  papillae absent. Glandular cell outlets type 1 as on preceding segment, but with
                  subdorsal ones situated even closer to each other, very close to paradorsal
                  positions. Small, rounded nephridial sieve plates present in lateral accessory
                  positions. Pachycycli, pectinate fringe of posterior margin and cuticular hairs as
                  on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 10 with long, slender laterodorsal tubes near posterior segment margin (
                  Figs 9M , 10J, L ). Sensory spots present in paradorsal positions ( Fig. 10J );
                  males with additional pair of sensory spots in ventrolateral positions ( Fig. 10K
                  ). Glandular cell outlets type 1 present as two longitudinally arranged middorsal
                  ones and in ventromedial positions. The posterior segment margin of the tergal
                  plate is straight, whereas margins of sternal plates are concave and extend into a
                  midventral point ( Fig. 10K ); fringe tips of pectinate fringe are as on preceding
                  segment on tergal plate, but considerably shorter on sternal plates. Cuticular
                  hairs as on preceding segments on tergal plates, but more sparse on sternal
                  plates. Pachycycli as on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 11 with lateral terminal spines ( Fig. 9B, K, M ). Males with three pairs of
                  penile spines ( Figs 9M , 10K ); dorsal and ventral penile spines are stout but
                  still flexible tubes, whereas the median ones are slightly thicker and more rigid;
                  females with short, and relatively stout lateral terminal accessory spines ( Figs
                  9K , 10J, L ). Sensory spots present in subdorsal positions medially on segment.
                  Two longitudinally arranged glandular cell outlets type 1 present in middorsal
                  position, anterior on segment. The dorsal side of the segment is sparsely covered
                  with thin, non-bracteate hair-like extensions; ventral side is almost hair-less.
                  Tergal extensions are well-spaced, short and pointed; sternal extensions short,
                  with ventrolateral seta-like tuft of extended fringe tips ( Fig. 10 K–L). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
