<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Echinoderes sensibilis Adrianov,
                        Murakami &amp; Shirayama 2002</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4420029</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03C79270FF89572CB2D6FC50190BF998</uri>
                  <article-title>Description, redescription and revision of sixteen putatively
                        closely related species of Echinoderes (Kinorhyncha: Cyclorhagida), with the
                        proposition of a new species group - the Echinoderes dujardinii
                        group</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes sensibilis Adrianov, Murakami &amp; Shirayama, 2002
            </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 11–15 ; Tables 11–12 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Emended diagnosis </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes </tp:taxon-name> with short middorsal spines on
                  segments 4 to 8, and lateroventral spines on segments 6 to 9; middorsal spines on
                  posterior segments barely or just reaching the posterior margin of their
                  respective segments. Tubes present in lateroventral positions on segments 2 and 5,
                  and in laterodorsal positions on 10. Minute glandular cell outlets type 2 in
                  midlateral positions on segments 8 and 9. Tergal extensions of segment 11 short,
                  pointed and well-spaced; sternal extensions short, with ventrolateral seta-like
                  tuft of extended fringe tips. Females with ventromedial female papillae resembling
                  glandular cell outlets type 2 on segments 6 to 8; intracuticular substructure of
                  female papillae crescentic on segment 6, and tubular on segments 7 and 8. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Holotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> JAPAN • ♂ ; Honshu Island , Tanabe Bay ; 33°42′12″ N ,
                        135°22′54″ E ; 0 m b.s.l.; Mar. 2001 ; A. Adrianov , C. Murakami and Y.
                        Shirayama leg.; calcareous red algae ( <tp:taxon-name> Corallina pilulifera
                        </tp:taxon-name> ) in tidal pool; SMBL CM-A-JAP-E04 . Specimen mounted for
                        LM. </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> JAPAN • 3 ♂♂ ; same collection data as for holotype; SMBL
                        CM-A-JAP-E01 , CM-A-JAP-E05 and CM-A-JAP-E08 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p>Specimens mounted for LM. One specimen was incorrectly identified as female in the
                  original description.</p>
            <p> Additional material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> JAPAN • 1 ♀ ; Honshu Island , Tanabe Bay ; 33°41′31″ N ,
                        135°20′10″ E ; 0 m b.s.l.; 12 Sep. 2012 ; H. Yamasaki leg.; detritus and
                        mixed sediment in tidal pool ; GenBank: LC557098 ; ICHUM-6127
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> DNA was extracted from this specimen, and cytochrome oxidase subunit 1 was
                  sequenced. The cuticle of the specimen was subsequently recovered and mounted for
                  LM ( ICHUM- 6127). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> JAPAN • 3 ♂♂ ; same collection data as specimen above;
                        personal reference collection of the last author. Specimens mounted for SEM.
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>Additional specimens from the same locality were collected by C.Y. Chang, mounted for
                  SEM, and stored in the personal reference collection of the first author.</p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> JAPAN • 1 ♀ ; Okinawa , Sesoko Station ; 26°39′00″ N ,
                        127°51′22″ E ; 0 m b.s.l.; 10 Nov. 2016 ; S. Fujimoto leg.; coarse sand in
                        tidal pool ; NHMD-115257 . Specimen mounted for LM </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> REPUBLIC OF KOREA • 2 ♂♂ ; Korean west coast , Wido Island
                        ; 35°36′52″ N , 126°17′01″ E ; 0 m b.s.l.; 31 Feb. 2000 ; J. Lee and Y.H.
                        Song leg.; intertidal macroalgae; NHMD-664200 , NHMD-664201
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ , 1 ♂ ; Jeju Island ,
                        Gimnyeong ; 33°33′33″ N , 126°45′16″ E ; 0 m b.s.l.; 1 Mar. 2000 ; C.Y.
                        Chang , J. Lee and Y.H. Song leg.; intertidal macroalgae; NHMD-664202 ,
                        NHMD-664203 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; Jeju
                        Island , Udo Islet ; 33°31′03″ N , 126°57′40″ E ; 0 m b.s.l.; 3 May 2000 ;
                        C.Y. Chang and J. Lee leg.; intertidal macroalgae; NHMD-664204
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p>All Korean specimens mounted for LM.</p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> HAWAII • 4 ♀♀ , 6♂♂ ; Oahu , Kaneohe Bay , lagoon at
                        Coconut Island , St. MVS-0224-HI-01 (= workshop St. KANM005); 21°26′09″ N ,
                        157°47′18″ W ; 0,5 m b.s.l. ; 22 May 2017 ; M. V. Sørensen leg.; subtidal
                        black mud, rich in organic matter; GenBank: MT999943 ; NHMD-662049 to 662058
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Specimens were mounted for LM. Additional 5 ♀♀ , 5 ♂♂ collected at the same station
                  were mounted for SEM and stored in the first author’s personal reference
                  collection. One specimen was picked up for molecular barcoding and a 625 bp long
                  cytochrome oxidase subunit 1 sequence was deposited in GenBank under accession
                  number MT999943 ; the cuticle could not be recovered afterwards, but the specimen
                  used for DNA extraction is shown on Fig. 11 . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> HAWAII • 6 ♀♀ , 4 ♂♂ ; Oahu , Kaneohe Bay , He’ia Fish Pond
                        , St. MVS-0229-HI-06 (= St. KANM034); 21°26′05″ N , 157°48′19″ W ; 3 m
                        b.s.l. ; 24 May 2017 ; workshop participants leg.; subtidal black mud, very
                        rich in organic matter; NHMD-662059 to 662068 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> Specimens were mounted for LM. Additional 7 ♀♀ , 3 ♂♂ collected at the same station
                  were mounted for SEM and stored in the first author’s personal reference
                  collection. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> See Table 1 for an overview. </p>
            <p> Redescription </p>
            <p> Since the present redescription adds several new features to the species, including
                  information on head structures, observations of live material, and significant
                  diagnostic traits, and since the distributional range of the species is extended
                  considerably, we are providing a full description for the species. As much
                  information as possible is based on observations of the type material, but the
                  specimens are partly deteriorated, hence structures such as sensory spots could no
                  longer be observed. Additional information is primary based on examination of
                  topotypes, supplemented with information from Okinawa and Hawaii populations that
                  morphologically agreed completely with the topotypes. </p>
            <p> Adults with head, neck and eleven trunk segments ( Figs 11–13 , 14A , 15A ).
                  Glandular cells appear brown-red in live specimens, giving the species a
                  conspicuous longitudinal colour pattern along its trunk ( Fig. 11 ). The colouring
                  fades, and eventually disappears, when the animal is fixed. The trunk appears
                  stout, with nearly equally broad sternal plates on segments 6 to 10 ( Figs 11A, C
                  , 14A ). Segments 1 to 4 were often strongly contracted in fixed specimens.
                  Lateral terminal spines slender, from 40% to 55% of trunk length. For complete
                  overview of measurements and dimensions, see Table 11 . Secondary pectinate fringe
                  present near anterior segment margin on segments 2 to 10, but it is usually
                  covered by the preceding segment. Distribution of cuticular structures, i.e.,
                  sensory spots, glandular cell outlets, spines and tubes, is summarized in Table 12
                  . </p>
            <p> The head consists of a retractable mouth cone and an introvert ( Figs 13 , 15 B–C).
                  Three rings of inner oral styles present, with five styles in each ring ( Fig. 13
                  ). The external mouth cone armature consists of nine outer oral styles; bases of
                  outer oral styles each with a V-shaped row of short fringe tips and a central
                  bristle of much longer fringe tips ( Fig. 15B ). The introvert sectors are defined
                  by the ten primary spinoscalids in Ring 01 ( Figs 13 , 15C ). Each primary
                  spinoscalid consists of a basal sheath and a distal end piece with a blunt tip.
                  The sheaths have a well-defined basal, transverse fringe, and a less distinct
                  fringe more distally on their exterior surfaces; fringe tips of the distal fringe
                  attach along a longitudinal line and alternatingly projects to the left and to the
                  right (see inset Fig. 4B for a similar morphology in a different species). End
                  pieces are smooth and flexible. Rings 02 and 04 have 10 spinoscalids and Rings 03
                  and 05 have 20. All spinoscalids in these rings are well-developed, and consist of
                  a basal sheath and a pointed end piece ( Fig. 15C ). The basal sheaths terminate
                  into fine, fringed margins in spinoscalids of Rings 02 to 05, and those of Rings
                  03 to 05 have in addition a basal median spike. A ring of short fringes extend
                  around the introvert in between spinoscalid Rings 04 and 05. Ring 06 has only six
                  spinoscalids, located in sectors 1, 3, 5, 6, 7, and 9 ( Fig. 13 ); Ring 06
                  spinoscalids resemble those in preceding sectors, but without a distinct
                  differentiation into sheath and end piece. Ring 07 also has 6 spinoscalids,
                  located as pairs in sectors 3 and 9, and unpaired but laterally displaced in
                  sectors 5 and 7 (trichoscalids are taking up the space in the opposite side of
                  each sector); Ring 07 spinoscalids resemble those in preceding sector. </p>
            <p> Described sector-wise ( Fig. 13 ), sectors 1 and 6 are similar, having spinoscalids
                  arranged as two double diamonds. Sectors 2, 4, 8 and 10 all have spinoscalids
                  arranged as a quincunx, located in between a medial anterior spinoscalid (Ring 02)
                  and a trichoscalid plate. Sectors 3 and 9 have spinoscalids forming double
                  diamonds anterior to a pair of spinoscalids. Sectors 5 and 7 also have
                  spinoscalids forming double diamonds, but anterior to an unpaired, lateral
                  spinoscalid ( Fig. 13 ). </p>
            <p> Regular trichoscalids with trichoscalid plates are present in sectors 2, 4, 5, 7, 8,
                  and 10. In addition, a single trichoscalid without trichoscalid plate is present
                  in sector 1 ( Figs 13 , 14H , 15C ). The trichoscalid has the typical furry
                  appearance ( Figs 14H , 15C ), but basally it also has a series of more
                  well-organized pointed denticles. </p>
            <p> The neck has 16 placids, measuring 18 µm in length. The midventral placid is
                  broadest, measuring 15 µm in width at its base, whereas all other are narrower,
                  measuring 11 µm in width at their bases. The trichoscalid plates are
                  well-developed; subdorsal and laterodorsal ones are narrow and elongated, and
                  ventromedial ones broadly oval. </p>
            <p> Segment 1 consists of a complete cuticular ring. Sensory spots are located near the
                  anterior margin in subdorsal and laterodorsal positions, and slightly more
                  posterior in sublateral and ventromedial positions ( Figs 12 A–B, 14B, 15D–E);
                  sensory spots are large, and rounded to oval, with numerous micropapillae, two
                  pores, and often a cilium emerging from one of the pores. Glandular cell outlets
                  type 1 present in middorsal and lateroventral positions ( Figs 12 A–B, 14B–C,
                  15D–E); all glandular cells with type 1 outlets on this and following segments
                  with conspicuous brown-red colouring that gets lost during fixation ( Fig. 11
                  A–B). Dorsal and lateral sides, and posterior half of ventral side, with scattered
                  cuticular hairs emerging through rounded perforation sites. The posterior segment
                  margin is straight around the segment, terminating into a pectinate fringe with
                  short, uniform fringe tips. </p>
            <p> Segment 2 consists of a complete cuticular ring. Pachycyclus of the anterior segment
                  margin is of medium thickness and not interrupted ( Figs 11B , 14 A–C). Sensory
                  spots are located in middorsal (but slightly laterally displaced), laterodorsal
                  (twin pair) and ventromedial positions ( Figs 12 A–B, 15D–E); sensory spots on
                  this and all following segments as on segment 1, but slightly smaller. Glandular
                  cell outlets type 1 present in middorsal and ventromedial positions, and quite
                  well-developed tubes present in lateroventral positions ( Figs 12 A–B, 14B–C,
                  15D–E). The segment is densely covered with bracteate hairs; hair cover slightly
                  thinner between ventromedial sensory spots. The posterior segment margin is nearly
                  straight; pectinate fringe from middorsal to midlateral positions with short
                  fringe tips, as on segment 1; fringe tips from midlateral to ventromedial
                  positions conspicuously longer, and then again very short between ventromedial
                  positions. </p>
            <p> Segment 3, and remaining segments, consisting of one tergal and two sternal plates.
                  Pachycyclus of the anterior segment margin of medium thickness, and interrupted
                  only at tergosternal junctions ( Figs 11 B–C, 14C). Sensory spots present in
                  subdorsal, laterodorsal and sublateral positions ( Fig. 12 A– B). Glandular cell
                  outlets type 1 present in middorsal and ventromedial positions ( Figs 12 A–B,
                  14B–C). Bracteate cuticular hairs are densely covering the segment from middorsal
                  to ventromedial positions; paraventral areas densely covered by non-bracteate,
                  hair-like extensions. Pectinate fringe of posterior margin hairs as on preceding
                  segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 4 with short acicular spine in middorsal position, not reaching the
                  posterior margin of the segment ( Figs 12A , 14B ). Sensory spots present in
                  subdorsal, midlateral and ventromedial positions ( Fig. 12 A–B); midlateral and
                  ventromedial sensory spots considerably smaller than all other sensory spots in
                  the species, but they occur consistently in all examined specimens. Glandular cell
                  outlets type 1 present in subdorsal and ventromedial positions ( Figs 12 A–B,
                  14B–C). Pectinate fringe of posterior segment margin with long fringe tips from
                  middorsal to ventromedial positions, and with very short tips between ventromedial
                  positions. Pachycycli and cuticular hairs as on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Fig. 11. Light micrographs showing overviews of live female of <tp:taxon-name>
                        Echinoderes sensibilis Adrianov et al ., 2002 </tp:taxon-name> from Coconut
                  Island, Oahu, Hawaii ( USNM-1616695). Note the brown-red glandular cells. DNA was
                  subsequently extracted from the specimen and it is voucher for CO1 barcode
                  sequence, GenBank Acc. number: MT999943. </p>
            <p> Fig. 12. Line art illustrations of <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes sensibilis Adrianov
                        et al ., 2002 </tp:taxon-name> . A . Female, dorsal view. B . Female,
                  ventral view. C . Segments 10 to 11 in male, dorsal view. D . Segments 10 to 11 in
                  male, ventral view. </p>
            <p> Fig. 13. Diagram of mouth cone (grey area), introvert and placids in <tp:taxon-name>
                        Echinoderes sensibilis Adrianov et al ., 2002 </tp:taxon-name> , showing
                  distribution of inner oral styles (full circles), outer oral styles (diamonds),
                  primary scalids (triangles), spinoscalids (thick open circles) and trichoscalids
                  (stars), with positions of trichoscalid plates and placids indicated. Table shows
                  the scalid arrangement by sector; single-lined boxes mark quincunxes, double-lined
                  boxes mark ‘double diamonds’. </p>
            <p> Table 11. Measurements from light microscopy for four Japanese type specimens and
                  selected specimens from the Hawaiian population of <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes
                        sensibilis Adrianov et al ., 2002 </tp:taxon-name> (in µm), including number
                  of measured specimens ( n ) and standard deviation (SD). </p>
            <p> Character Tanabe Bay, Japan (type material) n Range Mean SD n Hawaii Range Mean SD n
                  All Range Mean SD TL 4 342–383 354 19.51 14 301–385 335 26.81 18 301–385 339 26.10
                  MSW-8 4 72–76 74 2.06 14 69–76 73 1.72 18 69–76 73 1.84 MSW-8/TL 4 19.8–22.2%
                  21.0% 0.98% 14 19.2–24.2% 21.8% 1.53% 18 19.2–24.2% 21.6% 1.44% SW-10 4 71–75 73
                  1.83 14 68–73 70 1.77 18 68–75 71 2.14 SW-10/TL 4 19.6–21.6% 20.7% 0.86% 14
                  19.0–22.9% 21.0% 1.51% 18 19.0–22.9% 20.9% 1.38% S1 4 34–37 36 1.29 14 34–38 35
                  1.22 18 34–38 35 1.20 S2 4 36–38 37 0.82 14 34–38 36 1.16 18 34–38 36 1.23 S3 4
                  35–40 38 2.08 14 35–38 37 1.07 18 35–40 37 1.32 S4 4 37–41 39 1.73 14 37–42 40
                  1.68 18 37–42 39 1.72 S5 4 40–49 43 4.36 14 40–45 43 1.55 18 40–49 43 2.28 S6 4
                  44–50 46 3.00 14 43–49 46 1.92 18 43–50 46 2.10 S7 4 46–52 49 3.00 14 45–51 49
                  1.90 18 45–52 49 2.09 S8 4 50–52 51 1.15 14 50–55 53 1.40 18 50–55 52 1.48 S9 4
                  53–54 54 0.50 14 50–55 53 1.33 18 50–55 53 1.23 S10 4 53–55 54 0.82 14 44–56 50
                  3.17 18 44–56 51 3.34 S11 4 40–42 41 0.82 14 34–42 38 1.86 18 34–42 39 2.01 MD4
                  (ac) 4 9–13 11 1.71 11 10–15 12 1.79 15 9–15 12 1.74 MD5 (ac) 3 11–14 13 1.53 13
                  12–16 14 1.27 16 12–16 13 1.31 MD6 (ac) 3 16–17 16 0.58 13 13–19 15 1.81 16 13–19
                  16 1.67 MD7 (ac) 4 19–20 20 0.58 14 13–22 17 2.21 18 13–22 17 2.25 MD8 (ac) 3 21
                  21 0.00 13 17–26 20 2.31 16 17–26 20 2.13 13 LV2 (tu) 3 18–21 20 1.73 10 20–24 22
                  1.81 18–24 22 1.97 LV5 (tu) 3 18–20 19 1.00 10 17–25 22 2.49 13 17–25 21 2.56 LV6
                  (ac) 3 14–19 16 2.89 14 14–21 17 2.00 17 14–21 17 2.14 LV7 (ac) 4 14–18 15 1.89 14
                  15–22 19 2.02 18 15–22 18 2.49 LV8 (ac) 4 16–20 18 1.71 14 15–24 20 2.27 18 15–24
                  20 2.39 LV9 (ac) 4 18–21 19 1.41 14 17–25 22 2.24 18 17–25 21 2.33 LD10(tu) 4
                  26–28 27 0.96 12 23–30 27 2.52 16 23–30 27 2.21 LTS 4 150–156 154 2.65 14 132–168
                  154 11.78 18 132–168 154 10.37 LTS/TL 4 39.2–45.2% 43,5% 2.88% 14 39.5–55.6% 46.2%
                  4.35% 18 39.2–55.6% 45.6% 4.15% LTAS 0 – – – 8 40–45 43 1.83 8 40–45 43 1.83 </p>
            <p> Table 12. Summary of nature and location of sensory spots, glandular cell outlets,
                  tubes and spines arranged by series in <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes sensibilis
                        Adrianov et al ., 2002 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
            <p> Position Segment MD PD SD LD ML SL LA LV VL VM 1 gco1 ss ss ss gco1 ss 2 gco1, ss
                  ss, ss tu gco1, ss 3 gco1 ss ss ss gco1 4 ac gco1,s s ss* ss*, gco1 5 ac gco1, ss
                  ss tu ss, gco1 6 ac ss gco1, ss ss ac fpa (♀), ss, gco1 7 ac ss gco1, ss ss ac fpa
                  (♀), ss, gco1 8 ac ss gco1, ss gco2, ss ac ss gco1, fpa (♀) 9 ss gco1, ss gco2, ss
                  si ac ss gco1 10 gco1, gco1 ss tu ss (Ƌ) gco1 11 gco1, gco1 gco1, ss, ss 3xpe (Ƌ)
                  ltas (♀) lts ss </p>
            <p> Segment 5 with short acicular spine in middorsal position, not reaching the
                  posterior margin of the segment ( Figs 12A , 14D ), and well-developed tubes in
                  lateroventral positions ( Figs 12B , 14E ). Sensory spots present in subdorsal,
                  midlateral and ventromedial positions ( Fig. 12 A–B). Glandular cell outlets type
                  1, pachycycli, pectinate fringe of posterior margin and cuticular hairs as on
                  preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 6 with short acicular spines in middorsal and lateroventral positions ( Figs
                  12 A–B, 14D– E, 14G–H), not reaching the posterior margin of the segment. Sensory
                  spots present in paradorsal, subdorsal, midlateral and ventromedial positions (
                  Figs 12 A–B, 15G). Females with female papillae in ventromedial positions, close
                  to and lateral to sensory spots ( Figs 12B , 14E , 15H ); openings of papillae
                  resemble small glandular cell outlets type 2 ( Fig. 15H ), and intracuticular
                  substructures each form a semicircle with a small protuberance in the curved part
                  of the structure ( Fig. 14E ). Glandular cell outlets type 1, pachycycli,
                  pectinate fringe of posterior margin and cuticular hairs as on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 7 with short acicular spines in middorsal and lateroventral positions,
                  barely reaching the posterior margin of the segment ( Figs 12 A–B, 14D–E, 15G–I).
                  Females with female papillae as on segment 6, but with openings slightly more
                  anterior and lateral to sensory spots ( Figs 12B , 14E , 15 H–I); the substructure
                  of these papillae differs from those on preceding segment, and forms instead a
                  small intracuticular tube ( Fig. 14E ). Sensory spots, glandular cell outlets type
                  1, pachycycli, pectinate fringe of posterior margin and cuticular hairs as on
                  preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 8 with short acicular spines in middorsal and lateroventral positions,
                  barely or just reaching the posterior margin of the segment ( Figs 12 A–B, 14D–G,
                  15G, I). Minute glandular cell outlets type 2 present in midlateral positions, but
                  very close to the laterodorsal areas ( Figs 12A , 14G , 15F ). Sensory spots
                  present in paradorsal, subdorsal, midlateral (posterior to glandular cell
                  outlets), ventrolateral positions ( Figs 12 A–B, 15F, I). Females with female
                  papillae similar to those on segment 7, but with </p>
            <p> Fig. 14. Light micrographs showing overviews and details of <tp:taxon-name>
                        Echinoderes sensibilis Adrianov et al ., 2002 </tp:taxon-name> . A–I . ♀. A
                  . ICHUM-6127. B–F, I . NHMD-662049. G . NHMD-662066. H . NHMD-662060. A . Ventral
                  overview. B . Segments 1 to 4, dorsal view. C . Segments 1 to 4, ventral view. D .
                  Segments 5 to 8, dorsal view. E . Segments 5 to 8, ventral view, showing female
                  sexual dimorphism. F . Segments 8 to 10, dorsal view. G . Segments 8 to 9, dorsal
                  view. H . Detail showing ventral trichoscalids and trichoscalid plates. I .
                  Segments 10 to 11, ventral view, showing female sexual dimorphism. J . ♂
                  (NHMD-662056). Segments 10 to 11, ventral view, showing male sexual dimorphism. </p>
            <p> Fig. 15. Scanning electron micrographs showing overviews and details of
                        <tp:taxon-name> Echinoderes sensibilis Adrianov et al ., 2002
                  </tp:taxon-name> . A, D, F–J . ♀ ( MVS, personal reference collection). B–C, E,
                  K–L . ♂ ( MVS, personal reference collection). A . Ventrolateral overview. B .
                  Mouth cone, ventral view. C . Introvert sectors 1 and 10 (ventral). D . Segments 1
                  to 2, dorsal view. E . Segments 1 to 2, ventrolateral view. F . Segments 8 to 9,
                  lateral view; insets show glandular cell outlets type 2. G . Segments 6 to 8,
                  dorsal view. H . Segments 6 to 7, ventral view, showing female sexual dimorphism.
                  I . Segments 7 to 8, ventral view, showing female sexual dimorphism. J . Segments
                  10 to 11, dorsal view, showing female sexual dimorphism. K . Segments 10 to 11,
                  lateral view, showing male sexual dimorphism. L . Segments 10 to 11, dorsal view,
                  showing male sexual dimorphism. </p>
            <p> openings slightly more anterior and closer to midventral line ( Figs 12B , 14E , 15I
                  ). Glandular cell outlets type 1, pachycycli, pectinate fringe of posterior margin
                  and cuticular hairs as on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 9 with acicular spines in lateroventral positions, just reaching the
                  posterior margin of the segment ( Figs 12B , 15F ). Sensory spots, glandular cell
                  outlets type 1 and 2 as on preceding segment, but female papillae not present (
                  Figs 12 A–B, 14F–G, 15F). Small, rounded nephridial sieve plates present in
                  lateral accessory positions. Pectinate fringe of posterior segment margin with
                  uniformly long fringe tips around the segment. Pachycycli and cuticular hairs as
                  on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 10 with well-developed laterodorsal tubes near posterior segment margin (
                  Figs 12 , 14J , 15 J–L). Sensory spots present in subdorsal (but close to
                  paradorsal) positions ( Figs 12A, C , 15J, L ); males furthermore with sensory
                  spots in ventrolateral positions ( Fig. 12D ). Glandular cell outlets type 1
                  present as two longitudinally arranged middorsal ones and in ventromedial
                  positions ( Figs 12 , 14I ). The posterior segment margin of the tergal plate is
                  straight, whereas margins of sternal plates are concave and extend midventrally
                  into a point that almost reaches the posterior margin of the terminal segment;
                  fringe tips of pectinate fringe are considerably shorter than those on preceding
                  segments. Pachycycli and cuticular hairs as on preceding segment. </p>
            <p> Segment 11 with lateral terminal spines ( Figs 11A , 12 A–B, 14A). Males with three
                  pairs of penile spines ( Figs 12 C–D, 14J, 15K–L); dorsal and ventral penile
                  spines are thin, flexible tubes, whereas the median ones are slightly thicker,
                  conical, and more rigid; females with short, thin lateral terminal accessory
                  spines ( Figs 12 A–B, 14I, 15J). Two pairs of sensory spots present in subdorsal
                  positions and one pair in ventrolateral positions; one pair of subdorsal sensory
                  spots medially on segment, other pair at posterior margin ( Fig. 15J ). Glandular
                  cell outlets type 1 present as two longitudinally arranged middorsal ones and in
                  subdorsal positions, anterior on segment. The dorsal and most of the ventral side
                  of the segment are densely covered with non-bracteate hair-like extensions. Tergal
                  extensions are wellspaced, short and pointed ( Figs 12 , 14 I–J, 15J, L); sternal
                  extensions short, with ventrolateral seta-like tuft of extended fringe tips ( Figs
                  14J , 15J ). </p>
            <p> Notes on habitat and ecology </p>
            <p> The specimens collected in Kaneohe Bay, Hawaii , showed a very clear preference for
                  muddy localities, rich in organic matter. They seemed to thrive very well in it,
                  and appeared in high numbers. Especially at the locality in He’ia Fish Pond (St.
                  MVS-0229-HI-06) – an 800 year old fish pond established by isolating a part of the
                  coastal water with a 2 km long lava rock wall – specimens of <tp:taxon-name> E.
                        sensibilis </tp:taxon-name> occurred in ball-like aggregations composed of
                  detritus, and up to 40 specimens . At low magnification, these balls would just
                  resemble detritus pellets, but by gently opening the ball with a needle, it would
                  appear that the balls mainly consisted of mass aggregated kinorhynchs. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
