<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Phanaeus jackenioi Moctezuma &amp; Halffter 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4726227</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/84C7B93D129DEBDC2D0DDB84A0AF16D7</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic revision of the Phanaeus endymion species group (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae), with the descriptions of five new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/3f0b6eaf-c616-4865-811a-414a094b590c</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Phanaeus jackenioi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
CF4B33E3-1245-4631-A019-2CAF43709603
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1H
, 
2D
, 
6
, 
15
, 
18I
, 
19I
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Easily diagnosed species by the bright metallic green colour; striae wide, roughened, impressed basally as distinct fossae, with distinctly impressed punctation; the major male with posterolateral angles of pronotum sharply acute, elongate, projected posterolaterally (
Figs 2D
, 
6A
); the major female with pronotal process without frontal concavity; rounded pronotal tubercles, nearly aligned, with middle tubercle more developed than lateral tubercles (
Fig. 6B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
We are honoured to dedicate this new species to Jack Schuster and Enio Cano. They have significantly contributed to the knowledge of the Guatemalan scarab beetles, particularly of the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Passalidae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
(
11 ♂♂
, 
5 ♀♀
)
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
GUATEMALA
• 
♂
; 
Guatemala
; “ 

10/XI/1978

. 
Eugenia de Minondo
”; 
UVGC
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
</p>
      <p>
GUATEMALA
– 

Chimaltenango

• 
1 ♀
; “ 
Parramos
, 
El Injertal
. 

13/IX/1978

. 
Eugenia de Minondo
”; 
VMC

. – 

Chiquimula

• 
1 ♂
; “ 
Chiquimula.
7–14 II 2007

. 
R. Chicas
”; 
VMC

. – 

Guatemala

• 
1 ♂
; “nr. 
Barranca Sta. Catarina. Pinula
, Z-14. 

22 VI 1993

. 
E. Póll
leg. Luz incandescente”; 
VMC

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
Ciudad.
13 X 1982

. 
S. Roesch
”; 
TAMU

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
Guatemala.
214 

VIII 1984

. 
J. Perez
”; CNMN

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
Sta. Rosa
z.16. 
Kanajuyú
2. 

22.XI.2000

. 
M.L.Muller
”; 
UVGC

. – 

Huehuetenango

• 
1 ♂
; “ 
Nentón
. 
Camino entre Nentón y San José Chaquial.
22 VII 1998

. 
Bosque seco
. E.B. 
Cano Heces de perro
”; 
UVGC

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
Chivacabé.
31 X 1993

. 
E. Cano
”; 
UVGC

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
VMC

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
La libertad
, 
La Mesilla
, 
finca El Bolsón.
24 IX 2011

. Cafetal. Luz UV + HG. 
Col. M. Acevedo
&amp; 
H. Enríquez.
”; 
TAMU

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
UVGC

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 
VMC

. – 

Sacatepéquez

• 
1 ♀
; “ 
Bosque pasado
. 
Comunidad Ruiz
, 
km35 a Mixco Viejo via San Juan Sac
. 

29-X-1978

. 
E. Duarte
”; 
TAMU

. – 

Zacapa

• 
1 ♂
; “ 
San Lorenzo
, 
cerca de La Marmolera.
5 XII 2001

. 
En heces de vaca
. 
A. Higueros
, leg. 
Bosque de pino
, aprox. 1700msnm”; 
UVGC

.
</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
– 

Chiapas

• 
1 ♂
; “ 
Santa Rosa
, 

VIII-1962

. 
G. Halffter
leg.”; 
TAMU

.
</p>
      <p>
Type locality
</p>
      <p>
Guatemala
, 
Guatemala
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Major male
(
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>
Length 
17.1 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Clypeus bidentate, black on anterior margin, bright metallic green on posterior portion, with roughened sculpture. Genae bright metallic green, with roughened sculpture. Front black, with dark metallic blue-green on portions adjacent to cephalic horn. Cephalic horn black, curved posteriorly over pronotum (
Figs 2D
, 
6A
).
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM. Uniformly bright metallic green, becoming black on lateral margins of posterolateral angles. Keel absent in the middle of anterior pronotal margin. Disc triangular, flat, with two distinctly developed tubercles on anterior portion. Triangle with lightly granulate, scabriculous, impunctate. Sides scabriculous, with smooth sculpture, superficially impressed punctures. Lateral lines of pronotal triangle straight. Posterolateral angles sharply acute, elongate, projected posterolaterally. Lateral fossae distinctly impressed. Basal fossae obtusely oval, deeply impressed. Posterior margin distinctly punctate (
Figs 2D
, 
6A
).
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA. Thick, roughened, bright metallic green striae, scabriculous, impressed basally as distinct fossae, with distinctly impressed punctation. Interstriae black, partially roughened, scabriculous, with almost effaced punctation; except for almost completely rough, bright metallic green first stria. Sutural margin without apical tooth (
Fig. 6A
).
</p>
      <p>PROTIBIAE. Quadridentate with apical spine.</p>
      <p>TERGITE VIII. Bright metallic green; scabriculous; with rough, distinctly impressed punctures. Basal margin with thick, small setae.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Right lobe and left lobe of endophallite copulatrix similar in size. Right lobe obtusely triangular in shape, with apical portion projected posteriorly. Left lobe bent posteriorly, convex superiorly, lobed inferiorly. Central ridge and column similar in size (
Fig. 1H
).
</p>
      <p>
Minor male
</p>
      <p>Like the major male, except for the reduction of secondary sexual characters (i.e., cephalic horn, pronotal triangle and tubercles, and pronotal posterolateral angles).</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Phanaeus jackenioi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. Holotype, ♂ (UVGC). 
B
. ♀ (VMC).
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
Similar to the male, except for the head showing a cephalic trituberculate carina; carinate middle tubercle, less raised, slightly more frontally projected than lateral tubercles; lateral tubercles obtusely conical; frons with distinctly impressed punctures; pronotal sculpture completely smooth, with superficially impressed punctures; pronotum bright metallic green, with shining black, variable in size area on central portion of disc; pronotal process trituberculate, lacking concavity rounded pronotal tubercles, nearly aligned, with middle tubercle more developed than lateral tubercles; posterior pronotal midline completely effaced (
Fig. 6B
).
</p>
      <p>
Variation
</p>
      <p>
Mean length 
17.3 mm
(
16.2–18.4 mm
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Inner slope of the Sierra Madre de Chiapas, south-central 
Guatemala
and southeastern Chiapas (
Fig. 15
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The type series of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. jackenioi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
was originally labelled as 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. pyrois
</tp:taxon-name>
. The new species was referred to as 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. endymion
</tp:taxon-name>
by 
Edmonds (1994)
, 
Edmonds &amp; Zídek (2012)
, 

Lizardo 
et al
. 2017

, 
Moctezuma &amp; Halffter (2017)
and 
GBIF Secretariat (2019a)
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
