<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta haitensis
(
Michener, 1948
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 4A
, 
6C
, 
9A
, 10–11, 12B, 17
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Melecta haitensis
Michener, 1948: 16
</tp:taxon-name>

(
♂
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="vernacular_names">
      <p>
Proposed common name
</p>
      <p>Hispaniolan digger-cuckoo bee.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Unique within the genus to 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is that the T1–T3 fasciae of the male are complete (
Fig. 9A
). In all other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta
</tp:taxon-name>
, at least the T2 and T3 fasciae (if present) (as well as any fasciae on the succeeding terga) are interrupted medially in males (
Figs 8A–C
, 
9B
) as well as females, except in aberrant specimens in which the metasoma is entirely covered in pale tomentum (see 
Fig. 7A–B
). The following morphological features in combination (excluding any that are specific to the opposite sex of the one being diagnosed) can be used to tell 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
apart from all other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta
</tp:taxon-name>
except 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. tibialis
</tp:taxon-name>
, a Puerto Rican/ 
U.S. Virgin Islands
species: the mesoscutum and mesoscutellum both have well-defined bands of pale hairs along the entire midline that connect and thus give the appearance of a single band (
Figs 10B, D
, 
11
); the mesoscutellum sometimes also has pale hairs laterally but the pubescence is otherwise dark brown or black, sparse, and does not obscure the underlying integument (
Fig. 10D
); and each mesotibia of the female dorsally has a large glabrous area between a submedial band of off-white to pale yellow hairs (nearer the base than apex) and a band on the apical margin (
Fig. 10A
). Apart from the difference in the T1–T3 fasciae of the male, 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
may be separated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. tibialis
</tp:taxon-name>
as follows. Whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. tibialis
</tp:taxon-name>
the T1–T3 fasciae of the female are widely interrupted medially and the lighter hairs covering the head, mesosoma, and metasoma are off-white, in 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
the T1–T3 apical fasciae of the female are only narrowly interrupted medially and the lighter hairs covering the head, mesosoma, and metasoma are pale yellow. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is the only species in the genus known to occur in Hispaniola, where it is endemic.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 9.
Metasoma of male, dorsal view. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta haitensis
(
Michener, 1948
) (JAG)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. tibialis
(
Fabricius, 1793
) (UPRM)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
HAITI
• 
♂
; 
Ouest
, 
Port-au-Prince
; 
G.N. Wolcott
leg.; 
USNM
534228
.

</p>
      <p>
DNA barcoded material
</p>
      <p>Available. BIN: BOLD:AEH8436. Specimen examined and sequenced:</p>
      <p>
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC
• 
1 ♂
; 
Indepencencia
, 
Sierra
de 
Bahoruco
, 
Caseta
#2; 

23 Nov. 2008

; 
J.A. Genaro
leg.; BOLD sample ID: CMNTO_037; JAG

.
</p>
      <p>
Non-barcoded material
</p>
      <p>
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC
• 
2 ♂♂
; 
Indepencencia
, 
La Descubierta
, 
Lago Enriquillo
, 
Sierra de Neiba
; 

Nov. 2006

; 
J.A. Genaro
leg.; JAG

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
PCYU

• 

1 ♀
; 
La Vega
, 
Los Tablones
, 
La Laguna
, 
Parque Nacional José Armando Bermúdez
; 

30 Jun. 2004

; 
D. Pérez
leg.; 
USNM
RD-251

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 10.
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta haitensis
(
Michener, 1948
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–B
. Female (USNM RD-251). 
A
Habitus, lateral view. 
B
Habitus, dorsal view. 
C
. Male (JAG), habitus, lateral view. 
D
. Female (PCYU), axillae and mesoscutellum, dorsal view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length 
10.3 mm
; ITW 
2.4 mm
; head length 
2.6 mm
; head width 
2.9 mm
; fore wing length 
8.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
INTEGUMENT COLORATION. Dark brown to black except as follows. Mandible with apical third reddish brown (golden yellow in some non-type specimens). Mandible with middle third, labrum, mesoscutellum, metanotum, and legs, excluding dark brown coxae and tibial spurs (black in non-type specimens), brownish orange (reddish brown to reddish orange in multiple non-type specimens). Tegula amber. Fore wing dusky subhyaline throughout except around third submarginal crossvein and second recurrent vein, where hyaline (all wings badly damaged/stained in 
holotype
; described from non-type specimens). Hind wing dusky subhyaline to hyaline. Much of antenna and metasoma reddish brown in 
holotype
, possibly due to discoloration/fading; dark brown to black in non-type specimens.
</p>
      <p>
PUBESCENCE. Badly matted in 
holotype
(apparently due to prior wetting); described from non-type specimens. Face with hairs densest around antennal socket, predominantly off-white/pale yellow but dark brown/gray above antennal socket and in lower paraocular area. Clypeus with upper half densely hairy; lower half nearly bare. Upper paraocular and frontal areas and vertexal area (except along preoccipital ridge and margin of compound eye) mostly exposed. Head with dense, erect hairs along preoccipital ridge off-white/pale yellow except for pair of dark brown/gray patches, each behind lateral ocellus, separated by small band of off-white/pale yellow hairs along midline between median ocellus and preoccipital ridge, seemingly continuous with band of pale hairs along midline of mesoscutum. Genal beard hairs predominantly off-white/pale yellow. Mesoscutum sparsely hairy except densely hairy anteriorly and along margins, with hairs short, appressed, and predominantly dark brown/gray except for small patch of pale yellow hairs on each side along anterior margin between midline and pronotal lobe, pair of central spots of pale yellow hairs and narrow band extending posteriorly from each toward axilla, well-defined band of pale yellow hairs along midline, and pale yellow hairs along margins. Axilla with conspicuous patch of black hairs. Mesoscutellum with well-defined band of pale yellow hairs along midline, seemingly continuous with band of pale hairs along midline of mesoscutum, and small patch of pale yellow hairs laterally but with pubescence otherwise dark brown or black and sparse, not obscuring underlying integument. Metanotum with short, appressed off-white to dark brown hairs. Propodeum with erect, predominantly pale yellow hairs. Mesopleuron sparsely hairy, but with (off-white/pale yellow) hairs moderately dense ventrally as well as between two sparsely hairy circular patches (one beneath base of fore wing (hypoepimeral area), a larger one occupying much of ventrolateral half of mesopleuron). Legs, from coxae to tarsi, with appressed and erect off-white to pale yellow hairs, ventrally with golden-yellow hairs. Profemur with posteroventral fringe of dense, off-white hairs. Protibia with two bands or spots of short, appressed off-white hairs, one in basal half and one on apical margin. Mesotibia with patch of very dense short, appressed off-white/pale yellow hairs, occupying nearly entire dorsal surface. Metatibia with patch of sparser off-white/pale yellow hairs in apical two-thirds. T1–T3 with well-defined complete apical fasciae, those of T1 and T3 each with lobe-like anterolateral extension on each side with erect among appressed pale yellow hairs, that of T2 with pair of anterolateral extensions on each side. T3 with fascia laterally removed from apical margin, narrowed or interrupted mesad each anterolateral extension. T4–T6 without fasciae, although T4 with few sparsely scattered pale hairs present on apical impressed area. Exposed metasomal sterna mainly with short, appressed off-white hairs.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 11.
Female 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta haitensis
(
Michener, 1948
)
</tp:taxon-name>
taking nectar from flowers of Mexican oregano (
<tp:taxon-name>
Lippia graveolens
Kunth
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Verbenaceae</tp:taxon-name>
)) (location: Altamira, Puerto Plata, Dominican Republic). 
A
. Shown with mouthparts extended into corolla. 
B
. Shown with mesoscutellum and metasomal fasciae in view. Images courtesy of L. McDowell Johnson.
</p>
      <p>
SURFACE SCULPTURE. Labrum and clypeus with punctures equally dense (most i≤1d). Integument lateral to lateral ocellus punctate. Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum with fine punctures, not much coarser than those of metasomal terga. Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum with punctures equally dense (most i&lt;1d) and similar in size. Mesopleuron with denser (most i&lt;1d) punctures in upper half than ventrolateral half (many i=1–2d), interspaces well-defined and somewhat dull due to tessellate surface microsculpture. Discs of metasomal terga with punctures very fine, dense (i≈1d), interspaces dull due to tessellate surface microsculpture (difficult to see in 
holotype
because integument obscured by badly matted pubescence; described from non-type specimens).
</p>
      <p>
STRUCTURE. Mandible tridentate, with small inner tooth approximately ⅓ length of mandible from base and slightly larger inner tooth approximately ⅓ length of mandible from apex as well as usual large apical tooth (rutellum). Maxillary palpus apparently with one palpomere (three according to 
Michener 1948
). Scape with greatest length 1.8 × greatest width. F2 nearly as long as wide (L/W ratio = 0.9). Mesoscutellum strongly bigibbous, with pair of long, acute, subparallel spines, directed posteriorly. Lateral surface of propodeum posterior to spiracle with rugose crescent ridge, strongly carinate above and joining anterior lip of spiracle. Fore wing with three submarginal cells. T7 with slight median emargination.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
Description as for male except for usual secondary sexual characters and as follows: scape longer, with greatest length 2.1 × greatest width; mesotibia dorsally with large glabrous area between submedial band of off-white to pale yellow hairs (nearer base than apex) and band on apical margin; T1–T3 with fasciae narrowly interrupted medially; T 
4 in
some specimens with pair of small spots of pale yellow hairs along anterior margin of apical impressed area; T6 with narrow, V-shaped but apically rounded pygidial plate with median longitudinal ridge.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Previously known only from 
Haiti
and herein newly reported from 
the Dominican
Republic, this is the only species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta
</tp:taxon-name>
known to occur on the island of Hispaniola (
Fig. 4A
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>
Host records
</p>
      <p>
Unknown. Given that New World 
<tp:taxon-name>Melectini</tp:taxon-name>
have been associated only with anthophorine bees (mostly 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anthophora
</tp:taxon-name>
), presumably 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is a cleptoparasite of one or more of the three species
</p>
      <p>
of 

<tp:taxon-name>Anthophora</tp:taxon-name>
— 
<tp:taxon-name>A. hilaris</tp:taxon-name>

, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. hispaniola
Brooks, 1999
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tricolor
(Fabricius, 1775)
</tp:taxon-name>
— known to occur in Hispaniola (see 
Brooks 1999
).
</p>
      <p>
Floral records
<tp:taxon-name>
Lippia graveolens
Kunth
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Verbenaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) (
Fig. 11
). Images on iNaturalist (https://www.inaturalist.org) show this species visiting 
<tp:taxon-name>
Berylsimpsonia
B.L.Turner
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
) (det. by J. Llamacho). One of the
</p>
      <p>
authors of the present study (JAG) has observed males of this species visiting the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lantana
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Michener (2007)
indicated that in the Antillean species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xeromelecta
</tp:taxon-name>
the maxillary palpi have three (or possibly sometimes two) palpomeres. Both 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. alayoi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
were originally described as having three-segmented maxillary palpi. In the original description of the latter species, 
Michener (1948)
indicated that in the only other Antillean species known at that time (
<tp:taxon-name>
M. pantalon
</tp:taxon-name>
, later determined to be a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. tibialis
</tp:taxon-name>
) the maxillary palpi were reportedly two-segmented but noted that the discrepancy was possibly the result of an observational error by 
Dewitz (1881)
as the palpi are minute. In the present study, the maxillary palpus of a male specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(BOLD sample ID: CMNTO_037; JAG) was visualized with an SEM, which revealed an enlarged basal portion but no discernible articulations to suggest it has three or even two palpomeres (see 
Fig. 12
). The maxillary palpi of two other specimens (the 
holotype
and a non-type female) were also examined, albeit under a dissecting microscope, and similarly in each an enlarged basal portion was clearly evident but separate palpomeres were not.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibits unusual sexual dimorphism in that in females the T1–T3 apical fasciae are interrupted medially, albeit narrowly, whereas in males the T1–T3 apical fasciae are complete. This difference between the sexes is consistent across the specimens from Hispaniola that were studied. Previously known from a single (male) specimen, the female of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is described here for the first time.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
