<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Brachymelecta Linsley 1939</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4967915</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F2B679EDA5B392E9F0C486EEEC5DB30A</uri>
         <article-title>Brachymelecta Linsley, 1939, previously the rarest North American bee genus, was described from an aberrant specimen and is the senior synonym for Xeromelecta Linsley, 1939</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.754.1393</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Key to both sexes of the species of
<tp:taxon-name>Brachymelecta</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Mandible bidentate, with inner preapical tooth as well as usual apical tooth (rutellum) (
Fig. 14A
). Mesoscutum covered in dense, uniformly golden-yellow hairs (
Fig. 15
). Mesoscutellum without pair of spines or well-defined mammiform tubercles, although mesoscutellum bigibbous to some degree and sometimes with pair of very minute protrusions (
Fig. 15D
). Mesotibia with black hairs only (
Fig. 15A, C
). T1–T4 without fasciae or with only very faint apical bands of golden-yellow hairs (
Fig. 15B
) ...................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. larreae
(
Cockerell, 1900
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Mandible tridentate, with inner basal tooth as well as inner preapical tooth and usual apical tooth (rutellum) (
Fig. 14B
). Mesoscutum with pair of spots or bands (
Figs 3B
, 
5B
, 
10B
, 
11
, 
13B
, 
16B
). Mesoscutellum with pair of spines or mammiform tubercles (least developed pair shown in 
Fig. 13D
) (see also 
Figs 3D
, 
5D
, 
10D
, 
16D
). Mesotibia dorsally with some off-white or yellow-orange hairs, those of female sparser and usually reduced to small bands or spots (
Figs 3A–B
, 
5A
, 
10A–B
, 
11
, 
16A–B
); those of male forming patch of very dense off-white, golden-yellow, or yellow-orange hairs, occupying nearly entire dorsal surface (
Figs 3C
, 
5C
, 
7A, C
, 
8A–B
, 
13C
, 
16C
). T1–T3 with well-defined off-white to golden-yellow or yellow-orange apical fasciae (
Figs 3A–C
, 
5A–C
, 
8A–C
, 
10A–C
, 
11
, 
13A–C
, 
16A–C
), rarely entirely covered in pale tomentum (
Figs 7A–C
, 
8D
) ............. 2

</p>
      <p>

2. Mesoscutum with pair of anterior spots or bands of hairs darker than surrounding off-white or yellow-orange hairs (
Figs 5B
, 
13B
). Mesoscutellum with pair of short, mammiform tubercles (
Figs 5D
, 
13D
). Maxillary palpus with four or five palpomeres (
Fig. 12A
) [North America] .................. 3

</p>
      <p>

– Mesoscutum with pair of central spots of off-white or pale to golden-yellow hairs lighter than surrounding black hairs (
Figs 3B
, 
10B
, 
11
, 
16B
). Mesoscutellum with pair of spines (
Figs 3D
, 
10D
, 
16D
). Maxillary palpus with fewer than four palpomeres (
Fig. 12B
) [Greater Antilles] ................. 4

</p>
      <p>

3. T3 and T4 each with fascia narrowed or interrupted laterally, mesad the inner pair of anterolateral extensions (
Fig. 5A–C
). Fore wing infuscate apically, subhyaline in most cells and around third submarginal crossvein and second recurrent vein (
Fig. 5A–C
). Head, mesosoma, and metasoma with pale hairs off-white (rarely pale yellow and never orange) (
Figs 5A–C
, 
8
) ........................................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. californica
(
Cresson, 1878
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– T3 and T4 each with fascia broadened anterolaterally, that of T3 into inner pair of anterolateral extensions (
Fig. 13A–C
). Fore wing infuscate throughout except subhyaline around third submarginal crossvein and second recurrent vein (
Fig. 13A–C
). Head, mesosoma, and metasoma with pale hairs typically pale yellow to yellow orange (
Fig. 13A–C
) ......................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
(
Cresson, 1872
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

4. Mesoscutum with band of pale hairs along midline not attaining posterior margin (
Fig. 3B, D
). Mesoscutellum, except for pair of spines and around their bases, densely covered in pale pubescence greatly obscuring underlying integument (
Fig. 3D
) [
Cuba
] .................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. alayoi
(
Michener, 1988
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum each with uninterrupted band of pale hairs along entire midline (
Figs 10B, D
, 
11
, 
16B, D
). Mesoscutellum pubescence otherwise dark brown or black, sparse, not obscuring underlying integument (
Figs 10D
, 
16D
) [other regions] ................................................. 5

</p>
      <p>

5. T1–T3 with fasciae pale yellow, narrowly interrupted medially in female (
Fig. 10B
), complete in male (
Fig. 9A
) [Hispaniola] ................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. haitensis
(
Michener, 1948
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– T1–T3 with fasciae off-white, widely interrupted medially in female (
Fig. 16B
), narrowly interrupted medially in male (
Fig. 9B
) [
Puerto Rico
and 
U.S. Virgin Islands
] ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. tibialis
(
Fabricius, 1793
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
