<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Brachymelecta interrupta ANSP</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4967809</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D70584F521F3AB2850A95FFCD4C80A32</uri>
         <article-title>Brachymelecta Linsley, 1939, previously the rarest North American bee genus, was described from an aberrant specimen and is the senior synonym for Xeromelecta Linsley, 1939</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.754.1393</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta interrupta
(
Cresson, 1872
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 4C
, 
6D
, 13, 
14B
, 17
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
Cresson, 1872: 275
</tp:taxon-name>

(
♀
, 
♂
); 

Cresson, 1916: 121

(
♀
) (
lectotype
designation). 

<tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
var. 
fallugiae
Cockerell, 1904: 23
</tp:taxon-name>

(
♀
).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
var. 
rociadensis
Cockerell, 1904: 23
</tp:taxon-name>

(
♂
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="vernacular_names">
      <p>
Proposed common name
</p>
      <p>Interrupted digger-cuckoo bee.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The following morphological features in combination can be used to tell 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
apart from all other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta
</tp:taxon-name>
: the mesoscutum has a pair of anterior spots or (paramedian) bands of hairs darker than the surrounding yellow-orange hairs (
Fig. 13B
); the mesoscutellum has a pair of short, mammiform tubercles (
Fig. 13D
); the fore wings are infuscate throughout except around the third submarginal crossvein and second recurrent vein, where they are subhyaline (
Fig. 13A–C
); and T3 and T4 each have a medially interrupted fascia that is broadened anterolaterally, that of T3 into the inner pair of anterolateral extensions (there are two such lobe-like extensions on each side) (
Fig. 13A–C
). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
is most similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. californica
</tp:taxon-name>
, but in 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. californica
</tp:taxon-name>
the fore wings are infuscate apically, with most cells as well as the membrane around the third submarginal crossvein and second recurrent vein subhyaline, and T3 and T4 each have a medially interrupted fascia that is narrowed or interrupted (as opposed to continuously expanded) laterally, mesad the inner pair of anterolateral extensions. Additionally, in 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. californica
</tp:taxon-name>
the lighter hairs covering the head, mesosoma, and metasoma are off-white or very rarely pale yellow, whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
they range from pale yellow to yellow orange.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 13.
<tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta interrupta
(
Cresson, 1872
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A
. Female (CNC 891735), habitus, lateral view. 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
lectotype, ♀ (ANSP 2291), habitus, dorsal view. 
C
. Male (CNC 891719), habitus, lateral view. 
D
. Female (BOLD sample ID: 14511H06-AZ; PCYU 0003840), axillae and mesoscutellum, dorsal view (blue arrow indicates one of two short, mammiform tubercles of mesoscutellum).
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Primary type material
</p>
      <p>
USA
• 
♀
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
var. 
fallugiae
</tp:taxon-name>
holotype; 
New Mexico
, 
Pecos
; 

27 Jun.

; 
M. Grabham
leg.; 
CAS 4672

• 

♂
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
var. 
rociadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
holotype; 
New Mexico
, 
Rociada
, 
San Miguel County
; 

10 Aug.

; 
T.D.A. Cockerell
leg.; 
USNM 534231

• 

♀
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
lectotype
; 
Texas
; 
ANSP 2291

.
</p>
      <p>
DNA barcoded material
</p>
      <p>Available. BIN: BOLD:ABU5955. Specimens examined and sequenced:</p>
      <p>
USA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Arizona
, 
Southwestern Research Station
(

5 mi
W of Portal

), 
Cochise County
; 

28 Aug. 2007

; 
H.T. Ngo
leg.; BOLD sample ID: CCDB-34570 B06; 
PCYU

• 

1 ♀
; 
Arizona
, 
Southwestern Research Station
(

5 mi
W of Portal

), 
Cochise County
; 
31.8840° N
, 
109.2060° W
; 

31 Aug. 2011

; 
N. de Silva
leg.; BOLD sample ID: 14511H06-AZ; 
PCYU
0003840

• 

1 ♀
; 
New Mexico
, 

10 mi
N of Mimbres

, 
Grant County
; 
32.9778° N
, 
108.0528° W
; 

6 Aug. 2007

; 
M. Buck
leg.; BOLD sample ID: CCDB-34570 B04; 
DEBU
debu00291180

.
</p>
      <p>
Non-barcoded material
</p>
      <p>
USA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Arizona
, 
Canelo
, 
Santa Cruz County
; 

27 Jun. 1965

; 
R.F. Sternitzky
leg.; 
CNC 891717

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CNC 891718

• 

1 ♀
; 
Arizona
, 
Southwestern Research Station
(

5 mi
W of Portal

), 
Cochise County
; 

26 Aug. 2007

; 
H.T. Ngo
; 
PCYU

• 

5 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Colorado
; 
ANSP

• 

1 ♀
; 
Colorado
, 
Logan County
; 
40.4894° N
, 
102.7412° W
; 

31 May 2012

; 
M. Vandever
et al.
leg.; 
CSUC

• 

1 ♂
; 
Illinois
; 
ANSP

• 

1 ♀
; 
Kansas
, 
Wallace
, 
Wallace County
; 

Jul. 1885

; 
CNC 891738

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CNC 891737

• 

1 ♀
; 
Mississippi
, 
Lafayette County
; 

Sep.–Oct.1956

; 
E.R. Wall
leg.; 
CNC 891699

• 

1 ♀
; 
Missouri
, 
Lake Ozark
; 

20 Sep. 1939

; 
E.C. Van Dyke
leg.; 
CAS

• 

2 ♀♀
, 
2 ♂♂
; 
Nebraska
; 
ANSP

• 

1 ♀
; 
New Mexico
, 

1 mi
E of top of pass

, 
near Sierra Blanca
, Hwy 70; 

27 Aug. 1962

; 
F.M. Hull
leg.; 
CNC 891735

• 

1 ♀
; 
New Mexico
, 
Manzano Mountains
(

8 mi
W of Manzano, near New Canyon Campground

), 
Torrance County
; 

28 Aug. 1993

; 
J.E. O’Hara
leg.; 
CNC 891714

• 

1 ♀
(labelled as “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
Cress.
</tp:taxon-name>
♀ TYPE” but probably a non-type specimen); 
Texas
; 
USNM
534230

• 

1 ♂
; 
Texas
, 
The Rockpile
(

30 mi
NW of Fort Davis

); 

28 May 1959

; 
J.F. McAlpine
leg.; 
CNC 891719

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length 
12.7 mm
; ITW 
2.9 mm
; head length 
3.4 mm
; head width 4.0 mm; fore wing length 
11.7 mm
.
</p>
      <p>INTEGUMENT COLORATION. Dark brown to black except as follows. Mandible with basal two-thirds, legs, excluding black tibial spurs, and much of metasoma reddish brown. Fore wing dusky throughout except around third submarginal crossvein and second recurrent vein, where subhyaline. Hind wing dusky subhyaline.</p>
      <p>
PUBESCENCE. Face with hairs densest around antennal socket, predominantly pale yellow to yellow orange but almost entirely black in lower paraocular area and on clypeus. Upper paraocular and frontal areas and vertexal area (except along preoccipital ridge) mostly exposed. Head with dense, erect hairs along preoccipital ridge yellow orange except for pair of black patches, each behind lateral ocellus and in front of paramedian band (hairs somewhat faded in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
lectotype
; described from nontype specimens). Genal beard hairs almost entirely black. Mesoscutum sparsely hairy except densely hairy anteriorly, narrowly along lateral margin, and in space between parapsidal line and axilla, with hairs predominantly yellow orange except for black paramedian band. Axilla with conspicuous patch of black hairs. Mesoscutellum and much of lateral surface of propodeum (except near bases of mesocoxa and metacoxa) with erect, predominantly yellow-orange hairs. Metanotum and propodeal triangle with erect, predominantly black hairs. Mesopleuron and metapleuron each with upper half covered in dense, yellow-orange hairs greatly obscuring underlying integument and lower half covered in sparser, black hairs not obscuring underlying integument. Legs, from coxae to tarsi, with patches of appressed and erect pale yellow to yellow-orange hairs among more numerous dark brown to black hairs. Profemur with posteroventral fringe of dense, predominantly pale yellow hairs. Tibiae each with small, inconspicuous spot of short, appressed pale yellow hairs in basal half (in some non-type specimens, protibia and metatibia each with additional patch of short, appressed pale yellow hairs on apical margin). T1–T5 with well-defined medially interrupted apical fasciae, laterally with erect among appressed yellow-orange hairs. T2 and T3 fasciae each with pair of lobe-like anterolateral extensions on each side. T3–T5 each with fascia broadened anterolaterally, that of T3 into inner pair of anterolateral extensions. Exposed metasomal sterna with short, appressed black hairs.
</p>
      <p>SURFACE SCULPTURE. Labrum sparsely punctate (many i&gt;2d). Clypeus with punctures more or less equally dense throughout (most i≤1d) except for small impunctate shiny spot medially on lower margin. Small impunctate shiny spot lateral to lateral ocellus, another behind median ocellus. Mesoscutum and mesoscutellum with coarser punctures than metasomal terga. Mesoscutum densely punctate (most i≤1d) except for small impunctate shiny spot between paramedian band and parapsidal line and along posterior margin around midline, where more sparsely punctate (few i&gt;1d). Mesoscutellum with punctures more or less equally dense throughout (most i≤1d) and similar in size to those of mesoscutum. Mesopleuron densely punctate (most i&lt;1d) but with most interspaces well-defined, shining. Discs of metasomal terga with punctures very fine, sparse (most i&gt;1d), interspaces dull due to tessellate surface microsculpture.</p>
      <p>
STRUCTURE. Mandible tridentate, with small inner tooth approximately ⅓ length of mandible from base and larger inner tooth approximately ⅖ length of mandible from apex as well as usual large apical tooth (rutellum) (difficult to see in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
lectotype
because mandibles closed; described from non-type specimens). Maxillary palpus with five palpomeres (mouthparts not extended in 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
lectotype
; described from non-type specimen). Scape with greatest length 2.3 × greatest width. F2 nearly as long as wide (L/ W ratio = 0.9). Mesoscutellum moderately bigibbous, with pair of short, conical mammiform tubercles. Lateral surface of propodeum posterior to spiracle relatively flat and unmodified. Fore wing with three submarginal cells. T6 with narrow, V-shaped but apically rounded pygidial plate with median longitudinal ridge.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Description as for female except for usual secondary sexual characters and as follows: scape shorter, with greatest length 1.8 × greatest width; F2 shorter, wider than long (L/W ratio = 0.7); mesotibia with patch of very dense short, appressed yellow-orange hairs, occupying nearly entire dorsal surface; T7 with slight median emargination; S4 and S5 each with apical/subapical fringe of dense curved black hairs.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
is the second-most widely distributed member of its genus, after 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. californica
</tp:taxon-name>
. Its range includes much of the Central 
United States
, parts of the Southwestern 
United States
(as far west as eastern 
Arizona
), and north-central 
Mexico
(
Fig. 4C
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>
Host records
</p>
      <p>
According to 
Mitchell (1962)
, the host of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
is 
<tp:taxon-name>
Anthophora abrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
, but no details were provided with regard to the basis of this apparent association. That a different species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. walshii
Cresson, 1869
</tp:taxon-name>
, is the primary if not only host of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
is strongly suggested by three separate observations of the latter in the presence/vicinity of the former (by 
Robertson 1926
; 
Graenicher 1935
; 
Bouseman 1982
) and there being much greater range overlap (see 
Ascher &amp; Pickering 2020
) between 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. walshii
</tp:taxon-name>
(both are widespread from the Midwestern 
United States
to Western North America) than between 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. abrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
(an eastern species).
</p>
      <p>
Floral records
</p>
      <p>
The 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
var. 
fallugiae
</tp:taxon-name>
was collected from the flowers of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Fallugia
Endl.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Rosaceae</tp:taxon-name>
). 
Robertson (1929)
reported 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
(as 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
) on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Coreopsis palmata
Nutt.
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pycnanthemum flexuosum
(Walter) Britton, Sterns &amp; Poggenb.
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Lamiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
). 
Linsley (1939)
reported this species on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cleome
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Cleomaceae</tp:taxon-name>
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dalea
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) (as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Petalostemon
</tp:taxon-name>
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monarda
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Lamiaceae</tp:taxon-name>
), 
Hurd (1953)
on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Baccharis
</tp:taxon-name>
L., 

Hurd 
et al.
(1980)

on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Helianthus annuus
</tp:taxon-name>
, and 
Bouseman (1982)
on 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pauciflorus
Nutt.
</tp:taxon-name>
(as 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. rigidus
</tp:taxon-name>
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rudbeckia hirta
</tp:taxon-name>
L. (
<tp:taxon-name>Asteraceae</tp:taxon-name>
). Discover Life (
Ascher &amp; Pickering 2020
) cites the following floral record contributed by the Bee Biology and Systematics Laboratory: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cirsium
Mill. Images
</tp:taxon-name>
on BugGuide (https://bugguide.net) show this species visiting 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dalea candida
Willd. The
</tp:taxon-name>
label of one examined voucher specimen further indicates that this species has been collected from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Marrubium vulgare
</tp:taxon-name>
L.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Brachymelecta interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
was described (as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
) from 
two specimens
(
one female
and 
one male
), from Dallas and Comal Counties (
Texas
), although it is not clear from the description or the female specimen’s labels which locality corresponds to which specimen. We have not seen the male specimen, deposited in the Museum of Comparative Zoology (MCZ) in Cambridge, MA, 
USA
, but according to 
Cockerell (1907)
it is from Dallas, so presumably the female is from Comal County. 
Cresson (1916)
designated the female specimen, deposited in the ANSP (catalog number: 2291), as the 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
. Confusingly, there is also a female specimen in the primary type collection of the USNM (catalog number: 534230) bearing the label “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Melecta interrupta
Cress.
</tp:taxon-name>
♀
TYPE”. This specimen (also from 
Texas
) bears another label that says “Type No 1764 
U.S.
N.M” and is listed as the 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
in the Department of Entomology Collections database (https://collections.nmnh.si.edu/search/ento/). It is not clear when or if this designation was published or which of the 
two females
constituted the basis for the original description, but given that 
Cresson (1916)
, who described the species, designated the specimen at the ANSP as the 
lectotype
, it is herein regarded as such as well (with the male at the MCZ, labelled as a 
syntype
, recognized as the lectoallotype).
</p>
      <p>
Cockerell (1904)
described two “varieties” of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
(both from 
New Mexico
) on the basis that neither precisely agrees with the “typical 
<tp:taxon-name>form from</tp:taxon-name>
Texas
”. In 
Linsley (1939)
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M.
var. 
fallugiae
</tp:taxon-name>
appears in the synonymy list for 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
, although it is referred to as a 
<tp:taxon-name>variety rather</tp:taxon-name>
than a synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
, one in which the pale pubescence is more orange than yellow. 
Mitchell (1962)
apparently accepted this as a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
, and we agree with Mitchell’s treatment. In the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
var. 
fallugiae
</tp:taxon-name>
, the pale pubescence is the same yellow-orange color exhibited by the 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Linsley (1939)
regarded the other variety (
<tp:taxon-name>
M.
var. 
rociadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
) as a separate species (
<tp:taxon-name>
M. rociadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
) from 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
; however, later 
Hurd &amp; Linsley (1951)
indicated that they were unable to reliably distinguish 
<tp:taxon-name>
M.
var. 
rociadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
and therefore synonymized the former name under the latter. Aside from the paler pubescence exhibited by the 
<tp:taxon-name>
M.
var. 
rociadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
holotype
, its description applies equally well to the 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Cockerell’s (1904)
description, rather than differentiating the 
<tp:taxon-name>
M.
var. 
rociadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
holotype
from the “typical form” of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
, instead lists the features (the dark tegulae and wings and unique metasomal markings) that separate 
<tp:taxon-name>
M.
var. 
rociadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. miranda
</tp:taxon-name>
(now a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. californica
</tp:taxon-name>
). These differences, however, can be used to separate any representatives of 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
(including the 
lectotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
) from the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. miranda
</tp:taxon-name>
. Although the pale hairs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
B. interrupta
</tp:taxon-name>
range from pale yellow to yellow orange, the variation is continuous and the differences in hair color do not correspond to any geographic pattern. Hence, we agree with the treatment of 
Hurd &amp; Linsley (1951)
and do not regard 
<tp:taxon-name>
M.
var. 
rociadensis
</tp:taxon-name>
as a valid taxon.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
