<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Labrum not or slightly emarginate; pronotum with fore angles not or slightly protruding (
Figs 3
A- E); elytral interval three with four or five dorsal setiferous pores, elytral interval five without dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4
) .................................................................................................................... 2

</p>
      <p>

– Labrum conspicuously emarginate as a semicircular incision; pronotum with fore angles strongly protruding (
Fig. 3F
); elytral interval three with nine dorsal setiferous pores, elytral interval five with six dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4F
) (Longzhou: Zhuzhu Dong cave) ............................................... ................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G
. 
inexpectatus

Tian &amp; Zhou
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

2. Elytral interval three with four dorsal setiferous pores (
Figs 4B, C
) ................................................ 3

</p>
      <p>

– Elytral interval three with five dorsal setiferous pores (
Fig. 4A, D–E
) ............................................ 4

</p>
      <p>

3. Body smaller (
5.2 mm
); head stouter, labrum seven-setose, palpomeres slightly stouter, antennae shorter and stouter; entire lateral margin of elytra crenulated throughout, striae composed of larger punctures, interval six faintly carinated near base (
Fig. 4B
) (Longzhou: Paoma Dong cave)............ ........................................................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. bedosae
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body larger (
7 mm
); head slender, labrum five-setose, palpomeres slender, antennae longer and more slender; lateral margin of elytra crenulated on basal half, smooth on apical half, striae composed of smaller punctures, interval six strongly carinated near base (
Fig. 4C
) (Du’an: three caves) ............. ......................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. cavicola
Tian, 2013
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

4. Body larger (
9.2–9.5 mm
); frontal carinae long and nearly parallel-sided; pronotum wider than long; elytra with striae smaller and denser punctured, elytral intervals six to eight carinated near base, four and five not carinated (
Fig. 4A
) ........................................................................................................ 5

</p>
      <p>

– Body smaller and more slender (
4.5 mm
); frontal carinae short and not parallel-sided; pronotum longer than wide; elytra with striae composed of larger and sparser punctures, elytral intervals six to eight carinated throughout, four and five carinated near base (
Fig. 4D
) (Huanjiang: Dapo Dong cave) .................................................................................................................................................... ........................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. weii
Huang &amp; Faille
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

5. Body more depigmented, of light brown colour; pronotum shorter and stouter, with remarkably emarginate anterior margin (
Fig. 3A
); elytral intervals slightly vaulted, elytral striae broad and well marked, with large isolated punctures (
Fig. 4A
) (Huanjiang: Ji Dong cave, formerly called Shuiku Dong) ......................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. deharvengi
Tian, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body less depigmented, of reddish-brown colour; pronotum longer and more slender, with anterior margin almost not emarginate (
Fig. 3E
); elytral intervals rather strongly vaulted, elytral striae narrow and deep, with small isolated punctures (
Fig. 4E
) (Huanjiang: Huang Dong cave) .......................... ............................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. yueliangensis
Huang &amp; Tian
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
