<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Lutites lyriformis
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3FC3DB4D-AA14-43A6-B982-0137ED22D6B7
</p>
      <p>
Figs 51–52
; 
Table 26
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
with conch reaching 
140 mm
dm. Subadult stage with parallel-sided, compressed whorl profile (ww/wh = 0.60–0.70) and rounded venter; about 14 ventrolateral nodes per volution. Adult stage with subtrapezoidal, compressed whorl profile (ww/wh =0.50–0.60), concave flanks, concave venter and angular ventrolateral shoulder; numerous weak and densely arranged ribs. Prongs of external lobe bifid to multiply serrated; altogether 13–22 notches of E, A and L lobes.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From the Latin ‘ 
lyra
’, referring to the shape of the whorl profile.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain A section
; Hambast Formation; illustrated in 
Fig. 51A
; 
MB.C.29995
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
IRAN
• 
1 specimen
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain 1 section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29994

• 

2 specimens
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain C section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29996
to 
MB.C.29997

• 

1 specimen
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain E section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29998

• 

1 specimen
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain G section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.29999

• 

2 specimens
; 
Esfahan Province
, 
Baghuk Mountain H section
; 
Hambast Formation
; 
MB.C.30000
to 
MB.C.30001

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 51.
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites lyriformis
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, lateral and dorsal views. 
A
. Holotype MB.C.29995, section A, float. 
B
. Paratype MB.C.29997, section C, -1.00 m. 
C
. Paratype MB.C.29996, section C, -1.45 m. 
D
. Paratype MB.C.29999, section G, -1.20 m. Scale bar units =1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MB.C.29995 is a rather well-preserved specimen with 
96 mm
conch diameter (
Fig. 51A
). It allows the study of three and a half volutions, of which only one third of a volution belongs to the body chamber. Adulthood is indicated by the weak crowding of the last septa at 
73 mm
diameter. The whorl profile is, at the largest preserved conch diameter, subtrapezoidal with a broadly rounded umbilical margin and concave and converging flanks. The weakly concave venter is separated from the flanks by an angular ventrolateral shoulder. Half a volution earlier, the venter is plane and another half a volution back, the venter is broadly rounded. The sculpture shows significant ontogenetic changes from the subadult stage with 13 coarse and blunt ventrolateral nodes, which originate from weak and rounded radial ribs, per volution. They become weaker and more numerous in the last quarter volution of the phragmocone (about 12 weak ventrolateral nodes within this interval). The body chamber possesses a very weak sculpture consisting only of weak and rounded radial riblets in the inner flank area.
</p>
      <p>
The suture line of the 
holotype
possesses a parallel-sided external lobe with prongs being asymmetrically serrated by four and five small notches, respectively. The asymmetric ventrolateral saddle is nearly as wide as high; it is followed by an adventive lobe with oblique base serrated into seven small notches. The weakly asymmetric, inverted U-shaped lateral saddle is nearly as high as the ventrolateral saddle. Finally, the asymmetric lateral lobe has also seven small notches (
Fig. 52A
).
</p>
      <p>
The smaller 
paratype
MB.C.29997 has 
74 mm
conch diameter, of which the phragmocone has a diameter of 
64 mm
and one quarter of a whorl belongs to the body chamber (
Fig. 51B
). The whorl profile is subtrapezoidal with concave, converging flanks and the venter is weakly concave. The sculpture generally resembles the 
holotype
, but the ribs and nodes are weaker. The same is true for the additional
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 52.
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites lyriformis
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A
. Suture line, holotype MB.C.29995, at 58.3 mm dm, 23.1 mm wh. 
B
. Suture line, paratype MB.C.29997, at 53.8 mm dm, 19.0 mm wh. 
C
. Whorl profile proportions. Abbreviations: see Material and methods. Scale bar units =1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Table 26.
Conch dimensions (partly estimated) and ratios of selected specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites lyriformis
Korn &amp; Hairapetian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
from Baghuk Mountain.
</p>
      <p>
Specimen
dm
ww
wh
uw
ah
ww/dm
ww/wh
uw/dm
WER
IZR
MB.C.29995
95.8
19.9
34.6
35.8
31.7
0.21
0.58
0.37
2.23
0.08
MB.C.29996
94.3
18.6
31.1
41.3
30.0
0.20
0.60
0.44
2.15
0.03
MB.C.29998
79.7
18.3
26.6
31.3
24.4
0.23
0.69
0.39
2.08
0.08
MB.C.29999
79.2
18.0
28.6
29.3
25.5
0.23
0.63
0.37
2.18
0.11
MB.C.29997
74.3
16.8
25.3
30.1
24.5
0.23
0.66
0.41
2.23
0.03
MB.C.29994
72.0
15.1
24.4
29.2
23.0
0.21
0.62
0.41
2.16
0.06
MB.C.29995
95.8
19.9
34.6
35.8
31.7
0.21
0.58
0.37
2.23
0.08
</p>
      <p>
paratypes
MB.C.29996 (
Fig. 51C
) and MB.C.29999 (
Fig. 51D
), which is the conch geometry are nearly identical with the 
holotype
.
</p>
      <p>
The suture line of 
paratype
MB.C.29997 shows a parallel-sided external lobe that is deeper than the adventive lobe. The prongs are bifid and parallel-sided. All lobes and thus saddles are parallel-sided and all saddles have the same height. The adventive lobe and the lateral lobe possess six and four small notches (
Fig. 52B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new species differs in the coarse ventrolateral nodes of the subadult stage from most of the other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
with compressed whorl profile. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites lyriformis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. profundus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
but differs in the much weaker sculpture of the terminal body chamber, which shows only very weak ribs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. lyriformis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
but ventrolateral nodes in 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. profundus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Stratigraphic range
</p>
      <p>
Upper part of the Hambast Formation; 1.45 to 1.00 m below the extinction horizon (
<tp:taxon-name>
Lutites profundus
Zone
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Abichites abichi
Zone
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
