<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopolydora arabica
Radashevsky &amp; Al-Kandari, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1B
, 
5D
, 
10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopolydora arabica
Radashevsky &amp; Al-Kandari, 2020: 2−10
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 2−7.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopolydora
sp. B
</tp:taxon-name>
– 


Al-Kandari 
et al
. 2019: 9


. — Radashevsky 
et al
. 2020: table 1, fig. 1.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopolydora paucibranchiata
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Swaleh &amp; Mustaquim 1993: 204

, fig. 2. — Not 
Okuda 1937
.

</p>
      <p>
Adult diagnostic features
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Adults up to 
20 mm
long, 
1 mm
wide with 80 chaetigers (
Fig. 10A
). Live individuals with yellowishwhite pigment on lateral sides of prostomium and dorsal side of 3−5 anterior chaetigers (most intense on chaetigers 1−2), and up to 50 yellowish-white ramified chromatophores on each palp in (
Fig. 10A– B
); chromatophores not visible after fixation. Prostomium anteriorly narrow and rounded (
Fig. 10B
). Caruncle extending to end of chaetiger 4. Occipital antenna present. Chaetiger 1 with short capillaries in neuropodia; notochaetae absent. Anterior-row capillaries in notopodia from chaetiger 7 to chaetigers 10−20 with wide subtriangular, pennoned limbation. Chaetiger 5 almost as same in size as chaetigers 4 and 6 (
Fig. 10B
); dorsal superior capillaries slightly shorter and fewer than those capillaries on chaetigers 4 and 6; ventral capillaries as same as those on chaetiger 4; two kinds of notopodial spines arranged in a double J-shaped row; outer (anterior-row) notopodial spines with geniculate distal tip with wide limbation; inner (posterior-row) notopodial spines simple falcate (
Fig. 10C
). Bidentate hooded hooks in neuropodia from chaetiger 8. Branchiae from chaetiger 7 to chaetiger 30, up to 24 pairs. Pygidium small, cup-shaped, with dorsal gap. Glandular pouches in neuropodia from chaetiger 1, largest in chaetigers 6 and 7, single pouch in each neuropodium.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 10.
Adult morphology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopolydora arabica
Radashevsky &amp;Al-Kandari, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
live individuals (A–B) and formalin-fixed specimens stained with MG (C–G). 
A–C
. MIMB 39111. 
D–G
. MIMB 40911. 
A
. Left lateral general view, in reflected light, showing yellowish-white chromatophores on palps. 
B
. Anterior end, dorsal view, in reflected light. 
C
. Parapodia of chaetiger 5. 
D
. Anterior end, dorsal view. 
E–F
. Anterior ends, ventral view. Abbreviations: 
ne
= neuropodial postchaetal lamella; 
su
= dorsal superior capillary chaetae; 
ve
= ventral capillary chaetae. Scale bars: A = 1 mm; B = 200 µm; C = 20 µm; D–G = 100 µm.
</p>
      <p>
MG staining
</p>
      <p>
Intensely stained dorsal side of the prostomium in front of eyes, dorsal side of the peristomium, and ventral side of chaetigers: complete transverse paired bands moderate intense on chaetigers 1–4, very intense complete transverse paired bands on chaetigers 5–7, and paired transverse bands split into three parts from chaetiger 8 onwards (
Fig. 10D–G
). Remarkably, the three-parts banding was associated with the start of the hooded hooks in neuropodia and was invariable in all examined specimens.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudopolydora arabica
Radashevsky &amp; Al-Kandari, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
was originally described from the Arabian Gulf as one of the common polychaetes inhabiting soft sediments. The population density of the species in some places reaches 50 000 individuals per 
1 m
2
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Arabian Gulf: 
Kuwait
(
Fig. 1B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
