<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Neanthes galetae Fauchald
                        1977</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5122986</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03D687C6FFB5F525FDEDFB2CFEC9FA32</uri>
                  <article-title>Redescriptions of Neanthes Kinberg, 1865 (Annelida: Errantia:
                        Nereididae) species from worldwide regions</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://zoobank.org/917481ff-7c89-4b0f-8c91-77e616271ecc</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes galetae Fauchald, 1977 </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Fig. 2 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes galetae Fauchald, 1977: 26–27 </tp:taxon-name> , fig.
                  6a–b [ type locality: Galeta Island, Colón , Panama ]. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes galetae </tp:taxon-name> – Wilson 1984: 225 (species
                  list, group IIB). — de León-González et al . 2020: 19 (key). — Villalobos-Guerrero
                  &amp; Idris 2021: 559 (table 1), 561 (table 2). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Type material </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype PANAMA • atokous; Caribbean Sea , Colón , Canal
                        Zone , Galeta Island Reef ; 23 Oct. 1970 ; Smithsonian Tropical Research
                        Institute and A.A. Reimer leg.; intertidal , <tp:taxon-name> Laurencia
                        </tp:taxon-name> or <tp:taxon-name> Acanthophora </tp:taxon-name> zones ;
                        USNM 53088 . </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Paratypes PANAMA • 2 atokous ; same collection data as for
                        holotype; USNM 53089 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1
                        atokous ; same collection data as for holotype; 9°24′18″ N , 79°51′48.5″ W ;
                              <tp:taxon-name> Laurencia </tp:taxon-name> zone ; LACM-AHF Poly 1132
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> COLOUR AND MEASUREMENTS. Holotype atokous, complete, in good condition, 7 (9–14) mm
                  TL, 2.4 (2.5– 4) mm L15, 0.6 (0.6–0.9) mm W15, with 52 (56–58) chaetigers. Body
                  colour yellowish, with greyish pigmentation on distal half of prostomium,
                  cirrophores of anal cirri, and present throughout dorsally and ventrally as a
                  transverse, thin line in anterior margin of segments ( Fig. 2A–B ). </p>
            <p> PROSTOMIUM. Pear-shaped, as long as wide ( Fig. 2B ); anterior end narrow, distally
                  complete; anterolateral gap beside palpophore narrow, three-quarters as wide as
                  antennal diameter; dorsal groove distinct, shallow, running mid-subdistally.
                  Nuchal organs deeply embedded. </p>
            <p> PALPOPHORES. Ovoid, 1.6 times wider than long ( Fig. 2B ), as long as half of entire
                  prostomium; with inconspicuous sub-distal transverse groove. Palpostyles ovoid,
                  thick, with diameter as wide as half of palpophore ( Fig. 2B ). </p>
            <p> ANTENNAE. Tapered, slender, short, extending forwards to tip of palpophore ( Fig. 2B
                  ) and posteriorly to one-third length of prostomium; antennae close together, with
                  gap one-quarter as wide as basal diameter of antennae. </p>
            <p> EYES. Paired eyes blackish, arranged in a trapezoid form; gap between both pairs
                  one-quarter as wide as diameter of posterior pair of eyes ( Fig. 2B ); anterior
                  pair of eyes rounded, twice as wide as basal diameter of antennae, gap between
                  both eyes 2.5 times as wide as diameter of eyes, with lens distinct, purplish,
                  covering 30% of eye; posterior pair of eyes rounded, twice as wide as basal
                  diameter of antennae, with lens distinct, purplish, placed posterolaterally on eye
                  and covering 40% of it. </p>
            <p> APODOUS ANTERIOR SEGMENT. Segment 2.5 times wider than long, as long as chaetiger 1,
                  with flattening anterior margin, dorsum without marked transverse wrinkle ( Fig.
                  2B ). </p>
            <p> TENTACULAR CIRRI. Slender, multi-articulated ( Fig. 2B ); postero-dorsal cirri
                  extending posteriorly to chaetiger 4 (3), 1.6 times as long as antero-dorsal
                  cirri; antero-dorsal cirri extending posteriorly to between chaetigers 1 and 2
                  (1–2); postero-ventral cirri extended over half of prostomium; antero-ventral
                  cirri 1.5 times as long as postero-ventral cirri and extending beyond 1.3 times
                  length of palpophore; dorsal cirrophores cylindrical, ventral cirrophores
                  ring-shaped, postero-dorsal cirrophores 1.5 times as long as antero-dorsal
                  cirrophores, antero-ventral cirrophores 1.5 times as wide as postero-ventral
                  cirrophores. </p>
            <p> PHARYNX. Non-everted, previously dissected. Jaws with distal quarter brownish,
                  remaining yellow amber, 10 well-developed and sharp denticles; pulp cavity with
                  two canals ( Fig. 2C–D , paratype ). Reddish-brown paragnaths on maxillary and
                  oral rings ( Fig. 2C ), consisting of conical, p-bars, and merged paragnaths;
                  plate-like basements absent. Area I: 0 (0–1) ( Fig. 2C ); areas IIa: 9 (9–12) and
                  IIb: 9 (8–14), two slightly regular rows of uneven cones in eyebrow-shaped patch,
                  cones in outer row larger ( Fig. 2C ); area III: unknown but one paratype with 12
                  (5–12) paragnaths in two slightly regular rows of uneven cones in rectangular
                  patch, without distinct laterally-isolated cones, distal row with larger cones;
                  areas IVa: 11 (13–14) and IVb: 13 (11–17), crescent-shaped patch with two slightly
                  regular transverse rows of uneven cones located proximally and four long and
                  slender merged paragnaths (2–4 times longer than wide; Fig. 2C ) located distally;
                  area V: 0 (0) ( Fig. 2C ); areas VIa: 9 (9–11) and VIb: 9 (9–10), one rounded
                  patch of uneven cones, closely together ( Fig. 2C ); areas VII–VIII: 5 (13–15),
                  one band of uneven cones consisting of two transversely aligned rows ( Fig. 2C ).
                  Areas VI–V–VI ridge pattern, π- shaped ( Fig. 2C ). Gap between area VI and areas
                  VII–VIII narrow, as wide as palpostyle. </p>
            <p>PAIRED OESOPHAGEAL CAECA. Present.</p>
            <p> PARAPODIA. With one massive, dorsal, sub-spherical gland present from chaetiger 13
                  towards posterior end, becoming larger, reaching maximum size from chaetiger 36 (
                  Fig. 2A, H–I ). Notopodia consisting of dorsal cirrus, dorsal ligule (distal and
                  proximal), and median ligule in biramous parapodia; notopodial prechaetal lobe
                  absent throughout but as notoacicular process in some parapodia. Neuropodia
                  consisting of neuroacicular ligule, ventral ligule, and ventral cirrus; lobes
                  absent throughout. </p>
            <p> DORSAL CIRRI. Cirriform, thick, medium-sized, extending beyond distal region of
                  dorsal ligule throughout ( Fig. 2E, I ); dorsal cirri 3–3.5 times as long as
                  proximal region of dorsal ligule in anteriormost and posteriormost parapodia (
                  Fig. 2E, I ), 2–2.5 times as long as in remaining parapodia ( Fig. 2F–H );
                  attached basally to dorsal ligule in anteriormost parapodia ( Fig. 2E ), medially
                  in following parapodia ( Fig. 2F–I ). </p>
            <p> DORSAL LIGULE. Proximal region even towards posterior end, except faintly humped in
                  middle and posterior parapodia ( Fig. 2H–I ); shorter than distal region of dorsal
                  ligule in anteriormost parapodia ( Fig. 2E ), as long as that in following
                  parapodia ( Fig. 2F–I ); two irregular glandular patches covering partially
                  proximal region of dorsal ligule in anterior parapodia and entirely covering that
                  in following parapodia ( Fig. 2G–I ). Distal region well developed, becoming
                  narrower towards posterior end; digitiform in anteriormost parapodia ( Fig. 2E ),
                  bluntly rounded in anterior parapodia ( Fig. 2F ), conical in following parapodia
                  ( Fig. 2G–I ), slightly smaller than median ligule throughout; projecting beyond
                  notoacicula throughout; one irregular glandular patch covering entire distal
                  region of dorsal ligule ( Fig. 2F–I ). </p>
            <p> NOTOACICULAR PROCESS. Present from parapodia 5 to parapodia 20 ( Fig. 2F–G ), small,
                  blunt. </p>
            <p> MEDIAN LIGULE. Digitiform in anteriormost parapodia, bluntly rounded in anterior
                  parapodia ( Fig. 2F ), conical in following parapodia ( Fig. 2G–I ), becoming
                  narrower from middle parapodia towards posterior end. </p>
            <p> NEUROACICULAR LIGULE. Smaller than ventral ligule in anteriormost parapodia ( Fig.
                  2E ), as long as in following parapodia ( Fig. 2F–I ), 1.5 times as wide as
                  ventral ligule throughout. </p>
            <p> VENTRAL LIGULE. Well developed throughout; bluntly conical, thick in anteriormost
                  and anterior parapodia ( Fig. 2E–F ), conical and slender in following chaetigers;
                  smaller than median ligule throughout; as long as distal region of dorsal ligule
                  in parapodia 1 and 2 ( Fig. 2E ). </p>
            <p> VENTRAL CIRRI. Cirriform, slender; two-quarters as long as ventral ligule in
                  anteriormost and anterior parapodia ( Fig. 2E–F ), half as long as in following
                  chaetigers ( Fig. 2G–I ). </p>
            <p> ACICULAE. Reddish, with basal end uncoloured. Notoaciculae absent in first two
                  chaetigers ( Fig. 2E ). Neuroaciculae extending slightly beyond distal end of
                  notoaciculae throughout, with proximal half 1.4– 1.7 times as wide as
                  notoaciculae. </p>
            <p>NOTOCHAETAE. All homogomph spinigers; 8–9 spinigers present in anterior parapodia,
                  6–7 spinigers in middle parapodia, 4–5 spinigers in posterior parapodia and 2
                  spinigers in posteriormost parapodia.</p>
            <p> SUPRACICULAR NEUROCHAETAE. Consisting of homogomph spinigers ( Fig. 2J–K ),
                  heterogomph spinigers ( Fig. 2J ) and heterogomph falcigers ( Fig. 2L ). Homogomph
                  spinigers present throughout; 1 spiniger present in anteriormost parapodia, 2–4
                  spinigers in anterior and middle parapodia, 3–4 spinigers in posterior parapodia,
                  2 spinigers in posteriormost parapodia. Heterogomph spinigers present in first
                  seven parapodia, with 3 spinigers. Heterogomph falcigers present from parapodia 8
                  to end of body; 2 falcigers present in anterior parapodia, 1–2 falcigers in middle
                  parapodia, 2 falcigers in posterior parapodia, 1 falciger in posteriormost
                  parapodia. </p>
            <p> SUBACICULAR NEUROCHAETAE. Consisting of heterogomph spinigers ( Fig. 2J ) and
                  heterogomph falcigers ( Fig. 2M ). Heterogomph spinigers present throughout; 4–5
                  spinigers present in anteriormost and anterior parapodia, 1–2 spinigers in middle
                  parapodia, 1 spiniger in posterior and posteriormost parapodia. Heterogomph
                  falcigers present from parapodia 5 (5–6) to end of body, with 4–5 falcigers in
                  parapodia throughout. </p>
            <p> Fig. 2. <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes galetae Fauchald, 1977 </tp:taxon-name> . A–B, E–M
                  . Holotype (USNM 53088) from Galeta Reef, Panama, atokous. C–D . Paratype (USNM
                  53089) from Galeta Reef, Panama, atokous. A . Entire body in dorsal view. B .
                  Anterior end in dorsal view. C . Non-everted pharynx in ventral view, black arrow
                  indicates merged paragnaths. D . Right jaw in dorsal view, white arrow indicates
                  canals. E . Right parapodium from chaetiger 2 in anterior view. F . Right
                  parapodium from chaetiger 8 in anterior view. G . Right parapodium from chaetiger
                  16 in anterior view. H . Right parapodium from chaetiger 33 in anterior view. I .
                  Right parapodium from chaetiger 47 in anterior view. J . Supracicular (Sp) and
                  subacicular (Sb) neurochaetae (chaetiger 1). K . Homogomph spiniger from
                  supracicular neurochaetae (chaetiger 47). L . Heterogomph falciger from
                  supracicular neurochaetae (chaetiger 47). M . Heterogomph falciger from
                  subacicular neurochaetae (chaetiger 47). Roman numerals refer to the areas and
                  Arabic numbers to chaetigers. Scale bars: A = 0.5 mm; B = 0.2 mm; C–I = 0.1 mm; J
                  = 20 µm; K–M = 10 µm. </p>
            <p> BLADES. Both homogomph ( Fig. 2J–K ) and heterogomph ( Fig. 2J ) spinigers with
                  blades of medium and long size ( B/A ratio 3.8–9.1), finely serrated towards
                  toothed edge, evenly spaced in anteriormost and anterior parapodia, coarse
                  proximal teeth and notoriously separated in following parapodia ( Fig. 2K ).
                  Blades of heterogomph falcigers in anterior parapodia slender, convex, medium size
                  ( B/A ratio 1.3–1.7), terminal tooth blunt with inconspicuous tendon, serrations
                  present in about half to one-third (0.35–0.46) of total blade length; blades in
                  following parapodia thicker, convex, short ( B/A ratio 0.9–1.1), terminal tooth
                  incurved with distinct tendon, serrations present in about one-quarter to
                  one-third (0.25–0.34) of total blade length ( Fig. 2L–M ). Shaft of supracicular
                  falcigers thicker than subacicular ones in posterior parapodia; camerated, with
                  cavity divided sub-distally into two longitudinal partitions. </p>
            <p>PYGIDIUM. Distinctly projected, bluntly conical, as long as wide, with anal cirri as
                  long as last 4 (3–6) chaetigers; cirrophores of anal cirri barely developed.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Among all the currently known species of <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes </tp:taxon-name> ,
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. galetae </tp:taxon-name> from Galeta Island, Panama ,
                  resembles <tp:taxon-name> N. dawydovi (Fauvel, 1937) </tp:taxon-name> from Vietnam
                  , <tp:taxon-name> N. egregicirrata (Treadwell, 1924) </tp:taxon-name> from Antigua
                  in Lesser Antilles, <tp:taxon-name> N. hondoensis Khlebovich, 1996
                  </tp:taxon-name> from Japan , <tp:taxon-name> N. maculata Wu, Sun &amp; Yang, 1981
                  </tp:taxon-name> from China , <tp:taxon-name> N. mexicana Fauchald, 1972
                  </tp:taxon-name> from the Mexican Pacific, <tp:taxon-name> N. papillosa (Day,
                        1963) </tp:taxon-name> from South Africa , and <tp:taxon-name> N.
                        vandersandei (Horst, 1924) </tp:taxon-name> from Indonesia . These eight
                  species share proximal region of the dorsal ligules of similar size across the
                  body (or slightly enlarged in posterior parapodia), absence of notopodial
                  prechaetal, neuropodial postchaetal and superior lobes and subacicular homogomph
                  spinigers, areas VII–VIII with one well-defined band of fewer than 20 paragnaths,
                  area III with less than 20 paragnaths, and the area I with no more than two
                  paragnaths (see Villalobos-Guerrero &amp; Idris 2021 : table 2). Additionally,
                  they are all similar as they possess a pear-shaped prostomium and ovoid
                  palpophores. </p>
            <p> Nonetheless, <tp:taxon-name> N. galetae </tp:taxon-name> is easily distinguishable
                  from them all by the following diagnostic features: (I) rounded patch of 9–11
                  paragnaths on area VI, in contrast to transverse row of up to four paragnaths in
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. dawydovi </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> N.
                        egregicirrata </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> N. maculata
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> N. papillosa </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. vandersandei </tp:taxon-name> , one paragnath in
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. mexicana </tp:taxon-name> , and none in <tp:taxon-name>
                        N. hondoensis </tp:taxon-name> ; (II) the paired eyes of similar size, in
                  contrast to the anterior pair markedly larger than the posterior pair in
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. mexicana </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> N.
                        papillosa </tp:taxon-name> ; (III) the ventral ligule welldeveloped
                  throughout, in contrast to that markedly reduced in posterior parapodia of
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. dawydovi </tp:taxon-name> ; (IV) the dorsum of all
                  segments with transverse pigmentations, in comparison to its absence in chaetiger
                  2 in <tp:taxon-name> N. dawydovi </tp:taxon-name> ; and (V) dorsal cirri with
                  regular size, in contrast to it being markedly elongated on parapodia 6 in
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. egregicirrata </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
            <p> Likewise, <tp:taxon-name> N. galetae </tp:taxon-name> can also be differentiated
                  from <tp:taxon-name> N. vandersandei </tp:taxon-name> in the following features
                  based on its recent redescription ( Villalobos-Guerrero &amp; Idris 2021 ): (I)
                  the multi-articulated tentacular cirri, in contrast to those smooth in
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. vandersandei </tp:taxon-name> ; (II) the presence of
                  merged paragnaths on area IV, in comparison to its absence in <tp:taxon-name> N.
                        vandersandei </tp:taxon-name> ; (III) the presence of paired oesophageal
                  caeca, in contrast to its absence in <tp:taxon-name> N. vandersandei
                  </tp:taxon-name> ; (IV) the presence of heterogomph spinigers in a few anterior
                  supracicular neurochaetae, in comparison to its absence throughout in
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. vandersandei </tp:taxon-name> ; and (V) the blade of
                  heterogomph falcigers with incurved terminal tooth and distinct tendon in middle
                  and posterior parapodia, in contrast to those with blunt terminal tooth and
                  inconspicuous tendon throughout in <tp:taxon-name> N. vandersandei
                  </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
            <p> The species was described by Fauchald (1977) using eight immature specimens
                  collected from the Panama side of the Caribbean Sea among red algae, although only
                  six of those collected in the <tp:taxon-name> Acanthophora </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> Laurencia </tp:taxon-name> zones correspond to the type
                  series. At present, only four types remain ( holotype and three paratypes ). The
                  type material examined here partially matches the barely-illustrated original
                  description, which was seemingly based on the holotype . <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes
                        galetae </tp:taxon-name> was described with a higher number of paragnaths in
                  the areas of the maxillary ring (I: 2; II: 20; III: 18; IV: 25) when compared with
                  specimens from the type series (I: 0–1; II: 8–14; III: 5–12; IV: 11–17). The
                  dorsal cirri were mentioned as attached basally throughout in the original
                  description, although it is attached medially in the middle and posterior
                  parapodia of the type series. The replacement of homogomph spinigers by
                  heterogomph spinigers in supracicular neurochaetae of posteriormost parapodia
                  stated in the description was not observed in the type material. However, the
                  heterogomph spinigers were observed in a few anteriormost parapodia, which were
                  replaced by heterogomph falcigers in the following parapodia. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes galetae </tp:taxon-name> was not characterised or
                  redescribed previously until this study. The original description includes a
                  short, implicit comparison with four taxa of <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes
                  </tp:taxon-name> in having a few paragnaths on area VII–VIII: <tp:taxon-name>
                        Neanthes agulhana (Day, 1963) </tp:taxon-name> from South Africa ,
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. dawydovi </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> N.
                        kerguelensis (Mclntosh, 1885) </tp:taxon-name> from the Kerguelen Islands,
                  and <tp:taxon-name> N. kerguelensis oligodonta (Augener, 1913) </tp:taxon-name>
                  from Australia . They were distinguished by paragnaths occurring on area I,
                  although variations overlap in the species (see Villalobos-Guerrero &amp; Idris
                  2021 ; this study). The subspecies is not considered valid presently ( Wilson 1984
                  ), and the differences with <tp:taxon-name> N. dawydovi </tp:taxon-name> were
                  mentioned above. <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes galetae </tp:taxon-name> is easily
                  distinguished from both <tp:taxon-name> N. agulhana </tp:taxon-name> and
                        <tp:taxon-name> N. kerguelensis </tp:taxon-name> by the lack of notopodial
                  prechaetal lobe (present in those species) and the rounded patch of 9–11
                  paragnaths on area VI (transverse row of up to 4 paragnaths in <tp:taxon-name> N.
                        agulhana </tp:taxon-name> and 0–1 paragnath in <tp:taxon-name> N.
                        kerguelensis </tp:taxon-name> ). <tp:taxon-name> Neanthes galetae
                  </tp:taxon-name> is also different from <tp:taxon-name> N. kerguelensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> by the lack of neuropodial postchaetal lobe and subacicular
                  homogomph spinigers (both present in <tp:taxon-name> N. kerguelensis
                  </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
            <p> The species has also been recorded from the Pacific part of El Salvador ( Planas et
                  al. 2013 ) and Colombia ( Jaime et al. 1999 ) in ecological studies. However, they
                  are considered doubtful until a re-examination of the voucher material is
                  performed. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Panama : Galeta Island, Colón (Caribbean Sea). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Ecology </p>
            <p> Intertidal among red algae of the genera <tp:taxon-name> Acanthophora J.V.Lamour.
                  </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name> Laurencia J.V.Lamour. </tp:taxon-name> and
                  present among the seagrass <tp:taxon-name> Thalassia Banks ex König
                  </tp:taxon-name> ( Fauchald 1977 ) and <tp:taxon-name> Halodule Endl.
                  </tp:taxon-name> ( Vásquez Montoya &amp; Thomassin 1983 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Reproduction </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
