<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pentastiridius
(
Pentastiridius
) 
leporinus

(
Linnaeus, 1761
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 13A–G
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Cicada leporina
Linnaeus, 1761: 242
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Cixius latifrons
Walker, 1851: 283–284
</tp:taxon-name>

(for discussion of other synonyms see 

Webb 
et al
. 2013

).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>It differs from other European species of the genus in the following characters: (1) the apex of the velum ends in two processes, a ventral tongue-shaped expansion and, exceeding it, a thin, spine-like extension curved downward; (2) on the right, laterobasal to the base of the aedeagus, is a long, thin spine that extends around the theca and almost embraces it; this thorn is slender and the distal third is bent at a right angle.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
MADEIRA ISLANDS
– 

Ponta do Sol

• 
3 ♂♂
; 
Lugar de Baixo
lagoon; 

8 m
a.s.l.

; 

30 May 2004

; 
D. Aguín-Pombo
leg.; 

on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phragmites australis
</tp:taxon-name>

; 
UMACI

• 

6 ♂♂
, 
7 ♀♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 

15 Jun. 2017

; 
DAPC

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>BODY MEASUREMENTS (mm). BL: males 6.56–7.25 (n = 8); females 8.67–9.38 (n = 6).</p>
      <p>COLOURATION. Vertex with a medial rectangular blackish spot; lateral sides of the vertex, pronotum and the areolar and frontal carinal areas, pale yellow; frons, clypeus, gena, and lora black in males, golden brown in females. Mesonotum and femora black in males and lighter in females. Female tegmina milky white, semitransparent; veins and stigmas of pale golden colour, in males they are darker.</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Vertex almost as long as wide in the posterior margin (
Fig. 13A
). Epistomal suture pronounced in a wave form.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Mesonotum with five distinctly ridged carinae; the costal carinae are slightly divergent and reach almost the posterior margin of the mesonotum, being shorter than the medial and intercostal carinae; these two end up subapically at the caudal margin of the mesonotum; the intercostal carinae are shaped as a pair of parentheses and at the base are shorter than the medial and costal carinae (
Fig. 13A
). MALE GENITALIA (see also 

Holzinger 
et al.
2003

). Pygofer lobes concave distally (
Fig. 13C
). The anal tube is oblong dorsally and distally blunt; at the base it is 2 times shorter than caudallly (
Fig. 13F
); lateroventral margins widely concave (
Fig. 13G
). Parameres 2.5 times as long as wide in the widest part; caudally there is a large rounded subtriangular area that narrows basally towards the outer margin; inner lateral margin slightly concave and outer margin straight (
Fig. 13B
). The aedeagus base forms dorsolaterally an almost flat pentagonal plate; from the middle to the distal end of the plate rises dorsolaterally a caudally directed process. Velum is arch-shaped and narrows towards the apex; distally and dorsoventrally, the apex ends in a tongue-shaped process, and dorsally, exceeding this, there is a thin spine that curves down. On the right, laterobasal at the base of the aedeagus, there is a long and thin spine that extends parallel almost embracing it distally; this thorn narrows towards the apex and the distal third bends upward in the form of a sickle (
Fig. 13E
). Dorsally, at the base of the velum, there is a small spine-like process and from here three movable spines are raised, one long and thick and two small and thin; the longest extends parallel to the dorsal margin of the flagellum and reaches approximately half of its length; the shortest spine is almost parallel to the base of the flagellum and bends slightly medially downwards; the last spine is oblique to the velum (
Fig. 13D
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 13.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pentastiridus leporinus
(
Linnaeus, 1761
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Specimens from Lugar de Baixo lagoon, 30 May 2004, on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phragmites australis
Trin. ex Steud. 
A
.
</tp:taxon-name>
Head, pronotum, and scutellum (dorsal view). 
B
. Left paramere. 
C
. Pygofer (left lateral view). 
D–E
. Aedeagus (left and right lateral view). 
F–G
. Anal tube (dorsal and left lateral view).
</p>
      <p>FEMALE GENITALIA. Not described.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution and habitat
</p>
      <p>
The Palearctic region, except in the northern parts. In 
Madeira
, this species is found in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phragmites australis
Trin. ex Steud.
</tp:taxon-name>
in the only tide lagoon of the island, which is located on the southern coast.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The curvature of the long lateroventral spine of the aedeagus is variable at its distal end as is shown in 
Wagner (1970
: fig. 3c).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
