<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Aenigmatoconcha sumonthai Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan 2018</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5528130</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/24131F7B9F41C94F987DCD32245675A2</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the limestone karst-restricted land snail genus Aenigmatoconcha (Eupulmonata: Helicarionidae), with description of a new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.767.1487</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha sumonthai
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2018
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1
, 
2C–E
, 
7A–D
, 
8
, 
10C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha sumonthai
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2018: 171–173
</tp:taxon-name>
, figs 2–6. 
Type
locality: Tham Chang Phueak limestone range, Mueang District, 
Chumphon Province
, southern 
Thailand
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
THAILAND
• 
45 sh
, 
20 sp
; 
Chumphon Province
, 
Mueang District
, 
Limestone outcrops at Tham Chang Phuek Bureau of Monks
; 
10°26′50.0″ N
, 
99°02′07.1″ E
; 
CUMZ 7922

• 

40 sh
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CUMZ 7923

• 

18 sh
, 
10 sp
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CUMZ 7937

• 

45 sh
, 
6 sp
; 
Chumphon Province
, 
Mueang District
, 
Limestone outcrops at Wat Tham Sanook
; 
10°28′51.3″ N
, 
99°04′28.3″ E
; 
CUMZ 7924

• 

10 sh
, 
7 sp
; same collection data as for preceding; 
CUMZ 7925

• 

22 sh
, 
11 sp
; 
Chumphon Province
, 
Sawi District
, 
Limestone outcrops at Tham Nam Lod Thepnimit Bureau of Monks
; 
10°22′39.5″ N
, 
99°00′39.5″ E
; 
CUMZ 7927

• 

4 sh
, 
8 sp
; 
Chumphon Province
, 
Sawi District
, 
Limestone outcrops at Wat Nam Cha
; 
10°17′57.0″ N
, 
99°01′58.5″ E
; 
CUMZ 7926

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
SHELL (
Fig. 7A–B
). Shell strongly depressed to depressed, medium-sized (width 
14.4–16.6 mm
, height 7.0– 
8.2 mm
), thin, translucent, whitish colour, well-rounded to slightly shouldered body whorl, elevated spire, impressed suture, obvious varix, and open umbilicus.
</p>
      <p>
EXTERNAL FEATURES (
Fig. 2C–E
). Animal with five well-developed mantle lobes. Left and right shell lobes pale yellowish to fleshy-grey colour, usually with black margin, and with or without small to large black spots or blotches. Three dorsal lobes crescent-shaped and smaller than the other two shell lobes. Black stripes behind long tentacles.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
Fig. 8
). Atrium (at) enlarged and very short. Penis (p) long, cylindrical with thick penial sheath (ps) extending to half of penis length. Inner sculpture of penis with small conical penial pilasters (pp). Epiphallus (e1 + e2) as long as penis: e1 slender, and e2 bulbous. Inner sculpture of e1 with small thin longitudinal folds, while e2 with small papillae arranged in oblique rows. Epiphallic caecum (ec) short with thin penial retractor muscle (prm) attached at tip. Flagellum (fl) small and short.
</p>
      <p>
RADULA (
Fig. 10C
). Teeth arranged in anteriorly V-shaped rows with half row consisting of about 63– 65 teeth at the middle plate. All teeth monocuspid and spatulate-shaped with curved cusp.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 7.
Shells of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha
spp. 
A
</tp:taxon-name>
–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sumonthai
Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2018
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–B
. Specimen CUMZ 7922 from the type locality. 
C–D
. Specimen CUMZ 7937 from the type locality showing the calcareous epiphragm with a small perforation (white arrows). Only shell (C) and living (D) specimens in both lateral and ventral views. 
E–F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. eunetis
Pholyotha &amp; Panha
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
E
. Holotype CUMZ 7931. 
F
. Paratype CUMZ 7933 from Uthai Thani Province.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha sumonthai
</tp:taxon-name>
has a narrow distribution, with populations living on a few limestone hills in 
Chumphon Province
(
Fig. 1
). We extended our survey, especially among limestone sites about 
200 km
southwards down to southern peninsular 
Thailand
, but we could not find this species elsewhere.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The lack of a penial sheath and flagellum in the male reproductive organs of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sumonthai
</tp:taxon-name>
was originally reported to be similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. clivicola
</tp:taxon-name>
(Tumpeesuwan &amp; Tumpeesuwan, 2018: 174, fig. 6). In this study, based on topotypic specimens, however, 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sumonthai
</tp:taxon-name>
was found to have a large and thickened penial sheath and small flagellum encircled with loose tissue (
Fig. 8
).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aenigmatoconcha sumonthai
</tp:taxon-name>
shows variation in the black blotches on both shell lobes ranging from absent (
Fig. 2E
) to the lobes almost entirely covered (
Fig. 2C
). The DNA sequence analysis suggested that these variations formed a clade of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. sumonthai
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 2
). In addition, this species develops a calcareous epiphragm with a small perforation to limit body-water evaporation but allowing respiratory gas exchange during dormancy (
Fig. 7C, D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
