<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio brevicephalus
(
Risbec, 1956
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 7–8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon brevicephala
Risbec, 1956: 371
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 3 (
holotype
, 
Ƌ
, MNHN).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio brevicephalus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Masner 1976: 72

(transferred from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Syntypes

(images only) 
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 ♂
; 
Bekily
; 

Mar. 1930

; 
A. Seyrig
leg.; 
MNHN EY25669

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding but 

Feb. 1940

; 
MNHN EY25670

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>BODY LENGTH. 5.05 (4.4 –5.7) mm.</p>
      <p>
COLOUR (
Figs 7
, 
8A–E
). Body predominantly black, tegula brown, legs and mandibles reddish brown; radicle brown, remaining antennomeres dark brown.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 7
, 
8A, C–E
). 1.38 × as wide as high, 2.1× as high as long; IOS 0.64 × head width, 1.35 × eye length; OOL&gt;POL&gt; LOL in ratio of 33.0: 24.0: 13.0; OOL 3.4× OD; eye (L:W = 65.1: 40.2) setose; frons with oblique carinae, some dorsal carinae converge medially into a smooth area; space between carinae smooth with setigerous punctae; frons above interantennal process with semicircular carinae; vertex with uneven sized depressions; ocelli not raised above surface of vertex; sparse transverse carinae present between posterior ocellus and orbit; interocellar area with setigerous foveae; occiput with transverse carinae, space between carinae with setigerous punctae; occipital carina not foveate; upper gena with longitudinal carinae, remainder smooth; entire gena with setigerous punctae.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio brevicephalus
(
Risbec, 1956
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Syntype, ♂ (MNHN EY25669). 
A
. Habitus (dorsal view). 
B
. Habitus, (lateral view). Photos: Agnièle Touret-Alby 
©
, MNHN.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio brevicephalus
(
Risbec, 1956
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Syntypes, ♂♂ (A–C: MNHN EY25669; D–E: MNHN EY25670). 
A
. Head and pleuron. 
B
. Metasoma. 
C
. Head and mesonotum. 
D
. Head and lateral pronotal area. 
E
. Frons. 
F
. Type label. Photos: Agnièle Touret-Alby 
©
, MNHN.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA (
Figs 7
, 
8A, C–D
). Cervical pronotal area transversely carinate; mesoscutum (L:W = 94.0: 130.4) anteriorly areolate, with long setae, remainder longitudinally carinate, space between them setigerous foveate; pronotal cervical sulcus foveate, remainder of lateral pronotal area smooth except for a narrow patch of rugose sculpture above pronotal cervical sulcus; netrion foveate; dorsal mesopleuron without a rectangular, transversely carinate patch beneath tegula; mesopleural pit distinct; speculum transversely carinate, space between carinae smooth; mesepimeral sulcus foveate anteriorly; several transverse carinae present on femoral depression ventral to mesopleural pit, some of which extend ¾ width of mesopleuron; episternum foveate and ventral mesopleuron setigerous punctate, setae sparse; metapleuron anteriorly foveate, densely setose, posteriorly with large depressions without setae; scutoscutellar sulcus foveate laterally; mesoscutellum (L:W = 47.7: 93.2) areolate with several setigerous punctae; median keel present; metascutellum predominantly smooth, posteromedially with a triangular spine, metanotal trough foveate; lateral propodeal area laterally densely setose, remainder smooth with small foveae between longitudinal carinae; lateral propodeal area anterolaterally with a short spine; posterolateral margin of lateral propodeal area extending as a blunt in-curved spine. Fore wing (L: W = 347.1:120.7) and hind wing (L:W = 286.7: 60.3) weakly infuscate.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA (
Figs 7
, 
8B
). L:W = 256.6: 160.5; T1 longitudinally costate, space between costae foveate; T2 with basal foveae, remainder longitudinally costate, space between costae smooth with sparse punctae; T3 medially longitudinally costate on anterior half, posterior half smooth with setigerous punctae; remaining tergites smooth with setigerous punctae; T1 and T2 laterally sparsely setose; T3–T6 laterally with dense short setae; length and width of tergites T1–T 
7 in
ratio of 42.1: 42.1, 69.7.3: 60.5, 80.3: 155.3, 33.5: 155.3, 14.8: 101.9, 7.5:55.6, 5.6: 24.1, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
