<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Odontoscelio apperti</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4615116</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5EA5228B0BA67A4A9BE60F37758DE978</uri>
         <article-title>Review of Odontoscelio Kieffer, 1905 (Platygastroidea, Scelionidae) with the description of two new species from India</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1267</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio apperti
(
Risbec, 1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 5–6
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Dichoteleas Apperti
</tp:taxon-name>
[sic] 

Risbec, 1953: 569

, fig. 5 (
holotype
, 
♀
, MNHN).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio apperti
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Masner 1976: 72

(transferred from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dichoteleas
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype

(images only) 
SENEGAL
• 
♀
; 
Bambey
[M’Bambey]; 
J. Appert
leg.; 
MNHN EY25668
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
BODY LENGTH. 
5.8 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR (
Figs 5
, 
6A–D
). Body predominantly black; tegula, interantennal process, legs and apical ends of spines brown; A1 reddish brown, A2–A4 yellowish brown, remaining antennomeres blackish brown. HEAD (
Figs 5
, 
6A, C–D
). Head setose, 1.16 × as wide as high, 1.9 × as high as long; IOS 0.80 × head width, subequal to eye length; OOL&gt;POL&gt;LOL in ratio of 27: 24: 12; OOL 3.3× OD; eye (L:W = 78:39) setose; frons entirely smooth with setigerous punctae except for sparse longitudinal carinae laterally towards orbits; vertex, interocellar area and occiput smooth with sparse setigerous punctae; ocelli raised above surface of vertex; occipital carina foveate; setae dense on temples; gena with longitudinal striae interspersed with setigerous punctae; length and width of antennomeres A1–A 
12 in
ratio of 97.7: 11.6, 15.6: 9.3, 43.0: 11.6, 19.5:11.6, 7.0:11.6, 8.1: 12.8, 10.5: 16.3, 11.6: 17.4, 11.6: 16.3, 10.5: 16.3, 10.5: 15.1, 15.1: 12.8, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio apperti
(
Risbec, 1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Holotype, ♀ (MNHN EY25668). 
A
. Habitus (dorsal view). 
B
. Habitus (lateral view). Photos: Agnièle Touret-Alby 
©
, MNHN.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio apperti
(
Risbec, 1953
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Holotype, ♀ (MNHN EY25668). 
A
. Head and pleuron. 
B
. Metasoma. 
C
. Head and mesoscutum. 
D
. Frons, vertex and antennae. 
E
. Type label. Photos: Agnièle Touret-Alby 
©
, MNHN.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA (
Figs 5
, 
6A, C
). Cervical pronotal area transversely carinate; mesoscutum (L:W = 98.7: 122.7) anteromedially areolate, remainder longitudinally carinate, space between carinae smooth with setigerous foveae; pronotal shoulders with a wide spine, visible when viewed dorsally in addition to a spine above tegula; pronotal cervical sulcus foveate; lateral pronotal area dorsally foveate and setose, anteriorly smooth and posteriorly with intricate sculpture; netrion with large foveae; dorsal mesopleuron with a rectangular, transversely carinate patch beneath tegula; mesopleural pit distinct; speculum transversely carinate; mesepimeral sulcus not foveate; femoral depression with several transverse carinae, some of which extend the entire width; anterior episternum and ventral mesopleuron densely setose, obscuring sculpture; metapleuron anteriorly foveate, densely setose, posteriorly with large depressions; posterior margin of metapleuron with a wide spine; scutoscutellar sulcus foveate; mesoscutellum (L: W = 36.0:93.3) areolate with setigerous punctae; median keel absent; metascutellum smooth, posteromedially with a wide spine, metanotal trough foveate; lateral propodeal area densely setose laterally, remainder longitudinally carinate, space between carinae smooth; anterolateral margin of lateral propodeal area with a spine and posterolateral margin of lateral propodeal area extending as a blunt spine. Fore wing (L:W = 329.5: 95.5) and hind wing (L:W = 279.5: 61.4) weakly infuscate.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA (
Figs 5
, 
6B
). L: W = 286.0: 146.0; T1 longitudinally costate, space between costae predominantly smooth; T2 entirely longitudinally costate with shorter costae in between them on posterior half, except for a smooth patch laterally with setigerous punctae; T3 longitudinally costate on anterior half with foveae between costae, smooth on posterior half, laterally smooth with sparse setigerous punctae; T4 medially smooth with setigerous punctae, posteriorly smooth, remainder areolate, setose; T5 areolate, setose except for smooth posterior margin; T6 anteromedially punctate, with two densely setose, large lateral teeth and a median lobe; T1 and T2 with sparse lateral setae, T3–T5 with dense setae posterolaterally; length and width of tergites T1–T 
6 in
ratio of 46.0:42.0, 68.0: 56.0, 92.0: 136.0, 42.0: 134.0, 20.0:88.0, 20.0: 42.0, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
