<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Odontoscelio caelebs</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4610796</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D97B170E6ACD02DE6A4E1852718944B7</uri>
         <article-title>Review of Odontoscelio Kieffer, 1905 (Platygastroidea, Scelionidae) with the description of two new species from India</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1267</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio caelebs
(
Nixon, 1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 9–10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon caelebs
Nixon, 1936: 189
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 18 (
holotype
, 
♀
, NHMUK).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon caelebs
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Masner 1965: 99

(
type
information).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio caelebs
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Masner 1976: 72

(generic transfer from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype

(images only) 
MALAWI
• 
♀
; 
Mangochi
[labelled: Fort Johnston, Nyasaland]; 

Feb. 1922

; 
Dr W.A. Lamborn
leg.; 
taken crawling on sand
; 
NHMUK 013379412
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>BODY LENGTH. 7.0 mm.</p>
      <p>
COLOUR (
Figs 9
, 
10A–E
). Body black, tegula, interantennal process, mandibles and legs brownish black; radicle brown, A1 black, A2–A4 brownish black.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 9
, 
10A, D–E
). Head 1.32 × as wide as high, 1.45 × as high as long; IOS 0.60 × head width, 1.3× eye length; OOL&gt;POL&gt;LOL in ratio of 35.4:18.9: 10.4; OOL 3.9× OD; eye (L: W = 75.9:48.0) setose; dorsal frons areolate with setigerous punctae, with semicircular carinae above interantennal process, smooth medially, remainder with oblique carinae radiating towards centre interspersed with setigerous punctae; interantennal process foveate, setose; vertex areolate with setigerous punctae, interocellar area predominantly smooth; ocelli not raised above surface of vertex; occiput carinate; occipital carina foveate; gena longitudinally carinate, interspersed with setigerous punctae; length and width of antennomeres A1–A 
4 in
ratio of 98.0: 14.7, 14.7: 9.8, 46.1: 14.7, 16.7: 14.7, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA (
Figs 9
, 
10A, C
). Cervical pronotal area transversely carinate; mesoscutum (L:W = 114.0:132.8) anteriorly areolate interspersed with setigerous punctae, remainder with longitudinal carinae, space between carinae with setigerous foveae; pronotal shoulders with a wide spine, visible when viewed dorsally; lateral pronotal area dorsally areolate, setose, posteroventrally weakly transversely striate, remainder smooth; pronotal cervical sulcus foveate; netrion foveate; dorsal mesopleuron without a rectangular, transversely carinate patch beneath tegula; mesopleural pit distinct; speculum transversely carinate; mesepimeral sulcus not foveate; femoral depression transversely carinate; anterior episternum foveate, setose; postacetabular sulcus transversely carinate; ventral mesopleuron foveate, densely setose; metapleuron anteriorly densely setose, posteriorly with large depressions; scutoscutellar sulcus foveate laterally; mesoscutellum (L: W = 51.5: 117.1) areolate, median keel present; metascutellum foveate, posteromedially with a triangular spine, metanotal trough foveate; lateral propodeal area laterally densely setose, remainder longitudinally carinate, space between carinae smooth; posterolateral margin of lateral propodeal area extending posteriorly as a blunt, in-curved spine. Fore wing (L:W = 304.3: 102.1) and hind wing (L:W = 271.7: 71.7) weakly infuscate.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio caelebs
(
Nixon, 1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Holotype, ♀ (NHMUK 013379412). 
A
. Habitus (dorsal view). 
B
. Habitus (lateral view). Photos: D.G. Notton 
©
, NHMUK.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA (
Figs 9
, 
10B
). (L: W = 356.7: 188.7); T1 predominantly longitudinally costate, space between costae smooth; T2 with basal foveae, remainder longitudinally costate, space between costae with carinae posteriorly; T3 longitudinally costate, space between costae foveate, with short setae; T3 with a row of setigerous punctae on posterior margin, followed by a smooth patch; T4 medially smooth with sparse setigerous punctae, remainder with large depressions with setae; T5 setigerous punctate; T6 with two large teeth laterally and a median lobe, both densely setose; T1 and T2 sparsely setose laterally, T3 laterally punctate with a mix of dense short and long setae, T4 with dense setae laterally; length and width of tergites T1–T 
6 in
ratio of 54.2: 52.3, 81.3:63.6, 112.1: 168.2, 57.9: 172.0, 20.6: 112.1, 20.6: 56.1, respectively.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
