<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Odontoscelio striatifrons Kieffer
                        1905</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4610814</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E0893A1637D4046B16FA76FC297F8A</uri>
                  <article-title>Review of Odontoscelio Kieffer, 1905 (Platygastroidea, Scelionidae)
                        with the description of two new species from India</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1267</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Odontoscelio striatifrons Kieffer, 1905 </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 17–18 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Odontoscelio striatifrons Kieffer, 1905: 14 </tp:taxon-name> (
                  holotype , ♂, MCSN). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Odontoscelio striatifrons </tp:taxon-name> – Kieffer 1926: 350
                  (description). — Bin 1974: 457 ( type information). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> Holotype (images only) GUINEA BISSAU • 1 ♂ ; Bolama
                        [labelled: Bolama, Portuguese Guinea]; Jun.–Dec.1899 ; L. Fea leg.; MCSN .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Redescription </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> BODY LENGTH. 5.7 mm . </p>
            <p> COLOUR ( Figs 17 , 18A–E ). Body black; tegula and mandibles brown; coxa black and
                  remainder of leg brown; radicle brown, remaining antennomeres dark brown. </p>
            <p> HEAD ( Figs 17 , 18A, C–D ). Head 1.19 × as wide as high, 1.9 × as high as long; IOS
                  0.61 × head width, 1.23× eye length; OOL&gt;POL in ratio of 29.4: 22.0 (LOL not
                  visible in the image); OOL 3.34 × OD; eye (L: W = 68.1: 40.2) setose; frons with
                  oblique carinae directed towards anterior ocellus; space between carinae smooth
                  with long brown setae; vertex and interocellar area smooth with sparse setigerous
                  punctae; interantennal process rectangular, smooth with a medial longitudinal
                  carina; occiput entirely smooth with sparse setigerous punctae, except for a small
                  patch of dense setigerous foveae medially; gena longitudinally carinate with
                  setigerous punctae; ocelli raised above surface of vertex; antennomeres not
                  clearly visible. </p>
            <p> MESOSOMA ( Figs 17 , 18A, C ). Cervical pronotal area transversely carinate;
                  mesoscutum (L:W = 104.4:127.9) laterally smooth with setigerous punctae,
                  anteromedial ¾ areolate, remaining ¼ smooth with sparse longitudinal carinae;
                  adjoining this medial patch, longitudinal carinae extend for almost entire length
                  of mesoscutum; mesoscutum laterally smooth with sparse areolae and setigerous
                  punctae; pronotal shoulders with a blunt spine visible when viewed dorsally;
                  lateral pronotal area anteriorly foveate; posteroventral margin of lateral
                  pronotal area extending as a blunt spine; netrion foveate; dorsal mesopleuron with
                  a small triangular rugose patch beneath tegula; mesopleural pit distinct; speculum
                  with weak transverse carinae; mesepimeral sulcus not foveate; posteroventral
                  femoral depression with transverse carinae; episternum and ventral mesopleuron
                  densely setose, obscuring sculpture; metapleuron anteriorly and ventrally densely
                  setose, remainder with large depressions; scutoscutellar sulcus laterally with
                  large foveae; mesoscutellum (L:W = 36.7: 88.2) areolate; a median keel present;
                  metascutellum foveate and posteromedially with a triangular spine, metanotal
                  trough foveate; lateral propodeal area laterally densely setose, remainder smooth,
                  except for foveae present along posterior margin; lateral propodeal area extending
                  posterolaterally as a blunt straight spine. Fore wing (L:W = 142: 45) and hind
                  wing (L: W = 122:30) weakly infuscate. </p>
            <p> Fig. 17. <tp:taxon-name> Odontoscelio striatifrons Kieffer, 1905 </tp:taxon-name> .
                  Holotype, ♂ (MCSN). A . Habitus, dorsal view. B . Habitus, lateral view. Photos:
                  N.F. Johnson © , Ohio State University. </p>
            <p> Fig. 18. <tp:taxon-name> Odontoscelio striatifrons Kieffer, 1905 </tp:taxon-name> .
                  Holotype, ♂ (MCSN). A . Head and pleuron. B . Metasoma. C . Head and mesonotum. D
                  . Frons. E . Type label. Photos: A–D: N.F. Johnson © , Ohio State University; E:
                  Roberto Poggi © , MCSN. </p>
            <p> METASOMA ( Figs 17 , 18B ). L:W = 251.2: 140.3; T1 longitudinally costate, space
                  between costae weakly foveate; T2 with basal foveae, remainder longitudinally
                  costate, space between costae smooth; T3 longitudinally costate on anterior 4 /5,
                  sublaterally areolate, and laterally, posteromedially and posteriorly smooth;
                  space between costae with small foveae medially; T4 medially smooth, setose,
                  remainder with setigerous foveae; T5 and T6 predominantly with setigerous foveae;
                  T7 setose; T1 and T2 with sparse long setae laterally, T3–T6 densely setose
                  laterally; length and width of tergites T1–T 7 in ratio of 46.3: 37.8, 62.2: 51.2,
                  72.0: 115.8, 37.8:136.5, 19.5: 101.2, 11.0: 60.9, 73.2:36.5, respectively. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Kieffer erroneously referred to the holotype as a female specimen in his type
                  information, although later in the description of the genus he stated that females
                  are unknown. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
