<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Odontoscelio laticephalus</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4610808</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/12A0A403F2DFF658B7D714AFE9449FF4</uri>
         <article-title>Review of Odontoscelio Kieffer, 1905 (Platygastroidea, Scelionidae) with the description of two new species from India</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1267</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio laticephalus
(
Risbec, 1950
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 13–14
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hoplogryon laticephalus
Risbec, 1950: 581
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 59 (
holotype
, ♂, MNHN).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio laticephalus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Masner 1976: 72

(transfer from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hoplogryon
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Syntypes

(images only) 
CHAD
• 
4 ♂♂
; 
N’Djamena
[labelled: Mandjaffa], 
banks of Lower Chari River
; 

Jul. 1904

; 
Dr J. Decorse
leg.; 
Chari-Chad
mission; 
MNHN EY25672 to EY25675
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
BODY LENGTH. 
3.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR (
Figs 13
, 
14A–D
). Body predominantly black, tegula brown, interantennal process yellowish brown; radicle and basal A1 yellowish brown, apical ¾ of A1 brown, remaining antennomeres dark brown; coxae brown, remainder of leg yellowish brown; anterior T1 brown.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 13
, 
14A, C–D
). Head 1.19 × as wide as high, 2.0 × as high as long; IOS 0.68 × head width, 1.45× eye length; OOL&gt;POL&gt;LOL in ratio of 17.4: 16.8: 9.00; OOL 2.8 × OD; eye (L:W = 39.6:23.6) setose; frons medially from interantennal process to anterior ocellus smooth without setae, remainder with oblique carinae directed inwards; space between carinae smooth with long setigerous punctae; a short longitudinal carina present beneath anterior ocellus; all three ocelli connected by carinae; ocelli raised above surface of vertex; vertex and interocellar area predominantly smooth; occiput and gena longitudinally carinate, space between carinae with setigerous punctae; occipital carina weakly foveate; length and width of antennomeres A1–A 
11 in
ratio of 36.7: 7.8, 6.7: 6.1, 33.3: 7.8, 26.7: 7.8, 20.0: 7.2, 23.3: 6.7, 26.7:7.2, 27.8: 7.8, 27.8: 5.6, 26.7: 5.6, 26.7: 5.6, respectively; setae on antennomeres sparse.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA (
Figs 13A–C
, 
14A, C
). Cervical pronotal area transversely carinate; mesoscutum (L:W = 48.2: 81.4) anteriorly areolate, remainder longitudinally carinate and space between carinae unevenly smooth with setigerous foveae; pronotal shoulders without a lateral wide spine; lateral pronotal area predominantly smooth, except for a dense setose patch posteriorly; pronotal suprahumeral sulcus and pronotal cervical sulcus foveate; netrion not distinct; dorsal mesopleuron with a rectangular, weakly transversely carinate patch beneath tegula; mesopleural pit distinct; speculum transversely carinate; mesepimeral sulcus not foveate; femoral depression medially smooth, with several short transverse carinae posteroventrally; episternal foveae present; anterior episternum and ventral mesopleuron entirely with setigerous foveae; metapleuron anteroventrally densely setose, metapleural sulcus foveate, remainder with intricate sculpture; scutoscutellar sulcus foveate laterally; mesoscutellum (L: W = 27.3:59.2) predominantly areolate except for a smooth patch anteromedially; median keel distinct posteriorly; metascutellum foveate with posteromedially triangular spine, metanotal trough foveate; lateral propodeal area setose, with indistinct foveae; propodeum anterolaterally with a large blunt spine; posterolateral margin of lateral propodeal area extending posteriorly as a blunt spine. Fore wing (L:W = 212.4:72.5) and hind wing (L: W = 180.8: 31.5) weakly infuscate.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA (
Figs 13A–C
, 
14B
). L:W = 140.2: 86.2; T1 longitudinally costate, space between costae weakly foveate; T2 with basal foveae, remainder longitudinally costate, space between them with short costae posteriorly; T3 medially densely foveate, remainder longitudinally carinate (with foveae between carinae) except for a smooth posterior margin; T4 and T5 with setigerous punctae, with smooth posterior margins; T1 and T2 with sparse long setae laterally, T3–T6 with dense setae laterally; T6 and T7 smooth, with sparse setae; length and width of tergites T1–T 
7 in
ratio of 26.4:253, 34.5: 35.6, 57.5: 82.8, 18.4: 80.5, 6.9: 57.5, 5.0: 36.8, 2.3: 18.4, respectively.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
