<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Odontoscelio echion</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4610802</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E0893A163FD40A6B63FDD7FE217F84</uri>
         <article-title>Review of Odontoscelio Kieffer, 1905 (Platygastroidea, Scelionidae) with the description of two new species from India</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.739.1267</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio echion
(
Nixon, 1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 11–12
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon echion
Nixon, 1936: 190
</tp:taxon-name>

(
holotype
, ♂, NHMUK).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon echion
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Masner 1965: 99

(
type
information).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio echion
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Masner 1976: 72

(transfer from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon
</tp:taxon-name>
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Syntype

(images only) 
SOUTH AFRICA
• 
1 ♂
; 
Eastern Cape Province
, 
Wild Coast
, 
Pondoland
, 
Port St. John
; 

Dec. 1923

; 
R.E. Turner
leg.; 
NHMUK 013379413
[5 other syntype ♂♂ with the same collection data not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
BODY LENGTH. 
5.4 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
COLOUR (
Figs 11
, 
12A–D, F
). Body black; tegula and mandibles brown; interantennal process dark brown; radicle brown, A2 a shade darker than radicle, remaining antennomeres dark brown; legs in shades of brown; anterior T1 reddish brown.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 11
, 
12A, C–D, F
). Head 1.15 × as wide as high, 1.65 × as high as long; IOS 0.66 × head width, 1.84 × eye length; OOL&gt;POL&gt;LOL in ratio of 30.8: 16.8: 8.0; OOL 3.3× OD; eye (L: W = 44.5:34.2) setose; frons with oblique carinae extending towards centre; carinae in upper and lower frons do not converge medially; carinae present in medial frons, converge medially and are further connected with each other by a longitudinal carina; space between carinae smooth with long brown setae; interantennal process weakly foveate; vertex, interocellar area and occiput with setigerous punctae; occipital carina weakly foveate; ocelli not raised above surface of vertex; gena longitudinally carinate with setigerous punctae; length and width of antennomeres A1–A 
11 in
ratio of 56.3: 14.6, 8.3: 8.3, 52.1: 12.5, 37.5: 13.5, 33.3: 12.5, 41.7: 14.6, 43.8:14.6, 47.9: 13.5, 47.9: 13.5, 50.0: 13.5, 45.8: 13.5, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA (
Figs 11
, 
12A, C
). Mesoscutum (L:W = 68.7: 114.2) with longitudinal carinae, space between carinae smooth, with setigerous punctae and sparse weak foveae; pronotal shoulders without a spine laterally; lateral pronotal area dorsally foveate and setose, medially smooth; pronotal cervical sulcus weakly foveate, with additional sparse foveae anteriorly; netrion not distinct; dorsal mesopleuron with a triangular, transversely carinate patch beneath tegula; mesopleural pit distinct; speculum transversely carinate; mesepimeral sulcus foveate, foveae elongate; femoral depression with three transverse carinae beneath medial smooth area; anterior episternum and ventral mesopleuron with setigerous foveae, interspersed with transverse carinae; metapleuron anteriorly with setigerous foveae, posterodorsally foveate, posteroventrally smooth with short transverse carinae; scutoscutellar sulcus laterally with large foveae; mesoscutellum (L:W = 50:100) areolate; median keel not distinct; metascutellum foveate and posteromedially with a triangular spine, metanotal trough foveate; lateral propodeal area laterally densely setose, remainder with longitudinal rows of foveae; propodeum anterolaterally with a spine; posterolateral margin of lateral propodeal area extending posteriorly as a blunt, straight spine. Fore wing (L: W = 352.9:97.0) and hind wing (L: W = 300.0:58.8) weakly infuscate.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA (
Figs 11
, 
12B
). L:W = 264.7: 122.1; T1 anteromedially smooth with sparse foveae, remainder longitudinally costate, space between costae foveate; T2 with basal foveae, remainder longitudinally costate, space between costae with shorter costae posteriorly; T3 predominantly longitudinally costate, space between costae foveate; T3 laterally with setigerous punctae, posteriorly with a row of setigerous punctae followed by a smooth patch; remaining tergites setigerous punctate, punctae dense laterally on T4–T6; T1 and T2 with sparse long setae laterally, T3–T6 densely setose laterally; length and width of tergites T1–T 
7 in
ratio of 45.6: 36.8, 64.0: 63.2, 77.9: 117.6, 36.8: 120.6, 20.6: 89.7, 11.8: 58.8, 7.4:36.8, respectively.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
