<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio
Kieffer, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <p>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
         <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio
Kieffer, 1905: 13
</tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
(
type
species: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio striatifrons
Kieffer, 1905
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</tp:treatment-sec>
   </p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Macrogryon
Nixon, 1936: 116
</tp:taxon-name>

(synonymized by 
Masner 1976
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio
</tp:taxon-name>
is diagnosed by the following combination of character states: axillular spine elongate and posteriorly directed; eyes with dense, long setae; radicle very short; netrion narrow; T 
6 in
females with two lateral spines and a medial lobe; very large, robust black species (
Masner 1976
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Large, robust, densely setose, black species, with coarse sculpture; antennae in shades of dark brown except light yellow to light brown A3 and A 
4 in
females; radicle short, less than half length of interantennal process; A3 more than 2 × length of A 
4 in
females; clypeus wide with lateral corners pointed; eyes with dense bristles; mandible either tridentate or subtridentate (with median tooth shorter than upper and lower teeth); facial striae present; frons generally entirely carinate, sometimes with a medial smooth patch; central keel either present or absent; hyperoccipital carina absent; pronotum visible when viewed dorsally, sometimes with a short spine on pronotal shoulders; epomial carina present; notaulus absent; netrion present; femoral depression transversely carinate; mesoscutum and mesoscutellum coarsely sculptured, latter sometimes with a median keel; axillular spine elongate and posteriorly directed; metascutellum with a strong posteromedial spine; posterior propodeal projection present; metasoma spatulate; T1 sometimes with a horn; T1 and T2 longitudinally costate; T3 with varied sculpture; T 
6 in
females with lateral teeth and a median lobe. Males with elongate, stout antennomeres, A4 and A5 shorter than A3; T3–T6 densely setose, with lateral patch.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Masner (1976)
, in his revision of the world genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Scelionidae</tp:taxon-name>
, furnished a key to the genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Teleasinae</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gryonoides
Dodd, 1920
</tp:taxon-name>
are diagnosed in this key by the presence of lateral mesoscutellar spines (sensu 
Masner 1976
). 

Veenakumari 
et al.
(2011b)

described a third genus, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dvivarnus
Rajmohana &amp; Veenakumari
</tp:taxon-name>
, also possessing lateral mesoscutellar spines. 

Talamas 
et al.
(2016)

included the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trimorus carus
(
Nixon, 1936
)
</tp:taxon-name>
species group with this character state and provided a key for the three genera – 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gryonoides
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dvivarnus
</tp:taxon-name>
and the 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trimorus carus
</tp:taxon-name>
species group – all sharing lateral mesoscutellar spines. The lateral spines on the mesosoma in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio
</tp:taxon-name>
have now been clarified to be elongations of the axillula, and they are hence axillular spines and not mesoscutellar spine as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gryonoides
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dvivarnus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trimorus carus
</tp:taxon-name>
. As of now there are four lineages in 
<tp:taxon-name>Teleasinae</tp:taxon-name>
possessing lateral spines, one with an axillular spine and three with mesoscutellar spines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
