<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio agnieleae
Veenakumari
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
537CB22A-1229-4EE6-BD24-769208D50EA5
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species is closest to 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. apperti
</tp:taxon-name>
, but can be differentiated from it by the following characters: presence of a horn on T1, A3 and A4 subequal in length and T3 medially punctate; in 
<tp:taxon-name>
O. apperti
</tp:taxon-name>
: T1 without horn, A3 more than 2 × the length of A4, and T3 medially longitudinally costate on anterior half, smooth with setigerous punctae on posterior half.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is named in honour of Dr Agnièle Touret-Alby, Curator, MNHN.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
INDIA
• 
♀
; 
Rajasthan
, 
Udaipur
, 
Maharana Pratap University of Agriculture and Technology
(MPUAT); 
24°36′02″ N
, 
73°44′21″ E
; alt. 

583 m

; 

23 Sep. 2016

; YPT; 
ICAR-NBAIR P3963
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
INDIA
– 

Rajasthan

• 
3 ♀♀
; 
Udaipur
, 
Badagaon
, 
Krishi Vigyan Kendra
(KVK), 
24°38′11″ N
, 
73°40′48″ E
; alt. 

178 m

; 

24 Sep. 2016

; YPT; 
ICAR-NBAIR P3964 to P3966

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
ICAR-NBAIR P3976

• 

2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 
ICAR-NBAIR P3999 to P4000

• 

4 ♂♂
; 
Bhilwara
, 
Agarpura Chouraha
, 
Suwana
, KVK; 
25°21′29″ N
, 
74°43′25″ E
; alt. 

398 m

; 

28 Sep. 2016

; YPT; 
ICAR-NBAIR P3971 to P3974

. – 

Karnataka

• 
1 ♂
; 
Bengaluru
, 
Hessaraghatta
; 
13°08′01″ N
, 
77°29′27″ E
; alt. 

859 m

; 

18 Jun. 2015

; SN; 
ICAR-NBAIR P3968

. – 

Madhya Pradesh

• 
2 ♂♂
; 
Bhopal
, 
Central Institute of Agricultural Engineering
(CIAE); 
23°18′48″ N
, 
77°24′27″ E
; alt. 

499 m

; 

15 Jun. 2011

; YPT; 
ICAR-NBAIR P3969 to P3970

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>BODY LENGTH. 2.72 (2.55–2.83) mm, n = 4.</p>
      <p>
COLOUR (
Figs 1–2
). Body black, tegula, legs, interantennal process and apical ends of lateral spines of mesoscutellum yellowish brown; anterior margin of lateral pronotal area brownish yellow; radicle, basal half of A1 and distal end of A2 yellowish brown, remainder of A1 and A2, including A3–A6, brownish black; clava darker than preceding antennomeres; mandibles yellowish brown.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 1
, 
2A–C, E
). Head setose, 1.21 × as wide as high, 1.58 × as high as long; IOS 0.74 × head width, 1.9 × eye length; OOL&gt; POL&gt;LOL in ratio of 18.5: 7.2: 2.5; OOL 3.1 × OD; eye (L: W = 27.7:19.4) setose; frons anteriorly setigerous punctate, medially smooth; facial striae adjacent to medial smooth patch, decreasing in size as they progress towards centre; space between carinae smooth; interantennal process rectangular and rugose; vertex smooth with sparse punctae; ocelli not raised above surface of vertex; interocellar area smooth, sparsely setose; occiput smooth with sparse setigerous punctae; occipital carina foveate; facial striae prominent; gena smooth with sparse setigerous punctae and weak carinae; clypeus medially with a prominent longitudinal carina and transverse carinae basally, remainder smooth; length and width of antennomeres A1–A 
12 in
ratio of 46.2: 7.2, 7.8: 4.9, 14.1: 6.3, 13.9:6.0, 3.9: 5.0, 3.8: 5.6, 4.7: 7.9, 6.9: 8.2, 5.9: 8.7, 5.6: 8.3, 5.0: 7.9, 8.8: 6.3, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA (
Figs 1
, 
2C, E
). Cervical pronotal area smooth; mesoscutum (L: W = 34.2: 59.5) entirely areolate, areolae sparse medially; lateral pronotal area dorsally areolate, pronotal suprahumeral sulcus and pronotal cervical sulcus foveate, remainder smooth; netrion unevenly foveate; dorsal mesopleuron with a small rugose patch beneath tegula; mesopleural pit distinct; speculum with transverse carinae; mesepimeral sulcus foveate except in ventral ¼; femoral depression posteroventrally with elongate depressions; anteroventral mesopleuron areolate, setose; postacetabular sulcus indicated as a furrow; metapleuron anteriorly setose, with metapleural sulcus and posterodorsal metapleural sulcus foveate; ventral half of metapleuron areolate, setose; posterior margin of metapleuron with a wide spine; mesoscutellum (L: W = 18.1:41.0) with a row of cells on anterior margin, remainder areolate, with a weak median keel; metascutellum foveate and posteromedially with a spine, metanotal trough foveate; lateral propodeal area with uneven depressions, with a short spine anterolaterally and an outward bending long spine posterolaterally. Fore wing (L:W = 160.5:52.6) and hind wing (L: W = 132.9: 29.1) hyaline.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA (
Fig. 1A–B
). L:W = 126.7: 66.7; T1 anteriorly smooth, with a short, smooth horn anteromedially, remainder longitudinally costate with weak foveae between costae; T2 with weak basal foveae, longitudinally costate, space between costae predominantly smooth; T3 medially punctate, submedially and sublaterally longitudinally costate with foveae between costae, laterally and posteriorly smooth; remaining tergites smooth with setigerous punctae; T1–T3 laterally setose, remaining tergites evenly setose; length and width of tergites T1–T 
6 in
ratio of 25.9: 20.6, 26.8: 26.4, 45.8:59.8, 14.5: 62.1, 6.0: 42.6, 7.6: 17.7, respectively.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Odontoscelio agnieleae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Holotype, ♀ (ICAR-NBAIR P3963). 
A
. Habitus (dorsal view). 
B
. Habitus, showing axillular spines. 
C
. Head and pleuron.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>BODY LENGTH. 2.61 (2.48–2.85) mm, n = 8.</p>
      <p>
Similar to female; length of antennomeres A1–A 
12 in
ratio of 31.4:7.8, 4.2: 5.8, 21.5: 6.6, 20.3:5.4, 19.7: 6.5, 22.3: 5.5, 21.3: 6.2, 20.5:6.6, 21.2: 6.2, 20.1: 5.8, 20.2: 5.7, 21.6: 5.3, respectively (
Fig. 2F
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
