<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pectotibialis paghmanensis
Tshernyshev
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
93EC6FFD-B1D1-409F-B12A-081E1D5B96F5
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
AFGHANISTAN
• 
♂
; 
Kabul Province
, 
near Paghman village
, 
34°35′ N
, 
68°57′ E
, 

2600 m
a.s.l.

; 

12 Jul. 2009

; 
O. Pak
leg.; 
SCH_ISEA_000123
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
AFGHANISTAN
• 
6 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
SCH_ISEA_000124–129

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
, male

(
Fig 1A–B
)
</p>
      <p>BODY. Elongate, subparallel, slightly expanded posteriorly, elytra not covering two ultimate segments of the abdomen.</p>
      <p>
LABRUM, LABIUM, MANDIBLES, PALPI, MOUTHPARTS AND ANTENNAE. Yellow-brown, except for black spots on upper side of the 1 
st
antennomere (
Fig. 2D
), tibiae and tarsi in all legs, coxae and trochanters in anterior legs and commissure parts between them in intermediate and posterior legs and membranes of abdominal ventrites yellow, other body parts black–brown; upper surface of head, pronotum and elytra with a weak green metallic tint. Surface evenly covered with yellow-white dense fine long erect and curved hairs. Vesicles white-yellow, and thoracic mesepimera black.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectotibialis paghmanensis
Tshernyshev
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
A, B, D–I
. Holotype, ♂ (SCH_ ISEA_000123). 
C.
Allotype, ♀. 
A
, 
C
. External appearance, dorsal view. 
B
. External appearance, lateral view. 
D
. Right antenna. 
E
. Head, pronotum and scutellum, subdorsal view. 
F
. Metathorax, subdorsal view. 
G
. Metathorax, lateral view. 
H
. Left anterior tibia and tarsus, ventral view. 
I
. Left anterior tibia and tarsus, dorsal view. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Not wider than pronotum, interocular area slightly impressed and edged with thin carina, frons with two tubercles, eyes small, oval, weakly protruding; genae short and straight; clypeus narrow, transverse, straight; labrum narrow, transverse; palpae simple with apical segment slightly widened and securiform; surface of head dull, sparsely indistinctly punctured lacking microsculpture, evenly covered with light fine long and curved pubescence.</p>
      <p>
ANTENNAE. Weakly flabellate from 6 
th
to 11 
th
antennomeres (
Fig. 1D
), 
1.7 mm
long, reaching the base of elytra; 1 
st
antennomere enlarged, round-oval, 2 
nd
antennomere small, round, almost completely invisible, hidden by the 1 
st
antennomere, 3 
rd
and 4 
th
antennomeres triangular, the 3 
rd
is 1.2 times as long and wide as the 4 
th
antennomere, 5 
th
antennomere triangular with elongate outer edge and is as long as the 3 
rd
antennomere, but considerably narrower than it, 6 
th
to 10 
th
antennomeres with extended outer edges, apical segment elongate, thin, subcylindrical, slightly curved in basal third; surface evenly covered with short, yellowwhite adpressed pubescence with single erect longer light hairs on outer sides of the antennomeres.
</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Almost completely equilateral, narrowly transverse impressed near basal margin, disk convex with wide subtriangular tubercle in a middle and look bituberculate at base; anterior margin slightly convex; posterior margin straight; lateral sides almost completely straight with rounded angles; basal side and basal half of lateral sides slightly flattened and distinctly marginate, anterior side indistinctly marginate; surface glabrous, with sparse smoothed punctures lacking microsculpture, evenly covered with fine long curved light hairs.</p>
      <p>SCUTELLUM. Small, triangular with rounded tip, almost completely covered by pronotum, sparsely punctured and covered with light semi-erect hairs.</p>
      <p>ELYTRA. Oblong, parallel or slightly widened just behind the middle and evenly rounded distally, not covering three apical segments of the abdomen, at base not wider than pronotum; humeri small, slightly protruding; apices evenly rounded, simple; disc indistinctly marginate on external sides and along suture, lateral edge in middle near epipleura slightly impressed; surface dull, coarsely punctured and wrinkled, with smoothed microsculpture, evenly covered with yellow-white long erect hairs.</p>
      <p>HIND WINGS. Normally developed.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Not long; posterior femora not reaching elytral apices; anterior tibiae not swollen but widened distally and with a strong rectangular excavation inwardly in apical half so that the tip of the tibiae looks like a 1 
st
tarsomere (
Fig. 1H–I
), intermediate and posterior tibiae simple, not swollen or emarginate, with the setae similar to that in tarsal comb arranged in apical edge near tarsus, femora wide, roundly swollen, anterior with tooth in middle (
Fig. 2A–B
), anterior trochanter oval and impressed to the basal half of the femur, all tarsi 5-segmented, slightly compressed and elongate, 2 
nd
tarsomere in anterior tarsi with small transverse comb above, the 1 
st
tarsomere enlarged, triangular, 1.3 times as long as the 2 
nd
tarsomere, 2 times as long as the 3 
rd
tarsomere and 3 times as long as the 4 
th
tarsomere, claw-segment flattened, as long as the 1 
st
tarsomere, claws very short and thin, almost completely hidden by round semi-transparent membrane at base. Surface of legs covered with light short semi-erect pubescence and sparse white long erect hairs.
</p>
      <p>
VENTRAL BODY SURFACE. Sparsely punctured, shining, evenly and sparsely covered with long, fine, semierect white hairs; metathorax swollen and complicatedly sculptured: impressed in a middle, and with two protuberances, one lamellate transverse above, and the other longitudinal and possessing vertical round semi-transparent plate at apex (
Fig. 1F–G
). Pygidium slightly elongate, almost equilateral, evenly rounded distally, with long dark erect hair on outer side (
Fig. 2C
), ultimate abdominal ventrite is bilaciniate, narrow, transverse, evenly narrowed dorsally and emarginate in the middle (
Fig. 2D
), aedeagus simple, weakly curved dorsally, narrow, with elongate narrow and ventrally curved apical lamella, endophallus with three denticles at apex near lamella (
Fig. 2F
), tegmen long, narrow, with thin and short pointed parameres those are 2.3 times as short as the base of tegmen (
Fig. 2G
).
</p>
      <p>
LENGTH. 
3.8 mm
, width (at elytral base) 
0.8 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
Female differs in having simple head and pronotum lacking sculpture, anterior tarsi simple, lacking a comb above the 2 
nd
tarsomere, antennae dentate with the 3 
rd
and 4 
th
antennomeres narrow-triangular, and of the equal shape and length, anterior tibiae lacking excavation, but with stretched outer edge bearing the 1 
st
tarsomere, anterior femora lacking tooth, metathorax evenly convex lacking appendages, inner side of the apex of anterior and intermediate tibiae with a row of setae similar to that in tarsal comb of male, abdomen long, with four segments extending beyond apex of the elytra.
</p>
      <p>
LENGTH. 
4.3 mm
, width (at elytral base) 1.0 mm.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectotibialis paghmanensis
Tshernyshev
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂. 
A
. Femur of left anterior leg. 
B
. Left anterior leg, ventral view. 
C
. Left intermediate leg, ventral view. 
D
. Pygidium. 
E
. Ultimate abdominal ventrite. 
F
. Aedeagus, dorsal view. 
G
. Tegmen. 
H
. Distribution map. Scale bars: 0.5 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
         <p>
Distribution
</p>
         <p>
Known from 
type
locality only, 
Afghanistan
: Paghman environs (
Fig. 2H
).
</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:nomenclature/>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
            <p>
1. Male special structures are indistinct, antennae filiform or flabellate .....................................................2
</p>
            <p>
– Male special structures distinct and located on head, antennae, pronotum, metathorax, sternites or legs ..........................................................................................................................................................10
</p>
            <p>

2. Second segment of anterior tarsi lacking a comb above, elytra with green or blue metallic lustre .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Apalochrus
Erichson, 1840
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>
– Second segment of anterior tarsi with a comb above, elytra entirely black, sometimes with metallic lustre...........................................................................................................................................................3
</p>
            <p>

3. Body of staphylinoid shape, narrow, black, lacking metallic lustre, elytra strongly shortened and not covering abdomen, wings reduced, antennae filiform ............................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratinoides
Medvedev, 1964
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– Body typical of 
<tp:taxon-name>Malachiidae</tp:taxon-name>
, elytra completely covering the abdomen .................................................4

</p>
            <p>
4. Anterior tibiae simple, not widened or impressed, antennae flabellate of filiform .................................5
</p>
            <p>
– Anterior tibiae widened or impressed distally, antennae flabellate .........................................................9
</p>
            <p>
5. Antennae filiform ......................................................................................................................................6
</p>
            <p>
– Antennae flabellate ...................................................................................................................................7
</p>
            <p>

6. Antennomeres simple, not widened and slightly flattened, lacking impressions or grooves, anterior femora simple, lacking emarginations; surface of the body covered with long erect and short adpressed black pubescence ......................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Protapalochrus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– Intermediate3 
rdand
6 
thantennomereswidened
,dorsalsideof5 
th
–10 
thantennomeressulcateinmiddle
,anterior femora with oval emargination in apical half covered with white pubescence; surface of the body covered with short semi-erect and adpressed black-brown pubescence ...... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroapalochrus
Tshernyshev, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

7. Pronotum simple, lacking longitudinal grooves .............................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectapalochrus
</tp:taxon-name>
Tshernyshev, 2016

</p>
            <p>

– Pronotum bisulcate in middle ........................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Airomalachius
Pic, 1950
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

9. Anterior tibiae compressed and widened in apical half, intermediate tibiae impressed and flattened in outer side with weakly widened and curved apices, pronotum convex and narrowly depressed at base, elytra and pronotum uniformly dark with green or blue metallic lustre and covered with long erect grey hairs ................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mesapalochrus
</tp:taxon-name>
Tshernyshev, 2020

</p>
            <p>

– Anterior tibiae slightly widened anteriorly and weakly impressed dorsally, intermediate tibiae simple, not widened and not flattened, pronotum convex, not depressed at base, orange with longitudinal greenbronze stripe in a middle, elytra orange-yellow, each with two bronze metallic oval-triangular spots, surface covered with short erect fine white pubescence ................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nudopectinus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

10. Anterior tibiae simple, not widened or emarginate, male special structure is located in apical half of the pronotum as transverse fissure with elevate side and protuberance behind, anterior tarsi with a comb above the 2 
nd
tarsomere, posterior tibiae slightly but distinctly swollen in basal fourth .................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Simoderus
Abeille de Perrin, 1891
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– Anterior tibiae slightly but distinctly widened, simple or emarginate, pronotum simple or with protruding process in anterior side, male special structures located in femora or tibiae, head, metathorax or abdominal ventrites; anterior tarsi with a comb above 2 
nd
tarsomere or lacking it ..........................11

</p>
            <p>

11. Anterior tibiae simple, not emarginate, anterior tarsi with a comb above 2 
nd
tarsomere ......................15

</p>
            <p>

– Anterior tibiae emarginate at apical part, anterior tarsi with a comb above 2 
nd
tarsomere or lacking it ...............................................................................................................................................................12

</p>
            <p>
12. Head with emarginations and protuberances, antennae serrate or flabellate, abdomen simple ............13
</p>
            <p>
– Head simple, lacking emarginations and protuberances, antennae filiform ..........................................14
</p>
            <p>

13. Pronotum with narrow horn-like process protruding over the head, antennae serrate .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Troglolaius
Wittmer, 1952
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– Pronotum simple, antennae flabellate ......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trogloapalochrus
Pic, 1919
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

14. 4 
th
and 5 
th
abdominal ventrites modified and with thorn-like process in the middle ............................15

</p>
            <p>

– 4 
th
and 5 
th
abdominal ventrites simple, lacking process .........................................................................16

</p>
            <p>

15. Intermediate tibiae slightly widened and swollen, with the inner side emarginate at apical quarter, trochanters of anterior legs simple .......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Opisthapalochrus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– Intermediate tibiae simple, not widened or emarginate, trochanters of anterior legs dentate .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Spinapalochrus
Pic, 1919
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

16. 2 
nd
tarsomere in anterior legs with a comb above ..................................................................................17

</p>
            <p>

– 2 
nd
tarsomere in anterior legs lacking a comb above, antennae serrate, anterior tibiae evenly emarginate, intermediate tibiae widened and narrowly emarginate, with pheromone glands .................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mesopezus
Jacobson, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epitinus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
)

</p>
            <p>
17. Eyes extremely large, antennae flabellate ..............................................................................................18
</p>
            <p>
– Eyes simple, not large .............................................................................................................................19
</p>
            <p>

18. Metathorax swollen with appendage in the middle, elytral apices impressed near suture, anterior and intermediate femora swollen, intermediate tibia slightly widened posteriorly and possessing pheromone glands ............................................................................................... 
Mimapalochrus
Tshernyshev, 2015

</p>
            <p>

– Metathorax weakly swollen, lacking appendage in a middle, elytral apices not impressed, simple, all legs simple, not widened or curved, without glands ....................... 
Oculapalochrus
Tshernyshev, 2015

</p>
            <p>
19. Metathorax strongly swollen and possessing gladiate or rudimentary appendage with hairs in the middle ......................................................................................................................................................20
</p>
            <p>
– Metathorax slightly swollen, lacking appendage or hairs .....................................................................18
</p>
            <p>

20. Anterior tibiae slightly emarginate, intermediate tibiae swollen with apical margin simple and lacking setae, pronotum and head simple, lacking relief sculpture, metathorax possesses gladiate appendage in the middle directed to intermediate coxae, elytra completely covering the abdomen ......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dromanthomorphus
Pic, 1921
</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectinus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
)

</p>
            <p>

– Anterior tibiae deeply emarginate in apical quarter, apical margin of anterior and intermediate legs surrounded with pectinate setae similar to that in tarsal comb; intermediate tibiae slightly widened, not stout, with longitudinal groove within, pronotum with protuberance in basal half, forehead bituberculate, metathorax slightly swollen and impressed in the middle with two appendages, one lamellate transverse above, and the other appendage longitudinal with vertical round semi-transparent lamellate apex below, elytra not covering two apical segments of the abdomen ................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectotibialis
Tshernyshev
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
            <p>
21. Anterior tibiae strongly modified, deeply emarginated with lamellate processes, inner spurs of the anterior legs modified, antenna flabellate or filiform .............................................................................22
</p>
            <p>
– Anterior tibiae slightly widened or weakly emarginate, simple, spurs short and simple, antenna filiform .....................................................................................................................................................23
</p>
            <p>

22. 1 
st
tarsomere in anterior legs enlarged and compressed, leaf-shaped, dorsally with a row of golden hairs forming a tuft, 2 
nd
tarsomere very short, almost completely covered by the vane-shape longitudinal comb, anterior tibiae strongly emarginate, with a stretched apex bearing enlarged hook-like spur, intermediate tibiae strongly widened and modified, emarginate within and possessing a row of long hairs inside the emargination, antennae flabellate ................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hapalochrops
Bourgeois, 1908
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– 1 
st
tarsomere in anterior legs slightly enlarged and swollen, round-quadrate, 2 
nd
tarsomere with a simple short comb above, outer spur in anterior tibiae long and strong, thorn-like, intermediate tibiae with deep emargination in apical quarter, and a long narrow appendage bearing hair tuft in apex of inner side of the emargination, antennae filiform ........................................................ 
Tibipectinus
Tshernyshev, 2020

</p>
            <p>

23. Anterior tibiae weakly widened distally, not emarginate, intermediate tibiae widened in apical half and sulcate in the middle of inner side, lacking emarginations ................. 
Protopectinus
Tshernyshev, 2020

</p>
            <p>
– Anterior tibiae weakly emarginate in dorsal or ventral side, intermediate tibiae stout and emarginate or thin and not emarginate ..........................................................................................................................24
</p>
            <p>

24. Anterior tibiae emarginate in dorsal side, intermediate tibiae strongly dilate and convex, with triangular perpendicular process in a middle of inner side and strongly emarginate beneath it ..................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hadrocnemus
Kraatz, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
            <p>

– Anterior tibiae emarginate in ventral side, intermediate tibiae not widened and with a row of long erect thin hairs on inner side ................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setapalochrus
Evers, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
            </p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>
1. Male special structures are indistinct, antennae filiform or flabellate .....................................................2
</p>
      <p>
– Male special structures distinct and located on head, antennae, pronotum, metathorax, sternites or legs ..........................................................................................................................................................10
</p>
      <p>

2. Second segment of anterior tarsi lacking a comb above, elytra with green or blue metallic lustre .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Apalochrus
Erichson, 1840
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Second segment of anterior tarsi with a comb above, elytra entirely black, sometimes with metallic lustre...........................................................................................................................................................3
</p>
      <p>

3. Body of staphylinoid shape, narrow, black, lacking metallic lustre, elytra strongly shortened and not covering abdomen, wings reduced, antennae filiform ............................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paratinoides
Medvedev, 1964
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body typical of 
<tp:taxon-name>Malachiidae</tp:taxon-name>
, elytra completely covering the abdomen .................................................4

</p>
      <p>
4. Anterior tibiae simple, not widened or impressed, antennae flabellate of filiform .................................5
</p>
      <p>
– Anterior tibiae widened or impressed distally, antennae flabellate .........................................................9
</p>
      <p>
5. Antennae filiform ......................................................................................................................................6
</p>
      <p>
– Antennae flabellate ...................................................................................................................................7
</p>
      <p>

6. Antennomeres simple, not widened and slightly flattened, lacking impressions or grooves, anterior femora simple, lacking emarginations; surface of the body covered with long erect and short adpressed black pubescence ......................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Protapalochrus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Intermediate3 
rdand
6 
thantennomereswidened
,dorsalsideof5 
th
–10 
thantennomeressulcateinmiddle
,anterior femora with oval emargination in apical half covered with white pubescence; surface of the body covered with short semi-erect and adpressed black-brown pubescence ...... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroapalochrus
Tshernyshev, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

7. Pronotum simple, lacking longitudinal grooves .............................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectapalochrus
</tp:taxon-name>
Tshernyshev, 2016

</p>
      <p>

– Pronotum bisulcate in middle ........................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Airomalachius
Pic, 1950
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

9. Anterior tibiae compressed and widened in apical half, intermediate tibiae impressed and flattened in outer side with weakly widened and curved apices, pronotum convex and narrowly depressed at base, elytra and pronotum uniformly dark with green or blue metallic lustre and covered with long erect grey hairs ................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mesapalochrus
</tp:taxon-name>
Tshernyshev, 2020

</p>
      <p>

– Anterior tibiae slightly widened anteriorly and weakly impressed dorsally, intermediate tibiae simple, not widened and not flattened, pronotum convex, not depressed at base, orange with longitudinal greenbronze stripe in a middle, elytra orange-yellow, each with two bronze metallic oval-triangular spots, surface covered with short erect fine white pubescence ................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Nudopectinus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

10. Anterior tibiae simple, not widened or emarginate, male special structure is located in apical half of the pronotum as transverse fissure with elevate side and protuberance behind, anterior tarsi with a comb above the 2 
nd
tarsomere, posterior tibiae slightly but distinctly swollen in basal fourth .................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Simoderus
Abeille de Perrin, 1891
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Anterior tibiae slightly but distinctly widened, simple or emarginate, pronotum simple or with protruding process in anterior side, male special structures located in femora or tibiae, head, metathorax or abdominal ventrites; anterior tarsi with a comb above 2 
nd
tarsomere or lacking it ..........................11

</p>
      <p>

11. Anterior tibiae simple, not emarginate, anterior tarsi with a comb above 2 
nd
tarsomere ......................15

</p>
      <p>

– Anterior tibiae emarginate at apical part, anterior tarsi with a comb above 2 
nd
tarsomere or lacking it ...............................................................................................................................................................12

</p>
      <p>
12. Head with emarginations and protuberances, antennae serrate or flabellate, abdomen simple ............13
</p>
      <p>
– Head simple, lacking emarginations and protuberances, antennae filiform ..........................................14
</p>
      <p>

13. Pronotum with narrow horn-like process protruding over the head, antennae serrate .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Troglolaius
Wittmer, 1952
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Pronotum simple, antennae flabellate ......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Trogloapalochrus
Pic, 1919
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

14. 4 
th
and 5 
th
abdominal ventrites modified and with thorn-like process in the middle ............................15

</p>
      <p>

– 4 
th
and 5 
th
abdominal ventrites simple, lacking process .........................................................................16

</p>
      <p>

15. Intermediate tibiae slightly widened and swollen, with the inner side emarginate at apical quarter, trochanters of anterior legs simple .......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Opisthapalochrus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Intermediate tibiae simple, not widened or emarginate, trochanters of anterior legs dentate .............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Spinapalochrus
Pic, 1919
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

16. 2 
nd
tarsomere in anterior legs with a comb above ..................................................................................17

</p>
      <p>

– 2 
nd
tarsomere in anterior legs lacking a comb above, antennae serrate, anterior tibiae evenly emarginate, intermediate tibiae widened and narrowly emarginate, with pheromone glands .................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mesopezus
Jacobson, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epitinus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
)

</p>
      <p>
17. Eyes extremely large, antennae flabellate ..............................................................................................18
</p>
      <p>
– Eyes simple, not large .............................................................................................................................19
</p>
      <p>

18. Metathorax swollen with appendage in the middle, elytral apices impressed near suture, anterior and intermediate femora swollen, intermediate tibia slightly widened posteriorly and possessing pheromone glands ............................................................................................... 
Mimapalochrus
Tshernyshev, 2015

</p>
      <p>

– Metathorax weakly swollen, lacking appendage in a middle, elytral apices not impressed, simple, all legs simple, not widened or curved, without glands ....................... 
Oculapalochrus
Tshernyshev, 2015

</p>
      <p>
19. Metathorax strongly swollen and possessing gladiate or rudimentary appendage with hairs in the middle ......................................................................................................................................................20
</p>
      <p>
– Metathorax slightly swollen, lacking appendage or hairs .....................................................................18
</p>
      <p>

20. Anterior tibiae slightly emarginate, intermediate tibiae swollen with apical margin simple and lacking setae, pronotum and head simple, lacking relief sculpture, metathorax possesses gladiate appendage in the middle directed to intermediate coxae, elytra completely covering the abdomen ......................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dromanthomorphus
Pic, 1921
</tp:taxon-name>
(= 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectinus
Evers, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
)

</p>
      <p>

– Anterior tibiae deeply emarginate in apical quarter, apical margin of anterior and intermediate legs surrounded with pectinate setae similar to that in tarsal comb; intermediate tibiae slightly widened, not stout, with longitudinal groove within, pronotum with protuberance in basal half, forehead bituberculate, metathorax slightly swollen and impressed in the middle with two appendages, one lamellate transverse above, and the other appendage longitudinal with vertical round semi-transparent lamellate apex below, elytra not covering two apical segments of the abdomen ................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pectotibialis
Tshernyshev
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
      <p>
21. Anterior tibiae strongly modified, deeply emarginated with lamellate processes, inner spurs of the anterior legs modified, antenna flabellate or filiform .............................................................................22
</p>
      <p>
– Anterior tibiae slightly widened or weakly emarginate, simple, spurs short and simple, antenna filiform .....................................................................................................................................................23
</p>
      <p>

22. 1 
st
tarsomere in anterior legs enlarged and compressed, leaf-shaped, dorsally with a row of golden hairs forming a tuft, 2 
nd
tarsomere very short, almost completely covered by the vane-shape longitudinal comb, anterior tibiae strongly emarginate, with a stretched apex bearing enlarged hook-like spur, intermediate tibiae strongly widened and modified, emarginate within and possessing a row of long hairs inside the emargination, antennae flabellate ................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hapalochrops
Bourgeois, 1908
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– 1 
st
tarsomere in anterior legs slightly enlarged and swollen, round-quadrate, 2 
nd
tarsomere with a simple short comb above, outer spur in anterior tibiae long and strong, thorn-like, intermediate tibiae with deep emargination in apical quarter, and a long narrow appendage bearing hair tuft in apex of inner side of the emargination, antennae filiform ........................................................ 
Tibipectinus
Tshernyshev, 2020

</p>
      <p>

23. Anterior tibiae weakly widened distally, not emarginate, intermediate tibiae widened in apical half and sulcate in the middle of inner side, lacking emarginations ................. 
Protopectinus
Tshernyshev, 2020

</p>
      <p>
– Anterior tibiae weakly emarginate in dorsal or ventral side, intermediate tibiae stout and emarginate or thin and not emarginate ..........................................................................................................................24
</p>
      <p>

24. Anterior tibiae emarginate in dorsal side, intermediate tibiae strongly dilate and convex, with triangular perpendicular process in a middle of inner side and strongly emarginate beneath it ..................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hadrocnemus
Kraatz, 1895
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Anterior tibiae emarginate in ventral side, intermediate tibiae not widened and with a row of long erect thin hairs on inner side ................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Setapalochrus
Evers, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
