<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Plutocampa methoria
Chevrizov, 1978
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 49–50
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Plutocampa methoria
Chevrizov, 1978: 202
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 3(1‾10).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
RUSSIA
• 
♀
, 
holotype
(
5.6 mm
); 
Far East
, 
Primorye region
, 
environs of Khasan Lake
; 

17 May 1973

; 
S.I. Ljovuschkin
leg.; slide; 
ZMMU
Dip0002

.
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
1 ♀
(
5.4 mm
), 
1 ♀
(
3.9 mm
); 
Liaoning Province
, 
Benxi
, 
Haunren
, 
Pylone Cave
4; 

17 May 2019

; 
Deharveng
and 
Bedos
leg.; sample code 
CHILN19–007
; NEIGAE

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
(based on 
Chevrizov 1978
)
</p>
      <p>
Under optical microscope, one can see a smooth cuticle covered by thin and smooth clothing setae. The more complete antennae is apparently regenerated and it has 23 antennomeres in the 
5.4 mm
adult from Grotte du Pylone; the third antennomere has a thick sensillum in ventral position (
d–e
macrosetae) (
Fig. 49
). The small and pointed frontal process has one long and smooth anterior macroseta and two shorter posterior macrosetae; there are three smooth macrosetae along each side of the insertion line of the antennomere and smooth 
x
setae with similar length, ratios of 
a
/ 
i
/ 
p
/ 
x
are 14/19/14/ 
19 in
the 
holotype
, respectively. The labial palps have a large thick sensilla (
Fig. 50
). Pronotum with 1+1 
ma
, 2+2 
la
, 2+2 

lp 
1,3

, mesonotum with 1+1 
ma
, 2+2 (2+1) 
la
, 2+2 

lp 
2,3

, 1+1 
mp
, and metanotum with 1+1 
ma
, 0–1+1 
la
, 2+2 
lp2,3
, 1+1 
mp
macrosetae; long and thin notal macrosetae with thin barbs along their distal three-fourths; marginal setae are long and barbed as the macrosetae. Metathoracic legs reach the posterior border of the V–VI abdominal segment; femora has two long, barbed dorsal macrosetae and one ventral macroseta, while the tibia has one short ventral macroseta, a few distal barbs, and calcars with several long barbs; the tarsus has two rows of smooth ventral setae slightly thicker than the clothing setae, and in the distal portion: three long, smooth dorsal setae, one ventral seta and one distal seta; the pretarsus is without lateral processes, with unequal elbowed claws and large lateral crests. Urotergite I–II with 1+1 

post 
1

; urotergite III with 2+2 

post 
1,2

; urotergites IV–VII with 4+4 

post 
1–4

; urotegite VIII with 5+5 

post 
1–5

and abdominal segment IX 7+7 with 
post
, macrosetae are long with barbs along their distal three-fourths. Urosternite I with 6+6, urosternites II–VII with 4+4 and urosternite VIII with 1+1 macrosetae; urosternal macrosetae shorter than urotergal macrosetae with long barbs; smooth stylar setae. Appendages of the first urosternite (female) with large, short and subcylindrical appendages, each with apical field of glandular 

a 
1

setae. The most complete cercus is regenerated and it has six primary articles and a basal article, which are covered by several whorls of barbed macrosetae with long barbs along the third distal and a few whorls of smooth setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
