<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Pacificampa caesa Chevrizov 1978</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4423322</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E40878FFCAFFB4B343FBEFD2502CB3</uri>
         <article-title>Asian cave-adapted diplurans, with the description of two new genera and four new species (Arthropoda, Hexapoda, Entognatha)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pacificampa caesa
Chevrizov, 1978
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pacificampa caesa
Chevrizov, 1978: 199
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1(10‾19).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
RUSSIA
• 
♂
holotype
(
6.8 mm
); 
Far East
, 
Primoriye region
, 
Chandolaz Mountain Range
, 
Bliznets Cave
; 

23 Jun. 1974

; 
B.P. Chevrizov
leg.; slide; 
ZMMU
Dip0004
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
(based on 
Chevrizov 1978
)
</p>
      <p>
It has a smooth cuticle under optical microscope and is covered by abundant short and smooth clothing setae. The antennae are apparently intact with 27 antennomeres, medial antennomeres are 3 × as long as wide; third antennomere has a sensillum in ventral position (
c–d
macrosetae). The plain frontal process has one long anterior smooth macroseta and two, almost two times shorter, posterior macrosetae; the three macrosetae with short distal barbs along each side of the insertion line of the antennomere are longer than the smooth 
x
setae with length ratios of 
a
/ 
i
/ 
p
/ 
x
, 7/8/4/3, respectively. Pronotum with 1+1 
ma
, 1+1 
la
, 1+1 
lp
, mesonotum with 1+1 
ma
, 1+1 
la
, 2+2 
lp
, and metanotum with 1+1 
ma
, 1+1 
lp
macrosetae; all notal macrosetae are robust with a few short distal barbs, in particular the 
la
are longer and the 
lp
pronotal macrosetae have more numerous short distal barbs; the marginal setae are thicker than the clothing setae with short distal barbs, the lateral posterior marginal setae are larger and have more numerous small barbs. The metathoracic legs reach the end of the abdomen; the femora have one robust dorsal macroseta with short distal barbs, whereas the tibia has one ventral short macroseta with 1–2 apical barbs and the calcars are with 3–4 long barbs; the tarsus has two rows of robust, smooth ventral setae, three long, smooth dorsal and one distal ventral setae; the pretarsus is without lateral processes, with subequal elbowed claws, and with a smooth ventral surface ridged on the dorsal side that looks like very small lateral crests under optical microscopes, but they are not. Urotergites V–VII have 1+1 
ma
, 1+1 
la
, 2+2 
lp
; urotergite VIII and abdominal segment IX has 1+1 
mp
, 3+3 
lp
, all macrosetae are robust and with a few short distal barbs. Urosternite I has 6+6, urosternites II–VII 5+5, and urosternite VIII 1+1 macrosetae; all urosternal macrosetae are robust and with a few long barbs; robust smooth stylar setae. First urosternite appendages have (male) subcylindrical appendages thick, each of these has a large apical field with more than one hundred glandular 

a 
1

setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
