<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Plutocampa paurochaeta Chevrizov 1978</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4422573</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03E40878FFC9FFB6B31BFEA0D2E129E7</uri>
         <article-title>Asian cave-adapted diplurans, with the description of two new genera and four new species (Arthropoda, Hexapoda, Entognatha)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Plutocampa paurochaeta
Chevrizov, 1978
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>

Plutocampa paurochaeta 
Chevrizov

, 1978: 204
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 3(11‾19).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
RUSSIA
• 
♀
holotype
(
6.7 mm
); 
Far East
, 
Primoriye region
, 
Chandolaz Mt. Range
, 
Solyanik Cave
; 

25 Jun. 1974

; 
P.B. Chevrizov
leg.; slide; 
ZMMU
Dip0005
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
(based on 
Chevrizov 1978
)
</p>
      <p>
Under optical microscope, one can see a smooth cuticle covered by thin smooth clothing setae. Antennae, apparently intact, have 28 antennomeres, the central antennomere is 1.6 × as long as wide, the apical antennomere has about eight olfactory chemoreceptors; the third antennomere has a large sensillum in ventral position. The head has a small and pointed frontal process with one long anterior smooth macroseta and two shorter posterior macrosetae; three smooth macrosetae along each side of the insertion line of the antennomere and smooth 
x
setae with similar length, ratios of 
a
/ 
i
/ 
p
/ 
x
are 6/5/8/7, respectively. Pronotum with 1+1 
ma
, 2+2 
la
, 2+2 

lp 
1,3

, mesonotum with 1+1 
ma
, 2+1 
la
, 2+2 

lp 
2,3

, and metanotum with 1+1 
ma
, 2+2 
lp
macrosetae, notal macrosetae are long and thin with thin barbs on three-fourths of distal barbs; marginal setae are long and smooth. Metathoracic legs overpass the end of the abdomen; femora have two long barbed dorsal macrosetae and one ventral macroseta, and the tibia has one ventral short macroseta and calcars with several long barbs. The tarsus has two rows of ventral smooth setae slightly thicker than the clothing setae, three long and smooth dorsal subapical setae and one ventral subapical seta; the pretarsus is without lateral processes, with unequal elbowed claws, and with large lateral crests. Urotergite IV with 1+1 

post 
1

, urotergites V–VII with 4+4 

post 
1–4

, urotegite VIII with 5+5 
post1–5
, macrosetae are long, with barbs along their three-fourths. Urosternite I with 6+6, urosternites II–VII with 4+4, and urosternite VIII with 1+1 macrosetae; urosternal macrosetae are shorter than urotergal macrosetae with long barbs; smooth stylar setae. First urosternite appendages (female) have large, short subconical glandular 

a 
1

setae with a smaller apical field. The cerci have eight articles plus a basal one covered with whorls of smooth setae and whorls of macrosetae barbed with thin barbs at the proximal articles to smooth in medial and distal articles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
