<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Plutocampa speophila Chevrizov 1978</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4423312</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8B3CC4C944F54272ED7DACC5985539FB</uri>
         <article-title>Asian cave-adapted diplurans, with the description of two new genera and four new species (Arthropoda, Hexapoda, Entognatha)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Plutocampa speophila
Chevrizov, 1978
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Plutocampa speophila
Chevrizov, 1978: 201
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 2(1‾9).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
RUSSIA
• 
♀
, 
holotype
(
6 mm
), 
1 ♀
paratype (
5 mm
); 
Far East
, 
Primorye region
, 
Olgisk District
, 
Priiskovaya cave
; 

3 Nov. 1966

; 
S.I. Ljovuschkin
leg.; slide; 
ZMMU
Dip0007

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
(based on 
Chevrizov 1978
)
</p>
      <p>
Under optical microscope it has a smooth cuticle covered by thin smooth clothing setae. Antennae are apparently intact with 23 antennomeres in the 
paratype
, medial antennomeres 1.4 × as long as wide; third antennomere with a thick sensillum in ventral position (
c–d
macrosetae); last antennomere with at least eight olfactory chemoreceptors. Small and pointed frontal process has one long anterior smooth macrosetae and two shorter posterior macrosetae; there are three smooth macrosetae along each side of the line of insertion of antennomere and smooth 
x
setae with a similar length, ratios of 
a
/ 
i
/ 
p
/ 
x
are 20/23/22/23, respectively. Labial palps are large with thick sensilla. Pronotum with 1+1 
ma
, 3+3 (2+ 
2 paratype
) 
la
, 2+2 

lp 
1,3

mesonotum with 1+1 
ma
, 3+3 (2+ 
2 paratype
) 
la
, 2+2 

lp 
2,3

, 1+1 (0+ 
1 paratype
) 
mp
and metanotum with 1+1 
ma
, 2+2 
lp
, 1+1 
mp
macrosetae, long and thin notal macrosetae covered with thin barbs along their distal three-fourths; marginal setae are long and some of them are as long and barbed as the macrosetae. The metathoracic legs reach the posterior border of the VII abdominal segment; femora have two long barbed dorsal macrosetae and one ventral macrosetae. The tibia has one ventral short macrosetae, a few distal barbs, and calcars with several long barbs. The tarsus has two rows of smooth ventral setae, slightly thicker than clothing setae and on distal part: three long smooth dorsal setae and one ventral seta; the pretarsus has no lateral processes, with unequal elbowed claws, and with large lateral crests. Urotergite I with 1+1 

post 
1

; urotergite II 1+2 (1+ 
1 paratype
) 

post 
1,2

; urotergite III 2+2 

post 
1,2

; urotergites IV–VII 4+4 

post 
1–4

; urotergite VIII 5+5 

post 
1–5

and abdominal segment IX 7+7 
post
, macrosetae long with barbs along three-fourths. Urosternite I with 5+5, urosternites II–VII 4+4, and urosternite VIII 1+1 macrosetae; urosternal macrosetae are shorter than urotergal macrosetae with long barbs; smooth stylar setae. First urosternite appendages (female) have large, short and subconical appendages, each with apical field with about fifty glandular 

a 
1

setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
