<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
924B9ABA-1630-4832-86EE-19CE73C3E7CB
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Mueggejapyx brehieri
Sendra &amp; Komerički
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Large and elongated body; antennae with 36 antennomeres; trichobothria on antennomeres 
4–6 in
a 3/5/5 pattern; 
a
trichobothria in distal position; 1–2 placoid sensilla on medial and distal antennomere; apical antennomere with 16–18 placoid sensilla; dorsal and ventral side of head with numerous uniformly distributed sM and sm, and several M; five laminae pectinate on maxilla; elongated thoracic segments; and cuticle with tiny micro-holes, pronotum and mesonotum each with 5+5 M, metanotum with 2+2 M; strong internal Y cuticular furcisternite structures in pro-presternites and pro-, meso- and metasternites; urotergites with at most 1+1 M (
ma
), 1+1 M 
1
, 1+1 M 
2–5
; urite X longer than wide, with marked carinae with subparallel margins, with 2+2 intracarinal macrosetae; acropygium rounded; lateral angles of urotergites VI and VII with weakly to moderate lobiform projection; first urosternite with multiperforated surface and rounded protrusions, with 3+3 M on prescutum and 11+11 M on scutum; median glandular organ with seta-shaped sensilla; lateral subcoxal organs with one to three rows of short glandular setae (GS), one row of sensory setae (SS), and a row of setae with large socket; sternites with abundant sm and strong M; cerci strong, elongated, rectilinear and becoming curved subapically, heavily sclerotized with external dorsal and ventral carinae. Both cerci without medial tooth, but with one short row of small round denticles on the right cercus and two rows of small round denticles on the left cercus.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
This genus is dedicated to the memory of the American entomologist Mark Alan Muegge (pronounced Meggy), who died young due to an unfortunate car accident in 2015. He left behind a promising career and was devoted, among other groups, to diplurans; alongside other taxa, he provided a description of the highly cave-adapted japygid from 
Texas
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mixojapyx reddelli
Muegge, 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
