<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Arcofaciella penangensis
(
Muir, 1919
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>No specimen has been collected by the authors.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
The description and illustration are reproduced from 
Muir (1919)
.
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. “Body length: male 
2.1 mm
, female 
2.8 mm
; forewing length: male 
3.6 mm
, female 
4.4 mm
”.
</p>
      <p>COLORATION. “Male ochraceous buff; hind legs slightly fuscous, abdomen bright yellow with a few, small, black spots on sternites, chestnut brown over pygophor and genital styles; forewings chestnut brown, darkest over basal third, a clearer space along middle of costa at the emargination, a dark mark at apex of each apical vein, a small one at apex of claval vein, at fork of cubitus and fork of subcosta and radius, veins the same color as membrane, with numerous small, light granules. Female with forewings lighter than in male, abdomen ochraceous with a small black spot on each sternite, ovipositor same color as pygofer”.</p>
      <p>HEAD AND THORAX. “Width of vertex at base double the length, base nearly double the width of apex; length of face 1.5 times the width, sides slightly arcuate; antennae not reaching base of clypeus, second joint 1.5 times length of first. In lateral view the clypeus at right angle to face, apex of face projecting slightly beyond clypeus; mesonotum considerably arched. Hind femora short, not reaching beyond apex of abdomen; tibiae longer than femora, tarsi much shorter than tibiae, first tarsus subequal in length to other two together, spur small, about as long as first tarsus, fairly broad, thick, a tooth at apex but none on hind margin. Forewings acutely tectiform, compressed beyond apex of abdomen, costal margin shallowly emarginated beyond apex of abdomen, apex acute”.</p>
      <p>MALE GENITALIA. “Pygopher round with a small opening, no distinct dorsal emargination, anal segment short, exposed, without spines, anal style large, lanceolate; genital styles slightly curved, flattened, margins subparallel, apex truncate and produced into a quadrate process on inner margin”.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host plant
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>Malay Peninsula (Penang).</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
