<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Xenorhyncocoris , Miller 1938</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4700903</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F1CE55FFA3FF9EFD9AFC3FFA8A57D3</uri>
         <article-title>Taxonomic review of Xenorhyncocoris Miller (Heteroptera: Reduviidae: Ectrichodiinae), with description of X. attractivus sp. nov. and notes on sexual dimorphism of the genus</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.746.1315</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Xenorhyncocoris
Miller, 1938
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1–59
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Xenorhyncocoris
Miller, 1938: 135
</tp:taxon-name>

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species by original designation: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenorhyncocoris caraboides
Miller, 1938
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Xenorhyncocoris
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Cook 1977: 64

, 70. — 

Maldonado Capriles 1990: 78

. — 

Putshkov &amp; Bérenger 1999: 92

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Revised diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This genus can be recognized within 
<tp:taxon-name>Ectrichodiinae</tp:taxon-name>
by the following combination of characters: macropterous (male, based on 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. attractivus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
) or micropterous (female); head club-shaped, subapically widened, distinctly longer than pronotum; ventral surface of anteocular part flat; antenniferous tubercle surrounded by lump-form process laterally; antennae four-segmented, with basiflagellomere shorter than other segments; labial segment II longest and dorsoventrally flattened, segment III inflated, segment IV flattened laterally; apex of prosternum acute, distinctly surpassing fore coxae; metathoracic gland evaporatorium invisible in lateral view; femora not thickened; apexes of tibiae bulbous; fossula spongiosa present on fore and mid tibiae; abdominal tergite II with three longitudinal ridges. In macropterous male, anterior pronotal lobe distinctly shorter but more than half as long as posterior lobe; scutellum broad, with 1+1 widely separated apical prongs and 1+1 lateral prongs; fore wing nearly reaching apex of abdomen. In micropterous female, anterior pronotal lobe distinctly longer than posterior lobe, swollen; scutellum broad, suberect or erect, with 1+1 widely separated apical prongs; fore wing not reaching apex of scutellum.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Macropterous male
(based on 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. attractivus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
)
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Body generally blackish brown (
Figs 12–14
); ocelli, basi- and disti- (except apical ⅓) flagellomeres, tarsi, anterolateral angles of each connexival segment and spiracles yellowish brown; connexivum faintly tinged with brown; apex of abdomen lighter.
</p>
      <p>
STRUCTURE. Body oblong; body surface generally glabrous, moderately shining and wrinkled. Body surface with decumbent, tiny pubescence, difficult to observe; antennae densely covered with decumbent and erect, short, white setae; inner surfaces of fore trochanter and femur with several sparsely distributed, erect, long, white setae; inner surfaces of tibiae (except basal ⅓) with decumbent and suberect, short setae; apexes of tibiae and ventral surfaces of tarsi densely covered with short golden setae (
Figs 21–22
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 18–20
). Elongate, club-shaped, widened at antenniferous tubercles, 1.35 times as long as pronotum; anteocular part distinctly longer than postocular part, ventral surface flat, midpoint slightly concave; eyes large, strongly protruding laterally, ventral margin far remote from ventral surface of head; width across eyes slightly broader than width between antenniferous tubercles; ocelli situated on tubercle; anteclypeus slightly elevated. Antennal insertion situated before middle of anteocular part but relatively far from apex of head; antenniferous tubercle produced, surrounded by lump-form process laterally (
Fig. 19
); antennae (
Figs 12, 14
) four-segmented, with antennal scape slightly shorter than head, pedicel longest and slightly curved, basiflagellomere shortest and distiflagellomere slightly longer than basiflagellomere. Labium (
Figs 19–20
) robust; labial segment II longest and dorsoventrally flattened, apex reaching posterior margin of eye, strongly curved at base; segment III strongly inflated; segment IV strongly flattened laterally, knife-like.
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM (
Figs 18–19
). Trapezoidal, wider than long; anterior pronotal lobe distinctly shorter but more than half as long as posterior lobe, slightly swollen, with medial longitudinal sulcus restricted in extreme base; posterior lobe broad, with deep, carinulate, medial longitudinal sulcus and a pair of deep, carinulate, lateral sulci; transverse sulcus distinct; lateral pronotal margins constricted; posterior margin slightly convex. Prosternum (
Fig. 20
) strongly developed, distinctly surpassing fore coxae, apically acute. Scutellum (
Fig. 18
) broad, with 1+1 widely separated apical prongs and 1+1 lateral prongs; midpoint of scutellum depressed. Anterior margin of mesopleuron with a row of distinct punctuations (
Fig. 19
). Mesosternum (
Fig. 20
) with a shallow, medial, longitudinal furrow. Metapleuron (
Fig. 19
) longer than high. Metasternum (
Fig. 20
) slightly swollen on both sides. Metathoracic gland callus present in lateral view; metathoracic gland evaporatorium small, not extend dorsally in lateral view.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Slender (
Figs 12–14
). Femora not thickened, slightly sinuated subapically; tibiae slenderer than respective femora, straight; apex of fore tibia bulbous, laterally compressed forming a blunt, weak dorsal carina (
Fig. 21
); tarsomere III subequal to combined length of tarsomeres I and II; fore and mid tibiae with fossula spongiosa occupying about apical 0.15 of their ventral surface (
Fig. 22
).
</p>
      <p>
WINGS. Well developed. Fore wing (
Fig. 23
) nearly reaching apex of abdomen; corium with majority parts of M and Cu separate; membrane with base of outer cell distinctly shorter than inner cell, distal part of R forming a close cell with M, distal part of M extending beyond apex of outer cell. Hind wing (
Fig. 24
) with distal parts of Sc, R and M reaching outer margin; hamus nearly reaching base of hind wing; only one secondary vein.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Ovoid, with lateral outline rounded (
Figs 12, 14
). Abdominal tergite II with three longitudinal ridges. Ventral laterotergites II to VI distinctly separate from respective sternites. Intersternal sutures of segments II to VI carinulate; midpoint of anterior margins of sternites IV to VI curved anteriorly; anterior margin of sternite VII strongly curved anteriorly; segment VII distinctly expanded posteriorly (
Fig. 25
); segment VIII invisible at resting state (
Fig. 25
). Spiracles round.
</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA. Pygophore (
Figs 26–28
) short, oblong; median process directed dorsoposteriad. Parameres (
Figs 29–32
) relatively stout, bent, with a subapical process.
</p>
      <p>
Micropterous female
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Body generally brown to blackish brown (
Figs 1–3
, 
15–17
, 
46–48
, 
57–59
); tarsi, anterolateral and posterolateral angles of each connexival segment, apical margin of abdomen, spiracles and valvula I yellowish brown.
</p>
      <p>STRUCTURE. Body shape and vestiture similar to those in male, but differs in the following characteristics: body robust; antennal scape and basal half of pedicel bare; lateral margins of prosternum with suberect, short, golden setae; head thickened, 1.8–2.2 times as long as pronotum; eyes small; width between antenniferous tubercles broader than width across eyes; ocelli strongly reduced; anteclypeus not elevated; antennal scape distinctly shorter than head; pronotum nearly square; anterior pronotal lobe much longer than and as wide as or slightly narrower than posterior lobe, swollen dorsally; medial longitudinal sulcus of pronotum reduced to deep, medial depression; lateral margins of anterior pronotal lobe marginated; posterior margin of pronotum concave; prosternum much longer, reaching or surpassing anterior margins of mid coxae; scutellum suberect or erect, with prongs weakly developed; fossula spongiosa larger, occupying about apical 0.2 of ventral surface of fore and mid tibiae; fore wing not reaching apex of scutellum; abdomen broader, with ventral surface slightly flattened in middle.</p>
      <p>
FEMALE GENITALIA. Platelike (
Figs 10–11
, 
42–43
, 
55–56
, 
59
); tergite VIII transverse, anterior and posterior margins nearly straight; tergite IX large, trapezoidal, with transverse depression subapically; posteromedian margin of valvifer I slightly sinuate; valvula I small, triangular, with posterior margin slightly concave; styloid visible in resting state.
</p>
      <p>
Diversity and distribution
</p>
      <p>
Four species, occurring in the Oriental Region (
Fig. 60
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Female-based key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Xenorhyncocoris
Miller, 1938
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Body length about 
37 mm
; head 2.2 times as long as pronotum; anteocular part 1.3 times as long as postocular part; labial segment II surpassing posterior margin of eye, curved dorsally, approaching ventral surface of head; apex of prosternum almost reaching posterior margins of mid coxal cavities ..................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. caraboides
Miller, 1938
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Body length about 
34 mm
or less; head 1.8–1.9 times as long as pronotum; anteocular part 1.4–1.7 times as long as postocular part; labial segment II reaching posterior margin of eye, straight or curved dorsally; apex of prosternum reaching middle of mid coxae or less .................................... 2

</p>
      <p>

2. Body blackish brown; labial segment II curved dorsally, approaching ventral surface of head; pronotum 1.15 times as broad as its length along midline; scutellum erect; fore wing reaching middle of scutellum ..................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. attractivus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
– Body brown; labial segment II straight; pronotum as broad as its length along midline; scutellum suberect; fore wing surpassing middle of scutellum ......................................................................... 3
</p>
      <p>

3. Anteocular part 1.4 times as long as postocular part; labial segment II 1.9 times as long as segment III, with ventral surface thickened at apical ⅔; prosternum reaching anterior margins of mid coxae ...................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. princeps
Miller, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Anteocular part 1.7 times as long as postocular part; labial segment II 1.6 times as long as segment III, with apex bulbous; prosternum reaching middle of mid coxae .................................................... ........................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
X. schoenitzeri
Putshkov &amp; Bérenger, 1999
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
