<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Nebalia strausi Risso
                        1826</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4577438</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03F287D25033AA28FDCBFE0FFE1A5BEE</uri>
                  <article-title>Leptostracans (Crustacea: Phyllocarida) from mud volcanoes at the
                        Gulf of Cadiz (NE Atlantic) with description of a new species of
                        Sarsinebalia Dahl, 1985</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia strausi Risso, 1826 </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 1–5 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia straus Risso, 1826: 84 </tp:taxon-name> , pl. V, fig. 20. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia straus </tp:taxon-name> – Koçak &amp; Katagan 2006: 321 ,
                  figs 1–3. — Koçak et al . 2007: 449 , figs 1–3. </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia strausi </tp:taxon-name> – Dahl 1985: 155 , figs 63–79. —
                  Ledoyer 1997: 34 , fig. 4. — Moreira et al . 2004: 84 , figs 1–7; 2009b: 101, lam.
                  1, figs 1–3. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> MOROCCO • 1 preovigerous ♀ , 4 ♂♂ , 3 juveniles ; Gulf of
                        Cadiz , Mercator MV; 35°17.916′ N , 06°38.709′ W ; 354 m depth ; 2 Mar. 2008
                        ; St 64PE284_12750W, experimentally deployed wood substrate ;
                        DBUA0001677.01.W </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 3
                        preovigerous ♀♀ , 8 ♂♂ , 4 juveniles ; same locality and coordinates as for
                        preceding; 3 Mar. 2008 ; St 64PE284_12752A, experimentally deployed alfalfa
                        substrate ; DBUA0001677.02.A </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description of female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Preovigerous females measuring TL 5.275–5.8 mm , RL 0.925 –1.025 mm ,
                  DCL 2.15– 2.25 mm , LCL 2.675–3.0 mm, CH 1.825–1.95 mm . </p>
            <p> CARAPACE, ROSTRUM AND EYE. Carapace covering at least lateral sides of pleonites
                  1–4; LCL about 1.5 times CH . Rostrum long, with parallel margins, length about
                  2.3 times width, 0.45 times DCL ( Fig. 2A, C ). Eye about 0.65 times as long as
                  rostrum; ommatidia numerous, distributed about 5/6 of eye ( Fig. 2B ); dark
                  pigment in most ommatidia. </p>
            <p> ANTENNAE. Antennule peduncle fourth article with anterior row of 5–6 simple setae
                  and two distal robust setae, proximal one shorter ( Fig. 2D ), juveniles (&lt; 4
                  mm TL) with one robust seta; antennular scale length 2.25–2.4 times width;
                  flagellum with up to 11–13 articles. Antenna peduncle third article lateral margin
                  with three proximal plumose setae on proximal half and three distal spine-like
                  setae ( Fig. 2 E–F); flagellum with up to 11–14 articles ( Fig. 2E ). </p>
            <p> MOUTHPARTS. Mandibular palp second article with two subequal setae: one seta
                  setulose along distal half on lateral margin at mid-length and one simple seta on
                  distal third; third article slightly longer than second ( Fig. 3A ). Maxilla I
                  palp well-developed, about 4.5 times as long as protopod ( Fig. 3B ). Maxilla II
                  endopod proximal article about 1.5–1.6 times as long as distal article; exopod
                  longer than endopod first article ( Fig. 3C ). </p>
            <p> THORACOPODS. Endopod slightly longer than exopod ( Fig. 3 D–E); endopod distal
                  article slightly enlarged, with several (ca 10) setae; endopod segmentation weak.
                  Thoracopod VIII epipod smaller than in other thoracopods and lacking setae ( Fig.
                  3F ). </p>
            <p> PLEONITES AND PLEOPODS. Pleonite IV epimeron posterolateral corner slightly pointed
                  ( Fig. 4C ). Pleonites VI–VII posterodorsal border bearing denticles acutely
                  pointed ( Fig. 4 G–H). Pleopod I exopod about 0.72 times as long as protopod and
                  endopod; lateral border with ‘comb-row’ of ca 30 bi-pectinate setae (sensu
                  Walker-Smith 2000 ) ( Fig. 4A ); protopod with long seta near base of exopod,
                  hardly reaching middle of ‘comb-row’. Pleopods II–IV exopod with row of 5–7 pairs
                  of smooth setae (‘spine pairs’) ( Fig. 4B ). Pleopod IV protopod posterior border
                  with four serrations. Pleopod V distal article 3.4 times as long as wide, with
                  five simple setae along distolateral and terminal margins, proximal-most the
                  shortest ( Fig. 4D ). Pleopod VI 2.0 times as long as wide, with five simple setae
                  along lateral and terminal margins, distal-most the longest ( Fig. 4E ). Pleopod
                  V–VI pairs with acute triangular process between rami bases. </p>
            <p> Fig. 2. <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia strausi Risso, 1826 </tp:taxon-name> . Preovigerous
                  female (DBUA0001677.01.W). A . Rostrum, eye and carapace outline, lateral view. B
                  . Eye and supra-orbital plate, lateral view. C . Rostrum, dorsal view. D .
                  Antennule, lateral view. E . Antenna, lateral view. F . Antenna, peduncle third
                  article, lateral view. D–E: only selected setae illustrated. </p>
            <p> ANAL SOMITE, ANAL PLATES AND UROPODS. Anal somite 0.8–0.95 times as long as pleonite
                  VII. Anal plates acutely tapering distally, ‘shoulder’ well-defined ( Fig. 4F, I
                  ). Uropods 0.8–0.92 times as long as pleonite VII+ anal somite; terminal seta 1.7
                  times as long as ramus. </p>
            <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia strausi Risso, 1826 </tp:taxon-name> . Preovigerous
                  female (DBUA0001677.01.W). A . Mandibular palp. B . Maxilla I. C . Maxilla II. D .
                  Thoracopod II. E . Thoracopod V. F . Thoracopod VIII. D–F: same scale bar; C:
                  setules and endites’ setae not illustrated; D–F: only selected setae illustrated. </p>
            <p> Fig. 4. <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia strausi Risso, 1826 </tp:taxon-name> . Preovigerous
                  female (DBUA0001677.01.W). A . Pleopod I, lateral view. B . Pleopod II, lateral
                  view. C . Pleonite IV, epimeron and pleopod IV protopod, lateral view. D . Pleopod
                  V, ventral view. E . Pleopod VI, ventral view. F . Anal plates, ventral view. G .
                  Pleonite VI, posterior dorsal and laterodorsal border, denticles. H . Pleonite
                  VII, posterior dorsal and laterodorsal border, denticles. I . Right uropod and
                  anal plate, ventral view. A–C, D–E, G–H: same scale bars; A–B, I: plumose setae
                  not illustrated. </p>
            <p> Description of male </p>
            <p> TL 3.95–5.375 mm , RL 0.825–1.05 mm , DCL 1.575 –2.125 mm , LCL 2.2–3.0 mm, CH 1.625
                  –1.925 mm . Carapace proportions (LCL: CH ) similar to females ( Fig. 5A ).
                  Ommatidia and dark pigment covering 5/6 of eye ( Fig. 5B ). Antennule peduncle
                  fourth article with 1–2 distal robust setae; antennular scale proportions similar
                  to females (2.25–2.30 times as long as wide) ( Fig. 5D ); flagellum with up to
                  10–12 articles, thicker than in females. Antenna peduncle third article lateral
                  margin with similar setation as in females; flagellum with many articles (&gt; 30)
                  but not surpassing TL ( Fig. 5C ). Pleonites VI–VII denticles acutely pointed.
                  Pleopod IV protopod posterior border with four serrations. Uropods length similar
                  to females. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia strausi </tp:taxon-name> is a well-known species that is
                  characterized by having ommatidia and dark pigment extending through most of the
                  eye; the antennular scale is more than twice as long as wide; the fourth article
                  of antennule peduncle bears two distal robust setae of different length; the
                  exopod of maxilla II surpasses the level of articulation of endopod articles, and
                  the endopod proximal article is clearly longer than the distal one; the
                  posterolateral corner of the pleonite IV epimeron is not acutely produced; the
                  posterior margin of pleopod IV protopod bears four serrations; and the
                  posterodorsal denticles of pleonites VI–VII are acutely pointed ( Dahl 1985 ;
                  Ledoyer 1997 ; Moreira et al . 2004 ). Furthermore, the terminal simple seta of
                  the pleopod I protopod barely reaches half-length of the ‘comb-row’ and the
                  uropods are at least as long as pleonite VII and anal somite combined, and
                  slightly longer in mature specimens ( Dahl 1985 ). </p>
            <p> Fig. 5. <tp:taxon-name> Nebalia strausi Risso, 1826 </tp:taxon-name> . Male
                  (DBUA0001677.01.W). A . Rostrum, eye and carapace outline, lateral view. B . Eye
                  and supra-orbital plate, lateral view. C . Antenna, lateral view. D . Antennule,
                  lateral view. C–D: only selected setae illustrated. </p>
            <p> Specimens from Mercator MV mostly agree with the diagnosis of the species. The only
                  minor difference is that the uropods are slightly shorter, but this may be due to
                  the state of development, i.e., no specimen was fully mature. Note that the
                  organic substrates where the specimens were found were enclosed by a 2 mm mesh
                  size net, and it is likely that the specimens settled on the substrates as
                  juveniles just released from the brood pouch. The anal plates have an even more
                  prominent shoulder than in the Mediterranean specimens described by Dahl (1985) ;
                  those reported by Ledoyer (1997) bear, in turn, a gently sloping ‘shoulder’,
                  whereas there is almost no ‘shoulder’ at all in those described by Moreira et al.
                  (2004) from the NW Iberian Peninsula. Most specimens bear two robust setae on the
                  fourth article of antennule peduncle but small males and juveniles bear instead
                  only one. Moreira et al. (2004) reported similar observations in immature females
                  whereas ovigerous and postovigerous females always had two robust setae of
                  different length. Number of setae is known to vary during ontogeny ( Dahl 1985 )
                  and therefore this character should be considered with care for identification
                  unless fully-grown specimens are available; this also applies for the number of
                  articles in the antennae flagella that are fewer on juveniles. On the other hand,
                  some minor variations have also been reported for specimens from the eastern
                  Mediterranean ( Koçak et al . 2010 ) and therefore the possibility of a complex of
                  species across its wide distribution range has been suggested ( Koçak et al . 2011
                  ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Ecology </p>
            <p> Recorded from the intertidal to depths of 140 m , in rocky substrates and sandy and
                  muddy soft bottoms, and among the seagrasses <tp:taxon-name> Zostera marina
                  </tp:taxon-name> L., 1753, <tp:taxon-name> Z. noltii Hornem., 1832
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Cymodocea </tp:taxon-name> sp. and
                        <tp:taxon-name> Posidonia oceanica </tp:taxon-name> (L.) Delile, 1813 ( Dahl
                  1985 ; Ledoyer 1997 ; Moreira et al . 2004 , 2009a , 2009b ; Koçak et al . 2007 ;
                  Latry &amp; Droual 2020 ). The present findings of the species from experimentally
                  deployed wood and alfalfa substrates at the Mercator MV extend its known
                  bathymetric range to depths of 354 m . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> SW European Atlantic from north western Ireland to NW Iberian Peninsula ( Dahl 1985
                  ; Moreira et al . 2004 , 2009a , 2009b ; McCormack et al . 2016 ; Latry &amp;
                  Droual 2020 ); Mediterranean Sea ( Dahl 1985 ; Ledoyer 1997 ; Koçak &amp; Katagan
                  2006 ; Koçak et al . 2011 ; Latry &amp; Droual 2020 ); Canary Islands ( Dahl 1985
                  ; Moreira et al . 2009b ), Madeira and St Helena ( Dahl 1985 ); Moroccan margin of
                  the Gulf of Cadiz (this study; Fig. 1 ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
