<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Deltochilum tenuistriatum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn: lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
9BBED604-6552-43D2-B7AF-44B2DF95DDF7
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1E
, 
2E
, 
3E
, 
4E
, 
5E
, 
6E
, 
7E
, 
8E
, 
10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. quasistriatum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
by having the striae I–VII conspicuous (
Figs 1D–E
, 
4D–E
), but III–VII successively thinner and more ill-defined and by the pronotal disc with irregular shiny points contiguous to punctures (
Fig. 3D–E
). However, it can be distinguished by having the first stria subequal to second stria, smallest interstrial punctures (
Fig. 4E
) and by pygidial punctures which are smallest and most disperse (
Fig. 5E
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From Latin 
tenuis
'weak' + 
stria
in reference to the ill-defined striae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
VENEZUELA
• 
1 ♂
; 
Bolívar
, 

10 km
E of S. [San] F. [Francisco] Yuruani

; 
5°1′34″ N
, 
61°2′34″ W
; alt. 

1300 m

; 

8–10 Jul. 1987

; 
S. and J. Peck
leg.; 
carrion traps
, 
Gran Sabana, forest
; [aedeagus and endophallus extracted]; 
CMNEN
WSD00041745
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS AND COLOR. 
Holotype
male, length 
8 mm
, humeral width 
5.2 mm
. Dark green with red reflections dorsally (
Fig. 1E
). Black ventrally, with shiny red reflections on metaventrite, metaventral process, meso- and metafemora and ventrite VI (
Fig. 6E
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 2E
). Dorsal inter-ocular distance approximately eight times width of the eye. Punctures on frons separated by less than one diameter of each puncture. Punctures on head disc separated by less than one diameter of each puncture, almost contiguous.
</p>
      <p>
PRONOTUM (
Fig. 3E
). Medial angle projected. Punctures on disc separated by less than one diameter, almost contiguous. Shiny points on disc irregular and contiguous to punctures.
</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA (
Figs 1E
, 
4E
). Carina of ninth interstria reaching middle of elytral length. Punctures on first stria subequal in size to second stria, but denser. Striae I–VII conspicuous. Width of first stria subequal to second stria. Striae III–VII narrow and ill-defined, successively narrower and more ill-defined, with VII almost inconspicuous. Width third stria approximately 
1/40
th
the distance between striae II and III. Stria VIII conspicuous only laterally, discontinuous in some parts and reaching apex of carina of the ninth interstria. Punctures of second interstria on disc separated by less than one diameter, on third by one diameter. Punctures of third interstria on disc occupying about 
1/14
th
the distance between striae II and III. Apical tubercles on interstriae III, V–VII (
Fig. 5E
).
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN (
Fig. 6E
). Width of expansion of ventrite I, on ventrite III, subequal to distance between clypeal teeth; expansion reaching distal margin of ventrite IV. Margins of expansion between ventrites II–III forming an acute angle. Expansion on ventrite IV narrower than on ventrite III, and margins almost parallel. Apex of expansion rounded. Basal area of expansion with punctures separated by less than one diameter, almost contiguous.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Apex of mesotibia on ventral-internal margin with a small spatulate expansion. Expansion of metafemur 1.7 × wider than the width of metafemur basal to expansion. Internal margin of metatibia with large tubercles, occupying almost all metatibial length.</p>
      <p>
PYGIDIUM (
Fig. 5E
). Most of the punctures separated by one diameter; punctures basally denser than punctures on disc. Discal punctures occupying approximately 
1/38
th
the width on middle of pygidium.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA (
Figs 7E
, 
8E
). Aedeagus as described in the 
<tp:taxon-name>
gilli
</tp:taxon-name>
species group. Medial endophallite sinuate. Sub-medial area of endophallus with scales.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This species is only known from the 
holotype
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Known distribution
</p>
      <p>
Venezuela
. 
Bolívar
: 
10 km
E San Francisco Yuruani (
Fig. 10
, white eight-point star).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
