<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
4AAADA13-1225-4927-A258-42AE8DF369BC
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis baiabonita
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(here described and designated).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
Other species
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis amazonica
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(here described).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the new genus is a contraction of ‘ 
Brasilo
’, after 
Brazil
, the country from which it is here described, and ‘ 
dopsis
’, referring to the stem of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cypridopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Cp sub-triangular in lateral view, with LV mildly overlapping RV along all sides. LV anteriorly, ventrally and posteriorly with a well-developed, largely inwardly displaced inner list, anteriorly with a submarginal selvage. RV anteriorly with submarginal inner list, posteriorly with one inner list and a marginal selvage. A2 with natatory setae well-developed, reaching well beyond the end claws. T 
1 in
female with two short setae a; seta d present in female, absent in male; setae b absent in both sexes. T2 with one short seta d2, seta d1 absent. T3 distally with incompletely developed pincer organ, fourth segment fused with third segment. CR in female with cylindrical base.
</p>
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
belongs to the cypridopsine genera where the LV overlaps the RV; only six other genera belong to that group (see 
Table 1
). The new genus differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Austrocypridopsis
McKenzie, 1982
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cavernocypris
Hartmann, 1964
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudocypridopsis
Karanovic, 1999
</tp:taxon-name>
by the long natatory setae on the A2 (short to very short in the other three genera). It further differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Austrocypridopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
in the shape of the base of the CR, (triangular in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Austrocypridopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
, cylindrical in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
) and in the shape of the valves in lateral view (rectangular in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Austrocypridopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cavernocypris
</tp:taxon-name>
also has a triangular base of the CR and furthermore lacks all inner lists and selvages on both valves, while the T1 has a seta b (missing in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudocypridopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
also lacks inner lists and selvages; while the CR is missing in both males and females. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
further differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cypridopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
s. str.
Brady, 1867 by the general shape of the Cp (much broader in dorsal view in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cypridopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
), while the posteroventral inner list in the LV does not run (sub-)parallel to the valve margin in this latter genus (it does so in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
), while the anterior inner list in this valve runs less than halfway the anterior valve margin (all the way to the dorsal margin in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
). The base of the CR in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cypridopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
is triangular, while it is elongated in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
Neocypridopsis
Klie, 1940
</tp:taxon-name>
has a very different shape of the Cp (rather high and swollen in dorsal view), but more importantly has the fourth segment of the T3 separate from the third segment, much like in 
<tp:taxon-name>Candonidae</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tungucypridopsis
Victor, 1983
</tp:taxon-name>
, finally, is ill-described which makes a comparison with the present new genus difficult. It appears to lack the inner lists on both valves, which are moreover much larger than in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
(
0.6 mm
versus 
0.4 mm
– see 
Table 2
).
</p>
      <p>
Table 1.
Present list of tribes and genera in the subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cypridopsinae 
Kaufmann, 1900
</tp:taxon-name>
. New tribe and new genera here described are in bold.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Cyprettadopsis
Savatenalinton, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
(placed in a separate tribe by this author) has a similar valve shape, including inner lists, but has (incomplete) marginal septae and a series of large ventral pores along the outer lists, which are both absent in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
, while the T3 also has a separate fourth segment (fused into an incomplete pincer in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Brasilodopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
