<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Zagrotes apophysalis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
E8CB0012-A945-45E7-9231-97E024B16661
</p>
      <p>
Figs 24–26
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Same as for the genus.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The specific epithet is an adjective and refers to the greatly enlarged retrolateral tibial apophysis of the male palp.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
♂
; 
Kohgiluyeh
&amp; 
Boyer-Ahmad Province
, 
Seyyed Safi
; 

May 2017

; 
A. Hosseinpour
leg.; 
MHNG
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
IRAN
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MHNG

• 

1 ♀
; 
Hormozgan Province
, 

75 km
N of Bandar Abbas

, 
Siahu
; 
27°33′ N
, 
55°38′ E
; 

16 Feb. 2018

; 
A. Zamani
leg.; 
MHNG

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
Habitus as in 
Fig. 24A
. Total length 4.29. Carapace 1.96 long, 1.38 wide. Eye sizes and interdistance of PMEs: AME = 0.09, ALE = 0.08, PME = 0.09, PLE = 0.07, PME–PME = 0.06. Carapace, chelicerae, maxillae, labium and sternum light brown. Legs the same color as carapace and without annulations. Chelicerae (
Fig. 24E
) with 5 pro- and 2 retromarginal teeth. Abdomen light grayish brown, without any pattern; scutum short, triangular, almost two times as wide as long. Spinnerets light grayish and uniform in color. Measurements of legs: I: 5.60 (1.48, 1.03, 1.23, 1.09, 0.77), II: 4.51 (1.16, 0.87, 0.95, 0.93, 0.60), III: 3.79 (1.06, 0.54, 0.74, 0.88, 0.57), IV: 6.00 (1.53, 0.90, 1.28, 1.52, 0.77).
</p>
      <p>
Palp as in 
Figs 24C–D
, 
25
. Femur 3 times as long as wide, slightly longer than patella+ tibia, or cymbium; patella modified, longer than tibia, with swollen proximal part; tibia modified, swollen retrolaterally, 2 times wider in the middle than in base, apophysis long, about 4 times as long as wide, deeply bifid, with ventral arm rounded on the tip and dorsal arm spine-like, sharply pointed; cymbium elongated, 2.3 times as long as wide, with cone-shaped tip; tegulum twice as long as wide, with large median apophysis, as long as bulb’s width, apophysis with 2 arms; spermophor U-shaped in ventral view; tegulum with membranous, finger-shaped apophysis near the base of embolus (not easily discernible); embolus filamentous, originating at the middle of the tegulum and encircling it, reaching the retrolateral margin of the cymbium.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 24.
<tp:taxon-name>
Zagrotes apophysalis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(A, C–E = holotype, ♂, MHNG; B, F–G = paratype, ♀ from Kohgiluyeh &amp; Boyer-Ahmad Province, MHNG). 
A–B
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
C–D
. Palp, ventral and retrolateral views. 
E
. Chelicerae, posterior view. 
F–G
. Epigyne, ventral and dorsal views. Abbreviation: 
Ds
= digitiform scape. Scale bars: A = 1 mm; B = 0.5 mm; C–D, F–G = 0.1 mm; E = 0.2 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 25.
<tp:taxon-name>
Zagrotes apophysalis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (MHNG), palp. 
A–D
. Palp, ventral, retrolateral, dorsal and retrodorsal views. 
E, H
. Bulb, apical view. 
F–G
. Bulb, prolateral and proventral views. 
I–J
. Full palp, dorsolateral and ventral views. Scale bars: 0.2 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
paratype
, Kohgiluyeh &amp; Boyer-Ahmad Province)
</p>
      <p>
Habitus as in 
Fig. 24B
. Total length 5.55. Carapace 2.14 long, 1.46 wide. Eye sizes and interdistance of PMEs: AME = 0.07, ALE = 0.09, PME = 0.09, PLE = 0.06, PME–PME = 0.06. Coloration and somatic features as in male. Measurements of legs: I: 5.87 (1.51, 1.10, 1.33, 1.08, 0.85), II: 4.61 (1.22, 0.76, 1.00, 0.93, 0.70), III: 4.24 (1.15, 0.64, 0.85, 0.94, 0.66), IV: 6.07 (1.58, 0.89, 1.28, 1.53, 0.79).
</p>
      <p>
Epigyne as in 
Figs 24F–G
, 
26
. Epigynal plate longer than wide; with distinct scape (
Ds
), basal part conical, goffered, tip heavily sclerotized, digitiform; posterior part of atrium with distinct margins and copulatory openings; copulatory ducts long, coiled and ending posteriorly in broad sacs.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known from the listed localities in Kohgiluyeh &amp; Boyer-Ahmad and 
Hormozgan
Provinces, southwestern and southern 
Iran
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
