<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Haplodrassus qashqai Zamani &amp; Chatzaki &amp; Esyunin &amp; Marusik 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4906477</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9819795D1F9F662D046A64AA88FE0488</uri>
         <article-title>One new genus and nineteen new species of ground spiders (Araneae: Gnaphosidae) from Iran, with other taxonomic considerations</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.751.1381</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Haplodrassus qashqai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
0EE16C9F-6CC6-4AF4-8343-750215C9FBD6
</p>
      <p>
Figs 12–14
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new species differs from other males (
<tp:taxon-name>
H. dalmatensis
(L. Koch, 1866)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. omissus
</tp:taxon-name>
(O. Pickard- Cambridge, 1872), 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. orientalis
(L. Koch, 1866)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. rufipes
(Lucas, 1846)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. securifer
Bosmans &amp; Abrous, 2018
</tp:taxon-name>
) that have one or two pointed teeth on the embolic apophysis and/or have the indented tibial apophysis by a combination of a largely serrated inner surface of the embolic apophysis and a tibial apophysis with a single pointed tip. Females of the new species resemble those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. pseudosignifer
Marusik, Hippa &amp; Koponen, 1996
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. typhon
(Simon, 1878)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. invalidus
(O. Pickard-Cambridge, 1872)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. concertor
(Simon, 1878)
</tp:taxon-name>
in having the epigynal plate with almost parallel margins and conical posterior ends but differ by the presence of distinct longitudinal folds along the spermathecal sacs (vs bell-shaped in all others).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet is a noun in apposition, referring to a conglomeration of clans in 
Iran
consisting of mostly Turkic peoples but also Lurs, Kurds and Arabs.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
♂
; 
Hormozgan Province
, 

75 km
N of Bandar Abbas

, 
Siahu
; 
27°33′ N
, 
55°38′ E
; 

16 Feb. 2018

; 
A. Zamani
leg.; 
MHNG
.

</p>
      <p>
Fig. 12.
<tp:taxon-name>
Haplodrassus qashqai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(A–B = paratype, ♀ from Lorestan Province, MHNG; C–H = holotype, ♂, MHNG). 
A, C
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B, D
. Habitus, ventral view. 
E–F
. Bulb, ventral and proventral views. 
G–H
. Palp, ventral and retrolateral views. Scale bars: 0.2 mm, unless stated otherwise.
</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
IRAN
• 
1 ♀
; 
Khuzestan Province
, 
Dezful
; 

Mar. 2018

; 
A. Zamani
leg.; 
MHNG

• 

4 ♂♂
, 
6 ♀♀
; 
Lorestan Province
, 
Pol-e Dokhtar
; 

Apr. 2017

; 
A. Zamani
leg.; 
MHNG

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>
Habitus as in 
Fig. 12C–D
. Total length 5.00. Carapace 2.26 long, 1.87 wide. Eye sizes and interdistance of PMEs: AME = 0.13, ALE = 0.15, PME = 0.14, PLE = 0.10, PME–PME = 0.08. Carapace dark brown, lighter in pars thoracica, with faded radiating lines from fovea to submarginal area. Chelicerae, maxillae and labium dark brown. Sternum light brown, slightly darker anteriorly. Chelicera with 2 pro- and 2 retromarginal teeth. Legs light yellowish and without annulations. Abdomen dorsally dark gray, with numerous transverse light bands, forming a patch posteriorly, ventrally with distinct tracheal marks and a V-shaped light pattern surrounding them. Spinnerets light gray and uniform in color. Measurements of legs: I: 6.19 (1.76, 1.00, 1.42, 1.16, 0.85), II missing, III: 4.74 (1.32, 0.68, 0.91, 1.02, 0.81), IV: 6.82 (1.82, 0.96, 1.47, 1.60, 0.97).
</p>
      <p>
Palp as in 
Figs 12E–H
, 
13A–D
, 
14A–C
. Tibial apophysis as long as tibia, paddle-shaped, angled dorsally, with a pointed tip; embolic apophysis with distinctly serrated inner surface; embolus with wide, blunt end and with an additional pointed outgrowth that arises from its base.
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
paratype
, 
Lorestan Province
)
</p>
      <p>
Habitus as in 
Figs 12A–B
. Total length 5.49. Carapace 2.54 long, 1.93 wide. Eye sizes and interdistance of PMEs: AME = 0.09, ALE = 0.14, PME = 0.15, PLE = 0.09, PME–PME = 0.05. Carapace, chelicerae, maxillae, labium and sternum light yellowish brown. Chelicera with 3 pro- and 2 retromarginal teeth. Legs light gray and without annulations. Abdomen dorsally dark gray, with two longitudinal light gray bands leading to numerous transverse light bands, ventrally with a light gray patch posteriorly. Spinnerets light gray and uniform in color. Measurements of legs: I: 6.74 (1.97, 1.13, 1.55, 1.24, 0.85), II: 5.99 (1.76, 1.01, 1.28, 1.04, 0.90), III: 5.24 (1.55, 0.78, 0.98, 1.07, 0.86), IV: 7.41 (2.05, 1.08, 1.67, 1.79, 0.82).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 13.
<tp:taxon-name>
Haplodrassus qashqai
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ from Lorestan Province (MHNG), SEM graphs of the male palp. 
A
. Ventral view. 
B
. Embolus, dorsal view. 
C
. Apical portion of bulb. 
D
. Tibial apophysis, retrolateral view. Scale bars: 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Epigyne as in 
Fig. 14D–H
. Epigynal plate about 1.3 times as long as wide, with weakly sclerotized anterior margin; atrium long and thin, almost 2 times as long as wide and ⅓ of epigynal plate width, with parallel lateral margins converging posteriorly and lateral sclerotization at anterior half; receptacles round, as wide as the narrowest part of the atrium; fertilization ducts long; distinct anterior bursae present with longitudinal folds; lateral anterior glandular heads at outer edges of the bursae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known from the listed localities in 
Hormozgan
, 
Khuzestan
and 
Lorestan
Provinces, southwestern to southern 
Iran
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
