<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Scotophaeus anahita
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
B5C9F25A-2966-43AF-91AF-994A6B783F96
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 19A–C, G–H
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The two new species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scotophaeus
</tp:taxon-name>
described here, 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
anahita
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
elburzensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, are very similar in the structure of their epigynal sclerotization and somatic characters but are clearly different in the structure of the endogyne. In 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
anahita
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, the lateral ducts are spiraled (vs relatively straight, slightly curved outward in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
elburzensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
) and the terminal lobes are smaller than the basal lobes and located anteriorly (vs larger than the basal lobes and located posteriorly in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
elburzensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
) (cf. 
Fig. 19B, E
). Similarly, they resemble 
<tp:taxon-name>
S
. 
nanus

Wunderlich, 
1995
</tp:taxon-name>
in the form of the epigynal atrium, but the configuration of the spermathecal cluster is very different from both of the new species (see 
Wunderlich 1995
: figs 6–8).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The specific epithet is a noun in apposition and refers to the divinity of the Waters (associated with fertility, healing and wisdom) in Persian mythology.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
♀
; 
Isfahan Province
, 
Qamsar
&amp; 
Barzok Protected Area
, 

55 km
SW of Qamsar

, 

14 km
NE of Kamoo

, 
near the road of Gargash observatory
; 
33°37′ N
, 
51°19′ E
; 

2710 m
a.s.l.

; 

19 May 2016

; 
P. Ponel
leg.; 
ZMMU
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
Total length 11.7. Carapace 5.90 long, 3.80 wide. Eye sizes and interdistance of PMEs: AME = 0.18, ALE = 0.18, PME = 0.20, PLE = 0.20, PME–PME 0.15. Carapace yellowish brown, covered with dark, short setae. Chelicera (
Fig. 19G
) dark brown (almost black), with 3 promarginal teeth. Sternum yellowish brown with dark border, covered with black setae. Maxillae and labium dark brown with white tip. Maxillae longer than wide, with medial indentation on the external edge. Legs yellowish brown with lighter femora and darker brownish metatarsi and tarsi. Abdomen gray, covered with white plumose hairs and dark setae dorsally, and yellow with dark setae ventrally. Spinnerets yellowish brown and uniform in color. Measurements of legs: I: 14.90 (4.18, 2.43, 3.48, 2.83, 2.00), II: 13.95 (3.93, 2.28, 3.18, 2.75, 1.83), III: 13.45 (3.75, 1.90, 2.95, 3.00, 1.85), IV: 18.23 (4.85, 2.20, 4.08, 5.05, 2.05). Spination: I: Fe: 2d, 1pl; Ti: 4v; Mt: 2v. II: Fe: 2d, 2pl; Ti: 4v; Mt: 2v. III: Fe: 2d, 4pl, 2rl; Ti: 1d, 3pl, 3rl, 6v; Mt: 5pl, 6rl, 9v. IV: Fe: 3d, 2pl, 2rl; Ti: 2d, 3pl, 3rl, 6v; Mt: 6pl, 6rl, 6v.
</p>
      <p>
Epigyne as in 
Fig. 19A–C, H
. Epigynal plate almost as long as wide, with transverse atrium posteriorly; atrium with chitinized ʻridgeʼ of the lateral ducts (
rLD
) posteriorly and bordered by lateral margin (
Lm
); lateral ducts (
Ld
) wide and spiraled; each receptacle with two pairs of concentric sacs (
Bl
and 
Tl
); dorsal blind tubes arise from the second pair.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality in 
Isfahan Province
, central 
Iran
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
