<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Xylothrips flavipes</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4716294</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/03FA5D650C66FFEDEA6C1177597DFE55</uri>
                  <article-title>A review of the powderpost beetle genera Xylothrips Lesne, 1901 and
                        Calophagus Lesne, 1902 (Coleoptera: Bostrichidae: Bostrichinae:
                        Xyloperthini)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://zoobank.org/d6aaf507-ac02-47e8-95db-47b936e625bc</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Xylothrips flavipes ( Illiger,1801 ) </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 1C–D , 2 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Apate flavipes Illiger, 1801:171 </tp:taxon-name> (male). </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Apate dominicanus Fabricius, 1801: 380 </tp:taxon-name> (female).
                  Synonymy in Lesne 1901: 621 . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Bostrichus mutilatus Walker, 1858: 286 </tp:taxon-name> . Synonymy
                  in Lesne 1901: 622 . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Bostrichus iracundus Snellen van Vollenhoven, 1869: 10
                  </tp:taxon-name> . Synonymy in Lesne 1901: 622 . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Apate sinuatus </tp:taxon-name> (non Fabricius, 1792) – Stephens
                  1830: 351. Synonymy in Lesne 1901: 622 . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Apate religiosae </tp:taxon-name> – Fairmaire 1850: 50 (in part).
                  Synonymy in Lesne 1901: 622 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
            <p> Diagnosis </p>
            <p> This species is easily separable from <tp:taxon-name> X. religiosus </tp:taxon-name>
                  by the reddish brown body, the shallower frontoclypeal suture, the absence of
                  punctures on the lateral part of the pronotum, the extension of the inferolateral
                  callus, which converges into the lower lateral margin of the elytra ( Fig. 2B ),
                  and the apical sutural angles raised with tubercles beneath the margin. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> The author has examined the type of <tp:taxon-name> Apate flavipes </tp:taxon-name>
                  from ‘Afrika’ in MNB , and the type of <tp:taxon-name> Bostrichus mutilatus
                  </tp:taxon-name> from Sri Lanka ( Ceylon ) in NHMUK . The author has also examined
                  more than 1000 specimens identified by Lesne, Vrydagh and others in 13 museums (
                  RBINS , MIZPN , MNB , MTM , NHMUK , NMBS , NME , NMPC , NMS , NMW , SDEI , SNSD
                  and ZSM ) as well as in private collections ( LYL , MAIC and PZP ), mainly from
                  Southeast Asia and the archipelagos of the Indian Ocean and Madagascar , but
                  detailed locality data were not recorded. </p>
            <p> New records </p>
            <p> The author received 10 specimens collected from Xishuangbanna, Yunnan , China . This
                  is the first record of the species from China . The data for the specimens are as
                  follows: </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> CHINA • 1 ♂ ; S Yunnan , Xishuang-banna , S Yunnan, 20 km
                        NW of Jinghong Man Dain ( Nabanhe National Nature Reserve ); 22°07′80″ N ,
                        100°40′05″ E ; alt. 730 m ; 18 Jul. 2008 ; A. Weigel leg.; forest ; EKL
                        light trap ; NME / LYL </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂
                        , 1 ♀ ; 13 May 2008 ; A. Weigel leg.; EKL light trap ; NME / LYL
                  </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 2 ♂♂ ; 6 Apr. 2009 ; L. Meng
                        leg.; EKL light trap ; NME / LYL </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; 26 km NW of Jinghong , near An Man Xin Zhai ;
                        22°11′45″ N , 100°38′44″ E ; alt. 760 m ; 10 Oct. 2008 ; L. Meng leg.;
                        forest ; EKL light trap ; NME / LYL </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; 37 km NW of Jinghong , near Guo Men Shan ;
                        22°14′48″ N , 100°38′22″ E ; alt. 1080 m ; 18 Jul. 2008 ; A. Weigel leg.;
                        UWP MF Malaise trap ; NME / LYL </tp:material-citation> •
                        <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; 27 Apr. 2009 ; light ; NME / LYL
                  </tp:material-citation> . </p>
            <p> In addition, two more specimens were collected from the branches of a rubber tree (
                        <tp:taxon-name> Hevea brasiliensis Müll.Arg. </tp:taxon-name> ) in Jinghong,
                  Xishuangbanna during Jan. 2018 (S.C. Lai, pers. comm.). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> BODY. 6–8.5 mm long, about 2–2.3 times as long as wide, elongate. Head, pronotum,
                  abdomen and disc of elytra testaceous, posterior of elytra and declivity dark
                  brown, antennae reddish, club often brown; femora testaceous, tibiae and tarsi
                  brownish. </p>
            <p> HEAD. Clypeus finely and densely punctured, concave in an arc in front.
                  Fronto-clypeal suture distinguished by different colour between frons and clypeus
                  or shallow suture with vertical longitudinal furrow in middle ending on anterior
                  margin of clypeus. Frons with punctures less fine and less dense than on clypeus,
                  slightly rough, covered by fairly long, fine pubescence directed upwards. First
                  antennomere elongated, second antennomere sub-rectangular, each funicle segment
                  with a rim of long hairs in middle, total length of funicle as long as or shorter
                  than first antennomere of antennal club, first and second antennomeres of antennal
                  club 1.3–1.5 times as long as wide, last antennomere rather elongated, about 2.5–3
                  times as long as wide. Club matt, without clear sensory impressions or an area
                  with stiff hairs ( Fig. 1C ). </p>
            <p> PRONOTUM. About 1.2–1.3 times as wide as long, fairly strongly narrowed in anterior
                  third, widest in basal part; a distinct upwardly-directed uncinate tooth on
                  anterolateral angle and a series of upwardlydirected teeth behind
                        <tp:taxon-name>form lateral</tp:taxon-name> border of rasp on anterior half
                  of pronotum, teeth gradually smaller and less erect towards summit of pronotum and
                  posterior border of rasp formed by small tubercles or granules, bearing
                  yellowish-red, short, recumbent pubescence between teeth ( Fig. 2A, D ); area
                  above anterior margin between uncinate teeth finely and more or less roughly
                  punctured; median and posterior areas shiny with fine, sparse punctures; sides
                  evenly rounded behind rasp; distinct, ridge-like lateral carinae extended to basal
                  margin of pronotum to <tp:taxon-name>form pointed</tp:taxon-name> posterolateral
                  angles ( Fig. 1D ). Basal half of pronotum with minute, moderately dense punctures
                  in middle only; laterally shining, glabrous, tiny white hairs present close to
                  infero-lateral margin ( Fig. 1C ). </p>
            <p> ELYTRA. 1.7–1.85 times as long as pronotum, 1.45–1.65 times as long as wide, disc
                  parallel-sided, widest at middle of declivity. Elytra shining, with sparse,
                  moderately fine and shallow punctures on disc, becoming deeper and larger on
                  posterior part of disc and declivity, upper half of declivity with strongest
                  punctures. Upper margin of elytral declivity with three pairs of tubercles, middle
                  one largest, with pointed tip and projecting furthest, other two forming short
                  ridges with rounded tips, infero-lateral callus extended and joining directly to
                  infero-lateral margin of elytra ( Fig. 2B–C ). Elytral suture raised from upper
                  margin of declivity and gradually swollen and thickest at apex, where it forms
                  rounded thickened angles, margin of elytra with one or several tubercles on
                  ventral side near sutural angle, which projects slightly. </p>
            <p> Fig. 2. <tp:taxon-name> Xylothrips flavipes ( Illiger, 1801 ) </tp:taxon-name> , ♀
                  (LYL). A . Frontal view. B . Lateral view of declivity. C . Declivity. D . Dorsal
                  view. E . Ventral view. Scale bars = 1 mm (upper scale for A–C; lower scale for
                  D–E). </p>
            <p>ABDOMEN. Ventral side vestiture with dense, white or reddish yellow pubescence, last
                  ventrite with narrow pleural pieces along margin to apical curved area, with a
                  long tuft of hairs in middle.</p>
            <p> LEGS. Dense, short golden hairs on ventroposterior margins of posterior femora (
                  Fig. 2E ). External face of pro- and mesotibiae broadly grooved, not narrowed
                  towards apex. Segments 2 and 3 of anterior tarsi distinctly wider than others. </p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> HEAD. Frons transversely convex, densely and very finely punctured, very finely
                  pubescent, with a few erect hairs next to inner margin of eyes. Clypeus with a
                  transverse band of upwardly directed hairs towards base with a narrow median line
                  ( Fig. 1C ). </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> HEAD. Frontal crown of hairs very thick, forming arc of a circle or a very wide V,
                  fairly distant laterally from eyes. Clypeal tufts of hairs as long as those on
                  frons ( Fig. 2A, D–E ). </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> Waterhouse (1888) transferred <tp:taxon-name> Bostrichus mutilatus Walker, 1858
                  </tp:taxon-name> to <tp:taxon-name> Xylopertha </tp:taxon-name> , noting that
                  material he examined bore the name “ <tp:taxon-name> religiosa Dej.
                  </tp:taxon-name> ”, and that it was very similar to material deposited in NHMUK as
                        <tp:taxon-name> Apate lifuana Montrouzier, 1861 </tp:taxon-name> . Lesne
                  (1901) later synonymised <tp:taxon-name> Xylopertha mutilatus </tp:taxon-name>
                  with <tp:taxon-name> Xylothrips flavipes </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
            <p> Biology </p>
            <p> Stebbing (1914) recorded <tp:taxon-name> X. flavipes </tp:taxon-name> attacking
                  cocoa trees ( <tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae</tp:taxon-name> : <tp:taxon-name> Theobroma
                        cacao </tp:taxon-name> L.), in Mauritius , and researchers have observed
                  this species in the wood of banyan ( <tp:taxon-name>Moraceae</tp:taxon-name> :
                        <tp:taxon-name> Ficus religiosa </tp:taxon-name> L.) and badanier (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Combretaceae</tp:taxon-name> : <tp:taxon-name> Terminalia
                        catappa </tp:taxon-name> L.), the latter a species native to India . In
                  India , <tp:taxon-name> X. flavipes </tp:taxon-name> has been recorded living in
                  the wood of the mango tree ( <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name> :
                        <tp:taxon-name> Mangifera indica </tp:taxon-name> L.), sal (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Dipterocarpaceae</tp:taxon-name> : <tp:taxon-name> Shorea
                        robusta Roth </tp:taxon-name> ), cocoa, rubber (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Euphorbiaceae</tp:taxon-name> : <tp:taxon-name> Hevea
                        brasiliensis </tp:taxon-name> ), etc. ( Lesne 1932 ). Beeson &amp; Bhatia
                  (1937) listed host plants belonging to 13 families in India :
                        <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name> Anacardium
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Lannea </tp:taxon-name> ),
                        <tp:taxon-name>Burseraceae</tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name> Canarium
                  </tp:taxon-name> ), <tp:taxon-name>Dipterocarpaceae</tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name> Dipterocarpus </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Hopea
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Vateria </tp:taxon-name> and <tp:taxon-name>
                        Vatica </tp:taxon-name> ), <tp:taxon-name>Fagaceae</tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name> Quercus </tp:taxon-name> ),
                        <tp:taxon-name>Euphorbiaceae</tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name> Mallotus
                  </tp:taxon-name> ), <tp:taxon-name>Lauraceae</tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>
                        Persea </tp:taxon-name> ), Leguminosae ( <tp:taxon-name> Albizia
                  </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name> Butea </tp:taxon-name> , <tp:taxon-name>
                        Caesalpinia </tp:taxon-name> ), <tp:taxon-name>Malvaceae</tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name> Bombax </tp:taxon-name> ),
                        <tp:taxon-name>Moraceae</tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name> Ficus
                  </tp:taxon-name> ), <tp:taxon-name>Myristicaceae</tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>
                        Knema </tp:taxon-name> ), <tp:taxon-name>Myrtaceae</tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name> Syzygium </tp:taxon-name> ),
                        <tp:taxon-name>Phyllanthaceae</tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name> Phyllanthus
                  </tp:taxon-name> ), <tp:taxon-name>Vitaceae</tp:taxon-name> ( <tp:taxon-name>
                        Vitis </tp:taxon-name> ) and several unidentified woods. It is apparent that
                        <tp:taxon-name> X. flavipes </tp:taxon-name> is a polyphagous species. It
                  has usually been collected from forests or orchards, not lumber yards, timber
                  processing premises or wooden items. </p>
            <p> Beeson &amp; Bhatia (1937) found that <tp:taxon-name> X. flavipes </tp:taxon-name>
                  has two generations a year in North India and recorded the first generation
                  emerging from the end of March to the end of May, with maximum abundance in the
                  third week of April, a second generation from the first week of July to the third
                  week of October. From logs of <tp:taxon-name> Mangifera indica </tp:taxon-name> (
                        <tp:taxon-name>Anacardiaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) felled in August,
                        <tp:taxon-name> X. flavipes </tp:taxon-name> was found to have a minimum
                  life-cycle of three months ( Beeson &amp; Bhatia 1937 ). Sittichaya et al. (2013)
                  surveyed the durian-based orchards in Southern Thailand and found <tp:taxon-name>
                        X. flavipes </tp:taxon-name> was the dominant species in the durian growing
                  areas. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> The distribution includes: Madagascar , Indian Ocean islands, Sri Lanka , India ,
                  Nepal , China ( Yunnan ), Southeast Asia, Philippines , Indonesia . It has
                  probably been introduced through human agency into the Mariana Is., Palau and the
                  Federated States of Micronesia in the Western Pacific. It has also been introduced
                  into the Arabian Peninsula, Socotra Island ( Yemen ), South Africa (Natal), Israel
                  , Europe and USA ( Borowski &amp; Węgrzynowicz 2007 , 2019 ). Roberts (1968)
                  recorded the species in Sapele, Nigeria at light. There are more than 10 specimens
                  deposited in MNB and 7 specimens in SDEI from Ethiopia . This suggests that the
                  species is established in that country. In the RBINS collection, there is one
                  specimen (Vrydagh ident.) collected from NSW, Australia in 1914 from imported wood
                  from India , and one specimen from Melbourne, Australia in SDEI. These appear to
                  be accidental introductions. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
