<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora hexalepis hexalepis
(
Cope, 1866
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 9
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Nine supralabials; sixth supralabial in contact with the eye; 10 infralabials; a single subocular sometimes present; 186–213 ventrals; 75–98 subcaudals; tail 20 to 25 % of total length; 10 +3 maxillary teeth; a pale vertebral line contacting the parietal region, three to five scale rows wide on the first third of the body, three rows wide posteriorly, bordered by a pair of dorsolateral lines up to four scale rows wide, extending from the temporal region to the tip of the tail, halfway along the body the dorsolateral lines are divided giving rise to another lateral line distinguishable to the tip of tail.</p>
      <p>
This taxon differs from 
S. h. klauberi
by having a single supralabial in contact with the eye, whereas 
S. h. klauberi
has two supralabials (the fifth and sixth) in contact; in 
S. h. mojavensis
the supralabials and the lower edge of the eyes are separated by two or more suboculars; 

S. h. 
<tp:taxon-name>hexalepis</tp:taxon-name>

is similar to 
S. h. virgultea
in that many individuals have a single supralabial in contact with the eye; however, these subspecies differ in coloration pattern, with the head of 
S. h. virgultea
being brown and the lateral line becoming faded and indistinguishable at about the middle of the body (in 

S. h. 
<tp:taxon-name>hexalepis</tp:taxon-name>

the head is gray, the vertebral line is up to five rows of scales wide, and in the middle of the body the lateral line is completely separated from the dorsolateral line).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From the Latin ‘ 
hexa
’ for ‘six’ and ‘ 
lepis
’ for ‘scale’, which can be interpreted as six-sided scales.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
It occurs from the southeast of 
California
, 
United States
, southward to northeastern Baja 
California
, central 
Arizona
southward through the northeast portion of the Sonoran Desert, including Tiburón Island (
Fig. 9
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
