<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Salvadora mexicana</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514525</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EE1CC7ACAEF901E37545CDED58694823</uri>
         <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships based on morphological data and taxonomy of the genus Salvadora Baird &amp; Girard, 1853 (Reptilia, Colubridae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1473</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora mexicana
(
Duméril, Bibron &amp; Duméril, 1854
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Zamenis mexicanus
Duméril, Bibron &amp; Duméril, 1854: 695–696
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora mexicana
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Günther 1863: 349

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Rostral elongated; 9 supralabials, 3 supralabials in contact with the eye, the fourth, fifth and sixth; 10–11 infralabials; a single preocular; a single loreal scale; prenasal in contact with the second supralabial; a second pair of chinshields in contact with each other or separated by a row of scales; 182–197 ventrals; 125–145 subcaudals; tail length is 31 to 42% of total length; 15 +3 maxillary teeth. Color pattern on the first third of the body consists of mottled transverse patches becoming transverse bars on the neck; the back of the head is dark with pale longitudinal patch in the center; the rest of the body has pale vertebral line flanked by two dark dorsolateral lines; and two dark lateral lines.</p>
      <p>This species differs from its congeners by having a single preocular scale; tail length is approximately one third of the total length (31–42%); and by having four dark longitudinal lines interrupted on the first third of the body where they are replaced by transverse bands or patches.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Patronym referring to the country of origin.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Type
material

MEXICO
• “Cap Corrientes, Mexique” [
Jalisco
, 
Cabo Corrientes
]; 
MNHN 3585
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution and conservation
</p>
      <p>
Endemic to 
Mexico
. Occurs from 
Nayarit
southward on the Pacific coast in the states of 
Nayarit
, 
Jalisco
, 
Colima
, 
Michoacán
, 
Guerrero
, and 
Oaxaca
entering the Balsas River Basin, toward central 
Guerrero
, the states of Estado de 
México
, 
Morelos
and southwestern 
Puebla
(
Fig. 4
).
</p>
      <p>Within its distribution it is found in at least four protected natural areas. Mexican legislation has listed this species as subject to Special Protection and the IUCN has it listed as a species of Least Concern.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
