<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Salvadora intermedia Hartweg 1940</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5514541</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EB406F600D915F0FD71321532B8CD6BC</uri>
         <article-title>Phylogenetic relationships based on morphological data and taxonomy of the genus Salvadora Baird &amp; Girard, 1853 (Reptilia, Colubridae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.764.1473</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora intermedia
Hartweg, 1940
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 10
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora intermedia
Hartweg, 1940: 256–259
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora intermedia richardi
Smith, 1941: 6–9
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Salvadora intermedia intermedia</tp:taxon-name>
–

Smith, 1941: 7

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Rostral scale elongated; generally 8 supralabials (occasionally 9), the fourth and fifth normally in contact with the eye; 10–11 infralabials; preocular scale divided; a single loreal scale; prenasal scale in contact with or separated from the second supralabial; chinshields in contact or separated by two small scales; ventral scales 172 to 190; subcaudal scales 84 to 114; tail is 23 to 30% of the total length; 11 +3 maxillary teeth. Color pattern formed by a vertebral line three scales rows wide, yellowish in color and in contact with the parietal region; a pair of lateral lines is fused with the dorsolateral lines on first third of body, separated at second third of the body to tail; dorsolateral lines wide and dark, diverging at the neck, passing through the temporal region to eye.</p>
      <p>
S 

alvadora 
<tp:taxon-name>intermedia</tp:taxon-name>

differs from its congeners by having a divided preocular scale; fewer than 116 subcaudal scales; 8 supralabials, the fourth and fifth in contact with the eye; the second pair of chinshields in contact with each other or separated by a row of scales; and two dark dorsolateral lines that diverge at the neck, passing through the temporal to eye.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type
material examined

</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
• 
♂
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora intermedia intermedia
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Guerrero
, 
vicinity of Chilpancingo
; 
W.W. Brown
leg.; 
UMMZ 85733

.
</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
• 
♂
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora intermedia richardi
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Puebla
, 

1 mile
N of Tehuacán

; 

8 Aug. 1940

; 
R.C. Taylor
leg.; Collection E.H. Taylor and H.M. Smith No. 23470; 
UIMNH 25071

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution and conservation
</p>
      <p>
Endemic to 
Mexico
. Distributed in central-southern 
Mexico
from the vicinity of Chilpancingo, 
Guerrero
, eastward through central 
Oaxaca
and northward to southwestern 
Puebla
(
Fig. 10
).
</p>
      <p>Within its distribution it is found in at least two protected natural areas. Mexican legislation has listed this species as subject to Special Protection and the IUCN has it listed as a species of Least Concern.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Salvadore intermedia</tp:taxon-name>
richardi

was described by 
Smith (1941)
, who based his description on a single specimen collected one mile from Tehuacán, 
Puebla
(UIMNH 25071). 
Smith (1941)
thought this specimen represented a disjunct population of the populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. intermedia
</tp:taxon-name>
at 
Guerrero
. 
Smith (1941)
defined 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. intermedia richardi
</tp:taxon-name>
as having the prenasal scale separated from the second supralabial and by its number of ventral scales. However, we examined 37 individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. intermedia
</tp:taxon-name>
along what appears to be a continuous distribution from 
Guerrero
and through 
Oaxaca
to southern 
Puebla
, and found that only seven of these specimens had the condition of the prenasal scale separated from the second supralabial described by 
Smith (1941)
: three from 
Oaxaca
(MZFC 04059, MZFC 23857, MZFC 23871), three from 
Guerrero
(
MCZ 33642
, MZFC 02878, FMNH 109866), one from 
Puebla
(MZFC 14384). Additionally, the number of ventral scales of these specimens falls within the range previously described for 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. intermedia
</tp:taxon-name>
. Based on these findings, we conclude that these characters are part of the intrapopulational variation of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. intermedia
</tp:taxon-name>
and that 
S. i. richardi
should be considered a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. intermedia
</tp:taxon-name>
as previously suggested by 
Davis &amp; Dixon (1957)
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
