<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora deserticola
Schmidt 1940
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 6
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora hexalepis deserticola
Schmidt, 1940: 146
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 14.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora hexalepis celeris
Smith, 1941: 9
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 6.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Rostral scale well developed, elongated and with free edges; 9 supralabials, two or rarely three in contact with the eye (generally the fifth and sixth in contact); 11 infralabials; preocular scale divided; a single loreal; prenasal in contact with the second supralabial; a second pair of chinshields separated by two rows of scales; 180–205 ventrals; 66–87 subcaudals; tail is 19 to 23.5% of the total length; maxillary teeth normally 11+ 3. Color pattern consists of a pale vertebral stripe, five scales wide on the anterior third of the body and three scales wide on the rest of the body, flanked by a pair of dark dorsolateral lines located on the sixth and seventh row and separated from the lateral lines by at least one row of scales; lateral lines begin on the fourth row or on the margins of the third and fourth rows of dorsal scales. Lateral and dorsolateral lines fused on the neck.</p>
      <p>Differs from the other species in the genus by having a single loreal, usually not divided; tail shorter (less than 24% of the total length) and fewer subcaudal scales.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name is derived from the Latin words ‘ 
desertum
’, which means ‘desert’, and ‘ 
icola
’, which means ‘inhabitant’, in reference to the habitat at the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type
material examined

</p>
      <p>
UNITED STATES
• 
♂
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora hexalepis deserticola
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Texas
, 
Brewster County
, 
Government Spring
, 
close to the Chisos Mountains
; 

6 Oct. 1935

; 
Tom Carney
leg.; 
FMNH 26615

.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
Locality records of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora deserticola
Schmidt, 1940
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
MEXICO
• 
♀
, 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Salvadora hexalepis celeris
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
Sinaloa
, 
San Blas
; 

28 Mar. 1910

; 
J.N. Rose
leg.; 
USNM 40043

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution and conservation
</p>
      <p>
Southwestern 
Texas
, southwestern 
New Mexico
, and southeastern 
Arizona
, southward on each flank of the Sierra Madre Occidental in 
Mexico
in the states of 
Sonora
, 
Chihuahua
, 
Coahuila
and 
Sinaloa
(
Fig. 6
).
</p>
      <p>
It is found in at least two protected natural areas in 
Sonora
. Mexican legislation has not listed this species and the IUCN has it listed as a species of Least Concern.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
