<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
74D16A9C-63DA-4190-9BC0-E0BC80904B17
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus
Li, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Adult
</p>
      <p>
Head with subtrapezoidal vertex smoothly passing into genae that lack processes. Frons triangular. Antenna about as long as head width. Clypeus flattened, triangular. Propleurites with subequal epimeron and episternum. Tibiae distinctly longer than femora; metacoxa with small pointed meracanthus and small membranous lobe on metatrochanteral cavity; metatibia without genual spine, bearing an open crown of 8–9 densely spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs. Forewing weakly coriaceous, covered in surface spinules; costal break and pterostigma developed; veins 
R
and M+Cu subequal, branches of vein M, and vein Cu 
1a
very long; anal break close to apex of vein Cu 
1b
. Hindwing with costal setae not grouped; vein 
R
+M developed. Male proctiger one-segmented; in profile, with large posterior lobe in basal half. Female terminalia cuneate.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult
</p>
      <p>
Head, in profile, inclined at 45° from longitudinal body axis (
Fig. 2A
). Vertex subtrapezoidal, passing smoothly into genae which are not produced into processes; coronal suture fully developed (
Fig. 2C
); frons triangular with median ocellus situated at dorso-median edge (
Fig. 2D
). Antenna 10-segmented, filiform, about as long as head width. Clypeus flattened, triangular (
Fig. 2D
), not visible in profile. Rostrum very short, hardly exceeding procoxae. Thorax moderately arched dorsally; pronotum transversely ribbon-shaped, longer medially than laterally; mesopraescutum in longitudinal body axis shorter than mesoscutum which is strongly bulged; propleurites with subequal epimeron and episternum. Legs (
Fig. 2B
) moderately slender, tibiae distinctly longer than femora; metacoxa with small pointed meracanthus and small membranous lobe on metatrochanteral cavity (
Fig. 2B
: lobe); metatibia without genual spine, bearing an open crown of 8–9 densely spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs (
Fig. 2B
). Forewing weakly coriaceous, membrane semitransparent, covered in surface spinules; costal break and pterostigma developed; veins 
R
and M+Cu subequal, branches of vein M, and vein Cu1a very long; anal break close to apex of vein Cu 
1b
. Hindwing slightly shorter than forewing, membranous; costal setae not grouped; vein 
R
+M developed. Male proctiger one-segmented; in profile, with large posterior lobe in basal half. Male subgenital plate semiglobular. Paramere shorter than proctiger. Female terminalia cuneate. Circumanal ring oval.
</p>
      <p>
Immature
Unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Comments
</p>
      <p>
In describing 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paurocephala longicella
Tuthill (1943a)
</tp:taxon-name>
noted that the forewing venation differs from other known species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paurocephala
Crawford, 1913
</tp:taxon-name>
. In a review of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhinocola
Foerster, 1848
</tp:taxon-name>
and associated genera, 
Heslop-Harrison (1952)
discussed 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. longicella
</tp:taxon-name>
for which he erected ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Parapaurocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
’ but failed to provide a description. The name is, therefore, a nomen nudum and not available (ICZN 1999/2012: article 13.1.1). 
Burckhardt &amp; Basset (2000)
referred to the taxon as “‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paurocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
’ 
<tp:taxon-name>
longicella
</tp:taxon-name>
group”. Based on a single male, 
Li (2002)
described 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus longicellus
Li, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
, from 
Hainan
(
China
). We have examined the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus longicellus
</tp:taxon-name>
(DB, 
31 Aug. 2009
) and material identified as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paurocephala longicella
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Fiji
and 
Samoa
(MHNG, 
9 Jul. 2018
). We conclude that the samples are congeneric but represent different species, one each in 
China
, 
Fiji
and 
Samoa
, respectively, and suggest the following nomenclatorial acts:
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus
Li, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
, stat. rev., removed from synonymy with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Peripsyllopsis
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus longicellus
(Tuthill, 1943)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paurocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus lii
</tp:taxon-name>
nom. nov.
for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus longicellus
Li, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
, nec 
Tuthill (1943a)
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>Microphyllurinae</tp:taxon-name>
subfam. nov.
: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
A
. Habitus, in profile view. 
B
. Legs. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Head, ventral view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="multiple">
      <p>
Included genus
</p>
      <p>
* 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllurus
Li, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
(syn. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Microphyllura
</tp:taxon-name>
, misspelling, 
Li, 2011
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Parapaurocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
Heslop- Harrison, nomen nudum; ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paurocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
’ 
<tp:taxon-name>
longicella
</tp:taxon-name>
group sensu 
Burckhardt &amp; Basset, 2000
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
