<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
B8BF6738-548A-4042-A942-7A21085A3973
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Platycorypha
Tuthill, 1945
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Adult
</p>
      <p>
Head with oval frons, which is almost completely covered by median ocellus. Clypeus pear-shaped, in profile hidden by genae and not visible. Propleurites with episternum subequal to or smaller than epimeron. Metacoxa with large, pointed, horn-shaped meracanthus; metatibia with large genual spine, bearing 4–5 irregularly spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs. Forewing rhomboidal; costal break and pterostigma developed; cell cu1 large; anal break close to apex of vein Cu 
1b
. Male proctiger one-segmented.
</p>
      <p>
Fifth instar immature
</p>
      <p>Body broadly oval, lacking capitate setae. Antenna with 4 rhinaria. Meso and metathoracic sclerites small. Forewing pad lacking humeral lobes. Margin of hindwing pad usually with one sectaseta. Legs lacking capitate setae; tarsal arolium fan-shaped with unguitractor and pedicel. Caudal plate developed, semi-circular; margin with up to 3+3 sectasetae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult
</p>
      <p>
Head, in profile, weakly to strongly inclined at 30–90° from longitudinal body axis (
Fig. 8A, C, E, G
). Vertex subrectangular to transversely subtrapezoidal (
Fig. 8B, D, F, H
); separated from genae sometimes by transverse or oblique suture, sometimes passing smoothly into genae; genae smoothly rounded (
Fig. 8D, H
) or forming short (
Fig. 7F
) or long conical processes (
Fig. 8B
); coronal suture fully developed or completely reduced; frons oval, almost completely covered by median ocellus; anteorbital tubercle sometimes developed (
Fig. 8D
: arrow). Antenna 10-segmented, filiform, ranging from slightly longer than head width to distinctly longer than forewing, segment 3 shorter or longer than segments 7 or 8. Clypeus pear-shaped, in profile hidden by genae and not visible. Rostrum usually short, only tip exceeding procoxae, sometimes longer (in some 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platycorypha
</tp:taxon-name>
spp.). Thorax weakly (
Fig. 7G
) to strongly (
Fig. 8A
) arched dorsally, about as wide as head; pronotum weakly or very strongly inclined from longitudinal body axis; propleurites narrow to broad, with episternum subequal to or smaller than epimeron. Legs moderately long, tibiae often shorter than femora, sometimes subequal or longer; basitarsi not much longer than broad; metacoxa with large, pointed, horn-shaped meracanthus; metatibia with large genual spine, bearing 4–5 irregularly spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs. Forewing rhomboidal, broadest in apical third or in the middle, narrowly rounded or angular apically; membrane semitransparent, covered in surface spinules; costal break and pterostigma developed; vein C+Sc weakly or strongly widened; vein R longer than M+Cu; cell cu 
1
large; caudal break close to apex of vein Cu
</p>
      <p>1b</p>
      <p>. Hindwing slightly shorter than forewing, membranous; costal setae ungrouped or grouped; vein R+M+Cu indistinctly trifurcating or splitting into R and M+Cu. Male proctiger one-segmented; in profile, tubular or with posterior lobe. Male subgenital plate subglobular or elongate. Paramere lamellar or complex. Female terminalia short or moderaly long; proctiger often with dorsal hump.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>Platycoryphinae</tp:taxon-name>
subfam. nov.
A–B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Allophorina
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
C–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Limbopsylla nata
Brown &amp; Hodkinson, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
E–F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Padaukia macrolobii
Burckhardt &amp; Queiroz, 2018
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
G–H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platycorypha nigrivirga
Burckhardt, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A, C, E, G
. Habitus, in profile view. 
B, D, F, H
. Head, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>
Fifth instar immature
</p>
      <p>Body broadly oval, lacking capitate setae. Antenna 7, 9 or 10-segmented, with 4 rhinaria. Meso and metathoracic sclerites small. Forewing pad lacking humeral lobes. Margin of hindwing pad usually with one sectaseta. Legs lacking capitate setae; tarsal arolium shorter or longer than claws, fan-shaped with unguitractor and pedicel. Caudal plate developed, semi-circular; margin with up to 3+3 sectasetae. Anus in ventral or terminal position; circumanal ring small heart-shaped to large undulate, restricted to ventral side or extended to dorsal side; consisting of a single row or multiple rows of pores, without additional pore fields.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Comments
</p>
      <p>
Brown &amp; Hodkinson (1988)
created 
<tp:taxon-name>
Limbopsylla
</tp:taxon-name>
as a polyphyletic holding place for ten “species of the subfamilies 
<tp:taxon-name>Acizziinae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Ciriacreminae</tp:taxon-name>
which cannot be placed in existing genera”. Three species have been removed previously and three species are transferred here (
Table 1
). Based on adult and immature material of an undescribed species from 
Brazil
associated with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tachigali rugosa
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Fabaceae</tp:taxon-name>
) (NHMB) which is congeneric with 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. nata
</tp:taxon-name>
, the 
type
species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Limbopsylla
</tp:taxon-name>
, we conclude that 
<tp:taxon-name>
Limbopsylla
</tp:taxon-name>
is a valid genus closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platycorypha
</tp:taxon-name>
, and that the other species included in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Limbopsylla
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Table 1
) are not congeneric with the 
type
species.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="multiple">
      <p>
Included genera
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Allophorina
Hodkinson, 1991
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Limbopsylla
Brown &amp; Hodkinson, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Padaukia
Hollis &amp; Martin, 1993
</tp:taxon-name>
(syn. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Peltapaurocephala
Heslop-Harrison
</tp:taxon-name>
nomen nudum, no description); * 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platycorypha
Tuthill, 1945
</tp:taxon-name>
(syn. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neopsyllia
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
