<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Katacephalinae Burckhardt &amp; Ouvrard &amp; Percy 2021, subfam. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4598865</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/858450955AF35B152BD6AD006E3EEDA7</uri>
         <article-title>An updated classification of the jumping plant-lice (Hemiptera: Psylloidea) integrating molecular and morphological evidence</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.736.1257</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
DE4F5C17-6685-47B9-9659-CEFD8828244D
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Katacephala
Crawford, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Adult
</p>
      <p>
Head with genae forming conical to lobular processes; preocular sclerite developed. Antenna 10-segmented, 0.9–2.2 times as long as head width, segment 3 usually longer than segments 7 or 8. Metatibia usually without genual spine, bearing an open crown of 6–19 evenly spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus usually with 2 spurs. Forewing with costal break and large pterostigma; anal break close to apex of vein Cu 
1b
. Hindwing almost as long as forewing. Male proctiger one-segmented, in profile, often with posterior lobes. Paramere usually simple with stout setae on the inner face.
</p>
      <p>
Fifth instar immature
</p>
      <p>Body often bearing lanceolate setae or sectasetae but lacking capitate setae. Antenna 7–10 segmented with 4 rhinaria. Tarsal arolium fan-shaped, unguitractor developed.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult
</p>
      <p>
Head, in profile, hardly to strongly (
Fig. 7
A–F) inclined at 0–90° from longitudinal body axis. Vertex trapezoidal (
Fig. 7J
) to almost subrectangular (
Fig. 7L
), separated from genae by transverse suture; genae forming conical to lobular processes which are separated or contiguous medially; coronal suture usually fully developed (
Fig. 7G
, I–L) but sometimes reduced (
Fig. 6H
); frons small, almost completely covered by median ocellus; anteorbital tubercle rarely developed (
Fig. 7L
: arrow); preocular sclerite always present (
Fig. 7J
: arrow). Antenna 10-segmented, filiform, 0.9–2.2 times as long as head width, segment 3 ususally longer than segments 7 or 8 (except for some species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tuthillia
</tp:taxon-name>
). Clypeus pearshaped, flattened in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tuthillia
</tp:taxon-name>
; hardly or not visible in profile. Rostrum short, distinctly exceeding procoxae. Thorax weakly (
Fig. 7F
) to strongly (
Fig. 7B
) arched dorsally, as wide as or wider than head; pronotum transversely ribbon-shaped; mesopraescutum in longitudinal body axis slightly to distinctly shorter than mesoscutum; propleurites narrow or broad, relative sizes of epimeron and episterum variable. Legs moderately long, tibiae longer than femora; basitarsi slightly longer than to about twice as long as broad; metacoxa with large, horn-shaped meracanthus; metatibia without genual spine (exception 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notophorina vitripennis
Burckhardt, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
), bearing an open crown of 6–19 evenly spaced, sclerotised, apical spurs; metabasitarsus with 2 spurs (exception 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notophorina monocentra
Burckhardt, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
). Forewing oval (
Fig. 7B
), somewhat rectangular, rhomboidal or very elongate (
Fig. 7F
), narrowly (
Fig. 7B
) to broadly rounded apically (
Fig. 7C
); membrane semitransparent, sometimes with pattern; costal break developed, pterostigma large; anal break close to apex of vein Cu 
1b
. Hindwing almost as long as forewing, membranous; costal setae indistinctly to clearly grouped; vein R+M+Cu branching into veins R+M and Cu or R and M+Cu. Male proctiger one-segmented, in profile, often with posterior lobes. Male subgenital plate subglobular or elongate. Paramere usually simple with stout setae on the inner face. Female terminalia cuneate or falcate. Circumanal ring oval.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>Katacephalinae</tp:taxon-name>
subfam. nov.
A, G
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Katacephala longiramis
(
Burckhardt, 1987
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Katacephala tenuipennis
Tuthill, 1944
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
C, I
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lautereropsis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
D, J
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notophorina brevicornis
Burckhardt, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
E, K
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notophorina
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
F, L
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tuthillia
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Katacephala
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
A–F
. Habitus, in profile view. 
G–L
. Head, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>
Fifth instar immature
</p>
      <p>Body oval to elongate, fairly robust; surface often covered in lanceolate setae or sectasetae but lacking capitate setae. Antenna 7–10 segmented with 4 rhinaria. Dorsal thoracic sclerites varying from small to large. Tarsal arolium fan-shaped, unguitractor developed, pedicel absent or present. Forewing-pads often with large humeral lobes. Anus in ventral or terminal position. Circumanal ring variable.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Comments
</p>
      <p>
The four genera included in the new subfamily were assigned by 
Burckhardt &amp; Ouvrard (2012)
to the polyphyletic tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Diaphorinini</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Euphyllurinae</tp:taxon-name>
) along with other genera referred here to 
<tp:taxon-name>Euphyllurinae</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Liviidae</tp:taxon-name>
), 
<tp:taxon-name>Ciriacreminae</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Diaphorininae</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>Psyllinae</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Psyllidae</tp:taxon-name>
). Putative autapomorphies of the new subfamily are the open crown of densely spaced metatibial spurs and the posteriorly lobed male proctiger in adults, as well as the presence of lanceolate setae and the lack of capitate setae in immatures. Hosts of the 
Oriental
<tp:taxon-name>
Lautereropsis
Burckhardt &amp; Malenovský, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
are unknown. The other three genera are associated entirely or partially with 
<tp:taxon-name>Myrtaceae</tp:taxon-name>
and are mostly Neotropical.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="multiple">
      <p>
Included genera
</p>
      <p>
* 
<tp:taxon-name>
Katacephala
Crawford, 1914
</tp:taxon-name>
(syn. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jenseniella
</tp:taxon-name>
); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lautereropsis
Burckhardt &amp; Malenovský, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Notophorina
Burckhardt, 1987
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tuthillia
Hodkinson, Brown &amp; Burckhardt, 1986
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
