<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Lysmata lipkei Okuno &amp; Fiedler 2010</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5572659</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/44493EA27F103FC06F47C36848C94CF9</uri>
         <article-title>The caridean shrimps of the genus Lysmata Risso, 1816 (Decapoda: Lysmatidae) from Madagascar collected during the Atimo-Vatae expedition: a new species and two new records</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.774.1535</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Lysmata lipkei
Okuno &amp; Fiedler, 2010
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Lysmata lipkei
Okuno &amp; Fiedler 2010: 599
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1–4.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Carapace with rostrum reaching to about middle of second antennular article, armed with 4–5 teeth on dorsal margin (including two postorbital ones) and 2–4 on ventral margin; antennal tooth welldeveloped; pterygostomial angle with small acute tooth. Antennule with stylocerite subacute, falling short of reaching to end of first antennular segment; lateral flagellum with accessory ramus consisting of short one-segmented finger-shaped article. Antenna with inferior tooth of basicerite strong; scaphocerite distinctly surpassing antennular peduncle, lateral margin slightly concave, distolateral tooth slightly overreaching blade; carpocerite small, not reaching to end of first antennular article.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>First pereiopod robust, chela with fingers bearing a narrow gap when closed, especially on proximal half. Second pereiopods unequal in size, longer one with 27–32 and shorter one with 23–27 carpal segments. Third pereiopod with merus armed with spinules on distal 0.6 of segment length; carpus unarmed; dactylus biunguiculate, ventral margin with two or three accessory spines, decreasing in size toward</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
Color pattern of the live ovigerous hermaphrodite, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lysmata lipkei
Okuno &amp; Fiedler, 2010
</tp:taxon-name>
. Photo by Tin-Yam Chan &amp; Chia-Wei Lin. Copyright MNHN.
</p>
      <p>proximal margin (in case of having three accessory teeth, proximal one very small). Fifth pereiopod with merus armed with 1–3 spinules disto-ventrally.</p>
      <p>Pleon with three anterior pleura rounded antero- and postero-ventrally, fourth pleuron angled posteroventrally, fifth pleuron with small acute tooth postero-ventrally. Posterior margin of telson with small acute median projection and two pairs of spines, with mesial pair stronger and longer than lateral pair.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 hermaphrodite
; 
southern Madagascar
; 
25°26.4′ S
, 
44°56.1′ E
; depth 

14–18 m

; 

29 May 2010

; MNHN exped.; Atimo-Vatae; Stn. BS03; GenBank 
MW798243
; 
MNHN-IU-2010-4898
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Although the lateral flagella of the two antennules in the single studied specimen of 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. lipkei
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Madagascar
are broken, all other morphological characters, as well as molecular data, are consistent with the description and variability provided by 
Okuno &amp; Fiedler (2010)
, except for one character – the number of accessory spinules on the flexor margin of the biunguiculate dactyli of the last three pereiopods. In the original description, there are three accessory spinules decreasing in size proximally, while only two accessory spinules are seen in the material of the present study. This single difference can be interpreted as inter-population variation, as specimens of 
Japan
and 
Madagascar
are very close genetically.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
This is the seventh record of 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. lipkei
</tp:taxon-name>
. After being originally described from 
Japan
by 
Okuno &amp; Fiedler (2010)
, reported again from 
Japan
by 

De Grave 
et al.
(2012)

, and subsequently reported from 
Singapore
by 
Anker &amp; De Grave (2016)
; this species, based on morphological and genetic data, was recorded from the south-western Atlantic Ocean, 
Brazil
, and classified as alien there by 

Alves 
et al.
(2018)

as well two other records from 
Brazil
(

Pachelle 
et al.
2016

, 
2020
). The present report on 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. lipkei
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Madagascar
significantly extends its known Indo-West Pacific range to the south-west Indian Ocean.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
