<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Lysmata kuekenthali</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5567127</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5E3FB665224191D9067C52541A7C5765</uri>
         <article-title>The caridean shrimps of the genus Lysmata Risso, 1816 (Decapoda: Lysmatidae) from Madagascar collected during the Atimo-Vatae expedition: a new species and two new records</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.774.1535</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Lysmata kuekenthali
(
De Man, 1902
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hippolyte kükenthali
De Man, 1902: 850
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hippolysmata kükenthali
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Kemp 1914: 115
, p. 6

fig. 2.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hippolysmata (Hippolysmata) kükenthali
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Holthuis 1947: 69

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>Carapace with rostrum reaching to between end of first antennular article to middle of third one, slightly up-turned distally, with four to seven teeth (mostly six) on dorsal margin including the Postrostral teeth, with greater gap between most posterior tooth and preceding one, bearing one to three teeth on ventral margin; antennal tooth strong, surpassing anterior margin of carapace, not fused with lower orbital angle; pterygostomial margin varying from rounded to bearing small tooth.Antennule with stylocerite subacute, falling short of end of first antennular segment; lateral flagellum with accessory free ramus composed of small one-segmented finger-liked projection. Antenna with inferior tooth of basicerite small, subacute; scaphocerite slightly overreaching antennular peduncle, disto-lateral tooth slightly surpassing blade, blade with anterior margin relatively straight, lateral margin slightly concave; carpocerite not reaching to end of second antennular segment.</p>
      <p>First pereiopods small, robust; chela with very narrow gap between fingers at their proximal half when closed, fingers with small accessory tooth distally. Second pereiopods subequal, carpus with 17–22 segments. Third to fifth pereiopods generally similar, merus with two or three spinules on disto-lateral margin, dactylus biunguiculate, with two accessory spinules on flexor margin.</p>
      <p>Pleon with three anterior pleura rounded antero- and postero-ventrally, fourth pleuron obtusely angulated postero-ventrally, fifth pleuron with small acute tooth postero-ventrally, six pleuron with triangular projection on postero-lateral angle flanking telson. Posterior margin of telson with subacute median projection and bearing two pairs of spines posteriorly, mesial spiniform setae longer than lateral ones.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 hermaphrodite
; 
southern Madagascar
; 
25°4′23″ S
, 
46°57′8″ E
; depth 

14 –18 m

; 

8 May 2010

; MNHN exped.; 
Atimo-Vatae
; Stn. TB06; GenBank 
MW798242
; 
MNHN-IU-2017-2377
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
IRAN
• 
5 hermaphrodites
; 
Ramin
; 
Gulf of Oman
; 
25°16′7.05″ N
, 
60°45′2.71″ E
; 

5 Nov. 2008

; 
A. Sari
leg.; 
sandy/rocky with cobbles
; GenBank 
MW798240
; 
MNHN-IU-2014-1246
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
4 hermaphrodites
; 
Ramin
; 
Gulf of Oman
; 
25°16′7.05″ N
, 
60°45′2.71″ E
; 

16 May 2018

; 
H. Ashrafi
leg.; 
sandy/rocky with cobbles
; GenBank 
MW798241
; 
MNHN-IU-2014-1247
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
13 hermaphrodites
; same collection data as for preceding; 
ZUTC 6840
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
8 hermaphrodites
; 
Djod
; 
Gulf of Oman
; 
25°26′40″ N
, 
59°30′45″ E
; 

18 May 2018

; 
H. Ashrafi
leg.; 
sandy/rocky with cobbles
; 
ZUTC 6841
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
8 hermaphrodites
; same collection data as for preceding; 

7 Feb. 2009

; 
H. Salehi
leg.; 
sandy/rocky with cobbles
; 
ZUTC 6842
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>
No information about the ecology of the specimen collected in 
Madagascar
is available. However, the specimens collected in the Gulf of 
Oman
(by HA) were found at night in the lower intertidal zone in a deep tidal pool surrounded by large rocks, together with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palaemon pacificus
(Stimpson, 1860)
</tp:taxon-name>
. More than 100 individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
L. kuekenthali
</tp:taxon-name>
, and around 30 of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. pacificus
</tp:taxon-name>
, were in the same tidal pool.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Although this species has been recorded from many localities in the Indo-West Pacific (see 
Kemp 1914
; 
Holthuis 1947
; 
Chace 1997
; 
Anker &amp; De Grave 2016
; 

Ashrafi 
et al.
2020

), this is the first record of this species from 
Madagascar
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
