<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sinetectula egregia Fraussen &amp; Vermeij 2021, gen. et comb. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4770784</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/92A8D24A16A085B6515D98B73A7C87D0</uri>
         <article-title>Sinetectula gen. nov., a new genus of Pisaniidae (Gastropoda: Buccinoidea) from the tropical Indian and Pacific Oceans</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.748.1351</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula egregia
(Reeve, 1844)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1–2
, 10A–C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Triton egregius
Reeve, 1844a: 119
</tp:taxon-name>

(see 
Fig. 10A
) (
three syntypes
in NHM(
UK
): BMNH-1967643, one of them figured by 

Cernohorsky 1975: 191

, fig. 43).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phos amoenus
Schwengel, 1950: 81–82
</tp:taxon-name>

, pl. 5 fig. 4 (see 
Fig. 10B–C
) (
holotype
in ANSP 186177).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Triton egregius
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Reeve 1844b
: pl. 18 fig. 78

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Engina egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Cernohorsky 1975: 191

, fig. 43. — 

Singer &amp; Mienis 1995: 26–27

. — 

Dekker &amp; Orlin 2000: 28

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Engina
cf. 
egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Sharabati 1984
: pl. 21 fig. 5.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Enzinopsis egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Dekker &amp; Gemert 2008: 129

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type
localities

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Triton egregius
</tp:taxon-name>
: “Island of 
Masbate
, 
Philippines
(found under stones at low water)”.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phos amoenus
: Mbega
</tp:taxon-name>
Island, 
Fiji Islands
.
</p>
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
FRENCH POLYNESIA
• 
1 dd
; 
Australes Archipelago
, 
Port de Rurutu
, BENTHAUS exped. stn DW2001; 
22°27′ S
, 
151°20′ W
; depth 

200–550 m

; 

Nov. 2002

; 
MNHN

.
</p>
      <p>
GUAM
• 
1 dd
; 
Orote cliffs
; 1978; KF 2164

.
</p>
      <p>
INDONESIA
• 
1 dd
; 
Lombok
, 
E of Gili Islands
; depth 

46 m

; 
F. Lorenz
leg.; 

Oct. 2002

; 
KF 4004

• 

1 dd
; 
W of Tomia
, 
Kaledupa
reefs; depth 

9–45 m

; 
F. Lorenz
leg.; 

Oct. 2001

; 
KF 4106

• 

1 lv
; 
Alor Island
, 
Kalabahi Harbour
; depth 

5–8 m

; 
F. Lorenz
leg.; 

Nov. 2002

; 
KF 4107

• 

1 lv
; 
Sulawesi
, 
near Pulau Raja
; 
1°08′ N
, 
121°51′ E
; depth 

5–40 m

; 
F. Lorenz
leg.; 

Oct. 2003

; 
KF 4854
(see 

Fig. 
1I
–L

)

.
</p>
      <p>
MARSHALL ISLANDS
• 
26 lv
; 
Kwajalein
, 
West Reef
; depth 

30–35 m

; 
F. Lorenz
leg.; 1989; 
KF 4817

• 

1 lv
; 
Kwajalein
, 
in cave
; depth 

7–20 m

; 
local collector
leg.; 
KF 2163

• 

20 lv
; 
Kwajalein
, 
oceanside of West Reef, in cave
; depth 

12 m

; 
F. Lorenz
leg.; 1989; 
KF 4756
(see 
Fig. 1A–H
)

• 

1 lv
; 
Majura Atoll
, 
in cave
; depth 

1–2 m

; 
local collector
leg.; 

Jul. 1996

; 
KF 2796

.
</p>
      <p>
MAYOTTE
• 
1 dd
; 
Pananzi Island
, BENTHEDI 1977 exped. stn 32; 
12°45′ S
, 
45°18′ E
; depth 

15–20 m

; 

Mar. 1977

; 
MNHN
(see 
Fig. 1M–O
)

.
</p>
      <p>
PAPUA NEW GUINEA
• 
1 lv
; 
Madang
, 
Astrolabe Bay
, PAPUA NIUGINI exped. PB14; 
5°13.8′ S
, 
145°48′ E
; depth 

15 m

; 

Nov. 2012

; 
MNHN
IM-2013-12540
(see 
Fig. 1P–Q
)

.
</p>
      <p>
SAMOA
• 2 dd; western Samoa; 
KF
5277.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
has a remarkably wide range, from eastern Africa (KF, MNHN) to 
India
(

Kurhe 
et al.
2014: 5

, 10), along 
Indonesia
(KF), 
Japan
(
Okutani 2000: 477
, pl. 237 fig. 112) and 
Australia
(
Wilson 1994: 93
, pl. 10 fig. 15) to the Australes Archipelago in 
French Polynesia
(MNHN) and the 
Marshall Islands
(KF).
</p>
      <p>
We have not studied the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
from the Red Sea reported on by 
Sharabati (1984
: pl. 21 fig. 5) and referred to by 
Singer &amp; Mienis (1995: 26–27)
, 
Dekker &amp; Orlin (2000: 28)
and 
Dekker &amp; Gemert (2008: 129)
, so cannot judge whether these records really belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
or whether they belong to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. naevosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
or both.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
is recognisable by its characteristic colour pattern consisting of small dark brown spots situated in the space between the spiral cords where they cross the axial ribs. Occasionally, these spots are also present in the axial interspaces. These spots produce, when seen without magnification and, depending on their arrangement, a combination of moderately broad spiral bands (1 on the spire whorls and 2 on the body whorl) or dark axial blotches. This in combination with a rather rough sculpture dominated by 2 strong primary spiral cords on the spire whorls, gives the spire whorls a rather angular appearance. The colour on the spiral cords (white or pale) and spiral interspaces (usually darker) may inverse after crossing the prelabral varix, where, nearing the edge of the aperture, the spiral cords may become darker while the interspaces become paler or white (see 
Fig. 2C
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula egregia
(Reeve, 1844)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
A–E
. Specimen from the Marshall Islands, Kwajalein Atoll, in cave at Oceanside of West reef, depth 12 m, 12.0 mm long (KF 4756). 
F–H
. Specimen with same collection data as for preceding, 14.5 mm long (KF 4756). 
I–L
. Specimen from Indonesia, Sulawesi, 1°08′ N, 121°51′ E, near Pulau Raja, depth 5–40 m, 16.9 mm long (KF 4854). 
M–O
. Specimen from Mayotte, Pananzi Island, BENTHEDI 1977 stn 32, 12°45′ S, 45°18′ E, depth 15–20 m, 15.0 mm long (MNHN). 
P
. Specimen from Papua New Guinea, Madang, Astrolabe Bay, PAPUA NIUGINI stn PB14, 5°13.8′ S, 145°48′ E, depth 15 m, 16.6 mm long (MNHN IM-2013-12540). 
Q
. Radula of preceding specimen. A–P. Images courtesy of MNHN – Alexandre Lardeur. Q. Image courtesy of Yuri Kantor. Scale bars: D–E, L, O = 2.0 mm; Q = 100 µm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2A–C.
<tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula egregia
(Reeve, 1844)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
, in situ, 
Marshall Islands
, 
Kwajalein Atoll
, images courtesy of Jeanette Johnson, © 2015 In-Depth Images 
Kwajalein
.
</p>
      <p>The serrated edge of the outer lip deserves some closer study and is worth an extensive description. The protruding cusps are preceded by spiral interspaces while the notches are in the extension of the spiral cords. Specimens with an inversed pattern, as described in the previous paragraph, cause the optical illusion that the white spiral cords produce the white cusps (in reality it are the darker interspaces that lead the way to the white cusps).</p>
      <p>The serrated edge shows quite some variation among the species as well as within some individuals. The spiral cords alternate between strong and slightly weaker: the original (primary) spiral cords already present on the upper spire whorls are slightly stronger than the (secondary) spiral cords that took shape along the antepenultimate whorl. As a consequence, the notch preceded by a stronger primary spiral cord is often slightly deeper than the notch preceded by a slightly weaker secondary spiral cord. This is more materialised along the basal (abapical) part of the lip (slightly above the transition from base to siphonal canal). As a result, the serrations may be arranged in pairs, causing a somewhat bilirate appearance.</p>
      <p>
The 12 
th
or 13 
th
cusp (counting from the suture) is often flanked by deeper and slightly broader notches and, as a result, accentuated (see 
Fig. 1B, G
). We haven’t detected any specimen where this accentuated cusp is also more protruding and surpassing the other cusps.
</p>
      <p>
The protoconch is paucispiral, consisting of 1¼ whorl with a rather flattened shape (see 
Fig. 1D–E, O
). The number of protoconch whorls is remarkably constant among all material we studied, with the exception of a single specimen from Sulawesi (KF 4854) that has 1¾ protoconch whorls (see 
Fig. 1L
). This shell is identical to other shells, including the shape of its protoconch, apart from the fact that the last protoconch whorl continues turning another half whorl. We counted the number of spiral cords according to the method of 
Verduin (1977)
. Other methods, for example following the suture in between the protoconch whorls, may be responsible for the 2 protoconch whorls counted in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phos amoenus
</tp:taxon-name>
by 
Schwengel (1950: 81)
. The slightly eroded apex of dead-collected but otherwise fresh looking specimens (for example KF 2164 from 
Guam
) may have the sculpture along the first teleoconch whorl smoothened in such a subtle way that the protoconch appears larger and with more whorls.
</p>
      <p>In some specimens, the adapical apertural knob, inside the apertural lip, may be situated slightly more adapically than the parietal knob on the columella, resulting in a somewhat skewed anal notch, rather than having both anal knobs aligned.</p>
      <p>
For the description of the radula, we refer to the diagnosis under 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
above.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula naevosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
by its larger protoconch (
0.9 mm
long and 
0.9 mm
in diameter (KF 5029) vs 
0.6 to 0.7 mm
long and 
0.7 to 0.8 mm
in diameter in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
), the slightly higher number of protoconch whorls (1½ instead of usually 1¼), the upper spire whorls that are higher and increase in size more quickly, resulting in a slenderer spire (whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. naevosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
the transition from 3 
rd
to 4 
th
whorl falls within the first 
5 mm
of the teleoconch length, in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
this occurs from the 4 
th
to 5 
th
whorl that falls within these first 
5 mm
). The spiral sculpture of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. naevosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
is finer, starting with 3 finer primary spiral cords on the first teleoconch whorls (instead of 2 dominant ones), resulting in a more convex shape of the upper spire whorls. The secondary spiral cords, to the contrary, are slightly stronger when situated in the center between the primary spiral interspaces in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. naevosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
but lower in number (1 to 3 vs 4 or 
5 in
<tp:taxon-name>
S. egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
). By contrast, the number of secondary spiral cords on the subsutural slope is higher in number in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. naevosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
The axial ribs are weaker but slightly higher in number, especially on the spire whorls.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sinetectula farinosa
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. egregia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
by its higher number of protoconch whorls, the much broader shape with shorter spire and slightly more convex whorls,
</p>
      <p>the more cancellate sculpture with stronger spiral cords and axial ribs that are covered by pronounced incremental lamellae, sharper denticles on the columella and fewer (5 to 8) but stronger knobs inside the outer lip.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
