<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Hyssura reptans Annisaqois &amp; Wägele 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5535919</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/5FDE4DE5AA81CA8341917DDA71D41E6F</uri>
         <article-title>Morphology and Taxonomy of Isopoda Anthuroidea (Crustacea) from Sulawesi with description of six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.768.1501</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
D0451121-5E07-4F60-BADC-85D3D8BA38E9
</p>
      <p>
Figs 2–5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Blind species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura
</tp:taxon-name>
(eyes also lacking in male), pereopod 1 propodus palm concave in male, a comb of 6 setae on mesial surface in addition to two stronger medial setae and distally 4 setae, pleopod rami rectangular, pleopod 1 exopod not larger than endopod; exopods of pleopods 1 and 2 distally with more, 10 resp. 9 swimming setae, endopods with 5, uropod exopod narrow lanceolate, outer lateral margin smooth, medial margin slightly serrated, apex with several long simple setae, endopod of uropod as wide as sympod but about 2.5 times longer, a bit shorter than exopod, proximal two thirds of margins nearly parallel, distal margins with simple setae of varying length. Telson tongue-like, lateral margins serrated, not parallel; apex rounded and with 5 pairs of simple setae.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura ligurica
Wägele, 1981
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Wägele 1981a
) is most similar, with a tail fan that resembles that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura ligurica
</tp:taxon-name>
also has rectangular pleopod rami, but in comparison with 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
longer meri and carpi in P4–7 and only one sensory spine on the propodi. The female has strong propodi of P1 and P2; unfortunately, the females of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
still remain to be discovered.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species epithet is derived from 
repto
(to crawl).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
and type locality

INDONESIA
• 
♂
(
2.1 mm
); 
Bangka Island
, 
off Areng Kambing
; 
1°46′27.53″ N
, 
125°11′19.53″ E
; 

5 m
depth

; 
in coral rubble
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 099.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

Description of 
type
specimen

</p>
      <p>BODY. Without chromatophores, 15–16 times as long as wide (rostrum to tip of telson). Head 1.7 times as long as wide, with a lateral constriction at half of its length. Eyes lacking. A small rostral projection between antennae. Pereonites dorsally smooth, as long as wide, length ratio of pereonites: 1&lt;2&gt;3&lt;4&gt; 5&gt; 6&gt; 7, pereonite 3 being about as long as pereonite 7. Pleonites 1–5 free, as wide as pereonites, total length of pleonites 1–5 exceeds length of pereonites 6 + 7. Telson about as long as uropods and shorter than three pleonites.</p>
      <p>
Table 1.
Anthuridea collected on the shores of Bangka Island.
</p>
      <p>
Species name
Sample locality
Substrate
Depth
Date
Collected specimen
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Bangka Island, off Areng Kambing, 1°46′27.53″N, 125°11′19.53”E
Coral rubble
5 m
24 Sept. 2019
1
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura indonesica
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Bangka Island, off jetty of Coral Eye resort, 1°44′22.04″ N, 125°8′41.19″ E
Coral rubble
2 m
17 Sept. 2019
8
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura maccaroni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Bangka Island, off jetty of Coral Eye resort, 1°44′22.04″ N, 125°8′41.19″ E
Coral rubble
2 m
17 Sept. 2019
2
<tp:taxon-name>
Pendanthura bangkaensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Bangka Island, off Coral Eye Resort, 1°44′22.04″ N, 125°8′41.19″ E
Coral rubble
1–2 m
21 Sept. 2019
3

E 
xpanathura
<tp:taxon-name>
collaris
(
Kensley, 1979
)
</tp:taxon-name>
Bangka Island, in front of Coral Eye Resort near jetti, 1°44′20.22″ N, 125°8′46.07″ E
Coral rubble
1–2 m
26 Sept. 2019
5
<tp:taxon-name>
Expanathura marcoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Bangka Island, in front of Coral Eye Resort, 1°44′20.22″ N, 125°8′46.07″ E
Coral rubble
1–2 m
26 Sept. 2019
1
<tp:taxon-name>
Colanthura gerungi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Bangka Island, west of Coral Eye Resort, 1°45′20.77″ N, 125°7′57.28″ E
Seagrass bed
1–2 m
18 Sept. 2019
14
Bangka Island, west of Coral Eye Resort, 1°45′19.92″ N, 125°7′58.96″E
M a n g r o v e roots
1–2 m
21.Sept. 2019
2
Bangka Island, off Coral Eye Resort, 1°44′22.04″ N, 125°8′41.19″ E
Coral rubble
1–2m
26 Sept. 2019
1
</p>
      <p>ANTENNAE. Antenna 1 peduncle of three articles, first 1.5 times as long as wide, articles 2 and 3 progressively shorter; flagellum with typical male modifications: nearly twice as long as peduncle and composed of 9 articles; distal articles narrower, last article tiny; all flagellum articles except the first with long and thin aesthetascs, arranged in a single transverse row per article, number of aesthetascs distally decreasing, last article with only one aesthetasc. Antenna 2 peduncle with 5 articles, second article longest and widest; flagellum of 8 articles, not as long as peduncle articles 4 + 5, with several simple setae, longest on distal article.</p>
      <p>MOUTHPARTS. Were lost during dissection; however, in situ a maxilliped palp with five articles was visible, not covering mouthparts but erected nearly perpendicularly, and a mandible with an atrophied endite. Presumably the mouthparts of males are not functional.</p>
      <p>PEREOPODS. Pereopod 1 weakly subchelate, propodus palm concave, a comb of 6 setae on mesial surface in addition to two stronger medial setae and distally 4 setae; carpus triangular with short, not prominent ventrodistal projection bearing a simple seta; more proximally another seta; merus dorsal portion nearly triangular. Pereopod 2 propodus less curved than in P1, elongated, about three times as long as wide, palm distally with 3 sensory spines and basally slightly concave; carpus ventrodistally only little projecting, as in pereopod 1. Pereopod 3 similar to pereopod 2. Pereopods 4–7 similar. Propodi distally with two short sensory spines on distoventral margin, with a tooth-like projection in between, carpus trapezoidal, with shorter dorsal margin, merus subtriangular and as long as carpus.</p>
      <p>
PLEOPODS. All of similar shape, rami nearly rectangular. Pleopod 1 exopod not larger than endopod; exopods of pleopods 1 and 2 distally with 10 resp. 9 swimming setae, endopods with 5. Exopod of Plp 2 composed of two articles. Appendix masculina on Plp 
2 in
form of a cylindrical rod about 30% as long as endopod, distally rounded, without further conspicuous features.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
Map of Northern Sulawesi with sampling sites on Bangka Island
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype in dorsal and lateral view (2.1 mm) (MZB Iso 099).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura reptan
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (MZB Iso 099). Abbreviations: A1 = antenna 1; A2 = antenna 2; P1–P3 = pereopods 1–3.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (MZB Iso 099). Abbreviations: P4–P7 = pereopods 4–7; Plp1–2 = pleopods 1–2.
</p>
      <p>UROPOD. Exopod narrow lanceolate, length about 7.6 times greatest width, outer lateral margin smooth, medial margin slightly serrated with some single setae in notches; apex with several long simple setae. Endopod as wide as sympod but about 2.5 times longer, a bit shorter than exopod, proximal two thirds of margins nearly parallel, distal margins with simple setae of varying length. Telson tongue-like, lateral margins serrated, not parallel; apex rounded and with 5 pairs of simple seate.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
We place this species in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura
Norman &amp; Stebbing, 1884
</tp:taxon-name>
because autapomorphies of other genera are missing. Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura
</tp:taxon-name>
are blind, the P1–3 carpus is barely projecting ventrodistally. A reduction of male mouthparts has been reported for 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. vimsae
(
Kensley, 1978
a)
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Wägele 1981a
), other males have not been described. The male of 
<tp:taxon-name>
H. vimsae
</tp:taxon-name>
also has a comb of setae on P1 propodus; similar combs have also been described for some species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura
</tp:taxon-name>
(

<tp:taxon-name>K. biriwa</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>K. marrongie</tp:taxon-name>
,

see 
Poore &amp; Lew Ton 1988
). It is remarkable that also the male is blind, while in other 
<tp:taxon-name>Hyssuridae</tp:taxon-name>
at least males have prominent eyes. In the present species the carpus of P4–7 is shorter than in previously described species. Other characters are plesiomorphic and occur also in other 
<tp:taxon-name>Hyssuridae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura reptans
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype. Abbreviations: Urp = uropod; Tel = telson.
</p>
      <p>
This is the first 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hyssura
</tp:taxon-name>
described from the Indo-Pacific. The other species occur in the Atlantic Ocean or in the Mediterranean and often in bathyal waters
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
