<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura indonesica
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
C6689867-1A0D-4D40-B97F-DEF712439118
</p>
      <p>
Figs 6–9
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura
</tp:taxon-name>
with pair of small dorsolateral black eyes, pereopod 1 propodus with two prominent strong setae on mesial surface, on palm two short sensory spines, carpus with acute posterodisal projection, pereopods 2 and 3 subsimilar to 1; however, propodus more slender, palm with 2 sensory spines and carpus projecting as in pereopod 1. Uropod exopod long-oval, greatest width proximally, lateroventral margin forming a shallow lobe; lateral margins smooth, a single short seta on each side, apex with several long simple setae; uropod endopod as long as sympod, shorter than exopod, elongated with rounded apex, telson tongue-like, lateral margins not parallel, distally on each side of apex a single prominent tooth; apex with central pair of short setae, and on each side of it another 5 setae.
</p>
      <p>
Focusing on species known from the tropical/subtropical Indo-Pacific, 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. afareiatu
Müller, 1991
</tp:taxon-name>
from Moorea has a broader uropod exopod and a Plp 1 endopod distinctly narrower than the exopod. It seems that on the propodus of P1 there is only 1 strong seta on the mesial surface. The species needs to be redescribed. 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. caudoserrata
Negoescu, 1994
</tp:taxon-name>
(
New Caledonia
) has serrated telson margins and uropod exopod dorsomedial margins, and a longer maxilliped endite (surpassing the second palp article). 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. currawan
Poore &amp; Lew Ton, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
(New South Wales), 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. gidgee
Poore &amp; Lew Ton, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. marrongie
Poore &amp; Lew Ton, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. werawera
Poore &amp; Lew Ton, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
from Queensland need redescriptions, but the tail fan drawings clearly show differences with the new species: serrated margins of uropods in 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. currawan
</tp:taxon-name>
, broader uropods in 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. gidgee
</tp:taxon-name>
, and slender uropod exopods without ventrolateral lobe in 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. marrongie
</tp:taxon-name>
. In 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. currawan
</tp:taxon-name>
the propodus palms of P1 and P2 have three (instead of two) spines. In 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. werawera
</tp:taxon-name>
the uropod exopod lobe at its ventrolateral margin is larger than in the new species, furthermore, in 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. werawera
</tp:taxon-name>
the lateral telson margins are parallel.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Named after the country where the species was discovered.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
INDONESIA
• 
immature adult
(
2.5 mm
); 
Bangka Island
(Northern Sulawesi), 
off the jetty of Coral Eye Resort
; 
1°44′22.04″ N
, 
125°8′41.19″ E
; 

2 m
depth

; 
in coral rubble
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

17 Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 100.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
INDONESIA
• 
3 immature
adults (
2.5–2.8 mm
), 3 manca stages (
1.8–2.25 mm
), 1 postmanca (
2.5 mm
); 
Bangka Island
(Northern Sulawesi), 
off the jetty of Coral Eye Resort
; 
1°44′22.04″ N
, 
125°8′41.19″ E
; 

2 m
depth

; 
in coral rubble
; 
M. Annisaqois
and 
J.W. Wägele
leg.; 

17 Sep. 2019

; 
MZB
Iso 101

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura indonesica
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, immature adult in dorsal and lateral view (2.5 mm) (MZB Iso 100). Abbreviations: Md = mandible; Mx = maxilla; Mxp = maxilliped.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 7.
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura indonesica
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, immature adult (MZB Iso 100). Abbreviations: A1 = antenna 1; A2 = antenna 2; P1–P3 = pereopods 1–3.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura indonesica
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, immature adult (MZB Iso 100). Abbreviations: P4– P7 = pereopods 4–7; Plp1–2 = pleopods 1–2; UEx = exopod of uropod.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

Description of 
holotype
</p>
      <p>BODY. Without chromatophores, 13–14 times as long as wide (rostrum to tip of telson). Head slightly as long as wide, with a pair of small dorsolateral black eyes. A small rostral projection between antennae. Pereonites dorsally smooth, as long as wide, posterior segments (4–7) slightly wider than anterior ones; length ratio of pereonites: 1&lt;2&gt;3&lt;4 = 5&gt;6&gt;7. Pleonites 1–5 free, as wide as pereonites, total length of pleonites 1–5 nearly length of pereonites 6 + 7, lateroventral margins with some feather-like setae. Telson about as long as uropods and as length of three pleonites.</p>
      <p>ANTENNAE. Antenna 1 peduncle of three articles, first longest, articles 2 and 3 progressively shorter and slightly narrower, a conspicuous long seta on third article; flagellum about as long as first peduncle article, of four articles, with a single aesthetasc on last article. Antenna 2 peduncle with 5 articles, second article longest and widest; flagellum of 8 articles, somewhat as long as peduncle articles 4 + 5, with several simple setae, longest on distal article.</p>
      <p>MANDIBLE. With pointed but not sharp molar, lamina dentata with 4 teeth, incisor with two stout teeth; palp of three articles, distally only two simple setae, second article longest. Maxilla 1 lateral endite apically with 5 curved spine-like teeth, spines 1.3 and 4 more slender than spine 2, apical spine 5 strongest; medial endite short, a single distal seta. Maxilliped with 5 palp articles, articles 2 and 3 longest and widest, last article small and narrow, with 3 apical simple setae; endite present, surpassing palp article 1 distally, with a single distal seta.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura indonesica
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, immature adult (MZB Iso 100). Abbreviations: Tel = telson; Usym = sympod of uropod; Uen = endopod of uropod.
</p>
      <p>PEREOPODS. Pereopod 1 subchelate, carpus triangular with ventrodistal projection forming a spine in vicinity of a simple seta; more proximally a sensory spine; propodus with two prominent strong setae on mesial surface, on palm two short sensory spines and thin serrated cuticular scales; dactylus distally with a single claw and a short spine (second claw). Pereopod 2 of similar shape, however, propodus more slender, palm with 2 sensory spines and carpus projecting as in pereopod 1. Pereopod 3 similar to pereopod 2. Pereopods 4–6 similar, pereopod 7 weaker. Propodi with single short sensory spine on distoventral margin, propodus of P4 more oval than in P5–7, carpus trapezoidal with shorter dorsal margin.</p>
      <p>PLEOPODS. All of similar shape, pleopod 1 exopod not larger than endopod; exopods of pleopods 1 and 2 distally with more swimming setae (11) than endopods (5). Uropod exopod long-oval, greatest width proximally, lateroventral margin forming a shallow lobe; length about 2.4 times greatest width, lateral margins smooth, a single short seta on each side, apex with several long simple setae. Endopod as long as sympod, shorter than exopod, elongated with rounded apex, on ventromedial margin a group of short plumose setae, two plumose setae more laterally; apex with many long and slender simple setae.</p>
      <p>TELSON. Tongue-like, lateral margins not parallel, distally on each side of apex a single prominent tooth; apex with central pair of short setae, and at each side of it another 5 setae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
A combination of characters is typical of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura
</tp:taxon-name>
: above all the shape of the uropod exopod with its lobe on the lateral (ventrally directed) margin, then the blunt (not acute) molar process, the ventrodistal projection of the P1 carpus, the short rectangular carpus of P4–7, and the lack of autapomorphies of other genera (e.g., longer distoventral carpus projections on P2 or P3, reduced setation on pleopod endopods, shortened telson, strong spines on uropods).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura flexibilis
(
Pasternak, 1982
)
</tp:taxon-name>
(redescribed by Negoescu 1984) does not fit the generic diagnosis and needs redescription. The operculiform Plp 1 exopod indicates that this might not be a member of the family 
<tp:taxon-name>Hyssuridae</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
The shape of the tail fan allows the identification of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kupellonura indonesica
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
The new species differs from all other hitherto described species. The telson has no distolateral serrations except a pair of prominent indentations. A similar telson shape occurs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. mediterranea
Barnard, 1925
</tp:taxon-name>
(see 
Wägele 1981a
) and, with weak indentations, in 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. werawera
Poore &amp; Lew Ton, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
, however, in these species the uropod exopod is medially strongly lobed. In comparison with other species the molar process of the mandible is more pointed.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
