<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Denticupachydomella
Yuan
</tp:taxon-name>
in 

Yuan 
et al
., 2009

</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Denticupachydomella spinosa
Yuan
</tp:taxon-name>
in 

Yuan 
et al
., 2009

by original designation.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Original diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
“A new 
<tp:taxon-name>Pachydomellidae</tp:taxon-name>
genus with left valve having straight dorsal border, two horny dorsal spines erecting at the anterior cardinal angle, one stronger spine at the posterior cardinal angle, three denticles along dorsal border, one posteroventral spine and pustulous lateral surface.” (from 

Yuan 
et al.
2009: 392–393

).
</p>
      <p>
Emended diagnosis
</p>
      <p>A new genus with a relatively massive postero-ventral spine, spines of various morphology and strength developed along the dorsal margin of the left valve and surface pustulose.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="taxon_list">
      <p>
Assigned species
</p>
      <p>
The following species are herein re-assigned to the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Denticupachydomella
</tp:taxon-name>
:
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Microcheilinella
</tp:taxon-name>
? 
<tp:taxon-name>
multinodosa
Forel
</tp:taxon-name>
in 

Crasquin 
et al.
, 2010

from the Changhsingian, Late Permian of the Meishan section, 
Zhejiang Province
, 
China
(

Crasquin 
et al.
2010

);
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Microcheilinella
sp. D
</tp:taxon-name>
in 

Zazzali (2016: 208–209

, pl. 14f–g, unpublished material, PhD thesis), Late Capitanian, Middle Permian, Penglaitan section, 
Guangxi
, South 
China
(
Fig. 11R–S
).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The thorough comparison of ornate 
<tp:taxon-name>Microcheilinellidae</tp:taxon-name>
revealed that all the above-mentioned species share postero-ventral spines on both valves and spines/nodules/pustules along the dorsal margin and over the lateral surface. Conversely, the two horny dorsal spines and the three denticles along the dorsal border originally described by 

Yuan 
et al.
(2009)

as of generic significance to the newly erected genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Denticupachydomella
</tp:taxon-name>
rather appear as variations of the morphology and strength of the spines, thus being of specific significance. The diagnosis of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Denticupachydomella
Yuan
</tp:taxon-name>
in 

Yuan 
et al.
, 2009

is here emended to clarify this issue of generic versus specific characters.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
