<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia mescaleroella
Forel
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
52B30AEF-EB47-4D12-A0BC-20EC095A2F6F
</p>
      <p>
Figs 5E
, 
8O–R
, 
9A–C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
A species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia
</tp:taxon-name>
with three spines, two long and one short, along the dorsal margin of LV and the ventro-lateral ala not terminated by spine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
From the tribe of Mescalero Apaches who inhabited parts of the Southwest US and Northwest 
Mexico
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
USA
• left valve, (
Fig. 8O
); 
Guadalupe Mountains
, 
West Texas
, ‘ 
McKittrick Canyon’ Member
, 
Bell Canyon Formation
, MKCS1 section, sample 4 (GM5); 
Capitanian
, 
Middle Permian
; 
MNHN.F.F63433
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
USA
• 
1 left valve
(
Fig. 9A
); 
Guadalupe Mountains
, 
West Texas
, ‘ 
McKittrick Canyon’ Member
, 
Bell Canyon Formation
, MKCS1 section, sample 4 (GM5); 
Capitanian
, 
Middle Permian
; 
MNHN.F.F63435
(
Fig. 8Q
)

• 

1 right valve
; same locality and sample as for preceding; 
Capitanian
, 
Middle Permian
; 
MNHN.F.F63437

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
USA
• 
1 left valve
; 
Guadalupe Mountains
, 
West Texas
, ‘ 
McKittrick Canyon’ Member
, 
Bell Canyon Formation
, MKCS1 section, sample 4 (GM5); 
Capitanian
, 
Middle Permian
; 
MNHN.F.F63434

• 

1 left valve
; same locality and sample as for preceding; 
Capitanian
, 
Middle Permian
; 
MNHN.F.F63436

• 

1 left valve
; same locality as for preceding but sample 2 (GM6); 
Capitanian
, 
Middle Permian
; 
MNHN.F.F63438

• 

1 left valve
; same locality and sample as for preceding; 
Capitanian
, 
Middle Permian
; 
MNHN.F.F63439
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9
(next page). SEM micrographs of ostracods from the Middle Permian (Roadian, Quarry section, samples GM1; Capitanian, 
MKCS
1 section, samples 4 (GM5) and 2 (GM6)) of the 
Guadalupe
Mountains (West 
Texas
, 
USA
). All specimens are temporarily housed in the collections of the Muséum national d’histoire naturelle, Paris, 
France
(
MNHN
). 
A–C
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia mescaleroella
Forel
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A
. 
Paratype
, A-1, external view of a right valve, sample 4 (GM5) (
MNHN
.F. 
F63437
). 
B
. External view of a left valve, A-2, sample 2 (GM6) (
MNHN
.F. 
F63438
). 
C
. External view of a right valve, A-2, sample 2 (GM6) (
MNHN
.F. 
F63439
). – 
D–J
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia sexagintaduella
Forel
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
D
. 
Holotype
, right lateral view of a carapace, adult, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63440
). 
E
. 
Paratype
, external view of a left valve, adult, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63441
). 
F
. External view of a left valve, A-1, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63442
). 
G
. Right lateral view of a carapace, A-2, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63443
). 
H
. External view of a left valve, A-2, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63444
). 
I
. Right lateral view of a carapace, A-3, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63445
). 
J
. External view of a left valve, A-3, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63446
). – 

K– 
R

. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia wordensis
(
Hamilton, 1942
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
K
. External view of a left valve, adult, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63447
). 
L
. External view of a left valve, adult, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63448
). 
M
. External view of a left valve, A-2?, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63449
). 
N
. External view of a right valve, sample 4 (GM5) (
MNHN
.F. 
F63450
). 
O
. External view of a right valve, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63497
). 
P
. External view of a right valve, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63451
). 
Q
. External view of a left valve, sample GM1 (
MNHN
.F. 
F63452
). 

R

. Right lateral view of a carapace, sample 4 (GM5) (
MNHN
.F. 
F63453
). Scale bars: 100 µm
</p>
      <p>.</p>
      <p>
• 

13 valves
; 
Guadalupe Mountains
, 
West Texas
, 
‘McKittrick Canyon’ Member
, 
Bell Canyon Formation
, MKCS1 section, samples 4 (GM5) and 2 (GM6); 
Capitanian
, 
Middle Permian
; 
MNHN.F.F63495
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Dimensions
</p>
      <p>
See 
Fig. 5E
.
</p>
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>LV: stocky, subtriangular in lateral view with Hmax along DB and Lmax in lower half of H; dorsal margin uniformly arched with concave ADB and PDB, and apex of curvature with 3 equidistant spines; the 3 spines triangular in shape and thickest at base, central spine sub-vertical, external spines biggest, anterior one oriented anteriorly and posterior one oriented posteriorly; AB beak-like located in upper fourth of H with long and subvertical AVB; ventral margin uniformly convex; PB beak-like, located below mid-H; anterior and posterior margins laterally compressed; ventro-lateral ala delimited by smooth subhorizontal ridge lacking terminal spine.</p>
      <p>RV: elongate, subtriangular in lateral view with Hmax at AD angulation and Lmax below mid-H; dorsal margin tripartite with DB slightly convex, very concave ADB and PDB; AB beak-like located in upper fourth of H with AVB long and straight; PB beak-like located in lower third of H; ventral margin long and straight except for tenuous oral concavity in anterior part; anterior and posterior margins laterally compressed; lateral surface inflated dorsally into narrow platform and ventrally delimited by lateroventral ala lacking terminal spine and raising upward anteriorly.</p>
      <p>
Occurrence
</p>
      <p>
Samples 4 (GM5) and 2 (GM6),MKCS1 section, ‘McKittrick Canyon’ Member, Bell Canyon Formation, 
Guadalupe
Mountains, West 
Texas
, 
USA
, Capitanian, Middle Permian (this work).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia dorsospinosa
Sohn, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
from the Roadian, Middle Permian of 
Texas
(
Sohn 1954
) is morphologically very similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia mescaleroella
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but the new species differs by its relatively smaller dimensions, three thicker dorsal spines, lack of a terminal sharp spine at the latero-ventral ridge and PB located higher and more upturned. 
Sohn (1954)
observed that specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia dorsospinosa
Sohn, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
have one or two spines along the dorsal margin of LV. However, all other characters of the carapaces and valves are very similar, so he suggested that all specimens are conspecific. Although very similar morphologically, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia mescaleroella
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
cannot be considered as another degree in the variability of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia dorsospinosa
Sohn, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
as the lateral morphologies of the two species are significantly different as detailed above. Contrary to what was shown for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia dorsospinosa
Sohn, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ceratobairdia mescaleroella
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
has a conservative number and position of dorsal spines, the only difference observed is in the expression of the central spine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
