<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophiopteris
E.A. Smith, 1877
</tp:taxon-name>
. (No other genera)
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
         <p>
Description
</p>
         <p>ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3–4× disc diameter; covering without granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate present. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section round, or oval. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.9–1. Arm spines flat or cylindrical; mainly lateral; predominantly erect, standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines longer than two segments. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; nearly as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section round. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs without constriction. Ventral position of LAP projecting ventroproximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; with a fully developed sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; larger in middle of arm. Distance between spine articulations equal. Nerve and muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.</p>
         <p>DORSAL DISC. Disc pentagonal or circular; high (above arm level). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules; with concealed primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with granules; length more than half of the disc radius; scalene (oblique) triangular.</p>
         <p>VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii with spines. Scales on ventral interradii absent. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae). Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP present; single row of lateral papillae; spiniform. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering more than one third of the length of an interradius; about as long as wide. Madreporite no data. Adoral shield separated. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate dorsal half widest; entire. Dental sockets heart-shaped(?); equal to or more than 50% of the width. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip, but never spine-like).</p>
         <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:nomenclature/>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p>
Type
genus

</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>
Clarkcoma
Devaney, 1970
</tp:taxon-name>
. (No other genera)
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
               <p>
Description
</p>
               <p>ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3–4× disc diameter; covering without granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present.Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section oval. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9. Arm spines flat; mainly lateral; predominantly erect, standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines longer than two segments. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; more than two times as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs with constriction. Ventral position of LAP projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventrodistal tip of LAP not projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; with a fully developed sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; dorsalwards increasing in size. Distance between spine articulations equal. Nerve and muscle openings separated by large, prominent ridge or regular stereom. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.</p>
               <p>DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules; with concealed primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with granules; length more than half of the disc radius.</p>
               <p>VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii with granules. Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of scales on H line of an interradius no data. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae). Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP present; single row of lateral papillae; paddle-shaped. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; about as long as wide. Madreporite no data. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate of equal width all over; entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped and circular; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as perforation with septum. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip, but never spine-like). Teeth on DP arranged as a single row on ⅔ and a cluster of tooth papillae on ⅓ of dental plate.</p>
               <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
            </tp:treatment-sec>
            <tp:taxon-treatment>
               <tp:nomenclature/>
               <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
                  <p>
Type
genus

</p>
                  <p>
                     <tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha
Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
               </tp:treatment-sec>
               <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
                  <p>
Other genera
</p>
                  <p>
                     <tp:taxon-name>
Ophialcaea
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophientrema
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiocanops
Koehler, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
Lyman, 1869
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiohamus
O’Hara &amp; Stöhr, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolebes
Lyman, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiomitrella
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiomoeris
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
; ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiophthalmus
</tp:taxon-name>
’ 
Matsumoto, 1917
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioripa
Koehler, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiosemnotes
Matsumoto, 1917
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiurothamnus
Matsumoto, 1917
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
               </tp:treatment-sec>
               <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
                  <p>
Description
</p>
                  <p>
ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3× disc diameter, or length 3– 4× disc diameter, or length more than 4× disc diameter; covering without granules/spines/tubercles.Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present.Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section round. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9, or 0.9–1 (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly erect, standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines between one and two segments long (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
), or longer than two segments. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; nearly as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs with constriction. Ventral position of LAP not projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP not projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; with a fully developed sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; dorsalwards increasing in size (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha bidentata
(Bruzelius, 1805)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
), or all similar (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha abyssicola
G.O. Sars, 1872
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
). Distance between spine articulations dorsalwards increasing. Nerve and muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.
</p>
                  <p>
DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms) or high (above arm level) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
); with concealed primary plates; with scales; with spines (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
) or without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with spines and with granules; length between one third and half of the disc radius (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bidentata
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
), or length more than half of the disc radius (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. abyssicola
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
); isosceles (mirror-symmetric) triangular to pear-shaped, or bar-like.
</p>
                  <p>
VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc or not restricted to the disc (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiocanops
</tp:taxon-name>
). Ventral interradii with spines (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. abyssicola
</tp:taxon-name>
) or with granules (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bidentata
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
, with spine and granules in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
). Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of scales on H line of an interradius about 7–14. Ventral teeth single. Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP present; single row of lateral papillae; spiniform. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; much wider than long. Madreporite one or multiple; with one pore or with numerous pores. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate of equal width all over, or dorsal half widest (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
); entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip, but never spine-like). Teeth on DP arranged as single row.
</p>
                  <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
               </tp:treatment-sec>
            </tp:taxon-treatment>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Clarkcoma
Devaney, 1970
</tp:taxon-name>
. (No other genera)
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
         <p>
Description
</p>
         <p>ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3–4× disc diameter; covering without granules/spines/tubercles. Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present.Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present. Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section oval. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9. Arm spines flat; mainly lateral; predominantly erect, standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines longer than two segments. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; more than two times as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs with constriction. Ventral position of LAP projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventrodistal tip of LAP not projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; with a fully developed sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; dorsalwards increasing in size. Distance between spine articulations equal. Nerve and muscle openings separated by large, prominent ridge or regular stereom. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.</p>
         <p>DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules; with concealed primary plates; with scales; without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with granules; length more than half of the disc radius.</p>
         <p>VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc. Ventral interradii with granules. Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of scales on H line of an interradius no data. Ventral teeth several (tooth papillae). Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP present; single row of lateral papillae; paddle-shaped. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; about as long as wide. Madreporite no data. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate of equal width all over; entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped and circular; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as perforation with septum. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip, but never spine-like). Teeth on DP arranged as a single row on ⅔ and a cluster of tooth papillae on ⅓ of dental plate.</p>
         <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:taxon-treatment>
         <tp:nomenclature/>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
            <p>
Type
genus

</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha
Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
Other genera
</p>
            <p>
               <tp:taxon-name>
Ophialcaea
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophientrema
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiocanops
Koehler, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
Lyman, 1869
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiohamus
O’Hara &amp; Stöhr, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolebes
Lyman, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiomitrella
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiomoeris
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
; ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiophthalmus
</tp:taxon-name>
’ 
Matsumoto, 1917
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioripa
Koehler, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiosemnotes
Matsumoto, 1917
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiurothamnus
Matsumoto, 1917
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
         <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p>
Description
</p>
            <p>
ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3× disc diameter, or length 3– 4× disc diameter, or length more than 4× disc diameter; covering without granules/spines/tubercles.Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present.Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section round. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9, or 0.9–1 (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly erect, standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines between one and two segments long (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
), or longer than two segments. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; nearly as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs with constriction. Ventral position of LAP not projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP not projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; with a fully developed sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; dorsalwards increasing in size (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha bidentata
(Bruzelius, 1805)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
), or all similar (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha abyssicola
G.O. Sars, 1872
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
). Distance between spine articulations dorsalwards increasing. Nerve and muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.
</p>
            <p>
DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms) or high (above arm level) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
); with concealed primary plates; with scales; with spines (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
) or without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with spines and with granules; length between one third and half of the disc radius (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bidentata
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
), or length more than half of the disc radius (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. abyssicola
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
); isosceles (mirror-symmetric) triangular to pear-shaped, or bar-like.
</p>
            <p>
VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc or not restricted to the disc (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiocanops
</tp:taxon-name>
). Ventral interradii with spines (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. abyssicola
</tp:taxon-name>
) or with granules (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bidentata
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
, with spine and granules in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
). Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of scales on H line of an interradius about 7–14. Ventral teeth single. Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP present; single row of lateral papillae; spiniform. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; much wider than long. Madreporite one or multiple; with one pore or with numerous pores. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate of equal width all over, or dorsal half widest (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
); entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip, but never spine-like). Teeth on DP arranged as single row.
</p>
            <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
         </tp:treatment-sec>
      </tp:taxon-treatment>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
genus

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha
Müller &amp; Troschel, 1842
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
Other genera
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ophialcaea
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophientrema
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiocanops
Koehler, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
Lyman, 1869
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiohamus
O’Hara &amp; Stöhr, 2006
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolebes
Lyman, 1878
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiomitrella
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiomoeris
Koehler, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
; ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiophthalmus
</tp:taxon-name>
’ 
Matsumoto, 1917
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
Verrill, 1899
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioripa
Koehler, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiosemnotes
Matsumoto, 1917
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiurothamnus
Matsumoto, 1917
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
ARM. Arm shape unbranched; length 3× disc diameter, or length 3– 4× disc diameter, or length more than 4× disc diameter; covering without granules/spines/tubercles.Arm combs absent. Dorsal arm plate present. Accessory dorsal arm plate absent. Ventral arm plate present.Accessory ventral arm plate absent. Girdle of tiny hooks on the arms absent. Spines all similar in shape. Arm spine cross section round. The ratio of thickness of distal ⅓ of arm spine to maximum thickness (in a given cross-sectional plane) 0.6–0.9, or 0.9–1 (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Arm spines pointed; mainly lateral; predominantly erect, standing perpendicular to arm axis. Longest arm spines between one and two segments long (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
), or longer than two segments. Tentacle scales present; pores visible along most of the arm; nearly as long as wide; shorter than the spine nearby; cross section oval. Position of lateral arm plate (LAP) arched (wrapped around the arm). Dorsal and/or ventral edge(s) of LAPs with constriction. Ventral position of LAP not projecting ventro-proximalwards. Ventro-distal tip of LAP not projecting ventralwards. Arm spine articulation with dorsal and ventral lobes; with a fully developed sigmoidal fold; arranged over entire distal LAP edge; dorsalwards increasing in size (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha bidentata
(Bruzelius, 1805)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
), or all similar (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha abyssicola
G.O. Sars, 1872
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
). Distance between spine articulations dorsalwards increasing. Nerve and muscle openings separated by small ridge if at all. Nerve opening smaller than muscle opening.
</p>
      <p>
DORSAL DISC. Disc circular; flat (about same level as arms) or high (above arm level) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Integument obscuring plates. Dorsal disc with granules (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
); with concealed primary plates; with scales; with spines (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiacantha
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
) or without spines. Dorsal disc scale/plate without tubercles. Radial shield present; with spines and with granules; length between one third and half of the disc radius (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bidentata
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophioplinthaca
</tp:taxon-name>
), or length more than half of the disc radius (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. abyssicola
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
); isosceles (mirror-symmetric) triangular to pear-shaped, or bar-like.
</p>
      <p>
VENTRAL DISC. Gonads restricted to the disc or not restricted to the disc (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiocanops
</tp:taxon-name>
). Ventral interradii with spines (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. abyssicola
</tp:taxon-name>
) or with granules (
<tp:taxon-name>
O. bidentata
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiochondrus
</tp:taxon-name>
, with spine and granules in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
). Scales on ventral interradii covering the whole area of an interradius. The number of scales on H line of an interradius about 7–14. Ventral teeth single. Infradental papillae on oral plate present. Buccal scales on OP absent. Accessory oral papillae on OP absent. Lateral oral papillae on OP present; single row of lateral papillae; spiniform. Adoral shield spine present. Lyman’s ossicle present. Oral shield covering less than one third of interradius; much wider than long. Madreporite one or multiple; with one pore or with numerous pores. Adoral shield meeting in front of the oral shield. Abradial genital plate not twisted. Number of genital slits one per bursa. Genital slit longer than half the length of an interradius. Genital papillae absent. Dental plate of equal width all over, or dorsal half widest (
<tp:taxon-name>
Ophiolimna
</tp:taxon-name>
); entire (single plate). Dental sockets slit-shaped; equal to or more than 50% of the width. At least one socket on DP as depression or perforation without septum. Teeth flat (with round or slightly pointed tip, but never spine-like). Teeth on DP arranged as single row.
</p>
      <p>VERTEBRAE. Vertebrae zygospondylous; beyond segment 5 with short keel; without oral bridge.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
