<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Stephostethus chinensis
(
Reitter, 1877
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 7–9
, 
11–14
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Lathridius chinensis
Reitter, 1877: 113
</tp:taxon-name>
.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Stephostethus chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Rücker 2018: 172

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Stephostethus chinensis
(
Reitter 1877
)
</tp:taxon-name>
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. carinatus
Sen Gupta, 1976
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
India
. However, the former species can be distinguished from the latter by the structure of the genital segments of the
</p>
      <p>
male, and the characters of the teeth on male tibiae, as 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. carinatus
</tp:taxon-name>
has one tooth on the mid tibia, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
has no teeth on the mid tibia.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
TAIWAN
• 
2 ♂♂
; 
Nantou County
, 
Ren’ai
, 
Meifeng
; 
24.0973° N
, 
121.1764° E
; 

2113 m
a.s.l.

; 

30 Mar.–1 Apr. 2020

; 
F.S. Hu
and 
Y.J. Chen
leg.; 
by flight interception trap
; 
PCHO

• 

1 ♂
; 
Nantou
, 
Meifeng
; 

3–15 Oct. 1990

; 
C.K. Starr
leg.; 
yellow pan trap
; 
NMNS
ENT 766-5

• 

1 ♂
; 
Nantou
, 
Jenai
, 
Meifeng
; 

12 Nov.– 10 Dec. 2002

; 
C.S. Lin
and 
W.T. Yang
leg.; 
Malaise trap
; 
NMNS
ENT 4913-1077

• 

1 ♂
; 
Kaoshiang
[Kaohsiung, mistyped] (TM7), 
Tengchih
; 

9–18 Feb. 2009

; 
C.T. Yao
leg.; 
TARI

• 

1 ♀
; 
Kaoshiang
[Kaohsiung, mistyped] (TM3), 
Tengchih
; 

9–18 Feb. 2009

; 
C.T. Yao
leg.; 
TARI

• 

1 ♂
; 
Kaohsiung City
, 
Taoyuan
, 
Shishan logging trail
; 

8 Feb. 2020

; 
C.T. Hsu
leg.; 
beating
; 
PCHO

• 

2 ♂♂
; 
Taitung Hsien
, 
Chihpen
; 

17–18 Feb. 1982

; 
L.Y. Chou
and 
K.C. Chou
leg.; 
TARI

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>LENGTH. 1.83-2.00 mm.</p>
      <p>
WIDTH. 
0.86-0.97 mm
.
</p>
      <p>COLOUR. General body colour brown to dark brown, with legs and antennae yellowish brown.</p>
      <p>HEAD. Slightly longer than wide, width to length ratio 1.00: 1.20, surface strongly punctate, base of head depressed, clypeus narrower than head, covered with some short setae; temple narrower than eye, about half length of eye, with sharp hind angle. Antennae 11-segmented, second segment slightly shorter than third segment, apical three segments clubbed. Eyes strongly developed, with more than 20 facets. Sometimes covered with wax in ventral view.</p>
      <p>PRONOTUM. Slightly wider than long, width to length ratio 1.00: 0.95; sides almost parallel, widest at anterior margin, narrowest at posterior one-third. Front angle slightly protruded and bluntly rounded, anterior third with a pair of triangular depressions. Surface irregularly and densely punctate, with a pair of carinae on disc. Prosternum short, procoxa separated. Sometimes covered with wax in ventral and lateral views.</p>
      <p>
ELYTRA. Broadly oval, width to length ratio 1.00: 1.40, broadest at middle, apex round. Posterior third depressed. With eight punctate striae, 1 
st
striae complete, 2 
nd
striae connected with 7 
th
striae at posterior end of elytra, 3 
rd
striae connected with 6 
th
striae, 4 
th
striae connected with 5 
th
striae, 8 
th
striae incomplete. 5 
th
interstriae weakly carinate, 7 
th
interstriae strongly protruding at front, and extended to middle, with short setae. Scutellum broadly pentagonal.
</p>
      <p>METASTERNUM. Strongly convex, with fovea situated under mid coxa on each side and surrounded by radial striae. Sometimes covered with wax on meso- and metasternum.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Long and slender, covered with short setae on femora and tibiae. Tarsi 3-3-3, tarsomere 3 longer than 1 and 2 combined; arolium indistinct. Male protibia expanded and curved at apex, with one distinct tooth on anterior end; mid tibia straight, without any teeth; hind tibia straight, with three distinct teeth on anterior end. Female without any teeth on legs.</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA. Aedeagus weakly chitinized. Long and slender, sides parallel, sharp at apex; bent at anterior two fifths, and weakly curved at anterior fifth. Genital segments broad and short, broadest at base, apical end deeply concave with two rounded lobes (
Fig. 8
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Figs 7–9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Stephostethus chinensis
(
Reitter, 1877
) (TARI)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
7
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
8
. Male genital segments, dorsal view. 
9
. Male tibiae, A = protibia, B = midtibia, C = hindtibia. Scale bars: 7 = 0.5 mm; 8–9 = 0.1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
This species is only known from Asia, including Eastern Siberia, 
China
, 
Japan
and 
Mongolia
(
Johnson 2007
; 
Rücker 2018
, 
2020
), and is new to 
Taiwan
(
Fig. 12
). It is distributed in mid to southern 
Taiwan
, and is widely recorded in various areas, ranging in altitude from 
300 to 2300 m
a.s.l.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Stephostethus chinensis
</tp:taxon-name>
was recorded as a household pest in 
Japan
(
Tanaka &amp; Tahira 1995
). However, we have never found this species in indoor environments in 
Taiwan
. Some specimens of this species were collected by beating damp leaves in an artificial red oak forest (~ 
1700 m
a.s.l.), and some were collected with flight interception traps in the forest (
2113 m
a.s.l.) (
Fig. 11
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
