<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus atripennis
Burmeister, 1835
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus neglectus
Gavrilov-Zimin, 2018: 159
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 9.4.6–9.4.7. 
Syn. nov. Remarks

(the taxonomic notes published in 
Gavrilov-Zimin 2018: 153
on this subject are partly reported here for clarity)
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus
</tp:taxon-name>
, the 
type
genus of the tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Monophlebini</tp:taxon-name>
, was originally introduced in the coccidological literature by 
Guérin-Méneville (1827)
who did not include any species in this genus, but provided a diagnosis: “Genre de 1’ordre des Hémiptères, section des Homoptères, famille des Gallinsectes, établi par Latreille (Familles Naturelles du Règne Animal) et dont il ne donne pas les caractères; il dit seulement qu’il diffère des Dorthésies et des Cochenilles, parce que les antennes sont moniliformes et composées d’environ vingt-deux articles” (
Guérin-Méneville 1827: 99
). Obviously, Guérin-Méneville mentioned male characters, because most of 
<tp:taxon-name>Monophlebinae</tp:taxon-name>
males have “antennes …moniliformes” in contrast to all known females. The first species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus
</tp:taxon-name>
were described 8 years later by 
Burmeister (1835)
, who provided very brief and incomplete descriptions of the males of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. atripennis
Burmeister, 1835
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Java
(
Indonesia
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. fuscipennis
Burmeister, 1835
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Germany
. The 
type
specimens of both these species were lost. 
Cockerell (1902a: 232
; 
1902b: 317
) designated and discussed 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. atripennis
</tp:taxon-name>
as a 
type
species of genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus
</tp:taxon-name>
, in spite of the absence of any characters for identification of this species. 
Reyne (1965)
conducted an extensive study of 
<tp:taxon-name>Monophlebinae</tp:taxon-name>
males, collected from Java, but was unable to identify 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. atripennis
</tp:taxon-name>
. Moreover, scale insect systematics and identification is mainly based on female characters, whereas females of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. atripennis
</tp:taxon-name>
are unknown at all. So, an unambiguous identification of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. atripennis
</tp:taxon-name>
is not possible until now. The second species of Burmeister, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. fuscipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
, was transferred by 
Cockerell (1894)
to his genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palaeococcus
Cockerell, 1894
</tp:taxon-name>
. Later 
Cockerell (1902a: 233)
designated 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. fuscipennis
</tp:taxon-name>
as the 
type
species of the genus. Several taxonomists (
Westwood 1845
; 
Hempel 1920
; 
Vayssière 1932
) described additional species in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus
</tp:taxon-name>
from other regions of the world, but not from Java! All these descriptions are also incomplete or even based on male characters only.
</p>
      <p>
In order to resolve this very old problem, 
Gavrilov-Zimin (2018: 153)
suggested to use the only properly described species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. neglectus
Gavrilov-Zimin, 2018
</tp:taxon-name>
, collected in Java, as the new type species of the genus. However, the replacement of the type species could only be accomplished with the used of the plenary power by the International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature (Art. 81.1). Before the application to the ICZN, the type specimen for each involved species (the older type species and a newly proposed type species) have to be fixed. Since the type of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus atripennis
</tp:taxon-name>
is lost, an alternative solution was suggested by one of the ICZN commissioners (D.A. Dmitriev, 
Illinois
Natural History Survey, 
USA
, pers. com.). A 
neotype
could be designated for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus atripennis
</tp:taxon-name>
, and if this type specimen is, at the same time, the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monophlebus neglectus
</tp:taxon-name>
, this would establish the objective synonymy between two species names. Following this recommendation, I here designate the 
holotype
specimen of 

Monophebus 
<tp:taxon-name>neglectus</tp:taxon-name>

also to be the 
neotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Monophebus atripennis
</tp:taxon-name>
, establishing the formal synonymy between the two names. The 
neotype
label data are: adult female, K 1301-a, 
Indonesia
, 
Java
, “Buitenzorg” [Bogor], 1907, host plant and collector’s name unknown. The 
neotype
is deposited in the Zoological Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
