<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Gompholopium Gavrilov-Zimin 2021, gen. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4704965</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/73842430649F46F8985ED3780F15E9B4</uri>
         <article-title>New and poorly known giant scale insects (Homoptera: Coccinea: Margarodidae s. lat.) from the Oriental region with taxonomic and nomenclatural notes on the subfamily Monophlebinae</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/c8b84fd5-c191-4228-9cc9-9cbb4f8a0c68</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gompholopium
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
99E62D80-CF7C-4BC2-A385-F91F9EAB7D05
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Gompholopium quercicola
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new genus differs from all other genera of the tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Monophlebini</tp:taxon-name>
in the presence of lanceolate conical setae, densely covering the body and in the presence of the discoidal wax glands with stalked centre.
</p>
      <p>
Morphologically, the new genus seems to be the most similar to the Palaearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudaspidoproctus
Morrison, 1927
</tp:taxon-name>
and Nearctic 
<tp:taxon-name>
Llaveiella

Morrison, 
1927
</tp:taxon-name>
in the presence of numerous conical setae (see the figure and the key for genera in 
Gavrilov-Zimin 2018: 154
, 158).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The generic name was constructed from the Ancient Greek words ‘γόμφος’ (‘nail, spine’) + ‘λωπίον τό’ (‘clothes’), the gender is neuter.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Adult female
</p>
      <p>
Body broadly oval, covered by solid wax plates (
Fig. 1
). Antennae 9-segmented. Legs normally developed; claw without denticle; claw digitules short, setose. Mouthparts well developed. Abdominal spiracles numbering 7 pairs; each abdominal spiracle with unilocular atrium, without wax pores inside or just near spiracular atrium. Anal apparatus represented by a short tube with internal sclerotized anal ring. Fifteen round cicatrices forming semicircle on abdominal sternites. Wax glands represented by four main 
types
of discoidal wax glands: 1) variable pores with stalked centre; 2) usual multilocular pores with round or oval central loculus and 10–12 peripheral loculi; 3) irregular multilocular pores with multiform central loculus and 6-10 peripheral loculi; 4) simple pores. Conical setae very numerous, with more or less lanceolate apices. Flagellate setae of different size and thickness numerous.
</p>
      <p>
Male and larval instars
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
