<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Hemaspidoproctus cinereus
                        Gavrilov-Zimin 2021</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4704971</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4A02B3551C2BFFF9FDECFC7ADE92F4D1</uri>
                  <article-title>New and poorly known giant scale insects (Homoptera: Coccinea:
                        Margarodidae s. lat.) from the Oriental region with taxonomic and
                        nomenclatural notes on the subfamily Monophlebinae</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://zoobank.org/c8b84fd5-c191-4228-9cc9-9cbb4f8a0c68</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Hemaspidoproctus cinereus ( Green, 1922 ) </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Fig. 3 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> INDIA • ♀ adult ; Uttar Pradesh , Allahabad ; 17Apr. 1958 ;
                        N.Alexandrov leg.; on <tp:taxon-name> Psidium sp. </tp:taxon-name> (
                              <tp:taxon-name>Myrtaceae</tp:taxon-name> ) , ZIN RAS, K 1502 .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Redescription </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> Adult female in life covered with thick plates of white wax ( Fig. 3 ). Body broadly
                  oval, about 9 mm long. Antennae 10-segmented, covered with flagellate setae of
                  different thickness. Legs normally developed; trochanter with 3 sensillae on each
                  face; claw without a denticle; claw digitules short, setose. Mouthparts well
                  developed. Thoracic spiracles with spiracularia and groups of small quadrilocular
                  pores, located in notch near each atrium. Abdominal spiracles numbering 7 pairs,
                  located along abdominal margin on dorsum; each abdominal spiracle with unilocular
                  atrium, without wax pores inside or just near spiracular atrium. Anal apparatus
                  poorly visible in the available specimen, but it exactly represented by a short
                  tube with internal sclerotized ring. Seven oval cicatrices present on venter
                  posterior to vulva. Oval and round cuticular pouches of different size forming
                  rows on dorsum and in marginal zone of venter (see Fig. 3 ). Wax glands
                  represented by four types of discoidal pores: 1) large quadrilocular pores (each
                  about 12 μm in diameter) with cuticular duct, scattered on dorsum and forming
                  ovisac band on venter; 2) small quadrilocular pores (each about 9–10 μm in
                  diameter) without cuticular ducts, scattered on venter; 3) trilocular pores (each
                  about 9–10 μm in diameter) – probably modified small quadrilocular pores,
                  occasionally present on dorsum and venter among normal quadrilocular pores; 4)
                  multilocular pores (each about 12 μm in diameter), forming group around anal
                  opening on dorsum and group around vaginal opening on venter. Large bitubular
                  glands totally absent. Ovisac band present, formed by large quadrilocular pores.
                  Conical setae very numerous, scattered on all dorsum and on ventral surface of
                  cephalothorax; on dorsum more densely located conical setae additionally forming
                  groups along margin, submargin and midline. Flagellate setae of different size and
                  thickness numerous in medial and submedial zone of ventral cephalothorax and on
                  abdominal sternites. </p>
            <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name> Hemaspidoproctus cinereus ( Green, 1922 ) </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  comb. nov. Morphology of the adult ♀ from India (Allahabad) (ZIN RAS, K 1502). Not
                  to scale. </p>
            <p> Primolarva </p>
            <p> According to Morrison (1928: 151) , the primolarva has 5-segmented antennae; short
                  anal tube with double row of wax pores at inner end, with internal ring of disc
                  pores and with circle of peculiar capitate setae around anal opening; single
                  cicatrix present; quadrilocular pores, multilocular pores and large marginal
                  bitubular glands present; dorsum covered with numerous conical setae. </p>
            <p> Adult male and other larval instars </p>
            <p>Unknown.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
            <p> Remarks </p>
            <p> The type specimens of the species from Sri Lanka and the specimens from India ,
                  studied by Morrison (1928: 148) , have 3–5 cicatrices, whereas the female, studied
                  by me shows 7 cicatrices. </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
