<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
A79B8C4E-1540-4031-A067-7F12809D5B95
</p>
      <p>
Figs 30–33
, 
39
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The new species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Figs 24A–D
, 
26A–B
) in having the distal arm of the paracymbium with two projections in the male palp and the long parmula with a median incision in the epigyne (
Figs 31A–B
, 
32A–D
); it can be distinguished by: the distal suprategular apophysis long, sword-shaped, protruding beyond the apex of cymbium in retrolateral view (
Figs 30B
, 
31B
), but short, retained below the apex of cymbium in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Figs 24B
, 
26B
). The dorsal projection of the embolic plate almost touches the base of the cymbium in prolateral view (
Figs 30A
, 
31A
), but doesn’t touch the base of the cymbium in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Figs 24A
, 
26A
). The lateral projection of the distal arm of the paracymbium is tongue-shaped, away from the posterior margin of the tibia (
Figs 30B, D
, 
31B
), but finger-shaped, almost touching the posterior margin of the tibia in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Figs 24B, D
, 
26B
). The posterior projection of the anterior wall of the epigynal plate is longer than wide, protruding beyond the epigastric furrow (
Fig.32A–B
), but wider than long, not protruding beyond the epigastric furrow in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Fig. 27A–B
). The distal part of spermathecae inverted L-shaped (
Fig. 32D
), but hook-shaped in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. latus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
(
Fig. 27D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name comes from the Latin adjective ‘ 
longus
’ + ‘ 
multus
’, meaning ‘long’ + ‘much’ and referring to the very long distal suprategular apophysis in the male palp.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Yunnan Province
, 
Fugong County
, 
Lumadeng Township
, 
Yaping Village
, 
Shibali
; 
27.16515° N
, 
98.77975° E
; alt. 

2527 m

; 

1 May 2004

; 
Guang–xu
leg.; 
HNU-20040501–1
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes

(
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
)
</p>
      <p>
CHINA
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
HNU-20040501–2

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
holotype
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Total length: 3.18. Carapace 1.53 long, 1.23 wide, cephalic region slightly elevated, brown; fovea, cervical and radial grooves distinct; clypeus 0.21 high (
Fig. 33A–B
); abdomen 1.65 long, 1.19 wide (
Fig. 33A–B
). Eye sizes and interdistances: AME 0.07, ALE 0.08, PME 0.07, PLE 0.09, AME–AME 0.04, PME–PME 0.07, AME–ALE 0.08, PME–PLE 0.08, ALE–ALE 0.44, PLE–PLE 0.51.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. With five promarginal and five retromarginal teeth; teeth of reteromargin almost equal in length.</p>
      <p>LENGTH OF LEGS. I = 5.56 (1.39, 1.61, 1.63, 0.93), II = 4.80 (1.32, 1.43, 1.28, 0.77), III = 3.87 (1.21, 1.08, 1.04, 0.54), IV = 5.45 (1.39, 1.73, 1.61, 0.72). Leg formula I–IV–II–III.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 30.
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (HNU-20040501–1), palp. 
A
. Prolateral view. 
B
. Retrolateral view. 
C
. Dorsal view. 
D
. Ventral view.
</p>
      <p>
PALP (
Figs 30A–D
, 
31A–B
). Paracymbium highly sclerotized, distal arm with three projections; lateral projection large, curved, beak-shaped with pointed end in retrolateral view; median projection tongueshaped, wider than long; ventral projection sclerotized, tip curved with blunt end, strongly overlapping subtegulum (
Figs 30B
, 
31B
); distal suprategular apophysis much longer than that of all other species in this genus, sword-shaped, protruding above cymbium (
Figs 30A–D
, 
31A–B
). Radical apophysis longer than wide, finger-shaped with broad blunt end, pointing towards distal margin of radix in ventral view (
Figs 30A–D
, 
31A–B
). Dorsal projection of embolic plate with broad, round end, curved and almost touching base of cymbium in prolateral view (
Figs 30A
, 
31A
). Embolus stout, short with pointed end (
Figs 30A–C
, 
31A–B
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
(HNU-20040501–02)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Total length: 2.67. Carapace 1.13 long, 0.91 wide, cephalic region slightly elevated, yellowish brown, with longitudinal band starting from base of posterior lateral eyes extending to middorsal; fovea, cervical and radial grooves distinct; Clypeus 0.24 high (
Fig. 33D–E
); abdomen 1.54 long, 1.16 wide. Eye sizes and interdistances: AME 0.06, ALE 0.08, PME 0.06, PLE 0.07, AME–AME 0.04, PME–PME 0.05, AME–ALE 0.06, PME–PLE 0.09, ALE–ALE 0.39, PLE–PLE 0.42, ALE–PLE contiguous.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. With five promarginal and five retromarginal teeth. LENGTH OF LEGS. I = 3.88 (1.19, 1.31, 0.86, 0.52), II = 3.74 (1.15, 1.08, 0.88, 0.63), III = 2.62 (0.8, 0.84, 0.61, 0.37), IV = 3.37 (0.93, 1.03, 0.86, 0.55). Leg formula I–II–IV–III.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 31.
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (HNU-20040501–1), palp. 
A
. Prolateral view. 
B
. Retrolateral view.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 32.
<tp:taxon-name>
Acroterius longimultus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, ♀, paratype (HNU-20040501–02). 
A–B
. Epigyne, ventral view. 
C
. Epigyne, lateral view. 
D
. Vulva, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>
EPIGYNE. Lateral margin of parmula wave-like on each side (
Fig. 32A–C
); parmula 0.45 long, 0.15 wide at base (
Fig. 32A–C
); posterior projection of anterior wall of epigynal plate longer than wide and protruding beyond epigastric furrow (
Fig. 32A–B
). Spermathecae slender, inverted L-shaped (
Fig. 32D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Yunnan Province
, 
Fig. 39
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
