<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus amamiensis
Nomura, 1959
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 5B
, 
6B, D, F
, 
7E
, 
8C–D
, 
9C, E
, 
10B
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus brevicornis amamiensis
Nomura, 1959: 33
</tp:taxon-name>

(original description).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus brevicornis amamiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Satô 1960: 252

; 

1965: 90

; 

1977: 1

. — 

Kodada &amp; Jäch 2006: 442

(catalogue).

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus amamiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Jung &amp; Bae 2014: 5

(new status, distribution). — Kodada &amp; Jäch 2016: 606 (catalogue). — 


Nakajima 
et al
. 2020: 178


, 322 (diagnosis, identification key, photographs of living specimens).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type
locality

</p>
      <p>
Amami Island, Ryukyu Archipelago, 
Japan
.
</p>
      <p>
Type
material

(not examined)
</p>
      <p>
See 
Jung &amp; Bae (2014: 5)
.
</p>
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
JAPAN
• 
1 ♂
; “ 
Amami-Ôshima Shinmura
| 

13. VI. 1962
M. Sato
”; 
NHMW

• 

1 ♂
; “(Ryukyus) 
Yona
Okinawa
13.VIII.1969
Y. Hori
leg.”; 
NHMW

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
Nago-shi
, 
Okinawa-ken
2-5.VIII.1980
Col. K. Baba
| 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus brevicornis amamiensis
Nomura Det. M. Sato 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
”; 
NHMW

• 

4 ♂♂
, 
4 ♀♀
; “ 
Shinokawa
, 
Setouchi-cho
, 
Amami-Ôshima
, 
Kagoshima
, 
Japan
, 
28.22513
, 
129.29986
, 

5.III.2020

, 
H. Yoshitomi
leg.”; 
JKCB

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus amamiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
is medium-sized (TL 
2.80–3.22 mm
), elongated oval, dorsally moderately convex, with the highest point slightly before the middle of the elytral length (lateral view); body outline slightly discontinuous between pronotum and elytra; plastron microscales covering the entire surface of the cranium, lateral portions of the pronotum and the whole dorsal surface of the elytra (
Fig. 5B
). Elytron with nine rows of moderately large, round punctures in shallow striae. Legs long and robust, somewhat shorter than the combined length of pronotum and elytra, claws moderately curved. Differences to the morphologically most similar 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. brevicornis
</tp:taxon-name>
are discussed above.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Measurements
(mm)
</p>
      <p>
TL: 
♂♂
2.80–2.99 (2.91 ± 0.06, n = 9), 
♀♀
3.09–3.22 (3.16 ± 0.05, n = 7); PL: 
♂♂
0.68–0.77 (0.74 ± 0.03, n = 9), 
♀♀
0.70–0.78 (0.76 ± 0.03, n = 7); PW: 
♂♂
1.14–1.24 (1.20 ± 0.03, n = 9), 
♀♀
1.25–1.35 (1.31 ± 0.03, n = 7); EL: 
♂♂
2.18–2.34 (2.27 ± 0.05, n = 9), 
♀♀
2.42–2.60 (2.50 ± 0.05, n = 7); EW: 
♂♂
1.38–1.46 (1.42 ± 0.02, n = 9), 
♀♀
1.48–1.59 (1.54 ± 0.04, n = 7); MsTL: 
♂♂
0.84– 0.96 (0.92 ± 0.03, n = 9), 
♀♀
0.83–0.87 (0.85 ± 0.01, n = 7); MtTL: 
♂♂
1.03–1.10 (1.07 ± 0.03, n = 9), 
♀♀
0.99–1.04 (1.02 ± 0.02, n = 7); PhL: 0.91–1.19 (1.02 ± 0.08, n = 7); PrL: 0.39–0.43 (0.42 ± 0.01, n = 7).
</p>
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>BODY. Elongated oval, widest behind mid-length of elytra, moderately convex dorsally. Colouration black; mouthparts, antennae, tibiae and tarsi reddish-brown; femora dark brown. Main pubescence consisting of very short and thin, decumbent yellowish setae, which arise from small punctures. Dorsal plastron present on the entire surface except for the pronotal disc. Ventral surface except for prosternal process and disc of metaventrite with hair-like plastron setae.</p>
      <p>
HEAD. With plastron and round setiferous punctures with a diameter of ca 0.75× a facet diameter, punctures separated by distance 0.50–1.00× a facet diameter. Labrum transverse, anterior margin straight, setose; anterolateral angles rounded; exposed portion microreticulate and micropunctate; male with a transverse row of strong, densely set conspicuous setae near middle (
Fig. 6B
), longest setae laterally, in length subequal to two-third of interocular distance; female with shorter and rather sparse setae, setal row hardly discernible. Anterior margin of clypeus straight, and not in the same plane as labrum. Eyes large, oval, protruding; interfacetal setae sparse, short; ID: 
♂♂
0.37–0.43 mm
(0.40 ± 0.02, n = 9), 
♀♀
0.43–0.48 mm
(0.44 ± 0.02, n = 7). Antennae 10-segmented, shorter than eye length.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
Female terminalia. 
A–B, D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus brevicornis
Sharp, 1888
</tp:taxon-name>
(JKCB). 
A
. Sternite VIII. 
B
. Ovipositor. 
C, E
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus amamiensis
Nomura, 1959
</tp:taxon-name>
(JKCB). 
C
. Ovipositor. 
D
. Bursa copulatrix. 
E
. Bursa copulatrix. Scale bars = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
THORAX. Pronotum transverse, moderately convex, widest at base, PW/PL: 
♂♂
1.60–1.71 (1.62 ± 0.04, n = 9), 
♀♀
1.66–1.91 (1.73 ± 0.08, n = 7); plastron on entire lateral portions, mesally reaching level of third elytral row; pronotal disc smooth, with large, round setiferous punctures; punctures slightly smaller than facets, nearly regularly spaced, interstices 0.75–1.20× a facet diameter. Anterior angles strongly protruding, acute and deflexed; lateral sides of pronotum convergent anteriad, slightly arcuate or nearly straight, narrowly explanate. Prosternal process with lateral margins divergent, moderately arcuate; posterior margin rounded; lateral portion slightly elevated, separated from median keel by longitudinal depressions; median keel nearly flat, surface finely punctate and irregularly wrinkled. Male with two clusters of conspicuous long setae in anterolateral portions of prosternal process (
Fig. 6D
), longest setae as long as prosternum in front of prosternal process. Scutellum longer than wide, surface smooth, with small, sparse punctures. Metaventrite along middle ca twice as long as prosternal process; disc flat in males, slightly elevated in females, discrimen present nearly along the entire length, surface finely sparsely punctate, and irregularly wrinkled. Metaventral process as long as prosternal one, with lateral sides keel-like, anterior margin not straight, flat; male with two clusters of conspicuous long setae in posterolateral portions of metaventrite (
Fig. 6F
). Elytra ovate, widest behind middle; sides moderately arcuate, more convergent posteriad than anteriad, narrowly explanate; EL/EW: 
♂♂
1.57– 1.64 (1.60 ± 0.02, n = 9), 
♀♀
1.57–1.65 (1.62 ± 0.02, n = 7); entire surface with plastron; each elytron with nine striae, strial punctures smaller than facets, separated by distance of 1.00–2.00× puncture diameter; punctures smaller laterad and toward apex. Tibiae all straight, slender; protibia ca 1.25× as long as protarsus; PrTL/PL: 
♂♂
1.12–1.25 (1.19 ± 0.04, n = 9), 
♀♀
1.03–1.21 (1.09 ± 0.05, n = 7). Terminal protarsomere in male ca 1.20× as long as all preceding tarsomeres combined; male foreclaws moderately curved, not widened or thickened, slightly less than half length of the terminal tarsomere length, both similar to each other and similar to female foreclaws.
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Ventrites completely covered with plastron; ventrites 1–5 with length ratio 1.00: 0.74: 0.52: 0.48: 
1.66 in
male, and 1.00: 0.88: 0.65: 0.57: 
1.84 in
female. Intercoxal process wide, about twice as wide as long, subtriangular, sides distinctly arcuate; admedian keels indistinct, feebly raised in male, reaching posterior margin of ventrite, but nearly absent in female. Mesal portion of male ventrite 5 flattened on anterior third and strongly deflected posteriad (lateral view); apex with distinct triangular excision and cluster of several long semi-erect setae on each side of excision (
Fig. 7E
). Female ventrite 5 evenly convex and only indistinctly flattened anteriorly, with minute longitudinal smooth keel at apex and few longer setae alongside keel; apex rounded. Aedeagus: phallobase long, narrow, expanded proximally (
Fig. 8C
), PhL/PrL: 2.32–2.74 (2.43 ± 0.12, n = 7); parameres strongly curved ventrad, especially in apical half (
Fig. 8D
), moderately narrowed, apices subacute; penis with apex slightly expanded and rounded in lateral aspect; sclerotized fibula absent. Ovipositor heavily sclerotized; right coxite ca 1.30× as long as left one; paraproct ca 1.52× as long as right coxite (
Fig. 9D
). Bursa copulatrix with cluster of minute spines on each side of distal portions and with several larger sclerites scattered over proximal portion (
Fig. 9E
).
</p>
      <p>
Sexual dimorphism
</p>
      <p>Females are on average larger than males, and the apex of their fifth ventrite is rounded, while in males it is triangularly excised. Moreover, males have long conspicuous setae arranged in a transverse row on the labrum and in clusters situated on lateral sides of the prosternal process, lateral sides of the metaventrite and on the apex of the fifth ventrite; females lack these groups of long setae.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Elmomorphus amamiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
has been so far recorded only from the Ryukyu Archipelago in 
Japan
(
Fig. 10B
): Amami Island, Tokunoshima, Okinawa-jima, Iheya-jima, Zamami-shoto, Aka-jima, and Kume-jima (

Nakajima 
et al.
2020

).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
