<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Augilina tetraina
Chen &amp; Gong
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
435849B6-4C72-4317-B035-1D6245751FFD
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–14
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Posterior margin of pygofer in lateral view with one finger-like process Dorsally (
Fig. 9
); posterior margin of pygofer with two small medioventral processes (
Figs 10, 12
); anal style small (
Figs 8–9
); aedeagus broadly concave in apical half (
Fig. 13
); genital styles with four processes (
Figs 11–12
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific name is DeriveD from the Latin worD ʻ 
tetra
ʼ which refers to the genital styles with four processes.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CHINA
• 
♂
; 
Yunnan Province
, 
Yingjiang County
, 
Nabang Town
; 
24°70′ N
, 
97°90′ E
; 

18 Aug. 2015

; 
Xiang-Sheng Chen
leg.; 
on bamboo
; 
IEGU
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
CHINA
• 
2 ♂♂
; same collection Data as for holotype; 
Lin Yang
leg.; 
IEGU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length including forewing: male 
6.7–6.8 mm
(N = 3); forewing length: male 
5.4 mm
(N = 3).
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION (in alcohol). Body mainly yellow (
Figs 1–5
). Eyes yellowish brown. Antennae with one black spot at apex of pedicel. Central area of vertex yellowish brown. Pronotum and mesonotum with wide median light red stripe. Spines of legs with black apices.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD AND THORAX. Vertex including eyes 0.8 times width of pronotum. Vertex (
Fig. 3
) longer in middle line than broad at widest part (2.62:1). Frons (
Fig. 4
) 2.97 times as long as middle line at widest part. Pronotum (
Fig. 3
) shorter in middle line than vertex (1:2.59). Mesonotum (
Fig. 3
) 0.7 times as long as vertex and pronotum together in middle line. Forewing (
Fig. 6
) longer in middle line than broad at widest part (4.95:1); veins visible, with nodal line, R and MP with common stem, R with 3 branches before noDal line; after noDal line, R single, MP with five branches, CuA with two branches, Pcu uniting A1 at basal third of clavus. Hindwing (
Fig. 7
) 2.22 times as long as broad at widest part, ScP and RP single, MP and CuA with two branches.
</p>
      <p>
MALE GENITALIA. Anal segment in dorsal view (
Fig. 8
), 2 times as long as middle line at widest part, broadening apically, broadest at apical third; in lateral view (
Fig. 9
), dorsal margin slightly concave, ventral margin slightly concave. Anal style small (
Fig. 8
). Pygofer in lateral view (
Fig. 9
), posterior margin with one finger-like process Dorsally, upper ⅔ concave, lower ⅓ almost straight; in posterior view (
Fig. 10
), nearly oval, 1.5 times as long as widest part; in ventral view (
Fig. 12
), posterior margin with two short and broad medioventral processes, anterior margin convex. Genital styles (
Figs 11–12
) with median portion broad, large, each with four processes, 2.2 times as long as widest part. Aedeagus (
Figs 13–14
) tubular, slender and long, tapering apically, in lateral view, strongly curved to the basement, apical half broadly concave.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Figs 1–14.
<tp:taxon-name>
A. tetraina
Chen &amp; Gong
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂ (holotype, IEGU). 
1
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
2
. Habitus, lateral view. 
3
. Head and thorax, dorsal view. 
4
. Face. 
5
. Head and thorax, lateral view. 
6
. Forewing. 
7
. Hindwing. 
8
. Anal segment, dorsal view. 
9
. Male genitalia, lateral view. 
10
. Pygofer, posterior view. 
11
. Genital styles, lateral view. 
12
. Pygofer and genital styles, ventral view. 
13
. Aedeagus, lateral view. 
14
. Aedeagus, dorsal view. Scale bars: 1–5, 9 = 0.5 mm; 6–7 = 1 mm; 8, 10–14 = 0.3 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host plant
</p>
      <p>Bamboo.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
China
(
Yunnan
) (
Fig. 35
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This new species is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. namboina
</tp:taxon-name>
, but Differs in: 1) pygofer in lateral view, posterior margin with one finger-like process near Dorsal margin (vs without in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. namboina
</tp:taxon-name>
); 2) aedeagus broadly concave posteriorly on apical half (vs almost straight in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. namboina
</tp:taxon-name>
); 3) pygofer in ventral view, posterior margin with two small medioventral processes (vs relatively large medioventral processes in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. namboina
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
