<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ysachron pilosus García &amp; Botero &amp; Santos-Silva 2021, gen. et sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4555415</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8137D9FFD308C40F09A9A1AEC7613BD7</uri>
         <article-title>A new genus of Achrysonini and new records in Cerambycidae (Coleoptera, Chrysomeloidea) from Colombia</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Ysachron pilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
22FB104A-E069-4F84-9214-C5AD9ACA1877
</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–13
, 
17–29
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>As for genus.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species epithet comes from the Latin ‘ 
pilosus
’, referring to the general appearance of the species, covered by long and erect setae.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
COLOMBIA
• 
1 ♂
; 
Bolívar
, 
San Jacinto
, 
Reserva La Flecha
; 
09°51′12.4″ N
, 
75°10′41.4″ W
; 

324 m
a.s.l.

; 

19 Feb. 2018

; 
K. García
leg; 
tropical dry forest
, 
beating sheet
; 
MPUJ
_ 
ENT 0071150
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
COLOMBIA
• 
1 ♂
; 
Atlántico
, 
Usiacurí
, 
Reserva Campesina La Montaña
; 
10°46′2.6″ N
75°0.2′34″ W
; 

260 m
a.s.l.

; 

15–16 Feb. 2018

; 
K. García
leg; 
tropical dry forest
, 
white light trap
; 
MZSP

• 

1 ♂
; same collection data as for preceding; 

17–18 Mar. 2018

; 
MPUJ_ENT 0071151

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MZSP

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for preceding; 

16–17 Mar. 2018

; 
UV light trap
; 
MPUJ_ENT 0071152

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

Description of 
holotype
male

(
Figs 1–4
, 
10, 13
, 
17–29
)
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Integument brown with yellowish-white setae, whiter depending on light intensity. Head and prothorax reddish brown. Antennae light brown; scape and pedicel slightly darker; antennomeres III 
–
VI with apical margin dark brown. Ventral surface reddish brown, metaventrite darker on some areas. Base of femora light brown, remaining surface dark brown. Apical margin of tibiae dark. Body covered by long and erect, dense yellowish-white setae.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Frons alveolate. Area between antennal tubercles densely, coarsely alveolate. Antennal tubercles elevated, smooth. Median groove distinct from frons to area between anterior margin of upper eye lobes. Area between upper eye lobes alveolate, alveoli coarser toward antennal tubercles, smooth on central area; with abundant, long, erect setae, denser centrally. Area behind upper eye lobes slightly alveolate, with central area sparsely punctate; with a few erect setae. Genae smooth; with a few long, erect setae. Distance between upper eye lobes about three times width of an upper eye lobe. Antennae 2.1 times elytral length, reaching elytral apex at antennomere IX. Scape with sparse piliferous punctures. Antennomeres with abundant, distinctly long, erect setae, shorter toward distal segments. Antennal formula (ratio) based on length of antennomere III: scape = 0.59; pedicel = 0.14; IV = 0.76; V = 0.78; VI = 0.81; VII = 0.89; VIII = 0.81; IX = 0.76; X = 0.70; XI = 0.62; XII= 0.57.</p>
      <p>THORAX. Prothorax as long as wide. Surface of pronotum coarsely alveolate, except for small longitudinal area behind middle. Lateral sides of prothorax sparsely punctate. Prosternum slightly and transversely striated, smooth on anterior area. Prosternal process narrow, distinctly narrowed toward apex; width at narrowest point about 0.12 times width of procoxal cavity. Mesanepisternum and mesepimeron densely setose. Mesoventrite sparsely punctate. Mesoventral process microsculptured, with a few long, erect setae; emarginated at apex; width at narrowest point about 0.4 times width of mesocoxal cavity. Metanepisternum abundantly setose. Metaventrite smooth centrally, rugose on anterior sides; with sparse long, erect setae, gradually sparser toward glabrous central area. Scutellum smooth, with short, decumbent setae; posterior margin rounded. Elytra with distinct piliferous punctures, with erect setae irregularly organized. Apex of elytra obliquely truncate.</p>
      <p>
Figs 1–9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ysachron pilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
1–4
. Holotype, ♂ (MPUJ_ENT 0071150). 
1
. Dorsal view. 
2
. Ventral view. 
3
. Lateral view. 
4
. Details of head, frontal view. 
5–8
. Paratype, ♀ (MPUJ_ENT 0071152). 
5
. Details of head, frontal view. 
6
. Dorsal view. 
7
. Ventral view. 
8
. Lateral view. 
9
. Paratype, ♀ (MZSP). Dorsal view with sides of prothorax strongly rounded. Scale bars: 1–4, 6–9 = 0.5 cm; 5 = 0.25 cm.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Profemora fusiform, meso- and metafemora subclavate; lateral sides of femora rugose, remaining surface smooth; setae denser toward apex. Metatarsomere I about as long as II–III together.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Ventrites sparsely, finely punctate, punctures denser centrally; with long decumbent setae, erect laterally. Apex of ventrite V truncate.</p>
      <p>
TERMINALIA. Tergite VIII (
Fig. 17
) with distal margin distinctly emarginated, with long and short yellow setae, abundant and longer laterally. Sternite VIII (
Fig. 18
) transverse, distal margin slightly emarginated, projected forward laterally, with long yellow setae laterally; apophysis short, rounded at apex, about as long as central area of sternite. Dorsal arc sinuous (
Fig. 19
). Ventral arc (
Fig. 20
) fork-shaped, with apophysis as long as arms; arms straight. Tegmen (
Figs 24–26
) about 0.8 times length of median lobe; distal region divided into parameres; parameres triangularshaped, apex rounded and covered by short setae; ring piece subrounded, proximal part truncate, without projection. Median lobe (
Figs 27–29
) slightly curved in lateral view; dorsal lobe with apex rounded and reaching rounded apex of ventral lobe; basal apophysis about 2.3 times length of apical region.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 10–16. 10–12
. Details of pronotum of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ysachron pilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
10
. Holotype, ♂ (MPUJ_ ENT 0071150). 
11
. Paratype, ♀ (MPUJ_ENT 0071152). 
12
. Paratype, ♀ (MZSP). 
13–16
. Procoxal cavities in 
<tp:taxon-name>Cerambycidae Latreille, 1802</tp:taxon-name>
tribes. 
13
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Achrysonini 
Lacordaire, 1868
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ysachron pilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
14
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Achrysonini</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Achryson
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. 
15
. 
<tp:taxon-name>Hesperophanini Mulsant, 1839</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Hesperophanes
sp. 
16
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Oemini 
Lacordaire, 1868
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Oeme
sp.
</p>
      <p>
Figs 17–29.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ysachron pilosus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, ♂ (MZSP). 
17
. Tergite VIII. 
18
. Sternite VIII. 
19
. Dorsal arc. 
20
. Ventral arc. 
21–23
. Tegmen + median lobe. 
21
. Dorsal view. 
22
. Lateral view. 
23
. Ventral view. 
24–26
. Tegmen. 
24
. Dorsal view. 
25
. Lateral view. 
26
. Ventral view. 
27–29
. Median lobe. 
27
. Dorsal view. 
28
. Lateral view. 
29
. Ventral view. Scale bars: 17, 20 = 0.5 mm; 18 = 0.3 mm; 19 = 0.1 mm; 21–29 = 1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Female
(
Figs 5–9
, 
11–12
) Antennae shorter, reaching elytral apex at antennomere XII, with scape elongate; prothorax wider, with small gibbosity medially (in one female more evident – 
Fig. 12
); surface of lateral sides of prothorax densely alveolate; ventrite V longer than precedent, with rounded apex.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
(in mm)
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
male, total length: 7.5, prothorax length: 1.5, anterior prothoracic width: 1.1, posterior prothoracic width: 1.1, largest prothoracic width: 1.5, elytral length: 5.1, humeral width: 1.7. 
Paratypes
, ♂ / 
♀
, n = 2 / 2. Total length: 7–8.5 / 8.8–9.1, prothorax length: 1.4–1.8 / 1.6–1.6, largest prothoracic width: 1.35–1.7 / 1.4–2, elytral length: 4.6–5.7 / 6.2–6.5, humeral width: 1.6–1.9 / 2.1–2.2.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
