<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Prosopodopsis appendiculata</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4723780</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/B7D882BAA690A144C9F9B5F5B166C316</uri>
         <article-title>A new genus and species of tachinid flies from Iran (Diptera, Tachinidae, Goniini)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://zoobank.org/b8ae3f15-9eb5-4a7c-98fd-058a1ebe5ce9</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Prosopodopsis appendiculata
(de Meijere, 1910)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
TAIWAN
• 
1 ♀
; with printed white label: “Anping / Formosa / H. Sauter, 1911 [with handwritten addition: “ 
V.12
”]”, with printed white label: “det. 
Baranoff
”, with handwritten white label: “ 

<tp:taxon-name>Prosopodopsis</tp:taxon-name>
/ fasciata

Wied.”; 
SDEI

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key (based on 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter 1998
)

</p>
      <p>
The new genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
can be incorporated into the modified identification key of the Palearctic tachinid genera prepared by 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter (1998)
. One problem for the users of this key can be in distinguishing between upper frontal setae and upper orbital setae for which 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter (1998)
also mentioned, through the morphological description of the adult head, “One, two or more reclinate or lateroclinate upper orbital bristles present, in many genera not distinguishable from uppermost frontal bristles …”. The second problem is the intraspecific variation in the number of reclinate upper orbital bristles, which exist in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
(cf. 
Figs 3
, 
6A
, 
8A
with two vs 
Fig. 6C–E
with only one) and other genera, including 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palesisa
Villeneuve, 1929
</tp:taxon-name>
, which usually possesses only one upper orbital seta (but in 
Fig. 8B
with two). In case of two reclinate upper orbital setae, the anterior seta is mostly shorter than the second seta. In the description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palesisa nudioculata
, 
Cerretti (2010a: 276)
</tp:taxon-name>
stated “Una (raramente 2) setola orbitale reclinate superiore” and provided a photograph of the female head with two strong reclinate upper orbital setae (
Cerretti 2010b: 124
). 
Čepelák &amp; Sisojević (1974: 834)
had described the male of the same species as having “1 (auch 2, vordere kürzere) oi” [one or two reclinate upper orbital setae, the anterior seta shorter]. 
Mesnil (1949: 101)
had used this character (one or two upper orbital setae) in his key to separate Sturmiariae from Blepharellariae, and mentioned that he had encountered specimens with both 2 oi (reclinate upper orbital setae) and 1 oi among the individuals of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pales pumicata
(Meigen, 1824)
</tp:taxon-name>
(as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ctenophorocera
</tp:taxon-name>
). Even though the presence of 2–3 reclinate upper orbital setae has been described for the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gymnophryxe
Villeneuve, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
, mostly one is observed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. theodori
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 6F–H
). These remarks are intended to discuss the reliability of the used characters “One single reclinate upper orbital seta” and “Two or more reclinate upper orbital setae” in the keys. Therefore, we offer here two variants of the key by 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter (1998)
to facilitate the determination of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
in both occurrences and include the following combinations “One single reclinate upper orbital seta, if sometimes two, the uppermost stronger” and “Two reclinate upper orbital setae, the uppermost of same size or weaker, or more than two setae” in place of the original ones in the key to improve its accuracy as well.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
Characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
Ziegler &amp; Gilasian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palesisa nudioculata
Villeneuve, 1929
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–B
. Male head, lateral view. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (HMIM). 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palesisa nudioculata
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CZB). 
C–F
. Male terminalia: epandrium, cerci and surstyli. 
C–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ (HMIM). 
C
. Dorsal view. 
D
. Lateral view. 
E–F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palesisa nudioculata
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CZB). 
E
. Dorsal view. 
F
. Lateral view. Scale bars: A–B = 0.5 mm; C–F = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Key 1. Specimens with two or more reclinate upper orbital setae
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>
496. Lateral scutellar setae at least as long as half of subapical setae, but if shorter, then upper part of head with black setulae behind the postocular row. Two or three reclinate upper orbital setae present [Comment: Usually only one reclinate upper orbital seta occurs in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gymnophryxe theodori
</tp:taxon-name>
] ...................................................................................................... 499
</p>
      <p>
499. R 
4+5
setose from base to crossvein r-m or beyond ................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Prosopodopsis
Townsend,1926
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Suensonomyia
Mesnil, 1953
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Synamphichaeta
Villeneuve,1936
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– R 
4+5
setose at most halfway to crossvein r-m ............................................................................ 501
</p>
      <p>
501. Legs entirely or predominantly yellow (at most tarsi black). Tegula reddish. Body length 
4–7 mm
. ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Crapivnicia
Richter, 1995
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hebia
Robineau-Desvoidy, 1830
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Masistyloides
Mesnil, 1963
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– At least femora black or dark brown, but if (rarely) red or yellow, then body length 
8 mm
or more. Tegula usually black [Comment: The characters hardly fit in with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
because of predominantly brownish-black femora and tarsi (femora orange apicoventrally), dark brownish-orange tibia, brownish orange tegula, and body length 
6.3–7.5 mm
] ...................... 503
</p>
      <p>503. Height of gena one-sixth vertical diameter of eye or more, at least as great as width of parafacial at level of base of antenna. Parafacial not or not as strongly narrowed ventrally .................... 504</p>
      <p>504. Section of M between crossveins r-m and dm-cu distinctly longer than section between dm-cu and bend of M, the latter section shorter than section between bend and apex of M ...................... 505</p>
      <p>505. Arista thickened at least on basal half or more. Frons 1.1–2.5 times as wide as one eye in dorsal view. Abdominal tergites 3 and 4 with or without median discal setae .................................... 506</p>
      <p>
506. Upper part of head without black setulae behind the postocular row (rarely with a few setulae). Scutum with four pairs of postsutural dorsocentral setae. Preapical anterodorsal seta on fore tibia distinctly shorter than preapical dorsal seta (see 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter 1998
: fig. 143) ..... 507 (a)
</p>
      <p>507(a). Gena and sides of thorax with black setulae. Fronto-orbital plate in male with or without proclinate setae. Abdominal tergites 3 and 4 usually without median discal setae ............ 507 (aa)</p>
      <p>
– Gena and sides of thorax with pale setulae. Fronto-orbital plate in male without proclinate setae. Abdominal tergites 3 and 4 each with two or three pairs of median discal setae, with one pair anterior to the other ................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Frontina
Meigen, 1838
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
507(aa). Face usually 1.7–2.0 times as long as frons (
Fig. 6F
) [Comment: Face in 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. carthaginensis
(Bischof, 1900)
</tp:taxon-name>
only 1.3–1.5 times as long as frons, while frons measures 2.0–2.3 times as wide as one eye]. Frons more than 1.4 times as wide as one eye in dorsal view (
Fig. 6H
). Fronto-orbital plate in male with or without proclinate setae. 2–4 reclinate upper orbital setae present [Comment: Usually one reclinate upper orbital seta is present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. theodori
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Figs 6F–H
)]. Apical scutellar setae inclined at 45–90° to horizontal (see 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter 1998
: figs 126–127). Gena 0.3– 0.5 times as height as vertical diameter of eye (
Fig. 6F
). Male terminalia: Surstylus in lateral view broader and shorter than cercus (
Fig. 5D
) ................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gymnophryxe
Villeneuve, 1922
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Face 1.2–1.3 times as long as frons (
Fig. 6C
). Frons at most 1.15–1.40 times as wide as one eye in dorsal view (
Fig. 6E
). Fronto-orbital plate in male with two strong proclinate setae (
Fig. 6C–E
) and one single reclinate upper orbital seta (sometimes a fine semi reclinate seta before, 
Fig. 3
). Apical scutellar setae inclined at most at 30° to horizontal. Gena almost 0.2 times as heigh as vertical diameter of eye (
Fig. 6C
). Male terminalia: Surstyli and cerci in lateral view slender; surstylus longer than cercus (
Fig. 5B
) .............................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia
Ziegler &amp; Gilasian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Key 2. Specimens with only one reclinate upper orbital seta
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>
496. Upper part of head without black setulae behind the postocular row. One single reclinate upper orbital seta present (see 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter 1998
: fig. 50) [Comment: Two reclinate upper orbital setae rarely occur in the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
(
Fig. 8A
) and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palesisa
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 8B
), while is frequently observed in the specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kuwanimyia
Townsend, 1916
</tp:taxon-name>
; lateral scutellar setae in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
as strong and long as basal setae] ................................................ 497
</p>
      <p>
497. Ocellar setae reclinate. Prementum four to five times as long as its diameter. Scutellum without apical setae, but with a pair of straight nearly erect setulae on dorsal surface just anterior to apex (see 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter 1998
: fig. 123) .............................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Goniophthalmus
Villeneuve, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Ocellar setae proclinate (see 
Tschorsnig &amp; Richter 1998
: fig. 50). Prementum at most two times as long as its diameter. Scutellum with crossed apical bristles, without erect preapical setulae .... .............................................................................................................................................. 498 (a)
</p>
      <p>
498(a). Lateral scutellar setae strong, as long and strong as subapical scutellar setae. Fronto-orbital plate in both sexes with two strong proclinate setae and only a few short hair-like setulae (
Figs 6C–E
, 
8A
) .................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia
Ziegler &amp; Gilasian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
      <p>
– Lateral scutellar setae absent or hair-like. Fronto-orbital plate in male without proclinate setae, but with many long hair-like setulae (as in 
Fig. 8B
) [Comment: Rare specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kuwanimyia
</tp:taxon-name>
possess one proclinate upper orbital setae] ........................................................................ 498 (aa)
</p>
      <p>
498(aa). Second aristomere 1.0–2.5 times as long as its diameter. Postpedicel less than four times as long as pedicel ................................................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Palesisa
Villeneuve, 1929
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Second aristomere 2–10 times as long as its diameter. Postpedicel 4–10 times as long as pedicel in Palearctic species. For further characters see (
Cerretti 2009
) .................................................... ......... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Dolichocolon
Brauer &amp; Bergenstamm, 1889
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kuwanimyia conspersa
Townsend, 1916
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
