<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
Ziegler &amp; Gilasian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
7F3A2907-E8D8-46A9-9650-DAD0F7E01ADB
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3–4
, 
5A–B
, 
6A, C–E
, 
7
, 
8A, C–D
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
mira
</tp:taxon-name>
’ (Latin, adjective) is derived from ‘mirus’ (amazing, astonishing, surprising).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
IRAN
• 
♂
(pinned); 
IRAN
: 
Khuzestan prov.
, / 
Shoush
, 
Karkheh National
/ 
Park
, 
Persian Fallow Deer
/ 
Sanctuary
, 
32°04′30.1″N
/ 
48°14′24.2″E
, 

June 28–July 4 / 2013

, 66m, 
Malaise trap
, M. / Parchami- Araghi // HOLOTYPUS ♂ / 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
</tp:taxon-name>
/ 
Ziegler
&amp; 
Gilasian
/ 2021 [red label]; 
HMIM
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
IRAN
• 
2 ♂♂
(1 pinned, 
1 in
ethanol), 
2 ♀♀
(1 pinned, 
1 in
ethanol); same data as for holotype; 
HMIM

• 

1 ♂
(pinned); same data as for holotype except 
32°04′42.2″N
/ 
48°14′34.8″E
, near swamp, / 

May 13– June 14 2014

, 63 m, / 
Malaise trap
, M. Parchami- / 
Araghi
leg.; 
SDEI

• 

1 ♂
, 
1 ♀
(pinned); same data as for holotype except 
32°04′45.6″N
48°14′27.8″E
/ 

10.V.–10.VII. 2015

, 68 m / leg. 
Gilasian
; 
ZMHB

• 

1 ♂
(pinned); same data as for holotype except 
Dez National Park
, 
Mianrood
, / 
Persian Fallow Deer Sanctuary
, / 
32°06′23.5″N
/ 
48°26′17.2″E
, near marsh, / 

May 13–June 14 2014

, 54 m, / 
Malaise trap
, M. Parchami- / 
Araghi
leg.; 
HMIM

• 

1 ♀
(glued to a card point); 
IRAN
: 
Sistan &amp; Balouchestan prov.
, / 
Dalgan, vicinity of / Jolgeh, Chah Hashem, palm / grove
, 
27°06′08.3″N
/ 
59°07′11.3″E
, / 


28 April–2 May 
2017

, 388 m, 
Malaise / trap
, 
M. Parchami-Araghi
leg.; 
HMIM

.
</p>
      <p>
Each 
paratype
has an additional yellow label containing “ 
PARATYPUS
♂
[or 
♀
] / 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
</tp:taxon-name>
/ Ziegler &amp; Gilasian / 2021”.
</p>
      <p>
Additional studied material
</p>
      <p>
IRAN
• 
1 ♂
; same data as for holotype except 
32°04′45.6″N
48°14′27.8″E
/ 

10.V.–10.VII. 2015

, 68 m / leg. 
Gilasian
; 
CZB
.

</p>
      <p>
Specimen dissected. Head (
Fig. 6C–E
), postabdomen and left wing prepared separately, the other parts of the body have been destroyed during DNA extraction.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Figs 3–4
, 
5A–B
, 
6A, C–E
)
</p>
      <p>
Statements given within square brackets refer to 
paratypes
. Overall length: 6.3–[7.5] mm.
</p>
      <p>COLORATION AND MICROTRICHOSITY. Head predominantly brown; genal setulae black; frontal vitta and lunule light brown; face, parafacial, fronto-orbital plate, gena, genal dilation, ocellar triangle and occiput covered with dense silvery white microtrichosity; occiput with white setulae; scape, pedicel and basal margin of postpedicel orange, other parts of antenna including arista dark brown to black; prementum dark brown; palpus yellow; thorax black, predominantly covered with whitish-grey microtrichosity; presutural portion of scutum with 2 narrow dark median and 2 semi-triangular lateral vittae (seen from behind), posterior margin of postpronotum orange, postsutural portion of scutum orange laterally; scutellum entirely yellowish-orange or (rarely) darker in basal portion, covered with grey microtrichosity; wing hyaline; calypters white; tegula brownish-orange, basicosta pale yellow; halter orange; coxae, femora and tarsi brownish-black, apical half of femora orange ventrally, tibiae dark brownish-orange; abdomen dorsally and ventrally predominantly covered with dense grey microtrichosity on its whole length, without black bands posteriorly, but with black shining spots at base of every seta; syntergite 1+2 mostly black, posterior half of lateral and ventral portions orange; tergites 3–4 predominantly orange, each with a dorsal black trapezoidal spot; tergite 5 orange with a semi triangular black spot dorsally; margins of all tergites pale yellow; sternites black; postabdomen mostly orange.</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Figs 3
, 
6C–E
). Eye bare; height of gena in lateral view [0.17]–0.21 times as long as vertical diameter of eye; face [1.20]–1.27 times as long as frons in lateral view; frons at its narrowest point 1.15–1.39 [1.30] times as wide as an eye viewed dorsally; frontal vitta nearly as wide as fronto-orbital plate medially; medial vertical setae almost 0.65–[0.72] times as long as vertical diameter of eye, lateral vertical setae 0.50–[0.59] times as long as medial (inner) vertical setae; ocellar setae proclinate or [lateroreclinate]; postocellar setae parallel and [0.57]–0.75 times as long as lateral vertical setae; upper part of head without black setulae behind the postocular row; frons with 4–[6] frontal setae descending to level of lower margin of pedicel; the uppermost seta sometimes reclinate, as if upper orbital seta; facial ridge with erect setae on lower ⅔–[¾], parafacial bare, at its narrowest point [0.18]–0.21 times as wide as transverse eye diameter and almost [0.60]–0.70 times as wide as postpedicel in lateral view; fronto-orbital plate with a few scattered setulae; 2 proclinate orbital and 1 reclinate upper orbital setae (
Fig. 6A
), sometimes preceding a weaker reclinate upper frontal or orbital seta (
Fig. 3
); fronto-orbital plate at level of scape 0.30–[0.37] times as wide as the transverse diameter of eye; vibrissa arising at level of lower facial margin and 0.70–[0.75] times as long as face; lower facial margin not visible in lateral view; postpedicel about 6.8 [6.5–7.5] times as long as pedicel and 4.1–[4.2] times as long as wide; arista thickened in basal ⅗, first aristomere shorter than wide; second aristomere [2.0]–2.5 times as long as first aristomere, 1.2–1.8 times as long as wide; prementum very short; palpus slender and cylindrical, with only a few setulae.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
Ziegler &amp; Gilasian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, holotype, ♂ (HMIM); head in lateral view. Scale bar = 0.5 mm.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Prosternum setose; proepisternum bare; postpronotum with 3–4 setae, 3 strong basal setae arranged in a nearly straight line, often an additional distal weak seta between middle and basal setae; scutum with 3+3 acrostichal, 3+4 dorsocentral, 1+3 intra-alar, 2 notopleural, 3 supra-alar setae; first postsutural supra-alar seta longer than notopleural setae and longer than first postsutural intra-alar seta; postalar callus with 2 setae; anatergite bare below calypter; katepimeron bare; katepisternum with 3 setae almost in a line; postmetacoxal area membranous; scutellum with 4 pairs of marginal setae, apical setae weak, crossed and horizontal or [inclined at most at 30° to horizontal], lateral setae strong and as long as basal setae; subapical setae usually longer and stronger than other scutellar setae; dorsal surface of scutellum covered with erect setulae and with 1 pair of inclined discal setae on apical ⅓.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
Ziegler &amp; Gilasian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ (HMIM); terminalia. 
A
. Epandrium, cerci and surstyli, dorsal view. 
B
. Epandrium, cerci and surstyli, lateral view. 
C
. Sternite 5. 
D
. Aedeagus, lateral view. Scale bars = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
WING. Second costal section bare ventrally; costal seta nearly as long as crossvein r-m; fourth costal section (between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
)approximately as long as second costal section (between subcostal break and R 
1
); third costal section 1.8–[2.0] times as long as fourth costal section; vein R 
4+5
with 3–[5] basal setulae dorsally and 2–[4] basal setulae ventrally; wing cell r 
4+5
narrowly open or [closed at wing margin]; section of vein M between crossveins r-m and dm-cu [2.3]–2.5 times as long as section between dm-cu and bend of M; bend of M forming a right angle without appendix; crossvein dm-cu 5.0–[5.5] times as long as crossvein r–m.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore leg. Tibia with 2 posterior setae and a complete row of anterodorsal and posterodorsal setae; preapical anterodorsal seta shorter than preapical dorsal seta; tarsomere 1 nearly 2.1 times as long as tarsomere 2 and 0.4 times as long as tibia; claws short, 0.4 times as long as tarsomere 5. Mid leg. Tibia with a nearly complete row of different-sized anterodorsal setae, of which 2–3 setae very strong and long; 2–[3] posterior and [1]–2 ventral setae. Hind leg. Coxa bare on anterior and posterior surfaces; tibia with a complete row of anterodorsal setae of irregular size, 3–[5] posterodorsal, 2–[3] ventral setae, 2 preapical dorsal setae; preapical posteroventral seta shorter than preapical anteroventral seta.</p>
      <p>ABDOMEN. Middorsal depression of syntergite 1+2 extending back to posterior margin of segment; syntergite 1+2 and tergite 3 each with 1 pair of median marginal and 1 pair of lateral marginal setae; tergites 3–4 with depressed setulae dorsally, without median discal setae; tergite 3 0.45 times as long as wide; tergites 4–5 each with a complete row of marginal setae, tergite 5 with erect discal setae dorsally and 0.65 times as long as tergite 4.</p>
      <p>
POSTABDOMEN (
Fig. 4
). Sternite 5 with a deep median apical depression, without sensilla trichodea (
Fig. 4C
); membrane binding between sternite 6 and segment 7 very narrow; epandrium 2.3 times as long as syntergite 6–8; cercus convex in the middle of basal part and depressed downwards in the middle of apical part (
Fig. 4A
); cercus and surstylus narrow in lateral view, surstylus longer than cercus (
Fig. 4B
); aedeagus as in fig. 4D.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
Characters of male terminalia: epandrium, cerci and surstyli. 
A–B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
Ziegler &amp; Gilasian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ (HMIM). 
A
. Dorsal view. 
B
. Lateral view. 
C–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gymnophryxe theodori
(Kugler, 1968)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CZB). 
C
. Dorsal view. 
D
. Lateral view. Scale bars = 0.1 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
Characters of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
Ziegler &amp; Gilasian
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gymnophryxe theodori
(Kugler, 1968)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–B
. Habitus, ♂, lateral view. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, paratype, ♂ (ZMHB). 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gymnophryxe theodori
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CZB). 
C–H
. Male head. 
C–E
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Susamyia mira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, ♂ (CZB). 
C
. Lateral view. 
D
. Frontal view. 
E
. Dorsal view. 
F–H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Gymnophryxe theodori
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♂ (CZB). 
F
. Lateral view. 
G
. Frontal view. 
H
. Dorsal view. Scale bars: A–B = 2.0 mm; C–H = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Differs from male by combination of the following characters: facial ridge with only 3–4 erect and spaced setae on nearly lower ½; ocellar triangle and frontal vitta orange; postpedicel narrower and shorter, about 4.5–5.4 times as long as pedicel; trapezoidal black spots on abdominal tergites 3–4 much smaller; dorsal black spot on tergite 5 very small; margins of all tergites orange.</p>
      <p>
EGG (
Fig.7
). Microtype, oval, planoconvex(lenticular), maximum diameter 
0.18–0.23mm
, embryonated. Dorsal chorion thick, dark brown, with fine sculpture (
Fig. 7A
); seen from ventral semi-transparent (
Fig. 7B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
