<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>urn:lsid:ipni.org:names:77216331-1</p>
      <p>
Figs 2I
, 
5i–k
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum xukuruorum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. pernambucense
</tp:taxon-name>
in having verticillate leaves and involute lobes on the lower lip. It differs by its glabrous or glabrescent vegetative portions (vs villose) and usually lanceolate leaf blade with sparsely branched venation (vs elliptic to narrowly elliptic and densely branched venation).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The specific epithet is dedicated to the Amerindian Xukuru people, because the 
type
material was collected with their assistance on tribal lands in the Serra do Ororubá Range.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Type
BRAZIL

– 
Pernambuco

• 
Pesqueira
, 
Serra do Ororubá
, 
Reserva Indígena Xukuru de Cimbres
; 
08°19ʹ15ʺ S
, 
36°46ʹ12ʺ W
; 

1122 m

a.s.l.; 

30 Jun. 2015

; 

L.P. Felix
et al. 15647

; 
holotype
: EAN!; isotypes: IPA!, K!, RB!, UFP!.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL

– 
Paraíba

• 
São João do Tigre
, 
Serra do Paulo
; 
08°05ʹ35ʺ S
, 
36°40ʹ35ʺ W
; 

1193 m
a.s.l.

; 

16 Jul. 2010

; 

L.P. Felix
&amp; 
L.I.F. Alves
13085

; 
EAN[16,438]

! • 

ibid.; 

23 Aug. 2013

; 

L.P. Felix
14318

; 
EAN[19,895]

! • 

ibid.; 

3 Aug. 2011

; 

S. Nascimento
105

; 
EAN[18,513]

! • 

Serra do Enjeitado
; 

4 Aug. 2011

; 

S. Nascimento
168

; 
EAN[18,173]

! • 

Serra do Paulo
; 
08°05ʹ36ʺ S
, 
36°38ʹ34ʺ W
; 

1094 m
a.s.l.

; 

4 Aug. 2011

; 

S. Nascimento
151

; 
EAN[18,555]

! 
–
Pernambuco

• 
Pesqueira
, 
Serra do Ororobá
; 

2 Aug. 1979

; 

D. de Andrade-Lima
et al. 79-9,659

; 
IPA[46,742]

! • 

Serra do Gavião
; ± 

800 m
a.s.l.

; 

19 Jun. 2005

; 

M. Oliveira
1,817

; 
UFP[41,495]

! • 

Jataúba
, 
Sítio Sobrado
; 
08°04ʹ53ʺ S
, 
36°34ʹ48ʺ W
; 

1021 m
a.s.l.

; 

6 Jun. 2016

; 

E.M. Almeida
, 
L.I.F. Alves
&amp; 
J.A.L. Neves
1673

; 
EAN[24,603]

!.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Saxicolous chamaephyte up to 
80 cm
, occasionally with some secondary branching at the branch tips. Young branches slightly purplish, dull, slightly angular, often narrowly winged, covered by inconspicuous papillose trichomes; mature branches cinereous, slightly inclined to decumbent, cylindrical. Leaves verticillate with usually four leaves per node; leaf blade 2.5–8.2 × 
0.5–1.4 cm
, green, cinereous, lustrous, narrowly elliptic to lanceolate, sometimes elliptic, bullate; adaxial side glabrous; abaxial side glabrous to glabrescent, with trichomes aciculate and/or papillose; apex acute to acuminate, recurved; margin revolute when young, later flat to revolute; glabrous. Inflorescences in simple dichasia, frequently unifloral. Peduncle slightly purplish to green, cylindrical, glabrous; primary peduncle 0.25– 1.10 × 
0.05–0.08 cm
, secondary 0.2–0.3 × 
0.7 cm
. Pedicel 0.3–0.5 × 
0.1 cm
, slightly purplish to green, glabrous; ventral side without wings. Bracts 0.10–0.30 × 
0.05 cm
, purplish to green, glabrous. Calyx slightly purplish to green, glabrous; sepals lanceolate, dorsal one 0.75–1.10 × 
0.10–0.20 cm
, lateral ones 0.60–1.00 × 
0.15–0.20 cm
, ventral ones 0.60–1.00 × 
0.10–0.25 cm
. Corolla 
2.5–3.4 cm
, adaxial portion orange-red, ventral portion and proximal third yellow, base wide, glabrous; tube 
2–3 cm
; upper lip 0.55–0.75 × 
0.06–0.10 cm
, bilobate; lower lip, inner perianth with trichomes conical, yellowish white; lobes involute, median lobe 0.15 × 
0.04 cm
. Stamens exserted, adnate at the median third of the corolla tube; filaments white, 
1.8–3.5 cm
long; thecae ca 
0.15 cm
diam.; staminodium ca 
0.3 cm
, adnate at the proximal third of the corolla tube, glabrescent, with short-glandular trichomes, rarely papillose. Ovary 0.40–0.50 × 
0.15–0.30 cm
; style 
2.4–3.3 cm
, exserted, glabrous. Capsule 0.9–1.0 × 
0.3–0.5 cm
, green to slightly purplish. Seeds 0.10 × 
0.05 cm
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum xukuruorum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
has only been collected above 
1000 m
a.s.l., which corresponds to the highest areas of the Borborema Plateau in the states of 
Paraíba
(São João do Tigre in the Cariri Ocidental microregion) and 
Pernambuco
(Pesqueira in the Vale do Ipojuca microregion). Elevation between (800–)1000 and 
1200 m
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Ecology
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum xukuruorum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
appears to prefer higher elevation habitats. It was encountered flowering and fruiting between April and August and is pollinated by hummingbirds (pers. obs.).
</p>
      <p>
Population and threats
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum xukuruorum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is restricted to the municipalities of Jataúba, Pesqueira and São João do Tigre and has been collected in the Xukuru Indigenous Reserve on a rock outcrop covering approximately 50 ha, with a population of more than 100 individual adult plants. Additionally, the Serra do Ororubá Range, where the reserve is located, has a series of granite outcrops that are difficult to access, and it is possible that other populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. xukuruorum
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
(or other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ameroglossum
</tp:taxon-name>
) are yet to be discovered there. The two known locations in 
Paraíba State
have a total of ca 
100 adult
individuals. The isolated populations are exposed to burning and trampling by livestock.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
