<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Cerhomalus quedenfeldti
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
AC2F5EC0-10F3-4262-A85E-F06B7B699139
</p>
      <p>
Figs 4
, 
5D
, 
6
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Differential diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Cerhomalus quedenfeldti
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. mechowi
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. petrovitzi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in having the apices of the parameres with semi-circular excavations in apical view and with more or less developed fossae on ventral sides bordered with a keel, but can be separated from them in having the ventral fossae on the apices of the parameres not bordered proximally (
Fig. 4
G–K, arrowed) and the apices of the parameres in lateral view acute-angled (
Fig. 4D, H
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The new species is named after Friedrich Otto Gustav Quedenfeldt (1817–1891), a German coleopterist.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
♂
; “Congo Brazzaville O.R.S.T.O.M. 

XI-1965
R. Paulian
”; 
MNHN
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
• 
1 ♂
; “ 

Mai 1978

Voka 
Congo
Coll. Th. Porion
”; 
MNHN
; 
6 ♀♀
; “Congo Brazzaville O.R.S.T.O.M. 

XI-1965

R. Paulian”; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
CONGO
BRAZZAVILLE 

XI-57

/ ORSOM PARIS MOUCHET 1957”; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
Soil-Zoological Exp. Congo-Brazzaville Brazzaville
ORSTOM / 

18.10.1963

No 3 singled in park leg. Endrody-Younga”; 
HNHM

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
Soil-Zoological Exp. Congo-Brazzaville Brazzaville
ORSTOM park / 

16.1.1964

No 695 
soil trap
in forest
leg. 
Balogh
&amp; 
Zicsi
”; 
HNHM

• 

1 ♀
; “ 
Soil-Zoological Exp. Congo-Brazzaville Brazzaville
ORSTOM park / 

22.12.1963

No 492 
soil trap
leg. 
Balogh
&amp; 
Zicsi
”; 
MHNG

• 

2 ♂♂
, 
3 ♀♀
; “ 
Brazzaville
Congo
XI-1963

/ MUSEUM PARIS Mission A. Descarpentiers et A. Villiers 1963-1964”; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♂
; “ 
Soil-Zoological Exp. Congo-Brazzaville Kindamba
, 
Kimboukou river
/ 

28.10.1963

. No 38 
singled on river side
leg. 
Endrody-Younga
”; 
MHNG

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>

Male, 
holotype

(
Fig. 4
A–B, D–G)
</p>
      <p>
Body length 
19.8 mm
. Colour uniformly brown to black.
</p>
      <p>
Anterior margin of frontoclypeus somewhat rectangular, slightly convex in middle, bordered and slightly serrate in dorsal view (
Fig. 4A
). Frontoclypeus with a keel-shaped transverse process near anterior margin; height of keel about ¾ its width. Surface of frontoclypeus almost smooth, with minute punctures. Eye tubercles feebly developed. Eyes rather large: width about 
1/6
distance between eyes in dorsal view. Antennae 10-segmented.
</p>
      <p>Pronotum widely rounded laterally, as wide as elytra. Anterior border wide. Basal border narrow, keelshaped, separated from pronotal disc by deep groove with row of longitudinally elongated punctures. Pronotal disc depressed, somewhat rugose anteriorly. Most of pronotum surface covered with minute punctures separated by more than 3 puncture diameters. Anterolateral angles with much larger and denser punctures; posteriolateral angles with same punctures but in smaller numbers.</p>
      <p>
Scutellum subtriangular, narrowly rounded apically, about 
1/10
length of elytra.
</p>
      <p>Elytra 1.1 times longer than wide, with distinct humeral humps. Elytra widest in middle, lateral margins almost parallel in basal half. First (sutural) stria distinct, as groove with row of punctures. Other stria before humeral humps as rows of round setiferous punctures. Striae laterad of stria 5 feebly distinct. Elytral intervals covered with minute punctures, somewhat sparser than those on pronotum.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
<tp:taxon-name>
Cerhomalus quedenfeldti
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–B, D–G
. Holotype, ♂ (MNHN). 
C
. Paratype, ♀ (MNHN). 
H–K
. Paratype, ♂ from Voka ♀ (MNHN). 
A, C
. Habitus in dorsal view. 
B
. Labels. 
D, H
. Aedeagus in lateral view. 
E, I
. Parameres in dorsal view. 
F, J
. Parameres in apical view. 
G, K
. Parameres in ventral view. Scale bars = 1.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>Macropterous.</p>
      <p>Abdominal sternite 8 medially longer than sternites 6 and 7 combined; sternite 6 about as long as sternite 7. Pygidium invisible from above, with slightly truncate apex. Plectrum triangular with rounded apex, wider than long.</p>
      <p>
Aedeagus. Apices of parameres acute angled in lateral view (
Figs 4D, H
, 
5D
), with semi-circular excavations in apical view (
Fig. 4F, J
) and with more or less developed fossae on ventral sides not bordered proximally (
Fig. 4G, K
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
Female (
Fig. 4C
) differs from male in having a relatively smaller, convex pronotum without tubercles, frontoclypeus with much smaller, low keel not bimodal apically, protibial spur, and pygidium with rounded apex.
</p>
      <p>
Variation
</p>
      <p>
Body length of examined male 
paratypes
varies from 
18.5 to 22.5 mm
(males) and from 16.0 to 19.0 mm (females).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
The species is known from a few localities in the 
Republic of the Congo
(
Fig. 6
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
