<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus troglobius Baptista &amp; Giupponi 2002</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536843</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/09EF3258ACAB1AB86DFD8394A788DD3C</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus troglobius
Baptista &amp; Giupponi, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 43
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus troglobius
Baptista &amp; Giupponi, 2002: 106–110
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1–14.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus troglobius
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Baptista &amp; 
Giupponi 2003: 79–80

. — 

Trajano &amp; Bichuette 2010: 12

. — 

Miranda
&amp; Giupponi 2011: 66


, fig. 13. — 


Vasconcelos 
et al.
2013: 496


, fig. 12. — 


Monte 
et al.
2015: 5


. — 


Torres-Contreras 
et al.
2015: 145–146


. — 

Vasconcelos &amp; Ferreira 2016: 185

. — 

Miranda
et al.
2016c: 19


, 29.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Based in part on 
Baptista &amp; Giupponi (2002)
, this species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: corners of anterior carapace margin produced into truncated processes; median eyes and median ocular tubercle absent; lateral eyes reduced to small whitish spot on each side of carapace, without clearly defined lens; sternal platelets narrow, convex and rounded, tritosternum small, slightly larger than tetrasternum; pedipalps articulating transversally with cephalothorax, but not horizontally; pedipalp spines longer than in other species of genus; pedipalp femur with two dorsal spines and two ventral spines; pedipalp tarsus with two long spines, second spine longer than first; proventral corners of walking legs spiniform; leg IV basitibia + distitibia with 17 trichobothria (1 + 16); leg IV basitarsus much longer than distitarsus.
</p>
      <p>
This is the most markedly troglomorphic Brazilian species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
, in which the eyes are completely absent and the leg articles and pedipalp spines extremely elongated.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Latin adjective referring to the troglobitic habitus of the species (
Baptista &amp; Giupponi 2002
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Bahia
, 
Carinhanha
, 
Serra do Ramalho
, 
Gruna do Zé Bastos
; 
14°16′53.92″S
, 
43°46′24.29″W
; 

28 Jun. 2001

; 
R.L.C. Baptista
and 
A.P.L. Giupponi
leg.; 
MNRJ 9067
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9069
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9078
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9081
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♀♀
, 
9 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9068
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
IES
ex 
MNRJ 9079
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MZSP
ex 
MNRJ 9080
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9082
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
IES 3.2972
and 
IES 3.2973
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
BRAZIL
• 
1 juv.
; 
Bahia
, 
Serra do Ramalho
, 
Lapa do Boqueirão
; 

29 Jun. 2001

; 
R.L.C. Baptista
and 
A.P.L. Giupponi
leg.; 
MNRJ 9034
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Supplementary description
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Margin of carapace ventral to lateral eyes with rounded projection; six anterior setae; frontal process triangular, with oval apex, not visible in dorsal view. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle absent; pair of setae in place of median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes reduced to three small, whitish lenses, with seta posterior to lateral ocular triad.</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum short, with four long setae and several smaller setae posteriorly; other sternal platelets narrow and concave, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with four setae anteriorly and seta on membranous region.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin; gonopod sucker-like and barrel shaped. Male gonopod with base of fistula and lateral lobe sclerotized; lateral lobe 2 fimbriate.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with continous row of setae, basally to medially; claw with ten teeth; transverse row of setae on prolateral surface of basal segment absent, with longitudinal row of dense setae, instead; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with six prominent setae encircled by round carina and three setae on margin. Femur with two or three (dextral pedipalp of male 
paratype
) dorsal spines and two ventral spines; dorsal spines situated in distal third; four prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; setiferous tubercle between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines in primary series; prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I, and prominent setiferous tubercle between spines I and II, slightly shorter than first setiferous tubercle; two ventral spines in primary series; extra spine between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and three prominent setiferous tubercles proximal to ventral spine; twelve or thirteen setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 29–31 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles (up to 47 on regenerated legs); tarsus I with 40–42 articles (up to 62 on regenerated legs); first tarsal article shorter than second and subsequent articles. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known from Carinhanha in the Brazilian state of 
Bahia
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
According to 
Baptista &amp; Giupponi (2002)
, all specimens were collected on muddy walls near water bodies, in the dark zone of caves. A troglomorphic harvestman, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Giupponia chagasi
Pérez &amp; Kury, 2002
</tp:taxon-name>
, was also found in the cave. Other taxa observed in the cave include spiders (
<tp:taxon-name>Ctenidae Keyserling, 1877</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ctenus
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
), millipedes (
<tp:taxon-name>Chelodesmidae Cook, 1895</tp:taxon-name>
), crickets (
<tp:taxon-name>Phalangopsidae Blanchard, 1845</tp:taxon-name>
: possibly 
<tp:taxon-name>
Endecous
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
), cockroaches (
<tp:taxon-name>Epilampridae Brunner von Wattenwyl, 1865</tp:taxon-name>
) and beetles (
<tp:taxon-name>Cholevidae Kirby, 1837</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
