<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus montanus
Weygoldt, 1972
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 43
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus montanus
Weygoldt, 1972b: 115–122
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 12–21, 22a.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus montanus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Weygoldt 1972c: 107

, fig. 17; 1974: 217–222, figs 1, 2a–c; 1975: 311; 1996a: 187, fig. 7; 1999c: 107; 2000a: 17, 98, figs 23, 208–211. — 

Quintero 1975: 161

, figs 4–5, 7–8, 11–12. — 

Delle Cave 1986: 162

, fig. II. — 

Proctor 1998: 161

. — 

Harvey 2003: 6

. — 

Baptista &amp; 
Giupponi 2003: 80

. — 

Miranda
&amp; Giupponi 2011: 66


, fig. 13. — 


Vasconcelos 
et al.
2013: 495


, fig. 12. — 

Miranda
et al.
2016c: 19


, 21, 27, 29, 31.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: tegument covered with clavate setae; carapace and legs dark in color; leg I tarsus I with 23–28 articles with length of first tarsal article equal to combined length of subsequent ten articles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Although unspecified by the author, the name is a Latin adjective meaning ‘of mountains’, which refers to the occurrence of this species in a hilly landscape.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Espírito Santo
, 
Domingos Martins
, 

50 km
W of Vitória

; 
20°19′36.39″ S
, 
40°50′15.03″ W
; 
MNRJ 9015
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9015

• 

7 ♀♀
, 
6 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
SMF

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
BRAZIL
• 
5 ♀♀
, 
3 juv.
; 
Espírito Santo
, 
Santa Teresa
, 
Reserva Santa Lúcia
; 
19°56′10″ S
, 
40°36′06″ W
; 

15–19 Oct. 2003

; 
Almeida
, 
Baptista
, 
Giupponi
, 
Mendes
and 
Pedroso
leg.; 
MNRJ 9087

• 

4 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Espírito Santo
, 
Man. Livre
; 
MNRJ 9243

• 

3 ♀♀
, 
2 ♂♂
; 
Espírito Santo
, 
Alegre
, 
Reserva Biológica de Duas Bocas
; 
20°16′55.13″ S
, 
40°30′22.97″ W
; 
MNRJ 9242

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Supplementary description
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Tegument covered with short, broad setae. Six anterior setae; frontal process triangular, not visible in dorsal view. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci.</p>
      <p>Median eyes present; median ocular tubercle shallow, with pair of setae. Lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad.</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly, with typical setation; other sternal platelets wide, flat, with pair of setae on each side of platelets and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with four setae anteriorly and three setae on membranous region.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin; posterior margin of genital operculum with pair of lateral sulci; gonopod sucker-like, funnel-shaped [dissected gonopod of female (
MNRJ
9087) with sulcus on anterior side, as illustrated by 
Weygoldt (1972b)
in original description of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. brasilianus
</tp:taxon-name>
]; base of gonopods unsclerotized. Male gonopod with base of fistula and lateral lobe sclerotized; lateral lobe 2 fimbriate.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth on retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae basally to medially; claw with seven teeth; transverse row of around seven setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with prominent seta encircled by round carina and three setae on margin. Femur with four dorsal spines and three ventral spines; three prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; setiferous tubercle between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with five dorsal spines in primary series; prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; four ventral spines in primary series; prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine half length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 26–28 setae in ventral row.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 28 articles; length of first tarsal article equal to combined length of subsequent ten articles. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, without sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known from several localities in the montane region of 
Espírito Santo
, 
Brazil
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Found under fallen tree trunks and stones in tropical forest.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
