<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax javensis
(
Gravely, 1915
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 103
, 
115–116
; 
Table 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynichosarax javensis
Gravely, 1915b: 439
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 3.0.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynicosarax javensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Mello-Leitão 1931: 52

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynichosarax javanensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Giltay 1931: 24–25

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax javensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Harvey 2003: 8

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
in Southeast Asia and Oceania by the following combination of characters: ventral sac cover present; female gonopod finger-like; cheliceral basal segment with prominent, acute tooth on retrolateral surface, adjacent to bifid tooth; pedipalp patella with two short ventral spines between spine I and distal margin; pedipalp tarsus with one dorsal spine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Adjective referring to the Indonesian island of 
Java
, on which the 
type
locality is situated.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
INDONESIA
• 
Java
, 
Buitenzorg
[Bogor], 
Jawa Berat
; 
1 ex.
, Indian Museum (now the Zoological Survey of India, Calcutta) [not examined].

</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
INDONESIA
• 
1 ♀
; 
Java
, 
Gua Kokop
, 
Pacitan
; 

13 Jul. 1992

; 
Ratih Aryasari
le 
g
.; 
on wall
; 
WAM
T80539

• 

1 ♀
; 
Gua Kokop
, 
Pacitan
; 
J. Lowry
leg.; parts of exuvia; 
WAM
T80543

• 

2 ♀♀
, 
2 juv.
; 
Gua Kamidordo
, 
Pacitan
; 
Juguono
leg.; 
WAM
T80541

• 

1 ♀
; 
Leweng Jaran
, 
Pacitan
; 
Muksin
leg.; 
WAM
T80542

• 

1 ♀
; 
Gua Kendil
, 
Pacitan
; 
Muksin
and 
J. Lowry
leg.; 
WAM
T80540

• 

1 juv. ♂
[misidentified as 
1 ♀
]; 
Jjompea
; 

11 Mar. 1904

; 
ZMH
; 
1 ♀
; 
Ichmiedekneas
; 

5 Aug. 1902

; 
ZMH

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Six anterior setae; frontal process triangular. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed; pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, pale, seta lateral to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad situated near carapace margin; curved carina between ocular triads and carapace margin, not contacting eyes.</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae; other sternal platelets narrow and projected, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with four setae near posterior margin of platelet.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sac cover well developed.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with short setae posteromedially (
Fig. 115A–C
); pair of low, white bulges medially with slender setae apically (
Fig. 115A–C
); gonopod finger-like, unsclerotized basally (
Fig. 115A, C, E
); denticulate surface between gonopod and posterior margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 115D
). Adult male unknown (only male studied was immature).
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Retrolateral surface of basal segment with short, acute projection, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae basally to medially; claw with three teeth; row of several setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>PEDIPALPS. Coxae without seta encircled by round carina and with two or three setae on margin. Femur with three or four dorsal spines and three or four ventral spines; two or three prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; ventral spine between spine 1 and proximal margin; spine present or absent between ventral spines 1 and 2, and spines 2 and 3. Patella with four or five dorsal spines in primary series; prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I; three ventral spines; two short spines between spine I and distal border. Tibia with ventral spine distally and three setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with one dorsal spine; cleaning organ with 25–29 setae in ventral row.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; tarsal organ close to tarsal claw (
Fig. 116A– C
); rod sensilla with six setae and in shallow groove (
Fig. 116B, E
); first and second tarsal articles equal in length. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in medial third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 8
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the Indonesian island of 
Java
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Several specimens were collected in caves.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
According to 
Gravely (1915)
, the 
holotype
was deposited at the Indian Museum (now the Zoological Survey of 
India
, Calcutta). The types of some of 
Gravely’s (1915)
other species are deposited at SMF but the 
holotype
of this species could not be located and may be lost.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
