<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus eleonorae Baptista &amp; Giupponi
            2003</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536794</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FFF2FFBFA6EFFCDBFB12DBE8</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae
            Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Charinus eleonorae Baptista &amp; Giupponi, 2003 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Fig. 43 ; Table 4 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Charinus eleonorae Baptista &amp; Giupponi, 2003: 80–84 </tp:taxon-name> ,
         figs 1–14. </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Charinus eleonorae </tp:taxon-name> – Trajano &amp; Bichuette 2010: 12 . —
         Miranda &amp; Giupponi 2011: 66 , fig. 13. — Vasconcelos et al. 2013: 496 , fig. 12. —
         Torres-Contreras et al. 2015: 148 . — Monte et al. 2015: 6 , figs 1, 4. — Vasconcelos &amp;
         Ferreira 2016: 185 . — Miranda et al. 2016c: 19 , 29. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> This species may be separated from other <tp:taxon-name> Charinus </tp:taxon-name> in
         eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: anterior margin
         of carapace with corners weakly developed into small roundish knobs; median ocular tubercle
         indistinct; lateral eyes present, but reduced, with flattened lenses; female gonopods
         small, slightly longer than wide, sucker-like, with rounded opening; cheliceral claw with
         nine or twelve teeth; pedipalp femur with three dorsal spines and three ventral spines;
         pedipalp patella with four dorsal spines and three ventral spines; pedipalp tarsus with two
         long spines similar in length; tibia of leg I with 23 articles, tarsus I with 40 or 41
         articles; leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> Patronym honoring Dr Eleonora Trajano ( Baptista &amp; Giupponi 2003 ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Type material </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Holotype BRAZIL • ♂ ; Minas Gerais , Itacarambi , Gruta Olhos d’Água
            ; 15°06′47″ S , 44°10′11″ W ; 26 Jun. 2001 ; R.L.C. Baptista and A.P.L. Giupponi leg.;
            MNRJ 9070 . </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Paratypes BRAZIL • 6 ♀♀ , 7 ♂♂ , 2 juv. ♂♂ , 2 juv. ♀♀ , 2
            protonymphs; same collection data as for holotype; MNRJ 9033 </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same collection data as for holotype; MZSP [not examined]
         </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ , same collection data as for
            holotype; CZACC [now IES; L.F. de Armas, pers. com.; not examined]
         </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same locality as holotype; 10 Jul.
            1993 ; E. Trajano leg.; MNRJ 9024 </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ,
            1 juv. ; same locality as for holotype; 30 Mar.–2 Apr. 1994 ; P. Gnaspini and E. Trajano
            leg.; MNRJ 9023 </tp:material-citation> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Supplementary description </p>
      <p>CARAPACE.Ten anterior setae; frontal process triangular, not visible in dorsal view. Small
         granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes reduced,
         median ocular tubercle absent; seta near remnants of median eyes; lateral eyes reduced,
         pale, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad.</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly, with typical setation; other sternal platelets
         narrow, concave, with pair of setae anteriorly and some smaller setae posteriorly;
         pentasternum with twelve setae anteriorly and three setae near membranous region.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller
         setae near margin; posterior margin of genital operculum with pair of shallow lateral
         sulci; gonopod sucker-like, with short stem and wide opening of genital atrium; gonopods
         unsclerotized basally. Male gonopod with base of fistula and lateral lobe sclerotized;
         lateral lobe 2 fimbriate.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting slightly from retrolateral surface of basal segment,
         opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with two patches of setae, one
         situated basally, the other medially; claw with 9–12 teeth; transverse row of around ten
         setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp
         larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with three prominent setae encircled by round carina and
         three setae on margin. Femur with three dorsal spines and four ventral spines; small spine
         between dorsal spines 2 and 3; two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1
         and proximal margin; long spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin; small spine
         between spines 1 and 2 and 2 and 3. Patella with three dorsal spines in primary series;
         prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; three ventral
         spines in primary series; long spine between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral
         spine distally and five setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal
         spines, proximal spine half length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 29–30 setae in
         ventral row.</p>
      <p> LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article
         shorter than subsequent articles. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, without
         sclerotized, denticulate border at apex of articles; trichobothrium bt situated in proximal
         third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium bc situated closer to sbf than to bf ,
         sc and sf series each with six trichobothria. </p>
      <p> Measurements </p>
      <p> See Table 4 . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Known only from the type localities. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p> Natural history </p>
      <p> All specimens were collected in the dark zone of the cave; none were found in the dry,
         upper galleries, where the phrynichid, <tp:taxon-name> Trichodamon princeps Mello-Leitão,
            1935 </tp:taxon-name> , was abundant. <tp:taxon-name> Charinus eleonorae
         </tp:taxon-name> may be found inside small galleries or holes in the cave walls. Females
         carry up to 15 eggs and five embryos ( Baptista &amp; Giupponi 2003 ). The cave is
         experiencing intense human disturbance including the installation of a water pump and
         construction of a water dam (L.S. Carvalho, pers. com.). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
