<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax rahmadii
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
307E7237-3EF2-40B4-8390-AE3EF5C03017
</p>
      <p>
Figs 103
, 
120–121
; 
Table 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
in Southeast Asia and Oceania by the following combination of characters: large size; female gonopod finger-like (
Fig. 121A
); basal segment of chelicera with acute tooth on retrolateral surface; cheliceral claw with five teeth; pedipalp patella with long spine between dorsal spine I and distal margin (
Fig. 120E
); pedipalp tarsus with two spines (
Fig. 120D
); tibia of leg I with 23 articles, tarsus I with 41 articles; leg IV basitibia with four pseudoarticles; distitibia 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
This species resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. gravelyi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, but can be differentiated by the greater number of spines on the pedipalp.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Patronym honoring Dr Cahyo Rahmadi for his contributions to the study of Southeast Asian whip spiders.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
INDONESIA
• 
♀
[largest]; 
Khom Bheng caves
, 
Kalimantan Timut
; 
01°01′ N
, 
116°59′ E
; 
J. Lowy
leg.; 
WAM
T63201
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
INDONESIA
• 
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
, 
2 juv.
; same collection data as for holotype; 
WAM
T63201

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 120A
); frontal process triangular, visible in dorsal view (
Fig. 120C
). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed; pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, pale, seta lateral to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad near carapace margin; curved carina between ocular triads and carapace margin.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 120B
); other sternal platelets narrow and projected, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with six setae anteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs cover well developed.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with short setae posteromedially (
Fig. 121A–C
); pair of white bulges medially with slender setae apically (
Fig. 121A–C
); gonopod finger-like with apical invagination (
Fig. 121A, C, F
); denticulate surface between gonopod and posterior margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 121D
); slit sensilla on lateral margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 121E
); unsclerotized basally. Male gonopod LoL2 with sclerotized base.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Retrolateral surface of basal segment with short projection opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae basally to medially; claw with five teeth; more than two rows of several setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxae without seta encircled by round carina and with three or four setae on its margin. Femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines in primary series (
Fig. 120E–F
); four prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; spine between dorsal spines 2 and 3, and spines 3 and 4; long spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin, two thirds length of spine 1; spine between ventral spines 1 and 2, 2 and 3, and 3 and 4. Patella with five or six dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 120E
); prominent spine distal to spine I; four ventral spines (
Fig. 120F
); small spine between ventral spines 1 and 2, and spines 2 and 3; two or three small setiferous tubercles between spine I and distal border. Tibia with ventral spine distally and long setiferous tubercle proximally; three or four setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines (
Fig. 120D
), distal spine long, about one-third length of tarsus, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 30–32 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first and second tarsal articles equal in length. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, without sclerotized, denticulate border at apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 8
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
localities.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Exclusively found in caves; troglomorphic characters include large size and long spines on pedipalp.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
