<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus acosta
(
Quintero, 1983
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 12
; 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinides acosta
Quintero, 1983: 32–34
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1a, c, 
8g
, 9a–f, 12c.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus acosta
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Delle Cave 1986: 162

, fig. II. — 

Ávila Calvo &amp; Armas 1997: 31

. — 

Armas &amp; Teruel 1997: 46

. — 

Armas 2000b: 133–134

; 

2004: 38

; 

2005: 271

, 273; 

2006a: 169–170

; 

2006b: 225–226

, figs 4a–c, 5a–d, 6, 20; 2013b: 91, 94. — 

Armas &amp; Ávila Calvo 2000: 291–292

. — 

Weygoldt 2000a: 74

. — 

Baptista &amp; Giupponi 2002: 106

. — 

Harvey 2003: 4

. — 

Pérez &amp; Teruel 2004: 170

, fig. 12. — 


Teruel 
et al.
2009: 201–202


, fig. 1. — 
Teruel 2011: 345
, figs 1–3. — 

Seiter &amp; Hörweg 2013: 51

. — 

Seiter &amp; Wolff 2014: 233

. — 


Wolff 
et al.
2015: 3


, figs 2a–b; 2016: 2–4, figs 4–5; 2017: 2–3, 7, fig. 1. — 

Teruel &amp; Questel 2015: 46–47

. — 


Torres-Contreras 
et al.
2015: 127


. — 

Miranda
et al.
2016b: 555


, 557. — 

Teruel &amp; Rodríguez-Cabrera 2016: 135–136

, fig. 3a–b.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other Caribbean and Central American 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
by means of the following combination of characters: carapace frontal process with rounded apex; black median ocular tubercle reduced, sunken in carapace, with well-developed median eyes; lateral eyes well developed, black; bifid tooth of cheliceral basal segment with dorsal cusp shorter than ventral cusp; tritosternum projected anteriorly with meso- and metasternum undivided; prolateral surface of cheliceral basal segment with row of six fine setae; cheliceral claw with five teeth; pedipalp femur with three dorsal spines and three ventral spines; pedipalp femur with pair of setiferous tubercles preceding first dorsal and ventral spines; pedipalp patella with three dorsal spines and two ventral spines; pedipalp tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine less than half length of distal spine; tibia of leg I with 23 articles, tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article 1.4 times as long as second article; leg IV basitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated equidistant between 
bf
and 
sbf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria; female gonopod rounded, flat and cushion-like, without claw-like projection (
Quintero 1983
: fig. 
8g
). The male is unknown.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Patronym honoring the Cuban micropaleontologist Dr J. 
<tp:taxon-name>
T. Acosta (
Quintero 1983
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CUBA
• 
♀
; 
Camagüey Province
, 
Camagüey
; 
21°23′33.26″ N
, 
77°54′19.05″ W
; 1954; J

. 
<tp:taxon-name>T. Acosta</tp:taxon-name>

leg.; 
MCZ
[not examined].

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 1
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Widespread in 
Cuba
, recorded at several locations on the island (
Teruel &amp; Rodríguez-Cabrera 2016
), even in the same habitat as other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
, e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. wanlessi
</tp:taxon-name>
, although not at the same time of year
</p>
      <p>
(
Teruel 2011
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
Epigean, found in forests, but well adapted to disturbed habitats, e.g., 
Santiago de Cuba
, south of the Sierra Maestra range (

Teruel 
et al.
2009

). The widespread distribution of this species may be attributed to its parthenogenetic biology (
Armas 2000b
, 
2005
, 
2006b
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The internal and external morphology of the Caribbean species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
are quite homogenous, making it difficult to delimit and identify these species (

Miranda
et al.
2016b

). Separating the Cuban species is among the most difficult, especially when comparing 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. acosta
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. cubensis
</tp:taxon-name>
. The only reliable characters to separate the two species are the development of the median eyes and the counts of articles on the tarsus of leg I. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus acosta
</tp:taxon-name>
has reduced median eyes and the leg I tarsus consists of 41 articles, whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. cubensis
</tp:taxon-name>
lacks median eyes (occasionally visible as small blackish spots below the tegument) and the leg I tarsus consists of 36–37 articles. Genetic studies of the different populations of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. acosta
</tp:taxon-name>
and other Cuban species may illuminate the true diversity of the genus on the island.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
