<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus pescotti Dunn 1949</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536873</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/470AAC236603560706301D730913D18C</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus pescotti
Dunn, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 94
, 
101–102
; 
Table 7
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus pescotti
Dunn, 1949: 8–11
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1–3.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus pescotti
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Monteith 1965: 87

. — 

Baehr 1974: 101–104

, fig. 1. — 

Harvey 1985: 157

; 

2003: 7

. — 

Delle Cave 1986: 162

, fig. II. — 

Gray &amp; Robinson 1986: 218–224

, figs 1–16. — 

Quintero 1986: 208

, fig. 12. — 

Weygoldt 2006b: 30–32

, figs 40–44. — 


Harvey 
et al.
2012: 8


. — 


Gibbons 
et al.
2019: 498


, 500–503, figs 1f–g, 2.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in Oceania by means of the following combination of characters: chelicerae with small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of cheliceral claw with two patches of setae, basally and subdorsally; pedipalp coxa with seta encircled by round carina and three setae on margin; setiferous tubercle present between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin of pedipalp femur; leg I with first tarsal article similar in length to sum of subsequent four articles.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus pescotti
</tp:taxon-name>
is the only species with elongated first tarsal article to have 41 articles on tarsus I. All other species with the same character, i.e., proximal tarsal article longer than the length of the subsequent three to ten articles combined (
<tp:taxon-name>
C. carvalhoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. longitarsus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. magalhaesi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. montanus
</tp:taxon-name>
), have less than 40 tarsal articles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Patronym honoring R.T.M. Pescott (
Dunn 1949
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
AUSTRALIA
• 
♀
; 
Queensland
, 
Barron Falls
; 1923; 
G.F. Hill
leg.; 
NMV
[not examined].

</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
AUSTRALIA
• 
1 ♂
, 
1 subad. ♂
, 
1 juv.
; 
Freshwater Creek
, at 
Crystal Cascades
, 

10 km
S of Freshwater

; 
17°00′ S
, 
145°40′ E
; 

12 Jul. 1986

; 
M.S. Harvey
and 
P.J. Vaughan
leg.; 
WAM
T577
89

• 

2 juv. ♀♀
; 
Crystal Cascades
, 
NE of Cairns
; [
16°57′43.04″ S
, 
145°40′47″ E
]; 

24 Aug. 1980

; 
M.S. Harvey
leg., 
WAM
T57788

• 

1 ♀
; 
Flying Fish Point
, 
Innisfail
; [
17°29′45.53″ S
, 
146°04′17.03″ E
]; 

21 Jan. 1975

; 
R.J. Raven
leg.; 
WAM
T57787

• 

1 ♀
juv.; 
Iron Range
, 
West Claudie River
; 
12°43′ S
, 
143°17′ E
; 

3–10 Dec. 1985

; 
G. Monteith
and 
D. Cook
leg.; 
rainforest
; 
QM
S38779

• 

2 juv.
; 
West Claudie R. [river]
, 
Iron Range
; 

50 m
a.s.l.

; 

3–10 Dec. 1985

; 
G. Monteith
and 
D. Cook
leg.; 
rainforest
; 
QM
S38787

• 

1 ♂
; 

2 km
WNW of Cape Tribulation

; [
16°04′50.84″ S
, 
145°26′38.9″ E
]; 

23 Sep.–7 Oct. 1982

; 
QM
S38776

• 

2 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
, 
9 juv.
; 

2 km
WNW of Cape Tribulation

(site 2); [
16°05′16.44″ S
, 
145°26′26.82″ E
]; 

23 Sep.–7 Oct. 1982

; 
Monteith
, 
Yeates
and 
Thompson
leg.; 
QM
S38788

• 

1 ♀
; 
NeS of Pilgrim Sands
, 
Cape Tribulation
; [
16°04′06.68″ S
, 
145°27′53.49″ E
]; 

28 Aug. 1988

; 
R. Raven
, 
T. Churchill
and J. 
Gallon
le 
g
.; 
QM
S38792

• 

2 ♂♂
; 
Queensland
, 
Home Rule
; 
15°44′46.7″ S
, 
145°17′47.7″ E
; 
L. Monod
and 
G. Romand
; 

23 Jul. 2006

; 

191 m
a.s.l.

; 
walking track to waterfall, lowland rainforest, in between stones/in rock crevices
; 
AMCC
[
LP 6367
]

• 

1 ♂
; 
Queensland
, 
Crystal Cascades
; 
16°57′58.3″ S
, 
145°40′45.9″ E
; 

10 Jul. 2006

; 

46 m
a.s.l.

; 
L. Monod
leg.; 
rainforest, in rock cervices and in shallow burrows under stones, near a creek
; 
AMCC
[
LP 6366
]

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Supplementary description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed (
Fig. 101A
); pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from margin of carapace; frontal process triangular (
Fig. 101C
).
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation (
Fig. 101B
); other sternal platelets wide, with seta on each lateral border and some smaller setae in between; pentasternum with two setae anteriorly and without seta in membranous region.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Posterior margin of female genital operculum slightly convex; gonopod cushion-like (see 
Weygoldt 2006
: figs 41–42) and slightly sclerotized basally. Male gonopod (
Fig. 102A–C
) with border of fistula and lateral lobes sclerotized; lateral lobe 2 fimbriate (
Fig 102E
); dorsal lobe with more ventral position, situated behind lateral lobe 1 (
Fig. 102D
); processus internus short (
Fig. 102F
).
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with two patches of setae, basally and subdorsally; claw with four teeth; row of eleven or twelve setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with seta encircled by round carina and three setae on margin. Femur with four dorsal spines (
one specimen
with five dorsal spines on one pedipalp) and four ventral spines (
Fig. 101E–F
); setiferous tubercle between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines and three prominent setiferous tubercles proximal to spine III (
Fig. 101E
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; two ventral spines (
one specimen
with three ventral spines on one pedipalp); setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and seta between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, distal spine long, more than half length of tarsus, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine (
Fig. 101D
); several long, narrow setae ventral to distal spine; cleaning organ with 24–29 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article similar in length to sum of subsequent four articles, and second article very short (mean size of first article: 
0.89 mm
; mean sum of subsequent four articles: 0.81, n=4). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 7
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from 
Queensland
, 
Australia
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
Epigean, found on the forest floor. See 
Gray &amp; Robinson (1986)
for a detailed study of the ecology of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. pescotti
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
See 
Weygoldt (2006b)
for a redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. pescotti
</tp:taxon-name>
. The 
paratype
from Savo Island, 
Solomon Islands
, was misidentified. It is described below as 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax dunni
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
