<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax tiomanensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
7E64F7E1-1D3E-4586-9873-7CC190630783
</p>
      <p>
Figs 103
, 
126–129
; 
Table 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax
</tp:taxon-name>
in Southeast Asia and Oceania by the following combination of characters: median and lateral eyes well developed (
Fig. 126A
); median ocular tubercle shallow; secondary sexual dimorphism, males with longer pedipalp segments than females; pedipalp tarsus with three spines (two on dextral pedipalp of 
holotype
male) (
Fig. 126D
); leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
bf
than to 
sbf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Sarax tiomanensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax yayukae
</tp:taxon-name>
in having secondary sexual dimorphism, pedipalp segments longer in males; the presence of three ventral spines on the pedipalp patella and two or three dorsal spines on the pedipalp tarsus; and the position of trichobothria 
bt
and 
bc
on the tibia leg IV. It differs in the number of dorsal spines on the pedipalp femur (three to five spines in adults and immatures of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. tiomanensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
compared with three spines in adults and two or three in immatures of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. yayukae
</tp:taxon-name>
); five ventral spines on the pedipalp femur in adults and immatures (three spines in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. yayukae
</tp:taxon-name>
); five (immatures) or six (adults) dorsal spines on the pedipalp patella (three in immatures and four in adults of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. yayukae
</tp:taxon-name>
); 17 trichobothria on leg IV tibia (19 trichobothria in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. yayukae
</tp:taxon-name>
). 
<tp:taxon-name>
Sarax tiomanensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
exhibits a prominent carina ventral to the lateral eyes, extending to the anterior margin of the carapace, which resembles that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Weygoldtia davidovi
</tp:taxon-name>
, but is shorter.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Adjective referring to Tioman Island, 
Malaysia
, to which this species appears to be endemic.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MALAYSIA
• 
♂
; 
Pahang
, 
Pulau Tioman
, 
trail from Juara to Tekek, closer to Tekek
; 
02°49.301′ N
, 
104°10.183′ E
; 

135 m
a.s.l.

; 

15 Jun. 2013

; 
L. Prendini
and 
S.F. Loria
leg.; secondary forest/old plantation with many rubber trees; relatively dry; moderately open canopy; many granite outcrops; 
AMCC
[
LP 12001
].

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
MALAYSIA
• 
2 ♀♀
, 
2 ♂♂
, 
1 juv.
; 
Pahang
, 
Pulau Tioman
, 
trail between Kampung Genting and Kampung Paya
; 
02°46.427′ N
, 
104°07.198′ E
– 
02°47.009′ N
, 
104°07.113′ E
; 

11 Jun. 2013

; 

35–41 m
a.s.l.

; 
L. Prendini
and 
S.F. Loria
leg.; primary rainforest close to seashore; moderately open canopy; sparse understorey; moderate leaf litter layer; many large granite boulders, often with exfoliating flakes; brownish-orange, clayey granitic loam; under rocks; 
AMCC
[
LP 11998
]

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 juv.
; 
Pahang
, 
Pulau Tioman
, 
trail from Air Batang to Salang via Monkey Bay
; 
02°51.151′ N
, 
104°09.077′ E
; 

13 Jun. 2013

; 

48 m
a.s.l.

; 
L. Prendini
and 
S.F. Loria
leg.; primary rainforest close to seashore, moderately open canopy, sparse understorey, moderate leaf litter layer, many large granite boulders, often with exfoliating flakes, brownish-orange, clayey granitic loam; under rocks; 
AMCC
[
LP 11999
]

• 

2 ♀♀
; 
Pahang
, 
Pulau Tioman
, 
trail from Juara to Tekek
; 
02°48.622′ N
, 
104°10.745′ E
; 

15 Jun. 2013

; 

301–305 m
a.s.l.

; 
L. Prendini
and 
S.F. Loria
leg.; primary rainforest in interior of Tioman Island, closed canopy, moderate to dense leaf litter layer, limestone rocks on summit, becoming sandstone and then granite lower down, under log, 
AMCC
[
LP 12000
]

• 

1 ♂
; 
Pahang
, 
Pulau Tioman
, 
trail from Juara to Tekek, closer to Tekek
; 
02°49.301′ N
, 
104°10.183′ E
; 

15 Jun. 2013

; 

135 m
a.s.l.

; 
L. Prendini
and 
S.F. Loria
; secondary forest/old plantation with many rubber trees, relatively dry, moderately open canopy, many granite outcrops, 
AMCC
[
LP 12001
]

• 

1 ♀
, 
2 subad. ♀♀
, 
2 juv.
; 
Pahang
, 
Pulau Tioman
, 
trail from Salang to Air Batang via Monkey Bay
; 
02°51.09′ N
, 
104°09.221′ E
–02°52.322′ N, 104°09.14′ E; 

14 Jun. 2013

; 

33–36 m
a.s.l.

; 
L. Prendini
and 
S.F. Loria
leg.; primary rainforest close to seashore; moderately open canopy; sparse understorey; moderate leaf litter layer; many large granite boulders, often with exfoliating flakes; brownish-orange, clayey granitic loam; under logs and stones; 
AMCC
[
LP 12002
]

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Frontal process large, triangular, slightly curved anteriorly (
Fig. 126A
). Median eyes well developed and median ocular tubercle shallow (
Fig. 126C
); pair of setae on median ocular tubercle, aligned one after another, posterior to eyes; lateral eyes well developed, seta situated lateral to each lateral ocular triad
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly, with typical setation, except one medial seta instead of two, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 126B
); metasternum not paired, formed by single platelet, with pair of setae posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sacs cover well developed.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with pair of bulges near apex and medial invagination, with several setae along margin (
Fig. 127A–C
); pair of glands laterally on bulges (
Fig. 127F
). Gonopods finger-like with small invagination apically and wrinkled base (
Fig. 127E
); gonopods well separated from margin of genital operculum (genital operculum with wide margin); denticulate surface between gonopods and posterior margin of genital operculum (
Fig. 127D
). Male gonopod as wide as long, wider in distal third (
Fig. 128C
); Lol2 fimbriate, projections short (
Fig. 128A–B, D
); PI with spiny surface and acute apex (
Fig. 128E
); dorsal lobe short, surface covered with spines and apex curved laterally (
Fig. 128C, F–G
); LaM short, not fused medially, with smooth surface (
Fig. 128A–B, D
); fistula without inner spines.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth on retrolateral surface, opposite to bifid tooth; prolateral surface of basal segment with vertical row of several large setae; claw with three denticles.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxae with three setae on margin of round carina. Femur with 3–5 dorsal spines; small, extra spine between dorsal spines 1 and 3, closer to spine 3, may be present (
Fig. 126E
); two prominent setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 1; five ventral spines (
Fig. 126F
); extra spine, distal to spine 5, may be present; prolateral spine near base of spine I; prolateral row of spines, with three small spines, present in 
one specimen
(adult female, AMCC [LP 12002]). Patella with five dorsal spines (
Fig. 126E
); two spines between spine I and distal margin; three ventral spines, decreasing in length (extra spine proximally may be present) (
Fig. 126F
); small spine between spine I and distal margin, one-third length of spine I. Tibia with two dorsal spines; ventral spine in distal half, two-thirds length of proximal dorsal spine. Tarsus with two or three dorsal spines (
Fig. 126D
); 
holotype
with two spines on dextral pedipalp, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine, and three spines on sinistral pedipalp, two distal spines subequal, proximal spine two-thirds length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 28–33 setae in ventral brush.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; modified claw and tarsal organ at apex of leg (
Fig. 129D–E
); leg covered with bristles and clavate sensilla (
Fig. 129A–E
). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, trichobothrium 
bt
situated submedially on distal pseudo-article; apex of basitibia with strong sclerotized mark; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated mid-way to 
bf
and 
sbf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria; tarsus with weakly developed white annulus on second article.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 8
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
localities on Tioman Island, 
Malaysia
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Collected under logs and stones in moderately open to closed canopy, primary rainforest with moderate to dense leaf litter layer.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
