<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus madagascariensis Fage 1954</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536847</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/92D9483BC06A7EFF7E88B88D5DA779CC</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus madagascariensis
Fage, 1954
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 10K–L
, 
80–81
; 
Table 5
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus madagascariensis
Fage, 1954: 183–184
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1, 3.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus madagascariensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Lawrence 1969: 86

. — 

Remillet 1973: 142

. — 

Legendre 1972: 435

. — 

Weygoldt 1972b: 123

; 

2000b: 346

. — 

Delle Cave 1986: 157

, fig. II. — 

Harvey 2003: 6

.

</p>
      <p>

Non 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus jeanneli
Simon, 1936
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Fage 1946a: 260–262

, fig. 2 (misidentification).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus madagascariensis
</tp:taxon-name>
differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. africanus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. fagei
</tp:taxon-name>
in the count of spines on the pedipalp tarsus, with three spines in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. madagascariensis
</tp:taxon-name>
compared with two spines in the other species. It differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. loko
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in the higher count of spines on the pedipalp segments, and from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. milloti
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. susuwa
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in the well-developed median and lateral eyes.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Although unspecified, the name of the species is evidently an adjective referring to 
Madagascar
, the country in which the species was found.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Syntypes
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
[without gonopod], 
1 adult
[without gonopod], 
2 juv.
; 
Antsiranana Province
, 
Nosy Bé Island
, 
Réserve naturelle de Lokoubé
[as Lokobe]; [
13°23′59.47″ S
, 
48°18′58.76″ E
]; 

Sep. 1947

; 
J. Millot
leg.; 
MNHN

.
</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 juv.
; same collection data as for syntypes; 
MNHN

• 

1 ♂
and 
2 juv.
; same collection data as for syntypes; 
MNHN 112

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Ankari Sud
; 
Ankarana
; [
12°55′00.71″ S
, 
49°08′36.78″ E
]; 
MNHN

• 

2 ♀♀
, 
2 juv.
; 
Mahajanga
[
Majunga
]; [
15°43′ S
, 
46°18′59.96″ E
]; 1947; 
J. Millot
leg.; 
MNHN

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six short anterior setae (
Fig. 81A–B
); frontal process long; anterolateral border of carapace slightly projected anteriorly. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes well developed, median ocular tubercle shallow, with pair of setae (
Fig. 81A–B
); lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin.
</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation; other sternal platelets wide, with one seta at each lateral border and some smaller setae in between; pentasternum with two setae anteriorly and pair of setae in membranous region.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Anterior margin of female genital operculum with rounded projection medially and suckerlike gonopod; genital operculum with several prominent setae ventrally, and several longer, narrower setae near margin; gonopod unsclerotized basally. Male gonopod dorsal lobe with apex projected slightly; lateral lobe 2 fimbriate</p>
      <p>
CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth (
Fig. 10L
); retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae extending basally to medially; claw with five teeth (
Fig. 10K–L
); row of 9–11 setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.
</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with three setae on margin and without seta encircled by round carina. Femur with five or six dorsal spines (distal spine very small) and four ventral spines; small spine between dorsal spines 1 and 2, and spines 2 and 3 (
Fig. 81A–B
); small spines between all ventral spines of primary series; large spine proximal to ventral spine 1, one-third length of spine 1; three prominent setiferous tubercles between spine 1 and proximal margin, first two spines long, with geminate base. Patella with six or seven dorsal spines; prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I (
Fig. 81A–B
); five or six ventral spines; broad spine distal to spine I, between spine I and distal margin, one-third length of spine I. Tibia with ventral spine distally and seta between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with three dorsal spines, one medially on tarsus and two near proximal margin; dorsalmost spine larger among the proximal spines, about twice length of ventralmost spine; ventralmost and distal spines aligned and subequal in length; some long, slender setae between distal spine and distal margin; cleaning organ with 28–29 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article almost four times length of second article (mean length of first article: 
0.78 mm
; mean length of second article: 
0.22 mm
; n= 4). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 5
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known from northern 
Madagascar
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
