<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus muchmorei Armas &amp; Teruel 1997</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5573035</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BD59956FE860410329047CA349FF6F07</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus muchmorei
Armas &amp; Teruel, 1997
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 12
; 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus muchmorei
Armas &amp; Teruel, 1997: 43–46
</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1–6.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinides
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Muchmore 1993: 32

. — 

Ávila Calvo &amp; Armas 1997: 31

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus muchmorei
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Harvey 2003: 6

. — 

Armas 2004: 39

; 

2006b: 228

, figs 6, 10a–b; 2010: 58, 60. — 

Teruel &amp; Questel 2015: 46–47

. — 
Teruel 2016: 10
. — 

Miranda
et al.
2016b: 555


, 557. — 

Teruel &amp; Coulis 2017: 35

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other Caribbean and Central American 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
by means of the following combination of characters: small size; median eyes and median ocular tubercle absent; female gonopod cushion-like; secondary sexual dimorphism absent.
</p>
      <p>
The female gonopod of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. muchmorei
</tp:taxon-name>
resembles that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. vulgaris
</tp:taxon-name>
, with a projection at the apex of the external fold covering the atrial opening, but the two species differ in the count of articles on tibia of leg I, 
21 in
<tp:taxon-name>
C. vulgaris
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
23 in
<tp:taxon-name>
C. muchmorei
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Patronym honoring Dr W.B. Muchmore (
Armas &amp; Teruel 1997
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Holotype
US VIRGIN ISLANDS
• 
1 ♂
; 
Cinnamon Bay N.T., St John
; [
18°21′10.11″ N
, 
64°45′22.89″ W
]; 

6 Jun. 1980

; 
W.B. Muchmore
leg.; 
base of kipok
; 
FSCA
WM 5958
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
Paratypes
US VIRGIN ISLANDS
• 
1 ♀
juv., 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
FSCA
WM 5958
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; same locality as for holotype; 

4–6 Jun. 1980

; 
W.B. Muchmore
leg.; 
litter at base of trees
; 
FSCA
WM 5930
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♀♀
; 
Cinnamon Bay-Centerline Trail
; 
FSCA
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 juv.
; 
Fredenkstal
(probably Frederiksted); 
FSCA
WM 6810
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
St John Island
; 
FSCA
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Lameshur Bay
; 
Gray
; 
18°19′17.69″ N
, 
64°43′33.12″ W
; 
FSCA
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♀
; 
Trunk Bay
; 
18°21′07.81″ N
, 
64°46′06.59″ W
; 
FSCA
WM 5934
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
; 
Coral Bay
; 
18°20′52.83″ N
, 
64°42′47.49″ W
; 
FSCA
WM 6165
[not examined]
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
1 ♂
, 
2 juv.
; 
Coral Bay
; 

10 Oct. 1979

; 
W.B. Muchmore
leg.; 
ground litter
; 
FSCA
WM 5821
</tp:material-citation>
• 
<tp:material-citation>
2 ♀♀
; 
Colabash Boom
; 
18°19′39.84″ N
, 
64°42′11.49″ W
; 

16 Oct. 1980

; 
W.B. Muchmore
leg.; 
under rocks
; 
FSCA
WM 5961
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Supplementary description
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Six anterior setae; frontal process triangular. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle absent; pair of setae in place of median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin.</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae; other sternal platelets narrow, concave, each segment divided (forming pairs) with seta anteriorly; pentasternum with two setae anteriorly and without seta near membranous region.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with long setae posteromedially and smaller setae near margin; posterior margin convex; gonopod cushion-like, unsclerotized basally; apex pointed and projected. Male gonopod markedly sclerotized at apex of fistula and base of lateral lobe.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small flat tooth on retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with two patches of setae, one small, basal, another small, medial; claw with six teeth; row of seven setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with three setae on anterior margin and without seta encircled by round carina. Femur with three dorsal spines and four ventral spines; two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; setiferous tubercle between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines in primary series; prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin, one fifth length of spine I; two ventral spines; prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and seta between spine I and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 27 or 28 setae in ventral row of setae.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 22 or 23 articles, tarsus I with 37–39 articles; length of first tarsal article equal to sum of lengths of subsequent three or four articles. Leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles, without sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
bf
than to 
sbf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 1
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from St John, 
US Virgin Islands
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Found under rocks, in ground litter, and at base of trees.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
