<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus pecki Weygoldt 2006</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536871</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FF3DFF75A54BF945FE19DDBE</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae
            Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Charinus pecki Weygoldt, 2006 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Fig. 94 ; Table 7 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Charinus pecki Weygoldt, 2006b: 22–24 </tp:taxon-name> , figs 7–8, 11, 16,
         27–32. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p> This species may be separated from other species of <tp:taxon-name> Charinus
         </tp:taxon-name> in Oceania by means of the following characters: carapace with black
         markings radiating from fovea, cheliceral claw with five teeth, patella with three ventral
         spines, median and lateral eyes well developed. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> Patronym honoring Stewart B. Peck ( Weygoldt 2006 ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Type material </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Holotype NEW CALEDONIA • ♂ ; Hienghène , Taphozous Grotte ; 3 Aug.
            1978 ; 3 m a.s.l. ; S. and J. Peck leg.; MHNG . </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Paratypes NEW CALEDONIA • 4 ♀♀ , 2 juv. ; same collection data as
            for holotype; MHNG </tp:material-citation> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Supplementary description </p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median
         eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed; pair of setae on median ocular tubercle;
         lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad
         well separated from margin of carapace.</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation; other sternal platelets
         wide, with seta on each lateral border and some smaller setae posteriorly and in between;
         pentasternum with two setae anteriorly and one seta in membranous region.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Posterior margin of female genital operculum slightly convex; gonopod
         cushion-like, unsclerotized basally. Male gonopod with border of fistula and lateral lobes
         sclerotized; lateral lobe 2 fimbriate.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth on retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid
         tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae basally to medially; claw with 5
         teeth; two rows of around eight setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth
         on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p> PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with four setae encircled by round carina and four setae on
         margin. Femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines; spine between ventral spine
         1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines; prominent setiferous tubercle
         distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; three ventral spines ( holotype with two
         spines on dextral pedipalp); several setiferous tubercles between spine I and distal
         margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally, six long setae between spine and distal margin,
         and several setae throughout prolateral part of segment. Tarsus with two dorsal spines (
         holotype with three spines on dextral pedipalp), distal spine short, proximal spine
         one-third length of distal spine; several long, narrow setae ventral to distal spine;
         cleaning organ with 28–34 setae in ventral row. </p>
      <p> LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article
         similar in length to sum of subsequent 2–4 articles. Leg IV basitibia with four
         pseudo-articles, trichobothrium bt situated medially on pseudo-article; distitibia
         trichobothrium bc situated slightly closer to sbf than to bf , sc and sf series each with
         five trichobothria. </p>
      <p> Measurements </p>
      <p> See Table 7 . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Known only from the type locality. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p> Natural history </p>
      <p>Known only from caves.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
