<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus perquerens
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3ED8B7F8-C8A9-400C-B62C-793ACDD69184
</p>
      <p>
Figs 27
, 
32
; 
Table 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus perquerens
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in Amazonia and northern South America by means of the following combination of characters: relatively large size; female gonopod cushion-like; pedipalp femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines (
Fig. 32E–F
).
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus perquerens
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
can be differentiated from 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. magalhaesi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, the closest species geographically, by the greater number of pedipalp spines, including four dorsal spines and four ventral spines on the femur.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition taken from the noun ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
perquerens
</tp:taxon-name>
’, meaning ‘researcher’, honoring scientists of the National Institute for Amazonian Research (INPA), Manaus, 
Brazil
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Amazonas
, 
Manaus
, 
Campus INPA
; 
03°05′41.67″ S
, 
59°59′22.41″ W
; 

17–19 Mar. 2015

, 
A.P.L. Giupponi
and 
G.S. Miranda
leg.; 
INPA
ex 
MNRJ 9283
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
7 juv.
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9283

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 32A
); frontal process triangular (
Fig. 32C
). Small granules, densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle absent (
Fig. 32C
); lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin (
Fig. 32A
).
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 32B
); other sternal platelets narrow and concave, with pair of setae anteriorly; pentasternum with four setae anteriorly and without seta near membranous region.
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth on retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; seta absent on retrolateral surface of cheliceral claw; cheliceral claw with five teeth; three or four rows of 20 setae on prolateral surface of cheliceral basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin; gonopod cushion-like markedly sclerotized from base to apex. Male unknown.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with one to three prominent setae encircled by round carina and two or three setae at margin. Femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines (
Fig. 32E–F
); three prominent setiferous tubercles between first dorsal spine and proximal margin; one setiferous tubercle between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 32E
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one fifth length of spine I; two ventral spines; prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine (
Fig. 32D
); cleaning organ with 28 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 21 articles; tarsus I with 35–37 articles; first tarsal article shorter than subsequent articles. Leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles, without sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 2
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Found under tree trunks and stones in area of secondary tropical forest.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
