<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus miskito
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
574FE779-371C-4518-9EE5-55C4DD67AA7F
</p>
      <p>
Figs 5E–F
, 
10C–D
, 
12
, 
24–26
; 
Table 1
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other Caribbean and Central American 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
by means of the following combination of characters: median eyes and median ocular tubercle present, but reduced (
Fig. 24A, C
); retrolateral surface of cheliceral claw without row of setae; first (dorsal) tooth bifid, dorsal cusp smaller than ventral cusp (
Fig. 10C–D
); claw with four denticles (
Fig. 10C–D
); tibia of leg I with 21 articles, tarsus I with 39 articles; leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles; trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
bf
than to 
sbf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with 5 trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus miskito
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. bruneti
</tp:taxon-name>
, as both possess median eyes, tibia of leg I consists of 21 or 22 articles, and tarsus I consists of 39 articles. However, the median eyes are reduced in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. miskito
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and well developed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. bruneti
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>A noun in apposition referring to the Miskito, a Native American tribe in Central America.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
COLOMBIA
• 
♀
; 
Providencia Island
; [
13°20′50.72″ N
, 
81°22′28.3″ W
]; 
among stones
; 

31 Sep. 1969

; 
SMNS
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
COLOMBIA
• 
2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype [chelicerae and gonopod dissected in one paratype]; 
SMNS

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE.Anterior margin rounded, with six anterior setae (
Fig. 24A
). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and ocular tubercle present, but reduced (
Fig. 24A, C
); lateral eyes well developed, pale; small seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly into large blunt tubercle, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae, with typical setation (
Fig. 24B
); medial platelet (tetrasternum) and third platelet (pentasternum) formed by two convex platelets, each with large setae anteriorly, and several smaller setae posteriorly (
Fig. 24B
); pentasternum smaller than medial platelet, each platelet with seta anteriorly and some setae posteriorly (
Fig. 24B
); pentasternum without anterior setae in membranous region and with four setae posteriorly.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with posterior margin slightly convex, several setae along margin and surface (
Fig. 5E–F
); gonopods cushion-like with small rounded projection and sclerotized region on projection (
Fig. 5E–F
); small sclerotized region at base of gonopods (sclerotizations connected to each other) (
Fig. 5E–F
). Male gonopod with sclerotization at margin of fistula and lateral lobe 1; lateral lobe 2 fimbriate and short (
Fig. 25A–B, D
); lateral lobe 1 with acute apex (
Fig. 25F
); processus internus short and with median projection (
Fig. 25E
); dorsal lobe covered with denticulate projections (
Fig. 25C, F
).
</p>
      <p>
CHELICERAE. Chelicera with small, flat tooth in retrolateral row of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth (
Fig. 10D
); bifid tooth with dorsal cusp smaller than ventral cusp; prolateral surface of cheliceral basal segment with transverse row of around ten small setae, ventrally to dorsally; retrolateral surface of claw without row of setae; claw with four teeth (
Fig. 10C–D
).
</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with two or three setae on anterior border and without seta encircled by round carina. Femur with two distinct setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 1 (
Fig. 24E
); primary series with three dorsal spines and three ventral spines; femur with one setiferous turbercle between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines and one long setiferous tubercle, about one-third length of spine I, between spine I and distal margin of segment (
Fig. 24E
); several long setae between ventral spines. Tibia with ventral spine in distal half of article and prominent setiferous tubercle close to base (
Fig. 24F
); long seta between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, distal spine two thirds length of article and proximal spine one-third length of distal spine (
Fig. 24D
). Ventral row of cleaning organ with 28–32 setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 21 articles; tarsus I with 39 articles; tarsal organ situated near claw (
Fig. 26A, C–D
); rod sensilla with four setae in shallow groove (
Fig. 26B, E
). Leg IV basitibia with three pseudoarticles, without sclerotized, denticulate projection at distal apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third; leg IV distitibia with trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
bf
than to 
sbf
; 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 1
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality. Providencia is a volcanic island, part of the territory of 
Colombia
, but biogeographically part of the Caribbean and Central America, its fauna more closely related to Central America and the Lesser Antilles than to the Greater Antilles (
Morrone 2006
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Epigean, found under stones.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
