<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus magalhaesi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
748735F1-D676-4C38-AC45-4F6E99F51B6C
</p>
      <p>
Figs 27
, 
30
; 
Table 2
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in Amazonia and northern South America by means of the following combination of characters: tegument covered with clavate setae; median eyes and median ocular tubercle absent (
Fig. 30C
); female gonopods cushion-like; leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles; cheliceral claw with four or five teeth.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus magalhaesi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. vulgaris
</tp:taxon-name>
, but the setae on the carapace and pedipalp patella are clavate, as in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. carvalhoi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. longitarsus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. montanus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. quinteroi
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus magalhaesi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
may be distinguished from these species by the combination of cushion-like gonopods, the absence of median eyes and median ocular tubercle, and the length of the first tarsal article of leg I which is equal to the sum of the subsequent two articles.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Patronym honoring Dr Celio Magalhaes, for his contribution to the study of freshwater crustaceans and his efforts towards conservation of the Amazon.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Amazonas
, 
Manaus
, 
Reserva Florestal Adolpho Ducke
; 
02°58′31.59″ S
, 
59°58′42.33″ W
; 

18 Mar. 2015

; 
A.P.L.Giupponi
and 
G.S. Miranda
leg.; 
under wooden house
; 
INPA
ex 
MNRJ 9285
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
3 juv. ♀♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
INPA
ex 
MNRJ 9285

• 

1 juv.
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9279

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9282
, 
AMCC
[
LP 13406
]

• 

1 ♀
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9278
, 
AMCC
[
LP 13393
]

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 30A
); clavate setae scattered across carapace; frontal process triangular (
Fig. 30C
). Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle absent (
Fig. 30C
); lateral eyes well developed (
Fig. 30A
), seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin (
Fig. 30A
).
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 30B
); other sternal platelets small and flat, each with pair of setae; pentasternum with two setae near membranous region and two setae anteriorly (
Fig. 30B
).
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin; gonopod cushion-like, with base unsclerotized. Male unknown.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small, flat tooth on retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with continous row of setae, basally to medially; claw with four teeth; row of five setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with three prominent setae encircled by round carina and three setae on margin. Femur with three dorsal and three ventral spines (
Fig. 30E
); two prominent setiferous tubercles between first dorsal spine and proximal margin; setiferous tubercle between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines in primary series; prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one fifth length of spine I (
Fig. 30E
); two ventral spines (
Fig. 30F
); prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and seta between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines (
Fig. 30D
), proximal spine one-third length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 30–39 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 21 articles, tarsus I with 36–38 articles; length of first tarsal article equal to sum of lengths of two subsequent articles. Leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles, without sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 2
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Found under house on sandy soil at the Reserva Florestal Adolpho Ducke; not found in the forest.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
