<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus australianus
(L. 
Koch, 1867
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 94
; 
Table 7
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynus australianus
L. 
Koch, 1867: 231–232
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Phrynus australianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Butler 1873: 119

. — 

Moritz &amp; Fischer 1980: 138

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charon australianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– L. 

Koch &amp; Keyserling 1885: 40–41

, pl. 4 fig. 1a–b. — 

Simon 1892: 48

. — 

Hansen 1893: 159

. — 

Kraepelin 1895: 46–47

, figs 33, 38, 41; 1899: 249, fig. 93; 1901: 264. — 

Börner 1904: 5

. — 

Mello-Leitão 1931: 54

. — 

Werner 1935: 471

, fig. 176b. — 

Fage &amp; Simon 1936: 300

. — 

Weidner 1959: 142

. — 

Weygoldt 1972b: 123

, fig. 22f; 2006a: 244, figs 3–4, 8–9; 2006b: 10–13. — 

Strinati &amp; Aellen 1983: 21

. — 

Delle Cave 1986: 154–155

, fig. II. — 

Quintero 1986: 207

, figs 4, 7, 9. — 

Harvey 2003: 4

. — 

Jocqué &amp; Giupponi 2012: 59

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charon australiensis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 
Kästner 1932
: fig. 82. — 
Werner 1935
: figs 142–143.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus australianus australianus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Weygoldt 2006b: 13–16

, figs 17–21.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in Oceania by means of the following combination of characters: prolateral surface of cheliceral basal segment with more than 20 setae in two or three parallel rows, ventrally to subdorsally; cheliceral claw with four teeth, and setae present only at base; pedipalp coxa with distinct setiferous tubercle and small spine on its side; pedipalp femur with four dorsal spines, distal spine tiny, similar in length to setiferous tubercle, but with setae inserted laterally, not apically, two setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 1 of primary series, and three ventral spines; pedipalp patella with four dorsal spines and small setiferous tubercle similar in length to other setiferous tubercles, distal to proximal spine; pedipalp tibia with three ventral spines; pedipalp tarsus with two spines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Although unspecified, the species name is evidently an adjective referring to the Australasian region inhabited by this species.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
SAMOA
• 
Upolu Island
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phrynus australianus
L. Koch
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
ZMH 2281
.

</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
FIJI
• 
2 ♀♀
, 
1 juv.
; 
Viti Levu
, 
Wailotua Cave
; 

26 Aug. 1978

; 
S. Peck
leg.; 
MHNG
GSM 3

.
</p>
      <p>
SOLOMON ISLANDS
• 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus australianus
(L. 
Koch, 1867
)
</tp:taxon-name>
[labeled as holotype, but not part of original type series; see 
Weygoldt (2006)
]; 
ZMB 2505

• 

1 ♀
; 
Guadalcanal
, 
Kukum
; [
09°25′49.24″ S
, 
160°01′29.50″ E
]; 

10 May 1963

; 
P. Grenslade
leg.; 
BMNH 5158
[new record]

• 

1 ♂
; 
Wainoni Bay
, 
San Cristobal
; [
10°32′35.89″ S
, 
161°48′31.47″ E
]; 
J.F.P.
leg.; 
BMNH
P3

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Supplementary description
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes and median ocular tubercle well developed, with pair of setae; lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin.</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation; other sternal platelets wide, separated into pairs, with seta on each lateral margin and some smaller setae in between; pentasternum with two setae anteriorly and without seta in membranous region.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sac and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Posterior margin of female genital operculum slightly convex; gonopod cushion-like and markedly sclerotized basally.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with row of setae basally to medially; claw with six teeth; two or three parallel rows of more than 20 setae, ventrally to subdorsally, on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with four setae on anterior border and without seta encircled by round carina. Femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines; four or five prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; prominent spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines and two prominent setiferous tubercles proximal to spine 3; prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; two ventral spines; two or three setiferous tubercles between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with one ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two dorsal spines, distal spine one-third length of tarsus, and proximal spine one-third length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 33 setae in ventral row.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article twice length of subsequent articles. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles; denticulate sclerotized region distally on articles, but not projected; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in distal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
equidistant between 
sbf
and 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 7
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known from 
Fiji
, 
Samoa
(Upolu Island), and the 
Solomon Islands
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
