<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus sillami Reveillion &amp; Maquart
            2015</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5570704</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/8F431375FFDDFF96A519FD0BFE11DAE6</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae
            Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Charinus sillami Réveillion &amp; Maquart, 2015 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Figs 27 , 33 ; Table 2 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Charinus sillami Réveillion &amp; Maquart, 2015: 192–194 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Charinus sillami</tp:taxon-name> – Armas et al. 2016: 48 . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Charinus sillami </tp:taxon-name> is the only <tp:taxon-name> Charinus
         </tp:taxon-name> in Amazonia and northern South America with the following combination of
         characters: median eyes present ( Fig. 33A, C ); tibia of leg I and tarsus I with 23 and 37
         articles, respectively; leg IV basitibia with three pseudo-articles. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p> Etymology </p>
      <p> Patronym honoring David Sillam-Dussès ( Réveillion &amp; Maquart 2015 ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Type material </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Holotype FRENCH GUIANA • ♀ ; Commune de Sinnamary , Barrage de Petit
            Saut ; 05°03′46.67″ N , 53°02′51.26″W ; Mar. 2013 ; D. Sillam-Dussès leg.; in nest of
            termite, <tp:taxon-name> Neocapritermes taracua Krishna and Araujo, 1968
            </tp:taxon-name> ; BMNH [not examined]. </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Paratypes FRENCH GUIANA • 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for
            holotype; AMCC [ LP 13448 ] </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same
            collection data as for holotype; BMNH [not examined] </tp:material-citation> •
            <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for holotype; found in
               <tp:taxon-name> Spinitermes sp. </tp:taxon-name> nests ; CPOM [not examined]
         </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♀ , 1 ♂ ; Barrage de Petit Saut ; Mar.
            2014 ; CFR [not examined] </tp:material-citation> . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> CARAPACE. Six anterior setae ( Fig. 33A ); carapace extended anteriorly; frontal process
         triangular ( Fig. 33C ). Small granules, densely scattered between ocular triads and among
         sulci. Median eyes present ( Fig. 33A, C ); median ocular tubercle shallow; lateral eyes
         well developed, seta posterior to each lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well
         separated from carapace margin. </p>
      <p> STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of
         pedipalp coxae ( Fig. 33B ); other sternal platelets narrow and concave, with pair of setae
         anteriorly; pentasternum with two setae anteriorly and without seta near membranous region. </p>
      <p>OPSTHOSOMA: Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller
         setae near margin; pair of deep transverse sulci lateromedially; gonopod cushion-like,
         flat, unsclerotized basally. Male gonopod with apex of fistula and base of lateral lobe
         sclerotized.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to
         bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with medial row of setae; claw with five teeth;
         row of four setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with
         dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p> PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with prominent seta encircled by round carina and two setae
         at margin. Femur with three dorsal spines and three ventral spines ( Fig. 33E–F ); two
         prominent setiferous tubercles between first dorsal spine and proximal margin; spine
         between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin. Patella with three dorsal spines in primary
         series ( Fig. 33E ); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of
         spine I; two ventral spines ( Fig. 33F ); prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and
         distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and seta between spine and distal margin.
         Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine ( Fig. 33D
         ); cleaning organ with 30 setae in ventral row. </p>
      <p> LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 37 articles; first tarsal article
         approximately same length as subsequent articles. Leg IV basitibia with three
         pseudo-articles, without sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles;
         trichobothrium bt situated medially on pseudo-article; distitibia with trichobothrium bc
         situated slightly closer to sbf than to bf , and sc and sf each with five trichobothria. </p>
      <p> Measurements </p>
      <p> See Table 2 . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Known only from the type locality. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Natural history </p>
      <p>Found in termite nests.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Charinus sillami </tp:taxon-name> possesses a proximal spine on the
         pedipalp femur ventrally, that is not part of the primary series (additional spines are
         present dorsally), not described by Réveillion &amp; Maquart (2015) . This character may be
         important to distinguish this species from other species of <tp:taxon-name> Charinus
         </tp:taxon-name> occurring in the vicinity. The distal spine on the pedipalp tarsus points
         forward, whereas the proximal spine is directed dorsally ( Fig. 33D ). Réveillion &amp;
         Maquart (2015) mentioned that the anterior border of the carapace is dentate but, on
         examination, it was found to be smooth with some small tubercles, as in other species of
            <tp:taxon-name> Charinus </tp:taxon-name> . Additionally, the female gonopod is
         cushion-like and not sucker-like as stated in the original description. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
