<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus carioca Miranda &amp; Giupponi &amp; Prendini &amp; Scharff 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536774</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C5810A4DF7157C7AF05B95CAF007A81F</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus carioca
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
81F5FF9E-DACF-4B61-9893-94369C73B8F8
</p>
      <p>
Figs 6E–F
, 
43
, 
52–53
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: large size; short sucker-like female gonopod (
Fig. 6E–F
); cheliceral claw with nine teeth; pedipalp femur with five dorsal spines and five ventral spines (
Fig. 52E–F
); pedipalp patella with four dorsal spines and five ventral spines (
Fig. 52E–F
); marked secondary sexual dimorphism (
Fig. 53A–B
); leg IV distitibia 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus carioca
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
resembles 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. taboa
</tp:taxon-name>
in the shape of the frontal process of the carapace, but is easily distinguished from the latter by the higher number of trichobothria in the 
sc
and 
sf
series of the leg IV distitibia, six in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. carioca
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
compared with five in 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. taboa
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition taken from to the word ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
carioca
</tp:taxon-name>
’, referring to those born in 
Rio de Janeiro
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♀
; 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
Camorim
, 
Pedra Branca
; 
22°56′01.19″ S
, 
43°26′07.18″ W
; 

7 Sep. 2004

; 
Giupponi
and 
Pedroso
leg.; 
MNRJ 9201
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
2 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
MNRJ 9201

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae; frontal process triangular, with small apical projection (
Fig. 52C
). Small granules densely scattered between lateral eyes and among sulci. Median eyes well developed (
Fig. 52A, C
); median ocular tubercle weakly developed; pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad; lateral ocular triad well separated from carapace margin.
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly with typical setation, long, surpassing base of pedipalp coxae (
Fig. 52B
); other sternal platelets narrow and concave, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with fourteen setae anteriorly and four setae near membranous region.
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin (
Fig. 6E–F
); gonopod sucker-like and slightly sclerotized basally (
Fig. 6E–F
); tubular projection without constriction (
Fig. 6E–F
).
</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small flat tooth on retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of cheliceral claw with continous row of setae, basally to medially; claw with nine teeth; row of eleven setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with two setae encircled by round carina and four setae on margin. Femur with five dorsal spines and five ventral spines (
Fig. 52E–F
); spine between dorsal spine 2 and 3 and spine 3 and 4; three prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin; spine between ventral spines 1 and 2, 2 or 3 and 3 and 4. Patella with four dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 52E–F
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; patella with five ventral spines; spine between spines 2 or 3 and 3 and 4; prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and two setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with three dorsal spines, distal spine subequal to proximal spine (
Fig. 52D
); third spine situated proximally, near base of proximal spine; cleaning organ with 27–28 setae in ventral row.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles, tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article shorter than second article. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin projecting from apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated near midline of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Specimens were found in the photic zone of a gneiss cave, near a small river. Specimens were only observed at night, on the roof and in crevices in the roof, of the cave.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
