<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus jibaossu
Vasconcelos, Giupponi &amp; Ferreira, 2014
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 43
; 
Table 4
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus jibaossu

Vasconcelos 
et al.
, 2014: 156–161

</tp:taxon-name>

, figs 1–20.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus jibaossu
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Vasconcelos &amp; Ferreira 2016: 185

. — 

Miranda
et al.
2016c: 19


, 29.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in eastern South America by means of the following combination of characters: female gonopod sucker-like; cheliceral claw with 10–12 teeth; pedipalp femur with five or six dorsal spines in primary series and up to three spines in secondary series; pedipalp femur with five or six ventral spines in primary series and up to six reduced spines in secondary series; pedipalp patella with six or seven dorsal spines and three ventral spines; pedipalp tarsus with two or three dorsal spines.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Noun in apposition taken from the Tupi-Guarani word ‘ 
jibaoçu
’, which means ‘those with long arms’ (

Vasconcelos 
et al.
2014

).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
BRAZIL
• 
♂
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
, 
Gruta da Cazanga
; 
20°17′06.58″ S
, 
45°35′47.45″ W
; 

11 Jun. 2011

; 
R.L. Ferreira
leg.; 
MNRJ 9257
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
BRAZIL
• 
1 ♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
ISLA 3835
[not examined]

• 

1 ♂
; same locality as for holotype; 

31 Jan. 2009

; 
R.A. Zampaulo
leg.; 
MNRJ 9258

• 

1 ♂
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
, 
Gruta Branca
; 
20°17′06.67″ S
, 
45°35′47.39″ W
; 

31 Jan. 2009

, 
R.A. Zampaulo
leg.; 
ISLA 483
[not examined]

• 

1 ♂
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
; 

10 Aug. 2008

; 
I.G.S. Soares
leg.; 
MNRJ 9205

• 

2 ♀♀
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
; 

16 Mar. 2012

; 
I.G.S. Soares
leg.; 
MNRJ 9206

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
, 
Abismo Satélite cave
; 
20°36′31.51″ S
, 
45°56′55.57″ W
; 
R.L. Ferreira
leg.; 
CAVAISC

• 

2 ♂♂
, 
1 juv.
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
; 

10 Oct. 2011

; 
F. Bondezan
leg.; 
MNRJ 9187

• 

2 ♀♀
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
, 
Abrigo Caneleira I and II
; 
20°18′48.49″ S
, 
45°35′43.80″ W
; 
R.L. Ferreira
leg.; 
MNRJ 9095

• 

1 ♀
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
, 
Gruta do Índio
; 
20°19′07.33″ S
, 
45°36′07.95″ W
; 
R.L. Ferreira
leg.; 
MNRJ 9096

• 

3 ♀♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
, 
Meandro de Posse Grande cave
; 
20°19′56.31″ S
, 
45°35′53.96″ W
; 

11 Feb. 2006

; 
R.L. Ferreira
leg.; 
MNRJ 9097

• 

1 ♂
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Arcos
, 
Mineração Belocal
, 

25 Feb. 2012

; 
MZSP 46336
[not examined]

• 

1 ♂
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Pains
, 
Gruta da Mineração
; 
20°19′56.60″ S
, 
45°36′45.29″ W
; 

25 Jan. 2009

; 
R.A. Zampaulo
leg.; 
ISLA 480
[not examined]

• 

3 ♀♀
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Pains
, 
Gruta da Vila Corumbá
; 
20°19′55.8″ S
, 
45°36′43.23″ W
; 

25 Jan. 2009

; 
R.A. Zampaulo
leg.; 
ISLA 482
same collection data as for preceding; 
ISLA 3830
[not examined]; 
MNRJ 9217

• 

1 ♂
; 
Minas Gerais
, 
Pains
, 
Gruta da Mineiração
; 
MNRJ 9277

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Supplementary description
</p>
      <p>CARAPACE. Six anterior setae; frontal process triangular, not visible in dorsal view. Small granules densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci. Median eyes present, well developed, and median ocular tubercle shallow, with pair of setae; lateral eyes well developed, pale, seta posterior to lateral ocular triad.</p>
      <p>STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly, with typical setation; other sternal platelets narrow and concave, with pair of setae anteriorly on plaque and some smaller setae posteriorly; pentasternum with eight setae anteriorly and two setae on membranous region.</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae in the ventral-posterior region and some smaller setae near margin; genital operculum with pair of sulci near posterior margin; gonopod suckerlike, tubular; gonopods unsclerotized basally. Male gonopod with base of fistula and lateral lobe unsclerotized; lateral lobe 2 fimbriate.</p>
      <p>CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth; retrolateral surface of claw with two patches of setae, basally and medially; claw with eleven teeth; transverse row of around nine setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp.</p>
      <p>PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with seta encircled by round carina and three setae on margin. Femur with five or six dorsal spines and five ventral spines; two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin, and small spine between spines 1 and 2, 2 and 3, and 3 and 4. Patella with five dorsal spines in primary series; prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; four ventral spines in primary series; prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with prominent setiferous tubercle proximally and ventral spine distally; three setae between spine and distal margin. Tarsus with two or three dorsal spines, proximal spine half length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 29 setae in ventral row.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles; tarsus I with 41 articles; first tarsal article similar in length to second article. Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with six trichobothria.
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 4
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Known only from the 
type
localities.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus jibaossu
</tp:taxon-name>
exhibits marked secondary sexual dimorphism in the length of the pedipalps. The caves where this species was collected are rather dry, unlike the humid caves inhabited by most other Brazilian species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
. Most specimens were found on cave walls. Potential prey includes crickets (
<tp:taxon-name>
Eidmanacris
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Endecous
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
), moths, and cockroaches. The species is considered endangered due to mining activity in the area (

Vasconcelos 
et al
. 2014

).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
