<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Charinus insularis Banks 1902</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5567227</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/24C9170EAE34D94BD6CDEDDC57F6AD45</uri>
         <article-title>Systematic revision of the pantropical whip spider family Charinidae Quintero, 1986 (Arachnida, Amblypygi)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.772.1505</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus insularis
Banks, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1–2
, 
34
, 
36–41
; 
Table 3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus insularis
Banks, 1902: 67
</tp:taxon-name>

, 68, pl. 2 fig. 8.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Charinus insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Snodgrass 1902: 79–80

. — 

Mello-Leitão 1931: 54

. — 

Werner 1935: 471

. — 

Dunn 1949: 7

. — 

Roth &amp; Craig 1970: 119

. — 

Weygoldt 1972b: 123

. — 

Stockton 1976: 57–61

, figs 1–4. — 

Delle Cave 1986: 156

, fig. II. — 

Peck &amp; Kukalova-Peck 1986: 165

. — 

Peck &amp; Peck 1986: 44–46

. — 


Hernández Pacheco 
et al.
1992: 89


, 125, 133, 135, 141, 146, 149–150, 154, 158, 167. — 


Baert 
et al.
1996: 13–16


, fig. 7, map 4. — 

Harvey 2003: 5–6

. — 

Miranda
&amp; Giupponi 2011: 62


, 67, fig. 13. — 

Jocqué &amp; Giupponi 2012: 55

. — 


Vasconcelos 
et al.
2013: 497


. — 

Baert &amp; Mahnert 2015: 2–3

, 8–13, 70–71, 73–74, fig. 3. — 

Miranda
et al.
2016c: 19


, 31.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This species may be separated from other 
<tp:taxon-name>
Charinus
</tp:taxon-name>
in western South America by means of the following combination of characters: well-developed median eyes and median ocular tubercle (
Fig. 36A
); female gonopods cushion-like with small acute projection at apex of dorsal flap (
Fig. 37E–F
); male gonopod with thin, fimbriate lateral lobe 2 (
Fig. 38A–B, D
); dorsal lobe with acute spiky projections (
Fig. 38A– D, F
); cheliceral claw with seven teeth and short row of setae on retrolateral view (
Fig. 39D
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Although unspecified in the original description, the species name evidently refers to the provenance of this species on an island, in this case the 
Galapagos Islands
, to which it appears to be endemic.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Syntypes
ECUADOR
• 
Galapagos Islands
: 
Albemarle Island
(as Isla Isabela); [repository unknown]

• 

Narboro Island
; [repository unknown]

• 

Chatham Island
; [repository unknown]

• 

Hood Island
; [repository unknown] [not examined].

</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
ECUADOR
• 
1 protonymph
; 
Galapagos Islands
; 
RBINS 26445/23.2.6

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 exuvium
; 
Galapagos Islands
; 

17 Feb. 1986

; 
RBINS 27047

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 subad. ♂
; 
Galapagos Islands
, 
Turtle Bay
, 
Isla de Santa Cruz
; 

14 Jan. 1965

; 
J. and N. Leleup
leg.

• 

1 ♀
[most legs and one pedipalp detached]; 
in crevice at foot of ravine
, 

1200 m

from beach; 
RBINS

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 ♂
; 
Isla de Santa Cruz
; 

17 Feb. 1965

; 
J. and N. Leleup
leg.; 
entrance of cave, under stone on clay
[label indicates 2 ♀♀ and 1 juv., but vial contains only two specimens, one juvenile and another slightly larger, both with opisthosoma detached, hence impossible to determine sex of specimens]; 
RBINS

• 

1 ♀
, 
2 juv. ♂♂
; 
Española crest
; 

26 Apr. 1992

; 

25 m
a.s.l.

; 
S. Peck
and 
J. Cook
leg.; 

under 
<tp:taxon-name>
Opuntia
Miller, 1754
</tp:taxon-name>
bark and rocks

; 
RBINS 92-143

• 

1 ♀
, 
2 juv.♀♀
, 
2 juv. ♂♂
; 1988; 
L. Baert
, 
K. Desender
and 
J.P. Maelfait
leg.; 
RBINS 27318

• 

1 ♀
, 
1 juv. ♂
; 
RBINS 26445/23.2.1

• 

2 juv. ♀♀
, 
2 juv. ♂♂
; 
Isla de Santa Cruz
, 

800 m
from pier of St Darwin

; 

Dec. 1964

; 
J. and N. Leleup
leg.; 
at bottom of deep crevice
(

10 m

); 
under rubble stone with soil and wet sand
; 
RBINS

• 

1 ♀
, 
6 juv.
; 
Isla de Santa Cruz
; 

17 Nov. 1964

; 
J. and N. Leleup
leg.; 
volcanic cave
, 

3.5 km
N of Puerto Ayora village

; 
RBINS

• 

1 ♀
, 
2 juv. ♂♂
, 
1 protonymph
; 
Cueva Bellavista
, 
Isla de Santa Cruz
; 

160 m
a.s.l.

; 

22 Jan. 1989

; 

S. Peck 
et al
.

leg.; 
RBINS

• 

1 juv.
; 
Santa Fé
; 

Oct. 1964

; 
J. and N. Leleup
leg.; 
RBINS

• 

1 ♀
; 
Bellavista
, 
Isla de Santa Cruz
; 

150 m
a.s.l.

; 
S. Peck
leg.; 
bottle traps
in caves
; 
RBINS 96–97

• 

1 ♀
; 
Puerto Ayora
, 
Isla de Santa Cruz
; 

28 Dec. 1991

; 
S. Abedrabbo
leg.; 
RBINS

• 

2 ♀♀
; 
Hornemeu Farm
, 
Isla de Santa Cruz
; 

250 m
a.s.l.

; 

Nov. 1964

; 
J. and N. Leleup
leg.; 
RBINS

• 

4 juv. ♀♀
; 
RBINS 768

• 

1 ♀
juv.; 
Pampa
, 

36 km
from coast

, 
Isla de Isabela
; 

600–1000 m
a.s.l.

; 

Nov. 1964

; 
J. and N Leleup
; 
RBINS

• 

Isla de Santa Cruz
; 

1 km
from coast

; 

20 m
a.s.l.

; 

Feb. 1965

; 
J. and N. Leleup
leg.; 
inside cave
; 
RBINS

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Supplementary description
</p>
      <p>
CARAPACE. Six anterior setae (
Fig. 36A
); frontal process triangular (
Fig. 37D
), not visible in dorsal view. Small granules, densely scattered between ocular triads and among sulci (
Figs 36A
, 
37A–D
). Median eyes present; median tubercle shallow (
Fig. 37D
); one pair of setae on median ocular tubercle; lateral eyes well developed, with seta posterior to lateral ocular triad (
Fig. 37B
)
</p>
      <p>
STERNUM. Tritosternum projected anteriorly, with typical setation (
Fig. 36B
); other sternal platelets divided, concave, with one seta on each side of platelets and smaller setae posteriorly (
Fig. 37B
); pentasternum with four setae anteriorly and seta on membranous region (
Fig. 37B
).
</p>
      <p>OPISTHOSOMA. Ventral sacs and ventral sac cover absent.</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Female genital operculum with prominent setae posteromedially and some smaller setae near margin (
Fig. 37E
); gonopod cushion-like, flat, with projection on apex of retrolateral side of fold (
Fig. 37E–F
); base of gonopods sclerotized. Male gonopod markedly sclerotized at base of fistula and lateral lobe; lateral lobe 2 not fimbriate.
</p>
      <p>
CHELICERAE. Small tooth projecting from retrolateral surface of basal segment, opposite to bifid tooth (
Fig. 39A–G
); retrolateral surface of claw with small patches of setae basally and medially (
Fig. 39D– E
); claw with seven teeth; transverse row of around eight setae on prolateral surface of basal segment; bifid tooth on basal segment with dorsal cusp larger than ventral cusp; setae on basal segment with acute apex and serrate margin (
Fig. 39F
), setae on claw with mop-like apex (
Fig. 39G
); hinge between basal segment and cheliceral claw with multiple slit sensilla (
Fig. 39C
).
</p>
      <p>
PEDIPALPS. Coxal dorsal carina with three setae encircled by round carina and four setae on margin. Femur with four dorsal spines and four ventral spines (
Figs 2
, 
36C–D
, 
40A–D
); two prominent setiferous tubercles between dorsal spine 1 and proximal margin; spine between ventral spine 1 and proximal margin (
Fig. 2
). Patella with four dorsal spines in primary series (
Fig. 36C–D
); prominent setiferous tubercle distal to spine I, one-third length of spine I; two ventral spines in primary series (
Fig. 2
); prominent setiferous tubercle between spine I and distal margin. Tibia with ventral spine distally and two or three setae between spine and distal margin (
Figs 2
, 
36D
). Tarsus with two dorsal spines, proximal spine one-third length of distal spine; cleaning organ with 27–30 setae in ventral row. Spines with gland openings (
Fig. 40D
).
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia of leg I with 23 articles (up to 
29 in
regenerated legs); tarsus I with 43 articles (up to 
53 in
regenerated legs); first tarsal article similar in length to subsequent articles; slit sensilla present on tarsal article 21. Leg IV patella with pair of trichobotria dorsally; surface surrounding trichobothrial insertions filled with erect scales (
Fig. 41A
). Leg IV basitibia with four pseudo-articles, with sclerotized, denticulate margin at apex of articles; trichobothrium 
bt
situated in proximal third of pseudo-article; distitibia trichobothrium 
bc
situated slightly closer to 
sbf
than to 
bf
, 
sc
and 
sf
series each with five trichobothria. Leg IV tarsus with projection between claws similar in length to last tarsal article; arolium microstructures with linear pattern at lip (
Fig. 41C–D
), randomly scattered at truncus (
Fig. 41C, E
).
</p>
      <p>
Measurements
</p>
      <p>
See 
Table 3
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
This comparatively large species is endemic to the 
Galapagos
archipelago, and has been recorded on several islands (
Baert &amp; Mahnert 2015
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Natural history
</p>
      <p>Found inside and outside caves in cave entrances, ravines, under stones and rubble.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The type material was collected during the Hopkins Stanford 
Galapagos
Expedition, but the original description does not specify where the material is deposited. According to 
Dunn (1949)
, the 
type
specimens may be in the collection of the Stanford University, 
California
, but cannot be located.
</p>
      <p>
The opisthosoma of the subadult male (the only male examined) is wrinkled and the genitalia distorted, hence impossible to describe. The large female specimen from Española (RBINS 92-143) appears to be adult, but has duplicate trichobotria (2 
sbf
, 2 
bc
and 2 
bt
), a character thus far known to occur only in juveniles (
Weygoldt 2000a
).
</p>
      <p>
Miranda
&amp; Giupponi (2011)

misinterpreted the female gonopod of 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. insularis
</tp:taxon-name>
, stating it is sucker-like. However, the species has a cushion-like gonopod with an acute apical projection (
Fig. 37E–F
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
