<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
      <tp:treatment-meta>
            <mixed-citation>
                  <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Arhaconotus papuanus Belokobylskij
                        2000</named-content>
                  <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4649691</uri>
                  <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
                        >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD765F00FDA4E3313B833F8E</uri>
                  <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
                        Braconidae)</article-title>
                  <uri content-type="publication-doi"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
            </mixed-citation>
      </tp:treatment-meta>
      <tp:nomenclature>
            <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus papuanus Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name>
      </tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Figs 3–4 </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus papuanus Belokobylskij, 2000: 346 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus papuanus </tp:taxon-name> – Belokobylskij 2001: 162. —
                  Yu et al. 2016 . — Jasso-Martínez et al. 2019: 167 . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
            <p> Material examined </p>
            <p> Holotype </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> PAPUA NEW GUINEA • ♀ ; “Papua New Guinea, Milne Bay Prov. ,
                        Cape Vogel, Menapi, Oct. 24–29, 1989 , R. Wharton ”; TAMU .
                  </tp:material-citation>
            </p>
            <p> Paratypes </p>
            <p>
                  <tp:material-citation> PAPUA NEW GUINEA • 1 ♀ ; same collection data as for
                        holotype; TAMU </tp:material-citation> • <tp:material-citation> 1 ♂ ; same
                        collection data as for holotype; ZISP </tp:material-citation> . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
            <p> Description </p>
            <p> Female </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 3.7–4.3 mm ; fore wing length 2.7–3.1 mm . </p>
            <p>HEAD. Head width about 1.5 times its median length, 1.35 times width of mesoscutum.
                  Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex in anterior half, strongly and almost
                  linearly narrowed in posterior half. Transverse diameter of eye 2.0–2.4 times as
                  long as temple. Ocelli medium-sized, arranged almost in equilateral triangle; POL
                  almost equal to OD, 0.4–0.5 times OOL. Eye distinctly emarginated opposite
                  antennal sockets, 1.2–1.3 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.3 times height of
                  eye, 0.6–0.7 times basal width of mandible. Face width 0.8–0.9 times eye height
                  and 1.2 times height of face and clypeus combined. Upper margin of clypeus
                  situated distinctly higher than lower level of eyes. Width of hypoclypeal
                  depression 0.8–1.0 times distance from depression to eye, 0.4–0.5 times width of
                  face. Vertex convex. Head below eyes (front view) distinctly and almost linearly
                  or weakly roundly narrowed. Antennae filiform, more then 24-segmented (apical
                  segments missing). Scapus 1.5–1.6 times as long as its maximum width, 2.0 times
                  length of pedicel. First flagellar segment 4.5–5.0 times as long as its apical
                  width, 1.1 times as long as second segment.</p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. Length about 2.0 times its height. Pronotal carina distinct, situated
                  submedially. Mesoscutum (dorsal view) about as long as wide. Notauli deep in
                  anterior half and shallower in posterior half, rather wide, sparsely and finely
                  crenulate. Median lobe of mesoscutum distinctly convex anteriorly. Prescutellar
                  depression with high median and two lateral carinae, almost smooth on rest part,
                  distinctly curved along posterior margin, 0.3 times as long as scutellum.
                  Scutellum length almost equal to its maximum width. Subalar depression coarsely
                  crenulate. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) entirely smooth. Prepectal carina with low
                  lobes opposite fore coxae. Metanotum dorso-medially with two high and curved
                  carinae. Propodeum weakly arcuately sloping backward (lateral view). Metapleural
                  flange posteriorly with dense pubescence.</p>
            <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 3.4–3.7 times its maximum width. Pterostigma 4.0–4.5 times
                  as long as wide. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.1–1.2 times as long as pterostigma. Radial
                  (marginal) cell 3.3 times as long as wide. Radial vein (r) arising from middle of
                  pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming very obtuse corner with second
                  abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 3.8 times as long as first abscissa
                  (r), 0.75–0.80 times as long as the straight third abscissa (SR1), 1.6–1.8 times
                  as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell
                  long, not widened distally, 3.2–3.5 times as long as wide, about 1.7 times as long
                  as the narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) very
                  weakly sinuate. Second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M) short or very short.
                  Recurrent vein (m-cu) 0.8 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR).
                  Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) weakly curved in apical half. Distance from nervulus
                  (cu-a) to basal vein (1-M) 0.5–0.7 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Brachial
                  (subdiscal) cell closed distinctly before recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla
                  present but short; posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein
                  (CU1b)) present. Hind wing 6.0 times as long as wide. Recurrent vein (m-cu)
                  straight, strongly oblique towards base of wing.</p>
            <p> Fig. 3. <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus papuanus Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  ♀, holotype, TAMU. A . Habitus, lateral view. B . Head, front view. C . Head,
                  dorsal view. D . Basal segments of antenna. E . Head, lateral view. F . Fore leg.
                  G . Mesosoma, dorsal view. H . Mesosoma, lateral view. I . Hind coxa. J . First to
                  third metasomal tergites, dorsal view. K . First to third metasomal tergites,
                  lateral view. </p>
            <p> Fig. 4. <tp:taxon-name> Arhaconotus papuanus Belokobylskij, 2000 </tp:taxon-name> ,
                  ♀, holotype, TAMU. A . Wings. B . Metasoma, dorsal view. C . Metasoma, lateral
                  view. </p>
            <p>LEGS. Hind coxa almost 2.0 times as long as wide (with tooth). Hind femur 3.2 times
                  as long as wide. Hind tarsus 1.0–1.1 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus
                  with lower keel and with very dense pale setosity. Second segment of hind tarsus
                  0.3 times as long as basitarsus, 1.1–1.2 times as long as fifth segment (without
                  pretarsus).</p>
            <p>MESOSOMA. Metasoma 1.4 times as long as head and mesosoma combined, with sixth
                  visible tergites, remaining segments weakly protruding behind sixth tergite. First
                  tergite distinctly, almost linearly and evenly widened from base to apex. Maximum
                  width of tergite almost 2.0 times its minimum basal width; length 0.9–1.0 times
                  its apical width, 0.8 times length of propodeum. Apical area of second tergite
                  0.75 times as long as remaining of tergite. Median length of second tergite (with
                  areas) 1.0–1.2 times its basal width, almost 2.0 times median length of third
                  tergite. Sixth tergite weakly enlarged, almost straight on posterior margin,
                  without median emargination and postero-ventral lobes. Sixth tergite almost as
                  long as fifth and about 1.1 times as long as fourth tergites. Ovipositor sheath
                  about 1.1 times as long as metasoma, about 2.0 times as long as mesosoma, 0.9
                  times as long as fore wing.</p>
            <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Head smooth, face rugulose-striate in rather narrow
                  vertical stripes near smooth median and lateral areas. Mesonotum and mesopleuron
                  smooth. Metapleuron smooth and with fine reticulation or granulation in anterior
                  half, rugulose in posterior half. Propodeum with large, mainly coriaceous, with
                  fine rugosity along carinae and almost smooth basally basolateral areas; areola
                  rather small, rugulose, 1.5 times as long as maximum width; median carina 2.0–2.5
                  times as long as anterior fork of areola; propodeum in posterior third rugulose.
                  Hind legs smooth. First and second tergites entirely (but second in apical area
                  finely), third tergite in basal 0.2 medially and 0.8–0.9 laterally, fourth and
                  fifth tergites in basal furrow only medially and in basal 0.8 laterally distinctly
                  striate. Remaining parts of tergites and sixth tergite almost entirely smooth.
                  Second–sixth tergites laterally coarsely and densely striate but smooth apically.
                  Vertex glabrous medially, with sparse long and semi-erect setae posteriorly and
                  laterally. Mesonotum with dense semi-erect and rather short setae arranged wide
                  area along notauli and marginally. Mesopleuron mostly glabrous. Hind tibia
                  dorsally with dense numerous short setae and long sparse semi-erect setae, long
                  setae 0.6–0.8 times as long as maximum width of tibia. Laterotergites shortly and
                  rather sparsely setose.</p>
            <p>COLOUR. Body black, head below and third–sixth tergites in apical halves reddish.
                  Antenna reddish brown basally, darkened toward apex. Palps pale yellow. Legs
                  brownish yellow, middle coxae basally, hind coxae entirely and base of hind tibia
                  reddish brown, sometimes darker, rarely middle coxa light reddish brown; hind
                  femur in basal half brownish. Ovipositor sheath medially light reddish brown or
                  reddish brown, dark in basal third and apically. Fore wing distinctly and evenly
                  infuscate. Pterostigma brown, yellow in basal basally and in apical ¼ or ⅓.</p>
            <p> Male </p>
            <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 2.9 mm , fore wing length 2.1 mm . Malar space 0.25 times
                  height of eye and 0.55 times basal width of mandible. </p>
            <p>WINGS. Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 5.3 times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.9
                  times as long as third abscissa. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell 4.0 times
                  as long as wide, 2 times as long as brachial (subdiscal) cell.</p>
            <p>LEGS. Hind femur 2.7 times as long as width. Second tarsal segment of hind leg 0.25
                  times as long as basitarsus, 0.9 times as long as fifth segment (without
                  pretarsus).</p>
            <p>METASOMA. Narrow. Length of first tergite 1.35 times its apical width. Apical area of
                  second tergite 0.6 times as long as remaining part of tergite. Length of second
                  tergite 1.6 times its basal width, 1.8 times length of third tergite. Basal and
                  apical areas of second tergite almost entirely smooth. Third and fourth tergites
                  coarse striate in basal 0.6–0.7; fifth and sixth tergites reticulate-coriaceous in
                  basal 0.7–0.8. Apical tergites not concealed by sixth tergite.</p>
            <p>COLOUR. Body dark reddish brown. Hind femur almost entirely brownish. Otherwise
                  similar to female.</p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
      <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
            <p> Distribution </p>
            <p> Papua New Guinea . </p>
      </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
