<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ipodoryctes anticestriatus</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651656</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD555F3CFDABE0093B753AAC</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes anticestriatus
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 14–15
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes anticestriatus
Granger, 1949: 112
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes anticestriatus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1314

. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

. — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 167


.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MADAGASCAR
• 
♀
; “Madagascar, Bekily, reg sud de l’ile”, “Museum Paris, 

I – 37

, 
A. Seyrig
”, “Type”, “♀ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes anticestriatus
Granger, C. van Achterberg, 1983
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Holotype
”; 
MNHN
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
5.4 mm
, fore wing length 
3.8 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD.Width1.45 times its median length, 1.15times width of mesoscutum.Head behind eyes(dorsal view) distinctly roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye (dorsal view) about 2.0 times as long as temple. Ocelli rather small, arranged in triangle with base 1.1times its sides,situated near median line of eyes. POL almost equal to OD, 0.6 times OOL. Eye with distinct emargination opposite antennal sockets, 1.25 times as high as broad.Malar space 0.3 times height of eye and 0.8 times basal width of mandible.Face width0.75 times height of eye and 1.15 times height of face and clypeus combined. Clypeus convex. Hypoclypeal depression oval, its width 0.9 times distance from edge of depression to eye and 0.45 times width of face. Hypostomal flange narrow. Palps long, length of maxillary palps 1.1 times head height (without mandible). Antennae slender, weakly setiform, more than 34-segmented. Scapus 1.5 times as long as its maximum width. First flagellar segment 4.3 times as long as its apical width, 1.25 times as long as second segment. Subapical segments about 3.5 times as long as width.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.0 times its height. Median lobe of mesoscutum convex, distinctly protruding forward and rounded. Mesoscutum as long as maximum width. Notauli deep anteriorly and shallow posteriorly, wide and coarsely rugose-crenulate. Prescutellar depression with median and four lateral carinae, finely rugulose-reticulate, 0.4 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum weakly convex, as long as its maximum anterior width. Subalar depression striate, with additional rugulosity and granulation. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) shallow, running along anterior 0.6 of lower part of mesopleuron, finely reticulate. Metapleural lobe without dense pubescence.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing 3.3 times as long as its maximum width. Pterostigma 4.0 times as long as wide. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.2 times as long as pterostigma. First (r) and second (3-SR) radial abscissae forming obtuse angle. Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 3.8 times as long as first abscissa (r), about 0.9 times as long as third abscissa (SR1), 1.8 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell long, 3.4 times as long as its maximum width, 1.4 times as long as the rather wide brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) distinctly sinuate. Distance from nervulus (cu- a) to basal (1-M) vein 0.7 times as long as nervulus (cu-a) length. Hind wing 4.8 times as long as wide. First mediocubital abscissa (M+CU) 0.75 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) long, weakly curved, antefurcal, mostly sclerotised.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 14.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes anticestriatus
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, MNHN. 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head, front view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Head, lateral view. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
G
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
H
. Hind leg. 
I
. apical segments of metasoma, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 15.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes anticestriatus
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, MNHN. 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
C
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa 1.3 times as long as wide, 0.75 times as long as propodeum. Hind femur 3.0 times as long as wide. Hind tarsus almost as long as hind tibia. Basitarsus of hind tibia 0.5 times as long as second–fifth segments combined. Second tarsal segment 0.65 times as long as basitarsus, 1.6 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma 1.2 times as long as head and mesosoma combined. First tergite rather weakly and curvedly widened from base to subapex, then weakly narrowed towards apex. Maximum width of first tergite 1.75 times its minimum width; length about 1.5 times its apical width. Median length of second tergite (with both areas) 0.8 times its basal width, 1.8 times as long as third tergite. Basal area of second tergite 0.4 times as long as rest part of tergite; posterior (apical) area 0.3 times as long as rest part of tergite. Six tergite 0.9 times as long as fifth segment (measured from fine transverse basal furrow) and equal to fourth segment, its posterior margin very weakly incurved medially. Ovipositor sheath long, 0.8 times as long as body, 2.2 times as long as mesosoma, 1.5 times as long as metasoma, 1.1 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex very finally and densely coriaceous, partly posteriorly almost smooth; frons densely and finely granulate, almost smooth narrowly medially. Face densely granulate, with additional sparse punctation and laterally with fine rugulosity, almost smooth narrow medially. Temple very finely coriaceous, smooth below. Mesoscutum densely granulate, coarsely rugose on wide area in its medioposterior half. Scutellum densely and finely granulate. Mesopleuron densely and rather finely areolate-coriaceous, striate-granulate in upper 0.25–0.30. Propodeum with large and densely granulate basolateral areas and short rugae along carinae; areola coarsely rugose, wide and short, almost as long as its maximum width; basal carina1.6 times as long as side of anterior fork of areola. Hind coxae almost entirely and densely granulate, without dorsal striation. First tergite rugose-striate, with dense granulation in mediobasal third. Second tergite distinctly striate and with dense reticulation between striae, its basal and apical areas densely and finely granulate-coriaceous. Third and fourth tergites densely granulate-reticulate, smooth apically. Fifth tergite finely and densely reticulate-coriaceous, smooth apically. Sixth tergite finely reticulate basally, partly interruptedly transverse striate in apical half. Vertex with sparse, short and semi-erect white setae. Mesoscutum entirely with very dense, short and almost erect white setae. Hind tibia dorsally with rather short, sparse and semi-erect pale setae.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head dark reddish brown, face reddish brown, clypeus and mandible yellowish brown. Mesosoma light reddish brown. Metasoma reddish brown, darker basally and apically. Antenna dark brown to black, two basal segments reddish brown, subapical segments black. Palps entirely yellow. Legs yellow, tibiae and tarsi brownish yellow, hind coxa light reddish brown, hind tibia pale basally. Ovipositor sheath entirely black. Fore wing very faintly infuscate. Pterostigma entirely brown.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Madagascar
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
