<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ipodoryctes Granger 1949</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651654</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/9ED51788BA60A26CE74747DCB5F87948</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
Granger, 1949: 106
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1267

. — 

Belokobylskij 1994b: 129

; 2001: 135; 2019: 36.— 

Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto 2009: 284

. — 


Tang 
et al.
2011: 1


. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

. — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 167


. — 


Belokobylskij 
et al.
2019: 266


.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes anticestriatus
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
, by original designation.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(
Figs 14–21
)
</p>
      <p>Head. Head more or less transverse (dorsal view). Ocelli small or medium-sized, arranged in more or less obtuse triangle. Frons weakly convex or almost flat. Eyes glabrous. Occipital carina distinct, complete dorsally, obliterated below on distinct distance. Malar suture indistinct. Clypeal suture complete, but upper shallow. Hypoclypeal depression medium size, suboval or round. Face with two fine submedian elongate-oval depressions above clypeal suture. Postgenal bridge present, but narrow. Palps rather long; maxillary palps 6-segmented, its sixth (apical) segment about as long as fifth segment; labial palps 4-segmented, its third segment not shortened. Scapus of antenna wide and rather long, without apical lobe and basal constriction, its ventral margin (lateral view) shorter than dorsal margin. First flagellar segment not thickened, subcylindrical, longer than second segment.</p>
      <p>Mesosoma. Mesosoma not depressed, rather long. Neck of prothorax short. Pronotum weakly convex dorsally (lateral view), pronotal carina rather fine, situated submedially on pronotum; pronope absent. Propleural dorsoposterior flange distinct and rather narrow. Mesonotum high and roundly elevated above pronotum. Median lobe of mesonotum weakly protruding forward, without anterolateral corners, often with distinct, usually incomplete median furrow. Notauli complete, rather wide, deep in anterior half and rather shallow in posterior half. Prescutellar depression usually shallow, with distinct median and often several lateral carinae, weakly curved on posterior margin. Lateral longitudinal wing-like flanges on level of prescutellar depression very low. Scuto-scutellar suture distinct and complete. Scutellum convex, often with fine lateral carinae. Mesopleural pit distinct, narrow, rather long, connected with mesopleural furrow by distinct furrow. Sternaulus (precoxal sulcus) rather shallow, narrow, long, curved. Prepectal carina distinct and complete. Prepectus usually with two strong longitudinal lateral carinae. Postpectal carina absent. Metanotum (lateral view) almost without median tooth. Metapleural flange rather short, wide, rounded apically. Propodeum often with rather distinct basolateral areas delineated by distinct carinae; lateral tubercles very weak; propodeal bridge absent. Propodeal spiracles small and round.</p>
      <p>Wings. Pterostigma of fore wing wide and long. Radial vein (r) arising from middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Both radiomedial veins (2-SR, r-m) present. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell long, rather wide, not widened towards apex. Recurrent vein (m-cu) more or less distinctly postfurcal. Discoidal (discal) cell petiolate anteriorly, petiole (1-SR) short. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) very weakly curved to anal vein (2-1A) in posterior half. Nervulus (cu-a) distinctly postfurcal. Parallel vein (CU1a) often arising from or behind (from anterior 0.3) middle of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell, but in several cases interstitial. Brachial (subdiscal) cell distally closed by more or less oblique brachial (CU1b) vein. Transverse anal veins (2A, a) absent. Hind wing with three hamuli. Radial vein (SR) arising from costal vein (2-SC+R) distant from basal vein (1r-m). Radial (marginal) cell almost parallel-sided, without additional transverse vein (r). Medial (basal) cell wide, distinctly widened towards apex, about 0.5 times as long as hind wing. Nervellus (cu-a) present. Submedial (subbasal) cell present and short. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) distinctly shorter than second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) long, sclerotised at least partly and pigmented, distinctly oblique toward base of wing.</p>
      <p>Legs. Fore and middle tibiae with rather sparse and thick spines arranged in almost single line. Middle tarsal segments long and weakly thickened. Hind coxa medium-sized, with distinct basoventral corner and usually with tubercle. All femora with low or very low and wide dorsal protuberances. Hind femur thickened, elongate-oval. Inner spurs of hind tibia rather short, straight, shortly setose, about 0.2 times as long as hind basitarsus. Hind basitarsus usually with narrow ventral carina, often about 0.7 times as long as second–fifth segments combined. Claws short, simple, robust, usually distinctly widened basally.</p>
      <p>
Metasoma. First tergite not petiolate, medium length and wide. Acrosternite of first segment short, about 0.2 times as long as first tergite, not reaching spiracular segments. Dorsope of first tergite rather deep and not large; spiracular tubercles indistinct or weak, spiracle situated in basal 0.3 of tergite; dorsal carinae present only basally or almost entirely, subbasally not united by additional transverse carina. Second tergite always with rather distinct semi-oval or subtransverse basal area delineated by rather distinct and usually curved furrow or only different 
type
of sculpture; with distinct, more or less wide and curved or rarely almost straight posterior furrow delineated wide or narrow sublenticular apical area. Second suture distinct, rather deep and wide, evenly curved, without lateral bends. Fourth and usually fifth tergites with basal shallow, crenulate and curved furrows. Second–sixth tergites with separate laterotergites. Sixth tergite enlarged or not enlarged, almost equal to fifth segment (till subbasal transverse furrow) or often shorter than it, coarsely sclerotised, usually almost entirely sculptured, but sometimes finely sculptured till partly or entirely smooth; its posterior margin weakly convex, usually without median excision. Ovipositor apically with two obtuse and distinct or very low dorsal nodes. Ovipositor sheath often long, longer than metasoma.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
is morphologically similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bathycentor
Saussure, 1892
</tp:taxon-name>
. The differences between these two genera are mentioned in the redescription of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bathycentor
</tp:taxon-name>
and in the above key.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Composition
</p>
      <p>
This genus currently consists of two subgenera, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Afroipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
subgen. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
s.str.
The following species are belonged to the nominative subgenus: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
(
Ipodoryctes
) 
albiflagellus
(Shi &amp; 
Chen, 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
alutaceus
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
annulicornis
Belokobylskij, 1994
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
anticestriatus
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
brachiceps
(
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2009
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
elongatus
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
formosanus
(Watanabe, 1934)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus carolinensis
Watanabe, 1945
</tp:taxon-name>
) (PA, OR, PC); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
forticarinatus
(
Chen &amp; Shi, 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
giganteus
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
interstitialis
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
longus
(Shi &amp; 
Chen, 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
maculistigma
(
Chen &amp; Shi, 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
niger
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
nitidus
Belokobylskij, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
pallidipes
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
pilosus
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(AF); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
puber
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
rufiventris
(
Chen &amp; Shi, 2004
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
rugosiscutum
Belokobylskij, 1994
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
ryukyuensis
Belokobylskij, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
signatus
(Belokobylskij, 2001)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR, PA); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
signipennis
(Walker, 1860)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus flavistigmus
Belokobylskij, 1983
</tp:taxon-name>
) (PA, OR, NA); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
sonaicus
(
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2009
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
tamdaoensis
Belokobylskij, 1994
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
temporalis
Belokobylskij, 2001
</tp:taxon-name>
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
vagrans
(Bridwell, 1920) (PA, OR, PC)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
watanabei
(
Belokobylskij &amp; Maeto, 2009
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR); 
<tp:taxon-name>
I.
(
I.
) 
roslinensis
(Lal, 1939)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
(OR).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Hosts
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Lepidoptera</tp:taxon-name>
: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phragmataecia
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. (
<tp:taxon-name>Cossidae</tp:taxon-name>
); 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bissetia steniella
(Hampson, 1899)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chilo kanra
(Fletcher, 1928)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ch. partellus
(Swinhoe, 1885)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ch. saccharifagus
(Bojer, 1856)
</tp:taxon-name>
; 
<tp:taxon-name>
Eoreuma loftini
(Dyar, 1917)
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Scirpophaga
</tp:taxon-name>
sp., 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. excerptalis
(Walker, 1863)
</tp:taxon-name>
(
<tp:taxon-name>Crambidae</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Afrotropical, 
Oriental
and Palaearctic regions.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
