<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
Belokobylskij, 2005: 206
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Yu 
et al.
2016

. — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 165


.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Aivalykus niger
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
, by original designation.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(
Figs 12–13
)
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head not depressed, rather high, weakly transverse. Ocelli arranged in distinctly obtuse triangle. Frons flat, without median keel or furrow. Eyes glabrous. Occipital carina dorsally complete, not joined ventrally with hypostomal carina at rather long distance. Malar suture absent. Clypeal suture present, complete, rather deep entirely. Clypeus with short ventral flange. Hypoclypeal depression medium size, oval. Palps medium length; maxillary palps 6-segmented, its sixth (apical) segment about as long as fifth segment; labial palps short. Scapus very wide and rather long, with short apical fringe, without basal constriction, its ventral margin (lateral view) not longer than dorsal margin. First flagellar segment subcylindrical, weakly curved, shorter than second segment. Apical segment weakly pointed apically and without spine.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma weakly depressed and long. Neck of prothorax long. Pronotum dorsally distinctly convex, with distinct, high and pointed apically, not fused medioposteriorly pronotal carina. Pronope absent. Propleural dorsoposterior lobe long and wide. Mesonotum entirely densely granulate-reticulate, not highly and gently-roundly elevated above pronotum. Median lobe of mesonotum without median longitudinal furrow, without anterolateral corners. Notauli distinct and complete. Tegula short, widened distally, weakly convex along its posterior margin. Prescutellar depression long, with distinct median carina. Lateral longitudinal wing-like flanges on the level of prescutellar depression short and rather low. Scuto-scutellar suture distinct and complete. Scutellum convex, without distinct lateral carinae. Mesopleural pit deep, wide, subround, connected directly with mesopleural suture. Metanotum with very short, wide and subpointed median tooth. Sternaulus (precoxal sulcus) rather deep, narrow, long, running along all length of lower part of mesopleuron, weakly curved. Prepectal carina distinct and complete, rather high below, laterally following to sternaulus. Postpectal carina absent. Metapleural flange rather short, wide, subrounded apically. Propodeum without delineated areas; lateral tubercles absent; propodeal bridge absent. Propodeal spiracles small and subround.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Pterostigma of fore wing narrow and long. Radial vein (r) arising from middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Second radiomedial vein (r-m) absent. Radial (marginal) cell long and narrow. Recurrent vein (m-cu) strongly postfurcal. Discoidal (discal) cell wide and short, petiolate anteriorly, petiole (1-SR) short. Nervulus (cu-a) distinctly postfurcal. Brachial (subdiscal) cell closed postero-apically distinctly before recurrent vein (m-cu), without antero-posterior corner. Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial. Transverse anal veins (2A, a) absent. Hind wing with three hamuli. First abscissa of costal vein (C+SC+R) 0.45 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). Radial vein (SR) strongly unclerotised, arising from costal vein (2-SC+R) and rather far separating from basal vein (1r-m). Radial (marginal) cell unclear delineated. Medial (basal) cell very weakly widened towards apex from base, long and narrow, about 19.0 times as long as width, 0.4 times as long as hind wing. Nervellus (cu-a) present. Submedial (subbasal) cell short. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.35 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) absent.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore and middle tibiae with a few short and thick spines arranged in one row. Fore tarsus 1.5 times as long as for tibia. Middle tarsal segments long. Hind coxa rather long and wide, with distinct basoventral corner and tubercle.All femora with more or less distinct, wide and low dorsal protuberances. Hind femur wide. Hind basitarsus about 0.5 times as long as second–fifth segments combined. Claws thick, short and simple.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Widened to base of fourth segment, then weakly narrowed. First tergite not petiolate, rather long and wide. Acrosternite of first tergite short, about 0.2 times as long as first tergite, its apical margin situated before level of spiracles. Dorsope of first tergite shallow and small; basolateral processes absent; spiracular tubercles very small, spiracles situated in basal 0.3 of tergite; dorsal carinae indistinct. First and second tergite not fused immovably. Second tergite without basal area. Second suture absent; third tergites with wide, semicircular and coarsely crenulate concave furrow. Similar distinctly concave, widely situated, crenulate furrow developed on fourth and fifth tergites. Present six visible dorsally tergites with separated laterotergites (epipleura); other segments weakly protruding behind sixth one. Six tergites rather coarsely sclerotised, not enlarged, about as long as fifth tergite, with straight posterior margin, mainly smooth. Ovipositor sheath shorter longer than metasoma.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This genus differs from the remaining 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhaconotini</tp:taxon-name>
genera by the following combination of characters: 1) scapus of antenna is with distinct apical fringe; 2) first flagellar segment of antenna shorter than second one; 3) second radiomedial vein (r-m) and second radiomedial (submarginal) cell of fore wing absent; 4) second metasomal suture absent; 5) third–fifth metasomal tergites with distinct, strongly concave and crenulate furrows.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Composition
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes niger
(
Granger, 1949
)
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Hosts
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>Afrotropical region.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
