<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
) 
haeselbarthi

Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 47–48
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
) 
haeselbarthi
Belokobylskij 2005: 208
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
) 
haeselbarthi
</tp:taxon-name>
– Yu 
at al.
2016.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
SOUTH AFRICA
• 
♀
; “Mariepskop, 
Pilgrim’s Rest dist.
, Tvl. [Transvaal], 

14.iv.1964

, 
E. Haeselbarth
”; 
SSMG
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
3.2 mm
; fore wing length 2.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 47.
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
) 
haeselbarthi
Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, SSMG. 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head, dorsal view. 
C
. Head, lateral view. 
D
. Head, front view. 
E
. Head, posterior view. 
F
. Apical segments of antenna. 
G
. Basal segments of antenna. 
H
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
I
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
J
. Mesoscutum. 
K
. Pro-and mesopleura, lateral view.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 48.
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
) 
haeselbarthi
Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, SSMG. 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Median part of fore wing. 
C
. Basal part of hind wing. 
D
. Metasoma, lateral view. 
E
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
F
. Propodeum and first to second metasomal tergites, dorsal view. 
G
. Apex of metasoma, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Width 1.5 times its median length, 1.3 times width of mesoscutum (dorsal view). Head behind eyes (dorsal view) distinctly and almost linearly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 2.4 times length of temple. Ocelli small, arranged in triangle with base 1.2 times its sides; POL 1.2 times OD, 0.5 times OOL. Eye very weakly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.3 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.65 times height of eye, 1.6 times basal width of mandible. Face width almost equal to height of eye and equal to height of face and clypeus combined. Upper margin of clypeus situated below line on lower level of eyes. Hypoclypeal depression width 0.6 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.35 times width of face. Vertex distinctly convex. Head below eyes (front view) distinctly and almost linearly narrowed. Antennae rather slender, filiform, 25-segmented, 0.9 times as long as body. Scapus 1.7 times as long as its maximum width. First flagellar segment 3.3 times as long as its apical width, 1.1 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 2.4 times as long as its width, 0.6 times as long as first segment, 0.85 times as long as apical segment.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 1.9 times its height. Pronotal carina distinct, medial distances from carina to both sides of pronotum subequal. Mesoscutum 0.9 times as long as maximum width. Notauli entirely deep, rather wide, coarsely crenulate. Prescutellar depression deep, rather long, distinctly and linearly curved postero-laterally, distinctly rugulose, 0.3 times as long as the weakly convex scutellum. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) rather deep, wide, weakly curved, distinctly and densely crenulate. Prepectal carina without widened lobes opposite fore coxae. Subalar depression rather shallow, more or less narrow, distinctly crenulate and almost smooth between crenulae. Metapleural lobe long, rather narrow, rounded apically, with dense pubescence posteriorly. Mesopleural suture entirely and coarsely crenulate.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing 3.8 times its maximum width. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.2 times as long as pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming very obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 3.3 times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.4 times as long as straight third abscissa (SR1), 1.15 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell not widened distally, 2.6 times as long as wide, 1.6 times as long as brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) weakly sinuate. Discoidal (discal) cell 2.3 times as long as its maximum width. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) almost straight. Distance between nervulus (cu-a) and basal (1-M) vein almost equal to nervulus (cu-a) length. Brachial (subdiscal) cell narrow, almost perpendicularly closed distinctly before level of recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla present; posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) indistinct. Hind wing 5.4 times as long as wide. First costal abscissa (C+SC+R) 0.8 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.7 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) fine, unsclerotised, curved, weakly antefurcal.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa 1.5 times as long as wide (with tubercle). Hind femur with fine dorsal protuberance, length of femur 3.8 times maximum width. Hind tarsus 0.9 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.8 times combined length of second–fifth segments. Second tarsal segment 0.4 times as long as basitarsus, 2.0 times as long as fourth segment, 1.3 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length 1.1 times as long as head and mesosoma combined. First tergite with distinct but short subbasal lateral processes. Maximum width of first tergite 3.3 times its basal width; its length almost equal to apical width, 1.4 times length of propodeum. Second tergite with shallow and weakly curved subposterior transverse furrow indistinctly separated narrow apical area; median length of apical area about 0.4 times length of remaining part of tergite. Median length of second tergite 0.55 times its basal width, 1.35 times length of third tergite. Second suture rather wide, almost straight. Fifth tergite weakly convex in posterior margin, without median emargination and postero-ventral lobes. Fifth tergite 1.4 times as long as fourth tergite, 1.7 times as long as third tergite. Ovipositor sheath 0.55 times as long as metasoma, 0.8 times as long as mesosoma, 0.45 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex entirely densely granulate, without striae or rugae; frons coarsely and irregularly densely rugose, with granulation medio-posteriorly; face densely and rather distinctly granulate, finely granulate to almost smooth medially; temple densely granulate with rugose posteriorly, below finely coriaceous to smooth. Mesoscutum entirely densely and distinctly granulate, with distinct rugosity on median lobe and laterally, with long coarse striae in medio-posterior half of mesoscutum. Scutellum densely and distinctly granulate. Mesopleuron densely and coarsely granulate-rugose, finely and widely coriaceous medially, smooth below sternaulus. Metapleuron coarsely densely rugosereticulate. Propodeum with distinctly delineated and densely granulate-rugose basolateral areas, with three longitudinal median carinae in basal half, coarsely areolate in posterior half. Hind coxa rather densely and distinctly granulate in upper half, rugulose medially and smooth below. Hind femur obliquely striate in upper half and smooth in lower half. First tergite with distinct, complete and subparallel dorsal carinae, distinctly, sparsely and coarsely striate and with dense and fine rugulosity between striae. Second tergite entirely coarsely and linearly striate with very dense and fine rugulosity between striae. Third tergite in basal 0.8 and fourth tergite in basal 0.5 distinctly and rather densely linearly striate and with additional fine or very fine reticulation, smooth apically. Fifth tergite densely and finely areolatecoriaceous in basal half and smooth in apical half. Second–fourth tergites laterally entirely and rather densely striate with granulation. Vertex entirely with long, sparse and semi-erect pale setae. Mesoscutum with rather dense, long and semi-erect setae arranged on all median lobe, along notauli and in single row laterally. Mesopleuron medially widely glabrous. Hind tibia dorsally with long, dense and semi-erect pale setae; length of these setae 1.0–1.2 times maximum width of tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head reddish brown to dark reddish brown, black dorsally, with narrow reddish ring along eye. Mesosoma black, prothorax reddish brown to dark reddish brown. Metasoma reddish brown, almost black basally. Two basal segments of antenna yellow, flagellum mostly reddish brown to dark reddish brown, six apical segments brownish yellow. Palps yellow. Legs brownish yellow, tarsi faintly darker, hind tibia basally brown. Ovipositor sheath brownish yellow in basal 0.6 and brown in apical 0.4. Fore wing evenly faintly infuscate. Pterostigma yellowish brown, pale basally.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Republic of South Africa
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
