<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature/>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotini 
Fahringer, 1928: 8
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Leptorhaconotini</tp:taxon-name>
van Achterberg, 1984: 42
, 
syn. nov.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Leptorhaconotini</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Belokobylskij 1992: 920

— 

Quicke 1996: 115

— 

Yu 
et al.
2016

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Body medium sized to large, but rarely (
<tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
) small, with surface mostly granulate or granulate-reticulate, metasoma occasionally partly smooth, especially in posterior half. Hypoclypeal depression round or oval. Malar suture usually absent, and sometimes present but usually very shallow. Occipital carina upper usually distinct and complete, below often not reaching base of mandible and obliterated here. Scapus of antenna simple, without basal constriction and apical lobe.
</p>
      <p>Pronotal collar usually short, dorsally often convex and with distinct pronotal carina. Mesoscutum usually gently-roundly elevated above pronotum; mesoscutum with distinct and complete or rarely incomplete (present only anteriorly) notauli. Prepectal (epicnemial) carina complete, rather strong, sometimes ventrally coarse and wide. Propodeum without or with areas (at least basolateral ones) delineated by distinct carinae, areola present or absent.</p>
      <p>
Predominantly full-winged, but rarely (some 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
) present micropterous or apterous forms. Fore wing often hyaline, but sometimes maculated or infuscate. Pterostigma rather wide, only rarely (
<tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
) narrowed. Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell usually medium-sized. Second radiomedial (r-m) usually present, but rarely absent second (
<tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
) or first radiomedial (2RS) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Antespathius
</tp:taxon-name>
) veins. Recurrent (m-cu) vein often postfurcal (distal to first radiomedial vein (2RS)), more rarely interstitial or at least weakly antefurcal (
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
</tp:taxon-name>
, some species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Parallel vein (CU1a) often interstitial, rarely not interstitial (

<tp:taxon-name>Bathycentor</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Ipodoryctes</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Mimipodoryctes</tp:taxon-name>

, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
</tp:taxon-name>
) and arising before, from or behind middle of the vein (2CUa) closed brachial (subdiscal) cell posteriorly. Hind wing recurrent vein (m-cu) usually present, but often weakly sclerotised, sometimes absent. Submedial (subbasal) cell always closed distally by nervellus (cu-a), mostly short (except 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neorhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
), with first mediocubital abscissa (M+CU) distinctly shorter than second abscissa (1M).
</p>
      <p>Hind coxa mostly with basoventral corner and tubercle. Hind femur often with distinct basoventral knob.</p>
      <p>
Metasoma often with five (
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
) or six (

<tp:taxon-name>Arhaconotus</tp:taxon-name>
,

many 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mimipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
, many 

<tp:taxon-name>Rhaconotinus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Troporhaconotus</tp:taxon-name>

) dorsally visible, hardly sclerotised and widely sculptured tergites, accordingly fifth or sixth tergite in such case more or less enlarged and often longer than previous ones. In some cases (

<tp:taxon-name>Antespathius</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Grangerdoryctes</tp:taxon-name>

, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
</tp:taxon-name>
) apical tergites less strongly sclerotised, with more tergites visible behind fifth (seven or eight) and usually much less sculptured in distal half of metasoma. Laterotergites (epipleura) of second and following tergites usually distinctly separated and spiracle situated on lateral parts of tergites near folds. First metasomal tergite often medium length or weakly elongate, with short acrosternite (basal sternite); but sometimes (
<tp:taxon-name>
Antespathius
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
) this tergite long and distinctly narrowed with more or less strongly elongate acrosternite and this segment transformed in (sub)petiole. Second tergite without any furrows (

<tp:taxon-name>Antespathius</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Platyspathius</tp:taxon-name>

, some 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
</tp:taxon-name>
) or often with rather distinct curved or straight subbasal furrow (delineated anterior, basal area) (

<tp:taxon-name>Arhaconotus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Bathycentor</tp:taxon-name>

, 

<tp:taxon-name>Ipodoryctes</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Mimipodoryctes</tp:taxon-name>

) and subposterior furrow (delineated posterior apical area) (

<tp:taxon-name>Arhaconotus</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Bathycentor</tp:taxon-name>

, 

<tp:taxon-name>Ipodoryctes</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>Leptorhaconotus</tp:taxon-name>

, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mimipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotinus
</tp:taxon-name>
and some 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
). Third tergite usually without furrows, but strongly curved furrow known in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
. Subbasal (in many cases) or submedial (
<tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
) transverse furrow present on fourth and fifth or sixth tergites. Fifth (
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
) or sixth (
<tp:taxon-name>
Arhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
, many 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mimipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
, etc.) tergites more or less distinctly enlarged, often longer than previous ones; rarely these tergites in posterior margin with distinct submedian processes or median excision. Ovipositor (except 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leptorhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
) relatively long, dorsally with double small preapical notches and apico-ventrally serrate.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>

Key to the world genera of the tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhaconotini</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Metasomal tergites with large lateral part strongly bent downwards (
Fig. 23H
); ventral margins of sixth tergite below almost connected or closely situated (
Fig. 23F
); metasoma tube-shaped in dissection.Acrosternite of first metasomal segment elongated, about 0.35 times as long as first tergite (
Fig. 3H
), its apical margin situated behind level of spiracles. Ovipositor basally flat and wide, evenly narrowed toward apex, strong upcurved, without dorsoapical tubercles and ventroapical serration (
Figs 22K
, 
23C, E–G
). Ovipositor sheath-wide and flat, leaf-shaped (
Figs 22K
, 
23E, G
). (Subtribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Leptorhaconotina</tp:taxon-name>
) ............................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leptorhaconotus
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Metasomal tergites with short lateral part slightly bent downwards (
Figs 2D
, 
4C
, 
7D
); ventral margins of sixth tergite below widely separated from each other; metasoma dorso-ventrally flattened (
Figs 2D
, 
4C
, 
7D
). Acrosternite of first metasomal segment usually not elongated, 0.20–0.25 times as long as first tergite, its apical margin situated before level of spiracles (
Figs 3K
, 
7D
, 
9B
, 
13D
); occasionally acrosternite distinctly elongated (
<tp:taxon-name>
Antespathius
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
) (
Figs 1J
, 
28L
, 
30J
, 
32I
). Ovipositor round basally (in dissection), not narrowed toward apex and not upcurved, with dorsoapical tubercles and ventroapical serration (
Figs 1A
, 
3A
, 
6A
, 
17D
). Ovipositor sheath narrow and thick, stick-shaped (
Figs 1A
, 
3A
, 
6A
, 
17D
) (Subtribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Rhaconotina</tp:taxon-name>
) ........................................ 2

</p>
      <p>

2. Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing absent (
Figs 13A
, 
39A
) .............................................. 3

</p>
      <p>

– Second radiomedial vein (r-m) of fore wing present (
Figs 2A
, 
4A
, 
5H
, 
9A
) ................................... 4

</p>
      <p>

3. First flagellar segment of antenna shorter than second segment (
Fig. 12E
). Third–fifth metasomal tergites with deep, strongly curved and distinctly crenulate furrows (
Figs 13B–C
). Second suture absent (
Fig. 12I
). Brachial (subdiscal) cell closed apically distinctly before recurrent vein (m-cu) (
Fig. 13A
) .............................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Grangerdoryctes
Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– First flagellar segment of antenna longer than second segment (
Fig. 38E
). Third–fifth metasomal tergites without curved crenulate furrows (
Fig. 39B
). Second suture present and deep (
Fig. 39B
). Brachial (subdiscal) cell closed apically on the level of recurrent vein (m-cu) (
Fig. 39A
) ............................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus
van Achterberg &amp; Shaw, 2010
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

4. Metasoma dorsally with only five visible tergites (following tergites hidden under fifth one); fifth tergite usually longer than previous tergite (
Figs 9B
, 
11B
, 
45C
, 
46H
, 
48E
) .................................... 5

</p>
      <p>

– Metasoma dorsally with more than five (with sixth and seventh) visible tergites; sixth or seventh tergites longer or often not longer than previous tergite (
Figs 2C
, 
4B
, 
5G
, 
7C
, 
15B
) ...................... 8

</p>
      <p>

5. Submedial (subbasal) cell of hind wing long; first abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.8–1.0 times as long as second abscissa (1-M) (
Fig. 27B
). Propodeum with elongate areola distinctly delineated by carinae (
Fig. 26C
). Fourth–fifth metasomal tergites almost entirely smooth (
Figs 26C
, 
27C
) ................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Neorhaconotus
Belokobylskij, Iqbal &amp; Austin, 2004
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Submedial (subbasal) cell of hind wing short; first abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.3–0.5 (0.6) times as long as second abscissa (1-M) (
Figs 9A
, 
45B
, 
48A
). Propodeum usually without areola delineated by carinae (
Figs 8F
, 
44H
, 
46F
, 
47H
). Fourth–fifth metasomal tergites usually mainly sculptured (
Figs 9C
, 
45C
, 
46H
, 
48E
) ............................................................................................... 6

</p>
      <p>

6. Second metasomal tergite with basal area delineated posteriorly by distinct furrow (
Figs 9C
, 
10H
, 
11B
). Apical lenticular area of second tergite always present and sharply delineated anteriorly by deep and crenulate curved additional sulcus and posteriorly by deep second suture (
Figs 9C
, 
10H
, 
11B
) ................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus
Cameron, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Second metasomal tergite without basal area delineated posteriorly by furrow (
Figs 45C
, 
46H
, 
48E– F
). Apical lenticular area of second tergite present or absent (
Figs 45C
, 
46H
, 
48E–F
) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
Ruthe, 1854
</tp:taxon-name>
) ..................................................................................................................................... 7

</p>
      <p>

7. Recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing distinctly antefurcal (
Fig. 48A
). Propodeum with distinct lateral tubercles (
Fig. 47I
). Apical segments of antenna contrasting pale (
Fig. 47F
) .......................................................................Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pararhacon
Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing always postfurcal (
Fig. 45A
). Propodeum without distinct lateral tubercles (
Fig. 44I
). Apical segments of antenna same colour as previous segments (
Fig. 44G
) ..............................................................................................Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
s. str.
</p>
      <p>

8. First metasomal tergite narrow and long, weakly widened towards apex, petiolate or subpetiolate (
Figs 1I–J
, 
2C–D
, 
30J
, 
31C–D
, 
35B, D
, 
37C–D
); acrosternite of first segment more or less strongly or distinctly elongated (
Figs 1J
, 
2D
, 
30J
, 
31D
, 
35D
, 
37D
) .............................................................. 9

</p>
      <p>

– First metasomal tergite rather wide and usually short, distinctly widened towards apex (
Figs 4B–C
, 
5G
, 
7C–D
, 
15B–C
, 
17B, D
), never petiolate; acrosternite of first segment not elongated, short (
Figs 4C
, 
7D
, 
15C
, 
17D
) ...........................................................................................................................11

</p>
      <p>

9. Face with dense and fine transverse aciculation (
Fig.1C
). Nervulus (cu-a) of fore wing distinctly antefurcal. First radiomedial vein (2-SR) absent (
Figs 2A–B
). Acrosternite of first metasomal segment long, 0.6–0.7 times as long as tergite (
Figs 1J
, 
2D
). First tergite distinctly striate with reticulation (
Figs 1I
, 
2C
) .............................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Antespathius
Belokobylskij, 1995
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Face without dense transverse aciculation (
Figs 28C
, 
30C
, 
32B
, 
34C
, 
36B
). Nervulus (cu-a) of fore wing almost never antefurcal. First radiomedial vein (2-SR) always present (
Figs 29A
, 
31A
, 
33A
, 
35A
, 
37A
). Acrosternite of first metasomal segment rather short, 0.3–0.5 times as long as tergite (
Figs 28L
, 
29C
, 
30J
, 
31D
, 
32I
, 
33D
, 
35D
, 
37D
). First tergite usually densely and small areolate (
Figs 28I
, 
29B
, 
31C
, 
32H
, 
33C
, 
34F
, 
35B
, 
37C
). (
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
Viereck, 1911
</tp:taxon-name>
) ........................... 10

</p>
      <p>

10. Vertex entirely densely granulate or reticulate-coriaceous, without or with sparse and incomplete striation (
Figs 28D
, 
30D
, 
32C
, 
34D
). Median lobe of mesonotum not high and usually weakly evenly-curved (
Figs 28H
, 
30G
, 
32G
, 
34H
). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell of fore wing medium length, rather narrow, usually not widened apically (
Figs 29A
, 
31A
, 
33A
, 
35A
) .................................................................................................... Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Platyspathius
</tp:taxon-name>
s. str.
</p>
      <p>

– Vertex entirely densely and distinctly transverse striate (
Fig. 36C
). Median lobe of mesonotum highly hump-shaped (
Fig. 36H
). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell of fore wing very long, wide, distinctly widened towards apex (
Fig. 37A
) ............................................................................. ..................................................................................... Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lenticularia
van Achterberg, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

11. First and second metasomal tergites of female immovably fused (
Figs 3J, K
, 
4B–C
) ................... 12

</p>
      <p>

– First and second metasomal tergites of female movably connected (
Figs 5G
, 
7C–D
, 
15B, C
, 
17B, D
, 
41C–D
, 
43D–E
, 
50C, E
, 
59C–D
) ................................................................................................... 13

</p>
      <p>

12. Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing always interstitial (
Fig. 4A
). First and second tergites of male immovably fused. Vertex smooth or densely granulate, without striation (
Fig. 4C
) .......................... ....................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
Arhaconotus
Belokobylskij, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing usually not interstitial, arising from anterior third of distal margin of brachial (subdiscal) cell (
Fig. 25A
). First and second tergites of male movably connected. Vertex striate or rugose, sometimes with granulation between rugae, never smooth or only granulate (
Fig. 4C
) .................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mimipodoryctes
Belokobylskij, 2000
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

13. Second tergite with basal area delineated by furrow or different 
type
of sculpture ....................... 14

</p>
      <p>
– Second tergite without delineated basal area .................................................................................. 16
</p>
      <p>

14. Basal area of second tergite long and delineated posteriorly by deep furrow (
Figs 5G
, 
7C
). Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing arising from posterior third or occasionally from the middle of vein (3- CU1) closing distally brachial (subdiscal) cell (
Figs 5H
, 
7A
). Recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing antefurcal or interstitial (
Figs 5H
, 
7A
) .................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Bathycentor
Saussure, 1892
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Basal area of second tergite short and delineated posteriorly usually by only different 
type
of sculpture (
Figs 15B
, 
17B
, 
19B
, 
21B
). Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing arising behind middle of vein (3-CU1) closing distally brachial (subdiscal) cell (
Figs 15A
, 
17A
, 
19A
, 
21A
). Recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing postfurcal (
Figs 15A
, 
17A
, 
19A
, 
21A
(
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
)) ............ 15

</p>
      <p>

15. Hind coxa without or with very small basoventral tubercle (
Figs 16B
, 
18J
, 
20H
). Pro- and often mesothorax almost entirely smooth (
Figs 16C–D
, 
18H–I
, 
20F–G
). Notauli smooth or almost smooth (
Figs 16C
, 
18H
, 
20F
) ...........................................................Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Afroipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
subgen. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Hind coxa with distinct basoventral tubercle (
Fig. 14H
). Pro- and mesothorax at least partly granulate (
Fig. 14F–G
). Notauli crenulate or granulate (
Fig. 14F
) ....................... Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
</tp:taxon-name>
s. str.
</p>
      <p>

16. Recurrent vein (m-cu) antefurcal (
Figs 50A
, 
51I
, 
52K
, 
53A
, 
55A
, 
57A
). Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing not interstitial, arising behind middle of vein (3-CU1) closing distally brachial (subdiscal) cell (
Figs 50A
, 
51I
, 
52K
, 
53A
, 
55A
, 
57A
). First flagellar segment often not longer than second segment (
Figs 49D
, 
51E
, 
52E
, 
54D
, 
56D
). Metasoma behind third tergite smooth (
Figs 50C–D
, 
51H
, 
53B–C
, 
55B–C
, 
57B–C
) ............................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhacontsira
Belokobylskij, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Recurrent vein (m-cu) postfurcal (
Figs 41A
, 
43A
, 
59A
). Parallel vein (CU1a) of fore wing often interstitial (
Figs 41A
, 
43A
, 
59A
). First flagellar segment usually longer than second segment (
Figs 40D
, 
42E
, 
58E
). Metasoma behind third tergite sculpture at least in basal part of posterior tergites (
Figs 41C
, 
43D
, 
59C
) ......................................................................................................... 17

</p>
      <p>

17. First metasomal tergite very long, 2.0–2.7 times as long as its apical width (
Figs 58K
, 
59C–D
). Sixth metasomal tergite distinctly enlarged and covered following apical tergites (
Figs 59C–D
). Mesosoma long, 2.5–2.7 times as long as maximum width (
Figs 58I–J
) ........................................... ................................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Troporhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
      <p>
–
First metasomal tergite short, usually distinctly less than 2.0 times as long as its apical width (
Figs 40G
, 
41C
, 
43C, E
). Sixth metasomal tergite usually not enlarged and not covered following tergites (
Figs 41C–D
). Mesosoma short, 1.8–2.2 times as long as maximum width (
Figs 40F
, 
42H
) (
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotinus
Hedqvist, 1965
</tp:taxon-name>
) ...................................................................................................... 18

</p>
      <p>

18. Apical lenticular area of second metasomal tergite always present and sharply delineated anteriorly by deep and crenulate curved additional sulcus and posteriorly by deep second suture (
Figs 40G
, 
41C
) ................................................................................................... Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotinus
</tp:taxon-name>
s. str.
</p>
      <p>

– Apical area of second metasomal tergite always absent; anteriorly additional transverse sulcus absent or almost indistinct (
Fig. 43D
) ........................................Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Hexarhaconotinus
</tp:taxon-name>
subgen. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
