<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Leptorhaconotus brunneus Granger 1949</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651678</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BFE900560F05AAF9572EFD4982CD11F0</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Leptorhaconotus brunneus
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 22–23
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Leptorhaconotus brunneus
Granger, 1949: 138
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Leptorhaconotus brunneus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1316

. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

. — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 167


.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
MADAGASCAR
: • 
♀
; “Madagascar, Bekily, reg. sud de l’ile”, “Museum Paris, 

II. 37

, 
A. Seyrig
”, “42”, “Type”, “♀ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Leptorhaconotus brunneus
Granger, C. van Achterberg, 1980
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Holotype
”; 
MNHN
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 22.
<tp:taxon-name>
Leptorhaconotus brunneus
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, MNHN. 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B
. Head, front view. 
C
. Head, dorsal view. 
D
. Head, lateral view. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
G
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
H
. Propodeum, first metasomal tergite, hind coxa and femur, lateral view. 
I
. Hind coxae and first metasomal tergite, ventral view. 
J
. First to third metasomal tergites, dorsal view. 
K
. Ovipositor with sheaths, dorso-lateral view.
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 23.
<tp:taxon-name>
Leptorhaconotus brunneus
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, MNHN. 
A
. Fore wing. 
B
. Hind wing. 
C
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
D
. Second and third metasomal tergites, dorsal view. 
E
. Apex of metasoma and ovipositor with sheaths, lateral view. 
F
. Apex of metasoma and ovipositor with sheaths, ventral view. 
G
. Ovipositor with sheaths, dorsal view. 
H
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
7.3 mm
; fore wing length 
4.3 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD.Width 1.35 times its median length, 1.2 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) distinctly and almost linearly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye 2.6 times length of temple. Ocelli medium-sized, arranged in almost equilateral triangle; POL 0.8 times OD, 0.5 times OOL. Eye weakly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.1 times as high as broad. Malar space height 0.4 times height of eye, almost equal to basal width of mandible. Face width equal to height of eye and 1.25 times height of face and clypeus combined. Clypeus flat (lateral view). Upper margin of clypeus situated weakly upper lower level of eyes. Hypoclypeal depression round, its width 0.8 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.4 times width of face. Vertex almost flat. Head below eyes strongly and almost linearly narrowed Antennae slender, weakly setiform, more than 33-segmented (apical segments missing). Scapus 1.6 times as long as its maximum width. First flagellar segment 2.8 times as long as its apical width, as long as second segment. Subapical segments 2.2 times as long as their width.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 3.0 times its height. Mesoscutum (dorsal view) 1.1 times as long as maximum width. Notauli distinct, shallow (especially posteriorly), complete, rather narrow, densely rugose-crenulate. Median lobe of mesoscutum convex anteriorly. Prescutellar depression long, widened postero-laterally, with distinct median and several lateral carinae, distinctly rugose-reticulate between carinae, medially 0.35 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum about 1.5 times as long as its anterior maximum width. Subalar depression shallow, rather densely and distinctly rugose-granulate. Sternaulus (precoxal sulcus) absent. Prepectal carina below without wide lobes opposite fore coxae. Metanotum dorso-medially with three fine carinae (dorsal view). Metapleural flange without dense pubescence.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing 4.5 times its maximum width. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.35 times as long as pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell 4.7 times as long as wide. Radial vein (r) arising almost from middle of pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming very obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) almost 4.0 times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.75 times as long as the straight third abscissa (SR1), 1.6 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell not widened distally, almost 4.0 times as long as wide, 1.25 times as long as the narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) strongly sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) very weakly postfurcal, 0.6 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) weakly curved to anal vein (2- 1A) in distal half. Nervulus (cu-a) strongly postfurcal, distance between basal (1-M) vein and nervulus (cu-a) 1.4 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial; posterior bulla of brachial vein (CU1b) short, posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) present, but very fine; brachial vein (CU1b) distinctly oblique towards base of wing. Hind wing 5.4 times as long as wide. Recurrent vein (m-cu) almost straight, strongly oblique towards base of wing, very faintly pigmented.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa 1.6 times as long as wide (with basoventral tubercle). Hind femur wide, its length 2.3 times maximum width.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length 1.6 times as long as head and mesosoma combined, with seven coarsely sclerotised and at least basally (posterior tergites) sculptured visible tergites. First tergite weakly and almost linearly widened from base to subapex, weakly narrowed apically. Maximum subapical width of first tergite 1.5 times its minimum basal width; length 3.2 times apical width, 1.7 times length of propodeum. Second tergite without apical area, with long and wide subtriangular basal area, median length this area almost equal to length of remaining tergite. Median length of second tergite 1.6 times its basal width, almost equal to length of third tergite. Second suture very shallow, almost indistinct, with wide straight smooth transverse stripe on suture place. Sixth tergite not enlarged, distinctly concave on posterior margin, without median emargination and posteroventral lobes. Sixth tergite 0.7 times as long as fifth tergite, about as long as seventh tergite. Ovipositor sheath flat, leaf-like, very wide, evenly narrowed towards apex and towards base, about 3.0 times as long as its maximum width, 0.8 times as long as first metasomal tergite. Ovipositor thick, curved up, wide and flattened dorso-ventrally in basal 0.7, slender and pointed in apical 0.3.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex and frons densely and distinctly granulate, becoming finer on frons; face very finely punctate and coriaceous between punctation; temple densely granulate becoming granulate-coriaceous below. Mesoscutum entirely densely granulate, without rugosity along notauli, narrow rugulose-striate in its medioposterior half. Scutellum densely and finely granulate. Mesopleuron densely and finely granulate becoming finer below. Metapleuron densely granulate, with rugosity posteriorly. Propodeum without areolation, with distinct and dense longitudinal striation and dense fine granulation between striae, mainly granulate and with fine and incomplete striae in basolateral halves. Hind coxa dorsally finely granulate-coriaceous, smooth in lower half. Hind femur mainly smooth. First entirely, second mainly (except smooth basomedian place) and third in basal 0.7–0.8 tergites densely and coarsely striate with numerous fine rugulosity between striae; third tergite rugulose-granulate on subposterior 0.2 becoming smooth posteriorly. Fourth and fifth tergites entirely densely and rather coarsely rugulose-areolate with granulation in basal 0.5–0.6 and smooth apically. Sixth and seventh tergites finely or very finely granulate-coriaceous in basal half and smooth apically. Third–seventh tergites laterally densely and finely reticulate-granulate or reticulate-coriaceous in basal 0.5–0.3 and smooth on remaining parts. Vertex widely with rather dense, short and semi-erect pale setae, glabrous on rather small medio-anterior area. Mesoscutum entirely in dense, short and semi-erect golden setae. Mesopleuron glabrous on wide median area, in sparse and erect pale setae on rest parts.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head brownish yellow, darker dorsally, behind eyes and in lower 0.7 of face. Mesosoma reddish brown in upper half and dark brown to black in lower half. Metasoma reddish brown, dark reddish brown to black medially. Antennae brownish yellow, darkened towards apex, scapus mainly dark brown. Palps yellow. Fore leg entirely and middle coxa yellow (other parts of middle leg missing). Hind coxa and femur dark brown, but yellowish apically (other parts of this leg missing). Ovipositor sheath dark brown, but paler marginally. Fore wing faintly maculate usually along veins. Pterostigma brown, yellow basally and in apical third.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Madagascar
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
