<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Platyspathius (Platyspathius) pictipennis
            Viereck 1911</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4649719</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/AF1D4E27AD285F46FE78E0033F433CB9</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera,
            Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Platyspathius ( Platyspathius ) pictipennis Viereck, 1911 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Figs 28–29 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Platyspathius pictipennis Viereck, 1911: 185 </tp:taxon-name> . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Rhaconotus spathulatus Szépligeti, 1914: 198 </tp:taxon-name> (HNHM; not
         examined). </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Platyspathius pictipennis </tp:taxon-name> – Nixon 1943: 429 . — Granger
         1949: 153 . — Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1385 . — van Achterberg 2003: 286 . </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Rhaconotus spathulatus </tp:taxon-name> – Nixon 1943: 429 (as synonym of
            <tp:taxon-name> P. pictipennis </tp:taxon-name> ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p> Holotype </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> MOZAMBIQUE • ♂ ; “101”, “ CW Howard Collector”, “Xalasi ( Maputo )”,
            “Lor Marquez, Africa, 4.VI.09 ”, “Type, No 13489, U.S.N.M.”, “ <tp:taxon-name>
               Platyspathius pictipennis Vier. </tp:taxon-name> , Type ♂”; USNM .
         </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> Male </p>
      <p> MEASUREMENTS. Body length 3.9 mm ; fore wing length 2.7 mm . </p>
      <p>HEAD. Width 1.5 times its median length, 1.2 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes
         (dorsal view) weakly convex in anterior half and weakly roundly narrowed in posterior half.
         Transverse diameter of eye 1.15 times length of temple. Ocelli medium-sized, arranged in
         triangle with base 1.3 times its sides; POL 1.8 times OD, 0.7 times OOL. Eye with short and
         sparse setae, very weakly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.3 times as high as
         broad. Malar space 0.65 times height of eye, 1.3 times basal width of mandible. Face
         convex, its width almost equal to height of eye and 1.2 times height of face and clypeus
         combined. Clypeus marrow, its upper margin situated distinctly below than lower level of
         eyes. Hypoclypeal depression round, its width 0.6 times distance from edge of depression to
         eye, 0.4 times width of face. Occipital carina not fused below with hypostomal carina being
         obliterated on wide distance. Vertex weakly convex. Head below eyes distinctly and roundly
         narrowed. Antennae rather thick, filiform, 25-segmented, weakly shorter than body. Scapus
         1.5 times as long as its maximum width. First flagellar segment about 5.0 times as long as
         its apical width, 1.05 times as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 2.2 times as
         long as wide, 0.5 times as long as first segment, 0.8 times as long as apical segment.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.0 times its height. Mesoscutum (dorsal view) 0.9 times as long as
         maximum width; its median lobe weakly convex anteriorly. Notauli present and crenulate in
         anterior 0.6, completely absent in posterior 0.4. Prescutellar depression rather deep,
         short, distinctly and roundly curved posterolaterally, with seven distinct carinae, smooth
         between carinae, about 0.3 times as long as scutellum. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow)
         straight, finely reticulate-coriaceous. Prepectal carina below without widened lobes
         opposite fore coxae. Subalar depression finely crenulate with reticulation.</p>
      <p> Fig. 28. <tp:taxon-name> Platyspathius ( Platyspathius ) pictipennis Viereck,1911
         </tp:taxon-name> , ♂, holotype, USNM. A . Habitus, lateral view. B . Head, lateral view. C
         . Head, frontal view. D . Head, dorsal view. E . Basal segments of antenna. F . Apical
         segments of antenna. G . Mesoscutum, dorsal view. H . Mesosoma, lateral view. I . Propodeum
         and first metasomal tergite, dorsal view. J . Hind coxa and femur, lateral view. K . Hind
         tibia, lateral view. L . Propodeum and first metasomal tergite, lateral view. </p>
      <p> Fig. 29. <tp:taxon-name> Platyspathius ( Platyspathius ) pictipennis Viereck, 1911
         </tp:taxon-name> , ♂, holotype, USNM. A . Wings. B . Metasoma, dorsal view. C . Metasoma,
         lateral view. </p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing 4.3 times its maximum width. Radial (marginal) cell 2.9 times as long as
         maximum width. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.1 times as long as pterostigma. First radial abscissa
         (r) forming obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 2.8
         times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.75 times as long as the straight third abscissa
         (SR1), 1.55 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial
         (submarginal) cell long, weakly narrowed distally, 3.3 times as long as wide, 1.3 times as
         long as the rather wide basally and narrowed apically brachial (subdiscal) cell. First
         medial abscissa (1-SR+M) weakly sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) 1.3 times as long as second
         median abscissa (2-SR+M), 0.35 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Mediocubital
         vein (M+CU1) strongly curved to anal vein (2-1A) in distal half. Nervulus (cu-a)
         interstitial. Brachial (subdiscal) cell closed shortly before level of recurrent vein;
         posterior bulla and posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b))
         absent. Hind wing about 6.5 times as long as wide. Recurrent vein (m-cu) unsclerotised.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore femur about 3.0 times as long as wide. Hind coxa 1.3 times as long as wide. Hind
         femur almost 3.0 times its maximum width. Hind tibia with dense comb of long setae on inner
         apical margin. Hind tarsus 0.9 times as long as hind tibia. Second tarsal segment 0.45
         times as long as basitarsus, 1.8 times as long as fourth segment, almost as long as fifth
         segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length as long as head and mesosoma combined. First tergite weakly and linearly
         widened towards apex; its maximum width 1.8 times basal width; its length 2.1 times apical
         width, 1.4 times length of propodeum. Median length of second tergite 0.85 times its basal
         width, 1.6 times length of third tergite. Second suture shallow, rather narrow, distinctly
         evenly curved. Fifth and sixth tergite straight on posterior margins, without median
         emargination and postero-ventral lobes. Six tergites rather distinctly protruding behind
         fifth tergite.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex distinctly and very densely reticulate-granulate, partly
         with fine aciculation, without rugosity; frons densely rugulose-aciculate with dense
         granulation; face entirely, very densely and distinctly granulate with reticulation; temple
         entirely densely reticulate-granulate, partly upper and below with fine aciculation.
         Mesoscutum entirely densely and distinctly reticulate-coriaceous (granulation indistinct),
         finely rugulose on its wide medioposterior area, with distinct median carina in posterior
         0.3 of mesoscutum. Scutellum densely and finely reticulate-coriaceous. Mesopleuron entirely
         finely or very finely and densely reticulate-coriaceous. Metapleuron finely and densely
         reticulatecoriaceous, additionally rugulose-striate in posterior quarter. Propodeum without
         areas, with distinct and almost complete lateral carinae and distinct median carina in
         basal half, entirely densely granulateareolate with sparse and distinct rugosity in
         posterior half. Hind coxa almost entirely densely and very finely reticulate-coriaceous or
         reticulate, without rugosity. Hind femur entirely finely or very finely reticulate or
         reticulate-coriaceous. First and second metasomal tergites with very dense and very small
         but distinct areolation, with complete and distinctly lateral carinae, with short dorsal
         carinae in basal 0.2 of first tergite. Second suture very densely and small areolate,
         without striation. Third and fourth tergites entirely rather finely and very densely small
         areolate-reticulate; fifth and sixth tergites entirely finely reticulate-coriaceous. Vertex
         almost entirely with short, sparse or very sparse and semi-erect pale setae, glabrous in
         wide median part. Mesoscutum mainly glabrous, with sparse, short and semi-erect setae
         arranged rather widely along notauli and in narrow row marginally. Mesopleuron widely
         glabrous medially. Hind tibia dorsally with rather short, sparse and semi-erect pale setae;
         length of these setae 0.2–0.3 times maximum width of hind tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Body reddish brown to dark reddish brown, with light reddish brown areas laterally
         and dorsally, pronotum and head below brownish yellow or pale brown. Antenna yellow or
         brownish yellow, six apical segments contrasting black. Palps dark reddish brown. Legs
         light reddish brown, middle and hind coxae yellowish brown, tarsi (except dark apical
         segments) light reddish brown of brownish yellow, hind tibia basally dark, not paler than
         remaining part of tibia. Fore wing strongly darkened, less strongly apically, with three
         hyaline transverse stripes: wide basally (with very short and sparse setae), narrow on
         middle of basal half (crossing narrowest part of submedian area), narrow and interrupted
         medially on level of base of pterostigma. Pterostigma mostly dark brown, yellow in its
         basal 0.3.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p> Distribution </p>
      <p> Cameroon , Democratic Republic of Congo , Madagascar , Mozambique , South Africa , Sudan ,
         Uganda . </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
