<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus testaceiceps
Cameron, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 8–9
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus testaceiceps
Cameron, 1910: 100
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus testaceiceps
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Viereck 1914: 57

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus testaceiceps
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1342

. — Belokobylskij 2001: 133. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

. — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 167


.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
INDONESIA
• 
♀
; “ 
Siluas Sambas
, 
W. Borneo
, 

22/ 
26.7.07

, Micholitz”, “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus testaceiceps
Cam.
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Type
. Borneo”; 
MHBG
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
5.1 mm
; fore wing length 
3.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width 1.5 times its median length, 1.35 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) distinctly and roundly narrowed. Transverse diameter of eye almost 2 times length of temple. Ocelli small, arranged in almost equilateral triangle; POL almost equal to OD, 0.35 times OOL. Eye with very short and sparse setae, very weakly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.15 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.5 times height of eye, 0.9 times basal width of mandible. Face width 1.2 times height of eye and 1.45 times height of face and clypeus combined. Malar suture absent. Upper margin of clypeus situated almost on lower level of eyes. Hypoclypeal depression small and round, its width 0.7 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.35 times width of face. Clypeus with distinct, but short ventral flange. Occipital carina not fused ventrally with hypostomal carina being obliterated shortly upper base of mandible. Vertex distinctly convex. Head below eyes strongly and almost linearly narrowed. Antennae rather slender, filiform, more than 9-segmented (most part of apical segments missing). Length of scapus almost twice its maximum width. First flagellar segment 4.8 times as long as its apical width, 1.1 times as long as second segment.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus testaceiceps
Cameron, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, MHBG. 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B
. Habitus, lateral view. 
C
. Head, latero-posterior view. 
D
. Fore leg. 
E
. Head, lateral view. 
F
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
G
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
H
. Hind leg.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 9.
<tp:taxon-name>
Euryphrymnus testaceiceps
Cameron, 1910
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, MHBG. 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Metasoma, lateral view. 
C
. Metasoma, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.0 times its height. Pronotal carina rather distinct, distances from carina to both sides of pronotum subequal. Mesoscutum rather highly and roundly elevated above pronotum, 1.1 times as long as wide. Notauli entirely deep, complete, rather wide, distinctly crenulate. Median lobe of mesoscutum with shallow anteriorly and deep posteriorly median furrow. Prescutellar depression rather deep, short, distinctly and roundly curved posterolaterally, with five distinct carinae, finely rugulose, 0.25 times as long as convex scutellum. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) rather shallow, narrow, weakly sinuate, distinctly and densely crenulate, running along entire lower part of mesopleuron. Prepectal carina without widened lobes opposite fore coxae. Subalar depression rather shallow, narrow, distinctly crenulate and almost smooth between crenulae. Metanotum with rather long, narrow and pointed tooth directed backward. Metapleural lobe long, narrow, rounded apically, without dense pubescence. Mesopleural suture entirely and distinctly crenulate.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing 4.2 times its maximum width. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Metacarpus (1- R1) 1.2 times as long as pterostigma. Radial vein (r) arising from middle of pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming very obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 4.0 times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.55 times as long as weakly curved third abscissa (SR1), 1.85 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell rather long, widened distally, 2.5 times as long as wide, as long as brachial (subdiscal) cell. First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) distinctly sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) weakly postfurcal. Discoidal (discal) cell 2.9 times as long as maximum width. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) rather distinctly curved to anal vein (1-1A) in distal half. Nervulus (cu-a) postfurcal, distance between nervulus (cu-a) and basal (1-M) vein 0.5 times nervulus (cu- a) length. Brachial (subdiscal) cell rather wide, gently-roundly closed weakly before level of recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla and posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) absent. Hind wing 5.7 times as long as wide. First costal abscissa 0.55 times as long as second abscissa. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.4 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) very fine, unsclerotised, curved, postfurcal.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa with distinct basoventral tooth, 1.5 times as long as wide (with basoventral tubercle). Hind femur with not high dorsal protuberance, length of femur 3.3 times maximum width. Hind tarsus almost as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.7 times combined length of second–fifth segments. Second tarsal segment 0.45 times as long as basitarsus, 2.0 times as long as fourth segment, 1.25 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length 1.2 times as long as head and mesosoma combined, with five visible tergites (following tergites not protruding behind fifth one). First tergite without subbasal lateral processes. Maximum width of first tergite about 2 times its basal width; its length 1.35 times apical width, 1.3 times length of propodeum. Second tergite with short basal area, delineated posteriorly by curved furrow; with deep, narrow and curved transverse subposterior furrow very distinctly separated wide apical area median length of area 0.9 times length of rest part of tergite. Median length of second tergite 0.75 times its basal width, 1.5 times length of third tergite. Second suture deep, rather wide, distinctly regularly curved. Fifth tergite enlarged, distinctly convex in posterior margin, without median emargination and postero-ventral lobes. Fifth tergite 1.6 times as long as fourth tergite, 1.75 times as long as third tergite. Ovipositor sheath 0.55 times as long as metasoma, 1.3 times as long as hind tibia, 0.9 times as long as mesosoma, 0.4 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex densely distinctly granulate, with distinct and weakly undulate transverse striae; frons densely granulate and with distinct striae directed from lateral sides towards middle; face densely and rather finely granulate, almost smooth on narrow median area; temple almost entirely granulate. Mesoscutum entirely densely and distinctly granulate, with distinct and rather long rugosity along notauli and laterally, with short rugosity in medioposterior 0.3 of mesoscutum. Scutellum densely and distinctly granulate. Mesopleuron densely and entirely granulate, with fine rugulosity laterally. Metapleuron densely rugose-reticulate with granulation. Propodeum with distinctly delineated, densely striate with granulation large basolateral areas, with rather distinct, wide and coarsely rugosestriate areola. Hind coxa densely and distinctly granulate in upper half, finely granulate in lower half. Hind femur reticulate-coriaceous in upper half, finely coriaceous or almost smooth in lower half. First tergite with distinct, complete and weakly convergent dorsal carinae, distinctly coarsely striate with dense fine reticulation between striae, with additional dense granulation in anterior 0.3 of tergite. Second tergite entirely coarsely and undulately striate with dense fine rugulosity between striae. Third and fourth tergites in basal 0.8 distinctly densely linearly striate and with additional reticulation, narrowly smooth apically. Fifth tergite entirely, densely, coarsely and curvedly striate, with densely and distinct reticulate between striae. Second–fourth tergites laterally entirely densely striate with granulation. Vertex entirely with rather short, more or less dense and semi-erect pale setae. Mesoscutum dense, rather short and semierect setae arranged widely along notauli and laterally, with wide glabrous median areas. Mesopleuron entirely covered by dense pale setae. Hind tibia dorsally with rather short, more or less dense, semi-erect pale setae; length of these setae 0.6–0.8 times maximum width of hind tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head light reddish brown. Mesosoma reddish brown in anterior half and dark reddish brown in posterior half. Metasoma reddish brown. Antenna reddish brown to dark reddish brown, two basal segments light reddish brown. Palps brownish yellow. Legs brownish yellow, hind coxa light reddish brown, apical segments of all tarsi dark brown. Ovipositor sheath mainly black, reddish brown in its basal 0.3. Fore wing evenly faintly infuscate. Pterostigma mainly yellowish brown, yellow in its basal 0.4.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Indonesia
(Borneo).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
