<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus enervatus
van Achterberg &amp; Shaw, 2010
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 38–39
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus enervatus
van Achterberg &amp; Shaw, 2010: 3
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus enervatus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Yu 
et al.
2016

. — 


Jasso-Martínez 
et al.
2019: 167


.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
SPAIN
• 
♀
; “ 
Spain
: 
Granada
, 
Orgiva
, 305 VF 

68, 500 m

.”, “ 
Interception trap
, 

25.X.2007

, Jose Luis Ruiz de la Cuesta”, “ 
Don. A. Ribes
, 11223”, “♀ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
<tp:taxon-name>
enervatus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, 
van Achterberg &amp; Shaw, 2010
, 
Holotype
”; 
NMS
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
4.8 mm
; fore wing length 3.0 mm.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Width 1.4 times its median length, 1.3 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) distinctly and roundly narrowed; transverse diameter of eye 1.6 times length of temple. Ocelli small, arranged in triangle with base 1.25 times its sides; POL 2.0 times OD, 0.5 times OOL. Eye very weakly emarginated opposite antennal sockets, 1.2 times as high as broad. Malar space 0.55 times height of eye, equal to basal width of mandible. Face width 1.2 times height of eye and 1.4 times height of face and clypeus combined. Upper margin of clypeus situated distinctly below than lower level of eyes. Hypoclypeal depression width 0.6 times distance from edge of depression to eye, 0.3 times width of face. Vertex distinctly convex. Head below eyes distinctly and almost linearly narrowed. Antennae rather slender, weakly setiform, about 32-segmented (accordingly description, in studied 
holotype
kept only 15 segments). Scapus 1.8 times as long as its maximum width. First flagellar segment 3.3 times as long as its apical width, almost as long as second segment. Submedian segment 2.2 times as long as their width.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 38.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus enervatus
van Achterberg &amp; Shaw, 2010
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, NMS. 
A
. Habitus, dorsal view. 
B
. Head, dorsal view. 
C
. Head, front view. 
D
. Head, lateral view. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
G
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
H
. Hind leg.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 39.
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudorhaconotus enervatus
van Achterberg &amp; Shaw, 2010
</tp:taxon-name>
, ♀, holotype, NMS. 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
C
. Metasoma and hind leg, lateral view.
</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2.0 times its height. Distances from coarse pronotal keel to anterior margin of pronotum about 1.7 times larger than distance from keel to posterior margin of pronotum. Mesoscutum 0.9 times as long as its maximum width. Notauli complete, rather narrow, sparsely crenulate-rugulose with fine granulation. Median lobe of mesoscutum with distinct median furrow in its posterior 0.4. Prescutellar depression rather deep, distinctly and almost linearly widened towards lateral margins, with distinct five carinae, smooth or partly finely rugulose between carinae, medially 0.2 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum weakly convex, with lateral carinae, its maximum width 1.1 times median length. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) shallow, wide, straight, distinctly crenulate with fine reticulation, running along anterior 0.7 of lower part of mesopleuron. Prepectal carina below with weakly widened lobes opposite fore coxae. Subalar depression rather deep, narrow, sparsely and coarsely crenulate with granulation. Mesopleural suture entirely, coarsely, sparsely and shortly crenulate. Metapleural lobe rather long, wide basally, rounded apically, without dense pubescence.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing 4.3 times its maximum width, not coming forward apex of metasoma, apical margin of wing without setae. Radial (marginal) cell weakly shortened, narrow, 4.4 times as long as maximum width. Metacarpus (1-R1) 0.9 times as long as pterostigma, about 2.0 times as long as distance from apex of radial (marginal) cell to apex of wing. First radial abscissa (r) forming very obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) very weakly curved, 6.2 times as long as first abscissa (r), 2.6 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). First medial abscissa (1-SR+M) weakly curved distally. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) distinctly sinuate, distinctly curved to anal vein (2-1A) in distal half. Discoidal (discal) cell narrow, 2.5 times as long as wide. Distance between nervulus (cu-a) and basal (1-M) vein 0.6 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Brachial (subdiscal) cell roundly closed almost on level of recurrent vein; posterior bulla and posterior abscissa of longitudinal anal vein (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) absent. Hind wing 4.6 times as long as wide. First costal abscissa (C+SC+R) 0.6 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.5 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) antefurcal.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa 1.5 times as long as wide (with tubercle). Hind femur 3.2 times as long as its maximum width. Hind tarsus 0.9 times as long as hind tibia. Second tarsal segment 0.6 times as long as basitarsus, 2.0 times as long as fourth segment, 1.3 times as long as fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length 1.2 times as long as head and mesosoma combined. First tergite distinctly widened toward apex, with coarse lateral carinae Maximum width of first tergite 2.5 times its minimum width; its length 1.3 times apical width, almost equal to length of propodeum. Second tergite with very narrow basal area weakly delineated posteriorly by shallow furrow; with distinct, narrow, and straight transverse subposterior furrow weakly separated narrow subparallel apical area, median length of apical area 0.5 times length of rest part of tergite. Median length of second tergite 0.6 times its basal width, almost equal to length of third tergite. Second suture rather deep, wide, straight medially and weakly curved laterally. Fifth tergite strongly enlarged, weakly roundly convex in posterior margin, without median emargination, and postero-ventral lobes. Fifth tergite 1.3 times as long as fourth tergite, 1.5 times as long as third tergite. Ovipositor sheath 0.3 times as long as metasoma, 0.7 times as long as hind tibia, 0.5 times as long as mesosoma, 0.25 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex rater finely and densely granulate, with more or less distinct and weakly undulate transverse striae; frons coarsely curvedly striate with fine granulation between</p>
      <p>striae partly, densely granulate and without striation laterally. Face densely and distinctly granulate, with striation on two narrow vertical submedian stripes, medially finely coriaceous to almost smooth; temple entirely granulate or granulate-coriaceous, additionally vertically coarsely striate in posterior 0.5–0.7, sculpture becoming finer towards its lower part. Mesoscutum entirely densely and rather finely granulate-reticulate, without rugosity along notauli, with two median striae in medioposterior 0.4 of mesoscutum and short rugosity between their and around. Scutellum densely and rather finely granulate-reticulate, laterally widely with distinct curved striation. Mesopleuron entirely densely and finely granulate-reticulate, below sternaulus finely reticulate-coriaceous. Metapleuron finely reticulatecoriaceous in anterior half, rugose-areolate in posterior half. Propodeum with long basolateral areas mainly finely coriaceous and with rugosity along carinae, with distinct and long median carina in basal 0.4 of propodeum; areola narrow, finely and irregularly delineated; propodeum rugose-striate in its posterior 0.3. Hind coxa finely granulate-reticulate dorsally and reticulate-coriaceous laterally. Hind femur finely and densely reticulate-coriaceous becoming fine laterally, almost smooth below. First tergite densely and finely reticulate-coriaceous and medially with distinct and rather sparse wide striation. Second tergite almost entirely striate, with fine reticulation between striae and only reticulate on two medio-lateral narrow longitudinal stripes. Third tergite in its basal 0.5–0.7, fourth on its basal 0.3–0.5, and fifth basally striate, other parts of tergites densely granulate-reticulate becoming finely reticulatecoriaceous towards their posterior margins. Second–fifth tergites laterally entirely densely striate with fine reticulation between striae. Vertex with long, sparse, and almost adpressed pale setae. Mesoscutum with sparse, rather short and semi-erect setae arranged more or less widely along notauli and marginally, widely glabrous medially. Mesopleuron glabrous on narrow medial area. Hind tibia dorsally with rather long, sparse, and semi-erect pale setae; length of these setae 0.5–0.6 times maximum width of hind tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Head dark reddish brown, only reddish brown around eyes, anteriorly and below. Mesosoma reddish brown to dark reddish brown, dorsally almost black. Metasoma black with dark reddish brown spots, first tergite reddish brown. Antenna light reddish brown becoming darkened towards its middle. Palps yellowish brown, infuscate basally. Legs reddish brown to dark reddish brown, tarsi light reddish brown, fore and middle tibiae basally and hind tibia in its basal 0.3–0.4 brownish yellow. Ovipositor sheath black, light brown basally. Fore wing hyaline, with two large darkened stripes: one stripe crossed basal (1-M) vein and brachial (subdiscal) cell, second stripe crossed wing area below its posterior 0.7 of pterostigma and on all radial (marginal) cell. Pterostigma dark brown, yellow in basal quarter.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Western Palaearctic (
Spain
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
