<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pararhacon
Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
) Belokobylskij, 2005: 208
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
)
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Yu 
et al.
2016

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
) 
haeselbarthi
Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
(
Figs 47–48
)
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head transverse. Eyes with distinct, but sparse and short setae. Occipital carina complete, joining ventrally with hypostomal carina. Clypeal suture distinct and complete. Hypoclypeal depression rather small, subround. Postgenal bridge very narrow. Palps rather short. Scapus of antenna relatively wide and long. First flagellar segment almost straight, weakly longer than second segment. Apical segment pointed apically. Antennae brownish yellow to yellow in apical 0.3.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Pronotum with distinct pronotal carina situated medially. Mesonotum rather highly and roundly elevated above pronotum. Notauli complete and coarsely crenulate. Prescutellar depression rather long, with distinct median carina. Metanotum with short and subacuminate median tooth (lateral view). Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) deep and long, running along entire lower length of mesopleuron.</p>
      <p>Prepectal carina distinct and complete. Propodeum with basolateral areas not distinctly delineated by carinae, without areola; lateral tubercles distinct and thick.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Wings weakly shortened. Pterostigma of fore wing rather wide. Radial vein (r) arising distinctly behind middle of pterostigma. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Recurrent vein (m-cu) distinctly antefurcal. Nervulus (cu-a) postfurcal. Brachial (subdiscal) cell closed apically distinctly before recurrent vein (m-cu). Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial. In hind wing, radial (marginal) cell almost parallel-sided. Submedial (subbasal) cell medium size; First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) distinctly shorter than second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) present and almost straight.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore and middle tibiae with distinct spines arranged in almost single longitudinal row. Hind femur with fine dorsal protuberances. Hind basitarsus 0.7 times as long as second–fifth segments combined.</p>
      <p>METASOMA.First tergite rather short and wide. Second tergite with narrow apical lenticular area delineated by rather shallow furrows. Second suture deep and almost straight. Fifth tergite rather distinctly enlarged, longer than previous tergite, covered following apical segments.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This subgenus differs from nominative subgenus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
</tp:taxon-name>
s. str.
by the recurrent vein (m-cu) of fore wing weakly antefurcal (vs always postfurcal), the propodeum with distinct lateral tubercles (vs without or sometimes with small tubercles), and the apical segments of antenna contrastingly pale (vs always dark and the same colour as previous segments).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Composition
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Rhaconotus
(
Pararhacon
) 
haeselbarthi
Belokobylskij, 2005
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Hosts
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>Afrotropical region.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
