<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ipodoryctes (Afroipodoryctes) insignis Granger 1949</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4651670</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/C56EDB81AD63EC168012EB945EDE42BD</uri>
         <article-title>Reclassification of the doryctine tribe Rhaconotini (Hymenoptera, Braconidae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.741.1289</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes
(
Afroipodoryctes
) 
insignis
Granger, 1949
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 16–17
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes insignis
Granger, 1949: 109
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes insignis
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Shenefelt &amp; Marsh 1976: 1314

. — 

Yu 
et al.
2016

.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
MADAGASCAR
• 
♀
; “Madagascar, Perinet, Foret cote est”, “Museum Paris, 3–32, 
A. Seyrig
”, “36”, “ 
Type
”, “ 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ipodoryctes insignis
Granger
</tp:taxon-name>
” (head, all fore legs, and single middle and hind legs missing); 
MNHM
.
</tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length (according to original description) 4.0 mm; fore wing length 
3.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Head and antennae missing; but according to original description (
Granger 1949: 109
): head transverse, strongly narrowed behind eyes. Antennae 36-segmented, 1.5 times as long as body.
</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Length 2 times its height. Pronotum almost straight dorsally (lateral view). Pronotal carina distinct, situated submedially. Mesoscutum rather highly and roundly elevated above pronotum. Notauli deep, complete, smooth. Median lobe of mesoscutum without median depression. Prescutellar depression rather shallow, short, with five carinae, rugulose, 0.3 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum weakly convex. Sternaulus (precoxal furrow) shallow, straight, mostly smooth, finely crenulate only posteriorly, running along almost entire lower part of mesopleuron, connected with prepectal carina anteriorly. Prepectal carina below without widened lobes opposite fore coxae. Subalar depression shallow, narrow, densely striate. Metanotum with long pointed tooth. Metapleural lobe long and wide.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Length of fore wing 4.0 times its maximum width. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened. Metacarpus (1-R1) 1.2 times as long as pterostigma. Pterostigma 3.7 times as long as wide. Radial vein (r) arising almost from middle of pterostigma. First radial abscissa (r) forming distinct obtuse angle with second abscissa (3-SR). Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 5.3 times as long as first abscissa (r), 0.8 times as long as third abscissa (SR1), 2.2 times as long as first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell not widened distally, its length 3.5 times maximum width, 1.2 times length of rather narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. First abscissa of medial vein (1-SR+M) distinctly sinuate. Recurrent vein (m-cu) distinctly postfurcal, 3.5 times as long as second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M). Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) distinctly curved to anal vein (2-1A) in distal half. Distance from nervulus (cu-a) to basal (1-M) vein 0.6 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Brachial (subdiscal) cell apically gently and roundly closed distinctly before level of recurrent vein (m-cu); posterior bulla indistinct; posterior abscissa of anal vein (2-1A) (behind brachial vein (CU1b)) absent. Hind wing about 5.0 times as long as wide. First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.6 times as long as second abscissa (1-M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) strongly unsclerotised, antefurcal. Medial (basal) cell rather narrow, distinctly widened distally, 0.45 times as long as wing.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa without basoventral tubercle. Hind and middle femora without dorsal protuberances. Length of hind femur 3.0 times its maximum width. Hind tibia thickened. Tarsal segments of hind leg mostly missing, basitarsus short.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Length 1.5 times as long as mesosoma, with six visible tergites, but sixth tergites not strongly enlarged. First tergite long, regularly and linearly widened toward apex, with lateral keels, without spiracular tubercles. Apical width of first tergite 1.8 times its basal width; its length 1.6 times apical width, 1.4 times length of propodeum. Second tergite with deep, distinctly curved transverse furrow and with distinct wide apical lenticular area, this area 0.6 times as long as rest part of tergite. Median length of second tergite 0.8 times its basal width, almost 2 times length of third tergite. Second suture deep and distinctly curved. Fifth tergite 1.2 times as long as fourth tergite, 1.5 times as long as third tergite, weakly shorter than sixth tergite. Posterior margins of fifth and sixth tergites almost straight, without median emargination and postero-ventral lobes. Ovipositor sheath 0.7 times as long as metasoma, as long as mesosoma, 0.45 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Head (according to original description) smooth. Pro- and mesothorax mostly smooth; mesoscutum posteriorly with two straight carinae Propodeum almost entirely smooth, with median carina in basal half, basolateral areas long, about 0.7 times as long as propodeum; areola distinct, rather narrow, pentagonal, weakly rugulose. Hind legs very finely granulate, hind coxa almost smooth, without dorsal striation. First tergite entirely, second at most part (except smooth apical area) and base of third tergite distinctly striate, remainder parts of metasoma smooth, except narrowly striate bases of tergites. Mesoscutum with sparse long setae arranged along notauli and marginally. Hind tibia with erect sparse long setae dorsally; length of these setae 1.2–1.5 times maximum width of hind tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Body reddish brown. Legs yellow, hind coxa and especially distal half of hind femur brown to dark brown. Fore wings evenly and distinctly infuscate. Pterostigma brown, yellow in basal half.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
Madagascar
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
