<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Ganomymar dessarti De Santis 1972</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5076145</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/DEC17534D7D3EBDB759B50CCE704E825</uri>
         <article-title>Revision of Ganomymar De Santis, 1972, a remarkable genus of Mymaridae (Hymenoptera, Chalcidoidea) from Madagascar</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.757.1417</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Ganomymar dessarti
De Santis, 1972
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 6–7
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ganomymar dessarti
De Santis, 1972: 2–3
</tp:taxon-name>

(type locality: unknown, except being in 
Madagascar
(
De Santis 1972
)). 
Holotype
female [RBINS], dry-mounted except for one antenna and one fore wing mounted on a slide in Faure’s liquid (
De Santis 1972
), examined during a visit in 
June 1997
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Ganomymar dessarti
</tp:taxon-name>
is a member of the 
<tp:taxon-name>
dessarti
</tp:taxon-name>
species group. Females differ from those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
G. libertatium
</tp:taxon-name>
by the diagnostic features given in the key.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
MADAGASCAR
• 
1 ♀
(on slide); 
Alaotra-Mangoro Region
[formerly within 
Toamasina Province
], 
Andasibe-Mantadia National Park
; “MADAGASCAR: Toamasina Prov. Parc National Mantadia 
18°47.5′S
, 
48°25.6′E
, 

895 m
25–28.xi.1998

, 
H. J. Ratsirarson
(#111). Sifted litter (leaf mold, rotten wood), rainforest 
CAS
LOT # 014698
”; 
CAS

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Redescription
</p>
      <p>
Female
(non-type specimen)
</p>
      <p>
COLOR. Head black, rest of body (
Fig. 6A–B
) mostly light brown; scape and pedicel light brown, funicle brown, clava white; legs light brown except metacoxa and metatrochanter pale.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 6C
). Large, 1.35 × as wide as mesosoma. Face smooth and with fine, inconspicuous setae below toruli; toruli raised above face surface, in dorsal view projecting forward and in lateral view the anteriormost point on the head; vertex smooth, with 4 or 5 pairs of short, strong setae.
</p>
      <p>
ANTENNA (
Fig. 6E
). Scape, excluding radicle, 2.7× as long as wide; pedicel smooth, longer than F1 and 1.5× as long as wide; F5 as long as F6, length to width ratios of funiculars: F1 = 2.1, F2 = 6.4; F3 = 4.9; F4 = 3.3; F5 = 2.3; F6 = 1.9; clava 2.8× as long as wide, longer than combined length of 3 preceding flagellomeres.
</p>
      <p>
MESOSOMA (
Fig. 6D
). About 1.9× as long as wide, with mesoscutum except at anterior margin, scutellum + frenum, and metanotum reticulate, with sculpture on mesoscutum mesh-like, on scutellum and metanotum longitudinal, otherwise smooth; pronotum almost entire but with very short mediolongitudinal groove anteriorly, with 2 pairs of strong setae at posterior margin; axillar seta 
0.05 mm
long; scutellum + frenum a little longer than mesoscutum, scutellum not divided mediolongitudinally, with campaniform sensilla very close to its posterior margin; propodeum (
Fig. 7A
) with prominent, widely separated, subparallel, almost complete submedian carinae and area between them raised anteromedially (best observed in lateral view, 
Fig. 6B
).
</p>
      <p>
WINGS. Brachypterous. Fore wing (
Fig. 7C
) lanceolate and slightly, longitudinally folded apically (i.e., not quite flat) (
Fig. 6A–B
), 7.1 × as long as wide, extending far beyond apex of gaster (
Fig. 6A–B
); marginal vein with 1 dorsal macrochaeta; disc strongly infumate, with discal setae originating behind apex of submarginal vein and densely setose beyond venation; fringe setae short and reduced, those on anterior margin markedly thicker than on posterior margin, longest marginal seta 0.27 × greatest width of wing. Hind wings (
Fig. 7D
) of different length and degree of brachyptery, one about 25 × and the other 17.5 × as long as wide; disc strongly infumate, fringe setae few and reduced.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. All legs smooth, metacoxa with dense white setae. METASOMA. Petiole (
Fig. 7A
) smooth, 2.4× as long as wide and swollen medially, a little shorter than metacoxa. Ovipositor 0.85 length of gaster (
Fig. 7B
), not exserted beyond its apex, about 1.2× length of mesotibia and about as long as metatibia.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Ganomymar dessarti
De Santis, 1972
</tp:taxon-name>
, non-type, ♀, (CASENT 2079165), Andasibe-Mantadia National Park, Alaotra-Mangoro Region, Madagascar. 
A
. Habitus in dorsal view. 
B
. Habitus in dorsolateral view. 
C
. Head in frontal view. 
D
. Mesosoma. 
E
. Antenna.
</p>
      <p>MEASUREMENTS (µm). Body (of the critical point dried specimen prior to slide-mounting) = 1190; head (of the critical point dried specimen prior to slide-mounting) = 232; mesosoma = 455; mesoscutum = 130; scutellum = 150; petiole = 123; gaster = 535; ovipositor = 445. Radicle = 28; rest of scape = 188; pedicel = 72; F1 = 48; F2 = 151; F3 = 127; F4 = 100; F5 = 75; F6 = 75; clava = 322. Fore wing = 1246:175; venation = 297; longest marginal seta = 48. Hind wing = 527:21 (421:24); longest marginal seta = 45. Mesotibia = 381; metatibia = 436.</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
