<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Discometra rhodanica</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4419845</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/11161C5FE66C2055F4C5C40531970C4F</uri>
         <article-title>Discometra luberonensis sp. nov. (Crinoidea, Himerometridae), a new feather star from the Late Burdigalian</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Discometra rhodanica
(
Fontannes, 1877
)
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 3E
, 
4A
, 
5
A–B, 6
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Eugeniacrinus
? 

rhodanicus
Fontannes, 1877: 669
</tp:taxon-name>
.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Antedon meneghinianus
Fontannes, 1880: 412–413
</tp:taxon-name>

, pl. 2, fig. 11a–c.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Antedon rhodanicus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Fontannes 1880: 410–412

, pl. 2, fig. 10a–c. — de 

Loriol 1897: 121–124

, pl. 4, fig. 8 (non 9–10). — 

Nicolas 1897: 131–132

, fig. 6; 1898: 398–399, 402–404, fig. 1. — 

Airaghi 1904: 44–45

, figs 14–15. — 

Schütze 1904: 156–162

, pl. 2, figs 4–5. — 

Albus 1930: 291–292

, pl. 11, figs 5, 7.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Discometra rhodanica
</tp:taxon-name>
– 
Gislèn 1924:180–182
. — 

Biese &amp; Sieverts-Doreck 1939: 106–107

. — SievertsDoreck 1961: 110–117, 124, text fig. 2. — 
Rasmussen 1978
: T890, fig. 593-4a.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Antedon
cf. 
rhodanicus
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Valette 1928: 31–34

, fig. 5.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Discometra meneghiniana
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Biese &amp; Sieverts-Doreck 1939: 105

.

</p>
      <p>

non 
<tp:taxon-name>
Antedon rhodanica
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Vadasz 1915: 89–90

, pl. 7, figs 24–26.

</p>
      <p>

non 
<tp:taxon-name>
Discometra rhodanica
</tp:taxon-name>
– 
Rasmussen 1978
: T890, fig. 593-4b–c. — 

Hess &amp; Messing 2011: 107

, fig. 52-3a–d.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Emended diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Species known only from its calyx (centrodorsal + radial circlet). Centrodorsal hemispherical, often more flattened in large specimens, diameter can reach 
14 mm
; lateral surface with large cirrus sockets arranged in up to 3 irregular rows, each at bottom of a more or less marked depression; aboral pole depressed, conical in smaller (young) specimens (to ¼ maximum centrodorsal diameter) and bordered by smaller apical cirrus sockets arranged in two irregular rows; apical depression becoming wider (to ¾ maximum diameter) and deeper with increasing centrodorsal diameter and with numerous radial grooves.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 2.
Aboral view of the proximal crown and centrodorsal in three genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Himerometridae A.H. Clark, 1908</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–F
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Discometra luberonensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, Late Burdigalian of Ménerbes-Lacoste Plateau. 
A–B
. Holotype (MHNL 20.062682). 
C–D
. Paratype (MHNL 20.056148). 
E–F
. Paratype (MHNL 20-056151). 
G–H
. Extant species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Himerometridae</tp:taxon-name>
from western Pacific. 
G
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Himerometra robustipinna
(Carpenter, 1881)
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNHN-IE-2012-862). 
H
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Heterometra savignii
(Müller, 1841)
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNHN-IE-2016-1381). Scale bars: A–G = 10 mm; H = 5 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Neotype
</p>
      <p>
FRANCE
• 
1
calyx; 
Bouches du Rhône
, 
Notre-Dame du Château near Saint-Etienne-du-Grès
; 
MASR 2020.5011
(figured by de 
Loriol 1897
: fig. 8).
</p>
      <p>
Other material
</p>
      <p>
FRANCE
• 
1
calyx; 
Gard
, 
Les Angles
; 
UCBL 200025a

• 

2
calices; same collection data as for preceding; 
MRA
3.000.348
, 
3.000.349

• 

1
centrodorsal; same collection data as for preceding; 
UCBL 200025b

• 

3
calices; 
Vaucluse
, 
Caumont-sur-Durance
, 
Picabrier
; 
MHNL 20.062686
, 
20.062687
, 
20.062688

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 3.
Centrodorsal and radials in 
<tp:taxon-name>Himerometridae A.H. Clark, 1908</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A–D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Himerometra robustipinna
(Carpenter, 1881)
</tp:taxon-name>
(MNHN-IE-2012-862). 
A
. Adoral side of centrodorsal. 
B
. Cirrus sockets on lateral face of centrodorsal. 
C–D
. Radials. 
C
. Adoral view showing vermiculate grooves on inner face. 
D
. Distal articular facet. 
E
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Discometra rhodanica
(
Fontannes, 1877
)
</tp:taxon-name>
from Picabrier (MHNL 20.062687), cirrus sockets on centrodorsal. Scale bars: A–D = 1 mm; E = 0.5 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Locus typicus
</p>
      <p>
Late Burdigalian, facies with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Chlamys praescabriuscula
(Fontannes, 1878)
</tp:taxon-name>
, near Bollène (Vaucluse, southern 
France
).
</p>
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Neotype
</p>
      <p>
Extensive investigations in the collections of MHNL and MRA to retrieve the specimens used by 
Fontannes (1880)
to describe 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. rhodanicus
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. meneghinianus
</tp:taxon-name>
have been unsuccessful. They can be considered lost. Moreover, the locality from which they were collected, now located in an urbanized area, has now become inaccessible. The specimen illustrated by de 
Loriol (1897
: fig. 8) from the Late Burdigalian of Notre-Dame du Château (east of Saint-Etienne du Grès), an outcrop still accessible, is housed in the collection of the Musée des Alpilles in Saint-Rémy de Provence (MASR 2020.5011). We designate this specimen as the 
neotype
(
Fig. 5
A–B). Although smaller, its good preservation and its characters are similar to those of the specimen illustrated by 
Fontannes (1880
: pl. 2, fig. 10a–c). This specimen consists of a hemispherical centrodorsal and radial circlet. Its dimensions are given in 
Table 2
. The aboral surface of the centrodorsal (
Fig. 5A
) shows a marked depression surrounded by small apical cirrus sockets (diameter &lt;
0.4 mm
) partially worn out or biocorroded. The lateral surface is covered with larger cirrus sockets (diameter 
0.5 to 0.9 mm
) more or less oval and hollow; flattened socket floors sometimes displaying a roughly rectangular, low transverse ridge (
Fig. 5B
, arrow) like in extant 
<tp:taxon-name>Himerometridae</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 3B
). These larger cirrus sockets are arranged in up to three irregular rows. The maximum diameter of the radial circlet is much smaller than that of the centrodorsal (ratio 0.82). Centrodorsal height almost equals that of the radial circlet. Radial distal articular facet is almost entirely occupied by ligamentary areas, while muscular areas are comparatively inconspicuous. Its geometry is similar to that observed in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Himerometra
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 3D
). Irregular radiating grooves can be seen on the walls of the central adoral cavity, which is partially filled with sediment. They correspond to the vermiculate grooves reported above in the extant species of 
<tp:taxon-name>Himerometridae</tp:taxon-name>
(
Fig. 3C
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 4.
Cross sections near aboral surface of radial circlet showing Y-shaped coelomic canals in the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Discometra
Gislèn, 1924
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
A
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Discometra rhodanica
(
Fontannes, 1877
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
B
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Discometra eggenburgensis
(Schaffer, 1912)
</tp:taxon-name>
. Modified from Sieverts-Doreck (1961) in which A was modified from 
Fontannes (1880)
.
</p>
      <p>
Calices from the Picabrier deposit at Caumont-sur-Durance
</p>
      <p>
Three calices illustrate morphological changes during growth (
Fig. 6
). Centrodorsal diameter of the smallest specimen (MHNL 20.062688) is hemispherical, 
7.7 mm
across (
Fig. 6B
), with an aboral face similar to that of the 
neotype
. Centrodorsal of the largest specimen (MHNL 20.062686) is more discoidal, 
12 mm
across (
Fig. 6A
); its aboral depression deeper, ¾ of centrodorsal diameter; apex completely devoid of cirrus sockets and covered by numerous radial grooves, as in one of the specimens illustrated by 
Fontannes (1880)
(
Fig. 4A
). Cirrus sockets more or less circular, slightly concave and well delineated, and each located at the bottom of a well-marked depression (
Fig. 3E
). These depressions become almost contiguous, separated by fragile, often worn out crests. Centrodorsal of specimen MHNL 20.062687 is 
9.9 mm
across; specimen shows an intermediate morphology (
Fig. 6
C–D).
</p>
      <p>
Specimens from other sites
</p>
      <p>
Most of the other specimens examined were collected in the Rhône-Provence basin by one of us (MP) and are represented by centrodorsals only or centrodorsal and radial circlets, often worn out or biocorroded. Nevertheless, some characters of the calyx, such as degree of centrodorsal flattening, broadening and deepening of aboral cirrus-free depression, centrodorsal / radial circlet height ratio, and flaring of adoral cavity delimited by the radial circlet, are still visible and prove to be very variable (
Table 2
). The ancient quarries of Les Angles, now inaccessible, provided many specimens partly described by 
Nicolas (1898)
. Those that we have found in older collections, including the largest known specimens (UCBL 200025a, MRA 3.000.348, MRA 3.000.349), are worn out and do not allow detailed observation.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 5.
Late Burdigalian specimens attributed to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Discometra rhodanica
(
Fontannes, 1877
)
</tp:taxon-name>
by de 
Loriol (1897)
. 
A–B
. Neotype of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. rhodanica
</tp:taxon-name>
from Notre-Dame du Château (MASR 2020.5011). 
A
. Oblique aboral view of centrodorsal. 
B
. Oblique adoral view of calyx (arrow = sub-rectangular low ridge). 
C–E
. Unidentified 
<tp:taxon-name>Comatulidae Fleming, 1928</tp:taxon-name>
. 
C
. Adoral face of a centrodorsal from Entrechaux – ʻFerme Pieʼ (MHNL 20.062689). 
D-E
. Radial circlet from Notre-Dame du Château (MASR 2020.5021). Scale bars = 1 mm.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Gislén (1924)
pointed out the strong affinities between 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. rhodanica
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. eggenburgensis
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. meneghiniana
(
Fontannes, 1880
)
</tp:taxon-name>
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Discometra meneghiniana
</tp:taxon-name>
is only known from the single calyx described by 
Fontannes (1880
: pl. 2, fig. 11) and considered lost. It was collected from the same outcrops as the 
holotype
of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. rhodanica
</tp:taxon-name>
. Fontannes’s figure suggests that this specimen is strongly worn out; in particular the aboral depression of the centrodorsal displays an abnormally regularly circular appearance. It nevertheless falls within the field of variation of the species. We consider it to be a junior synonym of 
<tp:taxon-name>
D. rhodanica
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
