<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amblypsilopus andasibensis Grichanov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4986000</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/82D93212B5D189BCA56730CE9FDC55F7</uri>
         <article-title>Eleven new species of Amblypsilopus Bigot (Diptera: Dolichopodidae: Sciapodinae) and a key to the species of Madagascar and adjacent islands</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1399</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus andasibensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
EF68C2DC-2411-4736-B379-563FB79470CB
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus andasibensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is very close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. olgae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in habitus. The latter differs from 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. andasibensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
in the fore tarsomeres 4–5 white. The fore tarsomere 4 is entirely black in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. andasibensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
; the long lobe of the cercus has 2 long setae at the middle, but no modified setae at the apex.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species is named after the Andasibe-Mantadia National Park located about 
150 km
east of 
Antananarivo
, consisting principally of primary growth forest of the Alaotra-Mangoro Region in eastern 
Madagascar
. The park’s two component parts are Mantadia National Park and Analamazoatra Reserve (
Newsome &amp; Hassell 2014
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Analamazaotra Forest
; 
18°46ʹ S
, 
48°24ʹ E
; 

950 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Oct.–4 Nov. 2007

; 
A. Freidberg
leg.; 
SMNHTAU
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 8A
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
5.2 mm
; antenna length 
1.1 mm
; wing length 
4.5 mm
; wing width 
1.2 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 8B
). Frons black, white pollinose; strong short anterior vertical and long postvertical bristles; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white hairs; face densely silvery-white pollinose, narrow, 3.3 times as high as wide under antennae, 7 times as high as wide at clypeus, at clypeus as wide as postpedicel; clypeus small, slightly bulging; antenna (
Fig. 8C
) 1.3 times as long as height of head, with scape and pedicel dirty yellow, postpedicel brown; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal bristle; postpedicel ovate, 1.2 times as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus black, brown at base, dorsal, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.07/0.07/0.1/0.91; proboscis and palpus orange; palpus with brown hairs, 2 black setae.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum orange, with brown, shining greenish blue, medial stripe slightly expanding posteriorly; scutellum metallic blue; pleura yellow, weakly pollinose; 6 strong dorsocentral bristles gradually decreasing in size anteriorly with strongest posterior pair; acrostichals short, biserial; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Mostly yellow; coxae yellow; segment 4 of fore tarsus black, segment 5 silvery white (
Fig. 8D
); last segments of mid and hind tarsi brown; fore and mid coxae with light and dark hairs and 2–3 black subapical setae; hind coxa with 1 black seta at middle; femora without strong or long setae; fore tibia without conspicuous setae; fore basitarsus thin and long, with 1 rather short basoventral seta; segment 4 cylindrical; segment 5 flattened dorsoventrally, slightly widened; segments 4–5 with white flattened setae laterally, slightly longer than tarsomere width; with black setulae dorsally; mid tibia with one short anterodorsal and two short posterodorsals (broken), without conspicuous ventral setae; mid and hind tarsi simple, cylindrical; hind tibia with several short dorsal and ventral setae; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.19/1.63/3.82/0.58/0.54/0.24/0.15, mid leg: 1.51/2.23/2.15/0.58/0.4/0.23/0.15, hind leg: 1.55/2.63/1.53/0.63/0.36/0.25/0.13.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 8E
). Widened distally, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M straight in basal half, slightly convex anteriad in middle part; M 
1
with strong elbow, forming right angle with M 
1+2
; ratio of parts of costa between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
to those between R 
4+5
and M 
1
, 5/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M 
4
, 0.37.1.03/0.33; anal vein and lobe reduced; anal angle absent; lower calypter yellow, with fine brown-black cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
1+2
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Thin and long, mostly orange-yellow, brown along distal margin of tergites 2–5, with short black hairs and marginal setae; pregenital segments combined 2.4 times as long as mesonotum; segment 7 short, symmetrical (dorsal view); tergite 7 flat, with proximal angular emargination (dorsal view); sternite 7 distinct, embracing long and thin tergite 8; sternite 8 symmetrical, rounded, with short setae; hypopygium (
Fig. 8F
) black, with brown appendages; epandrial foramen located almost symmetrically on basoventral side of epandrium; hypandrium short, with reduced arms; cercus (
Fig. 8G
) brown, trifurcated from base; dorsal lobe flat, elongate-triangular, half as long as epandrium, with pointed apex, sparsely covered with dark setae on outer side, densely covered with microscopic hairs on inner side; middle arm of cercus (
Fig. 8H
) as long as epandrium, stick-shaped, flattened laterally, with 2 very long lateral setae at distal third; ventral arm of cercus strongly curved, finger-like, reaching to middle of middle arm, with small comma-like sclerotized process at base and 4 long apical setae; surstylus projected, bilobed, with irregularly curved broad flat arms; dorsal arm of surstylus pointed at apex, with one very long apical seta, with few short setae; ventral arm of surstylus with deep distal emargination, with 4 small modified setae on distoventral apex; epandrial lobe strongly projected distally, sclerotized, broad at base, narrow distally, with 2 fine epandrial setae at base (
Fig. 8F
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 8.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus andasibensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
Holotype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
A
. Habitus. 
B
. Head. 
C
. Antenna. 
D
. Fore tarsomeres 2–5, lateral view, with inset showing segments 4–5, dorsal view. 
E
. Wing. 
F
. Hypopygium, left lateral view, reflected light. 
G
. Cercal lobes, lateral view, transmitted light. 
H
. Cercal lobes, dorsal view, transmitted light.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
