<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Amblypsilopus Bigot 1888</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4985986</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/09E1F66A7346A5695A5714DDB6DDD7AB</uri>
         <article-title>Eleven new species of Amblypsilopus Bigot (Diptera: Dolichopodidae: Sciapodinae) and a key to the species of Madagascar and adjacent islands</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1399</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus
Bigot, 1888
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Psilopus psittacinus
Loew, 1861
</tp:taxon-name>
[as “ 
psitacinus
Fabricius”] (original designation).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Notes
</p>
      <p>
Bickel (1994)
associated the genus with the tribe 
<tp:taxon-name>Chrysosomatini</tp:taxon-name>
. 
Grichanov &amp; Brooks (2017)
provided a key to all Afrotropical genera of the subfamily 
<tp:taxon-name>Sciapodinae</tp:taxon-name>
. See 
Bickel (2019)
and 
Grichanov &amp; Brooks (2017)
for a diagnosis of the genus. About sixty (including the new) species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus
</tp:taxon-name>
are known from the Afrotropical Region. Males usually have modified and ornamented podomeres (male secondary sexual characters or MSSC) diagnostic in defining species and species groups; tarsomeres are elongated or shortened. Male surstylus and cercus are greatly variable. Females of closely related species are generally indistinguishable morphologically (e.g., 
Irwin 1974
; 
Grichanov 1998
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="multiple">
      <p>

Key to species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus
</tp:taxon-name>
from 
Madagascar
and adjacent islands (males)

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>
1. Fore coxa yellow; halter yellow with brown knob ........................................................................... 2
</p>
      <p>

– Fore coxa black on at least basal half or entirely brown to black; halter black-brown (yellowish brown in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. prysjonesi
</tp:taxon-name>
) ................................................................................................................... 21

</p>
      <p>
2. Fore tibia with long modified posterior apical or subapical seta ...................................................... 3
</p>
      <p>
– Fore tibia without such seta .............................................................................................................. 6
</p>
      <p>
3. All coxae wholly yellow ................................................................................................................... 4
</p>
      <p>
– Mid and hind coxae black ................................................................................................................. 5
</p>
      <p>

4. Antenna yellow; face broad, about three times as wide as postpedicel; fore tibia as long as basitarsus; fore basitarsus ventrally at base with cluster of very short bristles and one longer and stronger black bristle; cercus with capitate seta at middle (
Hardy &amp; Kohn 1964
: fig. 61h); 
4.5–5.5 mm
(
Madagascar
, 
Mahe
, Praslin, Silhouette; also Oriental, Pacific islands) ............ 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. pallidicornis
(Grimshaw, 1901)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Antenna black; face narrow, about as wide as postpedicel; fore tibia 
3/5
as long as basitarsus; fore basitarsus with long white ventral hairs on basal 
1/5
; cercus without flagellate seta at middle (
Fig. 7
); 
5 mm
(
Madagascar
) .......................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. freidbergi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

5. Fore and mid femora bare; hind femur with light ventral cilia; fore basitarsus three times as long as segment 2; cercus bifurcated, with wide lobes (
Grichanov 1998
: fig. 25); 
4.5 mm
(
Madagascar
) .... ................................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. bruneli
Grichanov, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– All femora with long dark ventral cilia; fore basitarsus two times as long as segment 2; cercus bifurcated, with thin lobes (
Grichanov 1998
: fig. 26); 
3.8 mm
(
Madagascar
) ................................... ............................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. dallastai
Grichanov, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
6. All coxae wholly yellow, at most mid or hind coxa with orange spot .............................................. 7
</p>
      <p>
– At least mid coxa dark brown or with blackish brown spot ........................................................... 12
</p>
      <p>

7. Mesonotum and abdomen mostly blue-green; fore tarsus simple; cercus narrow, elongate, as long as epandrium, sparsely covered with long setae dorsally and ventrally (
Grichanov 1999
: fig. 13); 
7.25 mm
(
Madagascar
) ........................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. kaplanae
Grichanov, 1999
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Mesonotum and abdomen almost entirely yellow; some segments of fore tarsus modified or bearing elongate setae; cercus various ........................................................................................................... 8
</p>
      <p>

8. Fore basitarsus shorter than fore tibia; cercus as long as epandrium, swollen at base and bearing long setae (
Fig. 12
); 
4.1 mm
(
Madagascar
) .................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. romani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
– Fore basitarsus as long as or longer than fore femur and tibia combined; cercus various ............... 9
</p>
      <p>

9. Segment 3 of fore tarsus two times as long as segment 2, with 1–2 long dorsoapical setae, longer than segment 4; segments 4 and 5 of fore tarsus flattened; cercus with 2 long dorsal setae; 
3–4 mm
(
Madagascar
) ................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. stuckenbergi
(
Vanschuytbroeck, 1957
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Segment 3 of fore tarsus as long as segment 2, without long dorsoapical setae; cercus with several short dorsal setae ............................................................................................................................. 10
</p>
      <p>

10. Segments 4 and 5 of fore tarsus black; cercus with subequal in length median and ventral lobes (
Fig. 9
); 
6.3 mm
(
Madagascar
) .............................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. leonidi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
– At least segment 5 of fore tarsus silvery white; median (distal) lobe of cercus much longer than ventral lobe ......................................................................................................................................11
</p>
      <p>

11. Segment 4 of fore tarsus black and segment 5 silvery white; long lobe of cercus with 2 long setae at middle, without modified setae at apex (
Fig. 2
); 
5.2 mm
(
Madagascar
) ..... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. andasibensis
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Segments 4 and 5 of fore tarsus white; long lobe of cercus ending with one long and one short thick setae, without long setae at middle (
Fig. 11
); 
5.7 mm
(
Madagascar
) ....................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. olgae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
12. Antenna mostly yellow ................................................................................................................... 13
</p>
      <p>
– Antenna black ................................................................................................................................. 17
</p>
      <p>
13. Mid tibia with dorsal row of erect hairs, slightly longer than tibia diameter; fore basitarsus as long as tibia, flattened; cercus simple, narrow, not longer than surstylus, with long apical seta ............ 14
</p>
      <p>
– Mid tibia without dorsal pectination; other characters various ...................................................... 15
</p>
      <p>

14. Mid tibia except basal fifth with dorsal row of short erect cilia; fore and mid basitarsi without erect setae; ventral lobe of cercus expanded distally; apical bristle on dorsal lobe of cercus at most 1.5 times as long as other cercal setae (
Grichanov 1998
: fig. 27); 
5–6 mm
(
Madagascar
) ................ ............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. grootaerti
Grichanov, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Mid tibia with full dorsal row of short erect hooked setae; fore and mid basitarsi with long erect setae; ventral lobe of cercus narrow to apex; apical bristle on dorsal lobe of cercus at least two times as long as other cercal setae (
Fig. 10
); 
5.2 mm
(
Madagascar
) ............................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. marinae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

15. Fore basitarsus 1.5 times as long as tibia, with ventral and dorsal pectination; cercus with broad ovoid basal part and long filiform distal part (
Fig. 4
); 
5.7 mm
(
Madagascar
) ....... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. bairae
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
– Fore basitarsus at least two times as long as tibia, with ventral pectination; cercus bifurcated, with long thin lobes ................................................................................................................................. 16
</p>
      <p>

16. Fore and mid femora with anteroventral and posteroventral rows of setae, nearly as long as respective femur diameter; fore tibia and basitarsus each with group of elongate ventral setae at base, longer than podomere diameter; cercus with one bristle between lobes, nearly as long as ventral lobe (
Fig. 8
); 
5.9 mm
(
Madagascar
) ......................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. friedmani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Fore and mid femora with at most few elongate anteroventral and posteroventral setae, at most half as long as respective femur diameter; fore tibia and basitarsus without groups of elongate ventral setae at base; cercus with one bristle between lobes, half as long as ventral lobe (
Fig. 6
); 
6.5 mm
(
Madagascar
) ............................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. flavus
(
Vanschuytbroeck, 1962
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
17. Mid and hind coxae black; tibia and tarsi simple, without modified setulae; segment 8 of abdomen with pair of rather long bristles in addition to short ordinary setae ................................................ 18
</p>
      <p>
– Hind coxa yellow; mid coxa coxa yellow with orange or brown spot; at least fore tibia or some tarsomeres modified, with erect ciliation; segment 8 of abdomen with short setae of equal length .. ......................................................................................................................................................... 19
</p>
      <p>

18. Segment 8 of abdomen with pair of very long bristles; the longest bristle about three times as long as epandrium; cercus with dorsal lobe shorter than ventral lobe (
Grichanov 2003
: fig. 12); 
4.9–5.1 mm
(
Réunion
) ....................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. reunionensis
Grichanov, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Segment 8 of abdomen with the longest bristle about ⅔ times as long as epandrium; cercus with dorsal lobe longer than ventral lobe (
Grichanov 2003
: fig. 13); 
4.65 mm
(
Réunion
) ........................ ............................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. takamaka
Grichanov, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

19. Fore tibia and tarsus with erect ciliation; fore tarsus simple in other respects, at most two times as long as fore tibia, entirely brown; cercus trilobed, with dorsal lobe with strong and long dorsal bristle at apex; surstylus large, about as large as epandrium (
Grichanov 1999
: fig. 12); 
3.75 mm
(
Madagascar
) ............................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ankaratrensis
Grichanov, 1999
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Fore tibia and tarsus without distinct erect ciliation; fore tarsus distinctly longer than three times fore tibia, with at least segment 5 white; cercus bilobed; surstylus trilobed, with short narrow lobes .. 20
</p>
      <p>

20. Fore tarsus nearly three times as long as fore tibia, with segment 4 yellow, flattened and widened, with posterior comb of 8–9 long flattened setae; segment 2 distinctly longer than segment 3 (
Fig. 5
); 
4.7 mm
(
Madagascar
) ................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. fianarantsoa
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Fore tarsus at least 4 times as long as fore tibia, with segment 4 black, simple; segment 2 distinctly shorter than segment 3 (
Fig. 1
); 
4.7 mm
(
Madagascar
) ............................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. analamazaotra
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>
21. Hind femur mostly yellow; fore tibia with very long posterior seta at apical third or fourth; cercus trilobed, with unequal lobes; dorsal lobe of cercus with 3 very long apical bristles ...................... 22
</p>
      <p>

– Hind femur mostly black or dark brown; fore tibia with or without long setae; cercus simple, with relatively short setae (
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus abruptus
</tp:taxon-name>
species group) ...................................................... 23

</p>
      <p>

22. Fore femur with yellow ciliation below; cercus with long median and short dorsal lobes (
Grichanov 2003
: fig. 10); 
3.9 mm
(
Madagascar
) ...................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ambila
Grichanov, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Fore femur with black ciliation below; cercus with short and fused median and dorsal lobes (
Grichanov 2003
: fig. 11); 
4.8 mm
(
Madagascar
) .......................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ranomafana
Grichanov, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
23. At least fore femur with long brown-black ventral bristles ............................................................ 24
</p>
      <p>
– Fore femur with white ciliation below, sometimes with few dorsal or preapical black hairs, or bare ......................................................................................................................................................... 25
</p>
      <p>

24. Fore basitarsus 1.5 times as long as segment 2; fore tibia with posteroventral row of 4–5 long fine setae on distal ⅔; fore tarsomeres 1 and 2 with posterior row of elongate setae, about as long as tarsomere diameter; cercus with black hairs and setae (
Fig. 3
); 
3.7 mm
(
Madagascar
) ..................... ........................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. ankarana
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.

– Fore basitarsus distinctly shorter than segment 2; fore tibia and tarsus devoid of long setae; cercus with short pale dorsal and dark apical hairs (see redescription of 
holotype
in 
Grichanov 1998: 118
); 
4.5 mm
(
Madagascar
) .............................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. madagascariensis
(Vanschuytbroeck, 1952)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

25. Cercus long and narrow, at least twice as long as epandrium, with slightly enlarged base, thickened apex and stronger hairs on apex (
Becker 1923
: fig. 16); fore tibia with two ventral setae on apical half; fore basitarsus slightly widened, as long as tibia and longer than tarsomeres 2–5 combined, with 5 strong dorsal setae; 
4 mm
(
Madagascar
) .................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. flabellifer
(
Becker, 1923
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Cercus short, usually broad, not much longer than epandrium; fore tibia without conspicuous ventral setae; fore basitarsus without strong setae ...................................................................................... 26
</p>
      <p>

26. Cercus very broad, triangular, with pointed apex (
Grichanov 1998
: fig. 28); fore tibia with posterior seta at apical fourth; fore basitarsus slightly widened, with ventral pile; 
5.2 mm
(
Madagascar
) ....... ................................................................................................................. 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. kraussi
Grichanov, 1998
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
– Cercus narrow, digitiform; fore tibia without remarkable setae ..................................................... 27
</p>
      <p>

27. Surstylus broad, about as long as wide, with basal seta 2 times as long as other setae; epandrial setae unequal in length (
Grichanov 1998
: fig. 25); 
3.4–3.8 mm
(
Madagascar
, Continental Africa) ........... ................................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. cilifrons
(Parent, 1937)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>

– Surstylus narrow, distinctly longer than wide, with basal seta not much longer than other setae; epandrial setae equal in length (
Meuffels &amp; Grootaert 2007
: fig. 5); body length: 3.0– 
3.2 mm
(Aldabra) ........................................................................ 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. prysjonesi
(
Meuffels &amp; Grootaert, 2007
)
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
