<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus romani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
3E431D86-C254-44BB-B5E5-E25745BCE437
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus romani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
keys to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. stuckenbergi
</tp:taxon-name>
, differing from this and other close species in the fore basitarsus distinctly shorter than fore tibia; cercus as long as epandrium, at base swollen and bearing long setae. The fore basitarsus is as long as or longer than the fore femur and tibia combined; and the cercus is distinctly elongate and setose in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. stuckenbergi
</tp:taxon-name>
and other close species of the group.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The species name is dedicated to Roman Grichanov, one of my grandsons (
St. Petersburg
, 
Russia
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
MADAGASCAR
• 
♂
; 
Andasibe
, 
Analamazaotra Forest
; 
18°46ʹ S
, 
48°24ʹ E
; 

950 m
a.s.l.

; 

31 Oct.–4 Nov. 2007

; 
A. Freidberg
leg.; 
SMNHTAU
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
MADAGASCAR
• 
2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for holotype; 
SMNHTAU

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
(
Fig. 6A
)
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
4.1 mm
; antenna length 
2.5 mm
; wing length 
3.8 mm
; wing width 
1.1 mm
.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD (
Fig. 6B
). Frons black (lateral view), white pollinose; strong short anterior vertical and long postvertical bristles; upper postocular setae black, short; lateral postocular setae white, uniserial; ventral postcranium covered with irregular white hairs; face black, densely white pollinose, broad, 1.5 times as high as wide under antennae, 2.7 times as high as wide at clypeus, at clypeus nearly 4 times as wide as postpedicel; clypeus small, slightly bulging; antenna (
Fig. 6C
) yellow, 2.8 times as long as height of head; pedicel with short bristles, with one long dorsal bristle; postpedicel conoid, 1.5 times as long as high, with short hairs; arista-like stylus black, brown at base, apical, microscopically haired; length (mm) of scape, pedicel, postpedicel, stylus, 0.06/0.06/0.12/2.23; proboscis yellow; palpus small, orange-yellow with white hairs and 2 black setae.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Amblypsilopus romani
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
A–F
. Holotype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
G–H
. Paratype, ♂ (SMNHTAU). 
A
. Habitus. 
B
. Head, frontal view. 
C
. Head and antenna, frontolateral view. 
D
. Fore femur. 
E
. Fore tarsus. 
F
. Wing. 
G
. Hypopygium, left lateral view, reflected light. 
H
. Distal appendages of hypopygium, transmitted light.
</p>
      <p>THORAX. Mesonotum orange, with brown, shining greenish blue, medial stripe expanding posteriorly; scutellum metallic blue; pleura yellow, weakly pollinose; 6 dorsocentral bristles with strongest posterior pair and 4 hair-like setae anteriorly; acrostichals biserial, decreasing in size anteriorly, with rather strong posterior pair behind suture; scutellum with 2 strong bristles and 2 hairs laterally.</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Yellow; segment 5 of all tarsi black; fore and mid coxae with dark hairs and 2–3 black subapical bristles; hind coxa with 1 black bristle at middle; fore femur with 2–3 strong dorsal bristles on basal half, 1.5–2 times as long as femur height, with few anteroventral and posteroventral strong setae at base (
Fig. 6D
); fore tibia and tarsus with complete rows of semi-erect setae except ventral side, with longer and stronger setae on distal ⅓ of tibia and basal ⅓ of basitarsus, longer than diameter of podomere (
Fig. 6E
); mid tibia with two anterodorsals and one very short posterodorsal, without conspicuous ventral setae; mid and hind tarsi simple, cylindrical; hind tibia with several short dorsal and ventral setae; femur, tibia and tarsomere (from first to fifth) length ratio (mm): fore leg: 1.33/1.49/1.21/0.61/ 0.48/0.23/0.14, mid leg: 1.3/1.94/1.38/0.49/0.33/0.18/0.1, hind leg: 1.58/2.5/0.81/0.54/0.29/0.22/0.09.
</p>
      <p>
WING (
Fig. 6F
). Widest at middle, almost hyaline, veins brown; R 
4+5
gently curved to M 

1
in

apical third; M almost straight; M 
1
with strong elbow, forming right angle with M 
1+2
; ratio of parts of costa between R 
2+3
and R 
4+5
to those between R and M 
1
, 5/1; crossvein dm-m straight; ratio of crossvein dm-m to apical part of M 
1+2
(fork-handle) to apical part of M 
4
, 0.38/0.88/0.32; anal vein foldlike, anal lobe developed; anal angle right; lower calypter brownish yellow, with fine brown cilia; halter yellow with brown knob.
</p>
      <p>
1+2
</p>
      <p>
4+5
</p>
      <p>
ABDOMEN. Elongate, with short black hairs and marginal setae; tergite 1 yellow; tergites 2–4 each yellow, with narrow brown band along distal margin; tergites 5–6 brown; pregenital segments combined 2.1 times as long as mesonotum; hypopygium (
Fig. 6G
) dark brown, with brown appendages; cercus brownish yellow, covered with brownish hairs, somewhat longer at rounded apex, with 3 long black dorsal setae at base, longer than cercus; cerci fused at base, shorter than epandrium; hypandrium asymmetrical, with narrow left lateral arm, arising near base of hypandrium; phallus with dorsal angle; surstylus (
Fig. 6H
) projected, bilobed, with long thin arms of equal length; dorsal arm of surstylus widened at apex, with 2 short dorsoapical setae; ventral arm of surstylus with 5–6 simple long outer setae; epandrial lobe large, leaf-like, sclerotized, with pointed apex bearing few short setae; small fingerlike epandrial lobe at base of large lobe with one very long and one short seta at apex; one short epandrial ventral seta at base of epandrial lobes.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
