<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Jessopocoris Carvalho 1981</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4695077</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/BE301C0DF869FF86FDE588627010F99F</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new genera and six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Jessopocoris
Carvalho, 1981
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 6A–C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Jessopocoris
Carvalho, 1981b: 480
</tp:taxon-name>

.

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Jessopocoris</tp:taxon-name>
–

Mu &amp; Liu 2012: 47

(redescr., figs 1–16).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Jessopocoris scutellatus
Carvalho, 1981
</tp:taxon-name>
(by monotypy).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The genus may be distinguished by the following characters: antennal segment I bottle-shaped, with a distinctly narrowed basal part, somewhat longer than vertex width; head, pronotum and scutellum with dense coarse punctures; pronotum with collar flat and not delimited posteriorly, calli notably expanded, with posterior depression, disc strongly raised, covering mesonotum, basal half of scutellum and bases of hemelytra; disc of pronotum with narrow, impunctate, whitish carina along midline; legs long and thin, with all femora somewhat swollen apically; hemelytra slightly constricted on basal fourth, with costal margin sinuate, concave on basal half and nearly straight apically (
Fig. 6A–B
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Carvalho (1981b)
described a single female from Ranikhet, northern 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
, as a new species and new monotypic genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jessopocoris scutellatus
</tp:taxon-name>
. He noted that the new genus differs from all other genera by the shape of pronotum, strongly expanded posteriorly and covering a substantial part of scutellum. Subsequently, 
Mu &amp; Liu (2012)
described two more species of the genus from 
Guangxi
and 
Yunnan
provinces of 
China
. According to the original description, both Chinese species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Jessopocoris
</tp:taxon-name>
have a boat-shaped, non-modified genital capsule, a large, L-shaped left paramere located in an entirely closed paramere socket and apparently absent right paramere. The only Indian species of the genus, 
<tp:taxon-name>
J. scutellatus
</tp:taxon-name>
, is still known only from the female 
holotype
.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Jessopocoris
</tp:taxon-name>
is superficially similar to 
<tp:taxon-name>
Ernestinus
</tp:taxon-name>
spp. due to the body proportions, raised and punctate pronotal disc and uniformly brown to dark brown coloration on the clavus, transverse spot on the medioapical part of corium, apex of cuneus and cells contrasting with the whitish-yellow remaining part of hemelytron and legs. However, it clearly differs from that genus in all other characters mentioned in the diagnosis.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
