<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Mertila rubrocephala Yeshwanth &amp; Konstantinov 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4695085</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/379C0B72662AA6E4ED8CD7472E4068FE</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the plant bug tribe Eccritotarsini (Hemiptera: Heteroptera: Miridae) of India and Sri Lanka with description of two new genera and six new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Mertila rubrocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
58C96AB0-D734-40BE-BDA1-AA987486F1BA
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3A–C
, 
19–20
, 
25C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Easily recognized from all congeners by the uniformly black pronotum, scutellum and entire hemelytron with only head dark reddish (
Fig. 3A–B
) and the structure of male genitalia devoid of two strongly twisted and tapering, hollow tubular processes of the dorsal wall of genital capsule (
Fig. 19
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The species epithet refers to the distinctive red head of the new species.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Type material
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
<tp:taxon-name>
INDIA
</tp:taxon-name>
• 
♂
; 
Karnataka
, 
Dakshina Kannada
, 
Vittla
; 
20°45.814ˊ N
, 
75°06.095ˊ E
; 

60 m
a.s.l.

; 

30 Sep. 2011

; 
H.M. Yeshwanth
leg.; at light; 
UASB
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
<tp:taxon-name>
INDIA
</tp:taxon-name>
• 
2 ♂♂
; same collection data as for 
holotype
; 
UASB

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
COLORATION. Black; head dark reddish, antennal segment I and labium reddish, antennal segment II reddish with apex brown; legs reddish with darkened tarsi; pronotum, scutellum and hemelytron black; membrane dark brown; body ventrally dark brown or black with genital capsule brown ventrally (
Fig. 3A–C
).
</p>
      <p>SURFACE AND VESTITURE. Head, pronotum and hemelytron with short, dense, whitish, erect simple setae, antenna and legs with brown simple setae; pronotum weakly punctate, hemelytron finely rugose.</p>
      <p>
STRUCTURE. Body oval, total length 5.2, twice as long as basal width of pronotum. Head: transverse, moderately produced anterior to eyes, slopping; eye large, occupying half the head height in lateral view and projecting laterally beyond anterior margin of pronotum; vertex 1.7× as wide as dorsal width of one eye, almost flat, postocular lobe not developed; antennal fossa large, located close to inferior margin of eye; antennal segment I tubular, basally narrow, subequal to vertex width, segment II shorter than head width; labium long, stout, reaching abdominal segment III. Thorax: pronotum 1.6× as wide as long, trapeziform, with weakly concave lateral margin and broadly convex posterior margin; mesoscutum narrowly exposed; scutellum broadly triangular, slightly raised; metathoracic scent-gland efferent system reduced, peritreme tongue shaped, of typical eccritotarsine structure (
Fig. 25C
). Hemelytron: costal margin slightly convex; cuneus broadly triangular, length subequal to basal width; large cell of membrane concave, apically angulate, well surpassing apex of cuneus, secondary cell small. Legs: femora comparatively short, moderately flattened; tibiae subequal in length to respective femora; tarsal segment I short, segments II and III subequal in length.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Genital capsule (
Fig. 19
) wide and short, with wide, posteriorly directed, V-shaped aperture, produced into three very large processes; lateral processes somewhat resembling parameres, distinctly longer than genital capsule; left lateral process elongate, rectangular with long and flattened spine-like apex; right lateral process longer than left one, gradually curved towards midline, broadly rounded apically; dorsal wall of genital capsule produced into median process, flattened oblong structure broadly rounded apically; parameres and aedeagus greatly reduced, located close to each other at ventralmost point of aperture of genital capsule; aedeagus typical of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Harpedona
</tp:taxon-name>
-group; phallotheca with slightly sclerotized dorsal wall, membranous elsewhere, endosoma simple, sac-like, without sclerotization; ductus seminis with sclerotized base followed by short membranous segment and strongly sclerotized, spine-like apical half (
Fig. 20E
); left paramere hooked, strongly twisted (
Fig. 20A–B
); right paramere spoon-shaped, with short upturned apical process (
Fig. 20C–D
).
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host
</p>
      <p>Unknown. All specimens were attracted to light.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Karnataka State
of 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
