<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Mertila
Distant, 1904
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 3A–C
, 
8
, 
19–20
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Mertila
Distant, 1904a: 113
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Mertila
</tp:taxon-name>
– 

Stonedahl 1988: 32–40

(revision).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Mertila malayensis
Distant, 1904a
</tp:taxon-name>
(designated by 

Distant 1904b: 472

).

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Recognized by the following combination of characters: antennae short, segment I thin, slightly shorter than vertex width, segment II shorter than or subequal to head width; dorsum shiny, with dense, whitish, erect simple setae; head reddish, pronotum, scutellum, and base of hemelytron reddish or bluish black to black, apical part of hemelytron bluish black to black (
Figs 3A–B
, 
8A, D, G
); disc of pronotum with faint punctures, hemelytron smooth or faintly wrinkled; head broad, with weakly convex frons, broadly depressed lateral margin bordering eye, and indistinct postocular lobe; eyes large, projecting laterally beyond anterolateral angles of pronotum; labium reaching hind coxa; pronotal collar narrow, equals in length to diameter of antennal segment I; calli weakly raised, separated by shallow impressed lines; anterior part of pronotum with shallow subtriangular area between lines delimiting pronotal collar and calli; posterior margin of pronotum slightly convex, moderately exposing mesonotum; membrane twocelled, with large, angulate and distinctly concave larger cell; genital capsule highly modified, short, with posteriorly directed wide aperture, lateral and dorsal margins of capsule with complex posterior processes (
Figs 3C
, 
8C, F, H
, 
19
); parameres and aedeagus reduced, very small; aedeagus with entirely membranous phallotheca, simple membranous endosoma and sclerotized, spine-like apical part of ductus seminis (
Fig. 20A–E
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="biology_ecology">
      <p>
Host
</p>
      <p>
Host data are available for 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mertila malayensis
</tp:taxon-name>
based on 
US
port interceptions from Java, 
Philippines
and 
Singapore
(
Stonedahl 1988
). Similarly to several 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lopidolon
</tp:taxon-name>
spp., this species was taken from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Phalaenopsis amabilis
</tp:taxon-name>
(L.) Blume, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Renanthera storiei
Rchb.
</tp:taxon-name>
f., and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Vanda
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. (Orhidaceae). A single female of 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. bhamo
Stonedahl, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
intercepted from 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
was also taken on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Vanda
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. (
Stonedahl 1988
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
, 
Burma
, 
Malaysia
, 
Philippines
, and 
Indonesia
(
Stonedahl 1988
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
Prior to this study, the genus comprised four species, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. sabah
Stonedahl, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. sarawak
Stonedahl, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Malaysia
), 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. malayensis
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Malaysia
, 
Philippines
, 
Indonesia
), and 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. bhamo
</tp:taxon-name>
(
Burma
). 
Stonedahl (1988)
also recorded the last species from 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
based on a single female without locality data from the 
US
port interception material. Description of one new 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mertila
</tp:taxon-name>
species from 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
is given below.
</p>
      <p>
Species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mertila
</tp:taxon-name>
may be recognized among other eccritotarsines by the bicolored, bright reddish and bluish black dorsum, shape of transverse head, structure of the anterior part of the pronotum and the male genitalia. Refer to discussion of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Lopidolon
</tp:taxon-name>
for details.
</p>
      <p>

Key to species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Mertila
</tp:taxon-name>
of 
<tp:taxon-name>India</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="key">
      <p>

1. Head dark reddish; pronotum, scutellum and hemelytron uniformly black (
Fig. 3A–B
). Tibiae reddish; antennal segment II reddish with darkened apex. Male genitalia as in 
Figs 19– 20
............................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. rubrocephala
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</p>
      <p>

– Head, pronotum, scutellum, and base of hemelytron bright reddish, apical two thirds of hemelytron metallic bluish black (
Fig. 8A
). Tibiae and antennal segment II dark brown. Male genitalia as in 
Fig. 8C
..................................................................................................... 
<tp:taxon-name>
M. bhamo
Stonedahl, 1988
</tp:taxon-name>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
