<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Parana arabica Belokobylskij 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5559900</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/4855E9F0CA02964E248965A410C8902C</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and Yemen</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Parana arabica
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
A3822C53-EC81-401C-A10A-EA53A5544086
</p>
      <p>
Figs 14–15
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Comparative diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species differs from the 
type
species of the genus by the following characters: furrow between second and third tergites present but shallow (without furrow in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. clotho
</tp:taxon-name>
), face entirely densely reticulateareolate (mainly smooth in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. clotho
</tp:taxon-name>
), antennal segments slender and longer (short and thick in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. clotho
</tp:taxon-name>
), mesoscutum and mesopleuron distinctly reticulate areolate (very finely coriaceous in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. clotho
</tp:taxon-name>
), neck long in dorsal view (short in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. clotho
</tp:taxon-name>
), propodeum and petiole long (shorter in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. clotho
</tp:taxon-name>
), radial vein arising behind middle of pterostigma (weakly before middle in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. clotho
</tp:taxon-name>
), hyaline stripes on fore wing wide (narrow in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. clotho
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>Named after its origin, the Arabian Peninsula.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
•
♀
; “United Arab Emirates, 
SSW of ad-Dhaid
(6154), light tr., 

24– 30.v.2006

, 
25º09′ N
, 
55º48′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
•
2 ♀♀
; same label as for holotype; 
RMNH

• 

1 ♀
; same label data as for preceding; 
ZISP
•
9 ♀♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah
Desert Park
(2049–2074), 
light tr.
, 

30.iv–31.v.2005

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’05”; 
RMNH

• 

2 ♀♀
; same label data as for preceding; 
ZISP
•
2 ♀♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah Desert
park (2517), 
light trap
, 

20.x–8.xi.2005

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
•
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Sharjah Desert Park
(1308), 
light tr.
, 

6–13.iv.2005

, 
25º17′ N
, 
55º42′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
•
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Al-Ajban
(5937), 
Malaise tr.
, 

27.v–26.vi.2006

, 
24º36′ N
, 
55º01′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
•
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Hatta
(6402–6403), 
at light
, 

24–30.vi.2006

, 
24º49′ N
, 
56º07′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
•
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Wadi Safad
(5020), 
at light
, 

14– 21.v.2006

, 
25º13′ N
, 
56º19′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
•
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Wadi Safad
(5026), 
at light
, 

1–8.vii.2006

, 
25º13′ N
, 
56º19′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH

• 

1 ♀
; same label data as for preceding; 
ZISP
•
2 ♀♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Wadi Safad
(5029), 
at light
, 

17–24. vi.2006

, 
25º13′ N
, 
56º19′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’06”; 
RMNH
•
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Wadi Maidaq
(6452–6456), 
water trap
, 

24.ix–22.x.2006

, 
25º18′ N
, 
56º07′ E
, 
A.v. Harten
, RNMH’07”; 
RMNH

• 

1 ♀
; same label data as for preceding; 
ZISP
•
1 ♀
; “Yemen (4055), 
Al Kowd
, 

ix.1999

, 
light trap
, 
A.v. Harten
&amp; 
S. Al Haruri.
RMNH’00”; 
RMNH

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
3.2–4.5 mm
; fore wing length 
1.7–2.6 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width (dorsal view) 1.2–1.3 times its median length, 1.2–1.3 times width of mesoscutum. Vertex weakly convex. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) rather distinctly and evenly roundness decreased. Transverse diameter of eye (dorsal view) 1.3–1.4 times longer than temple. Ocelli small, with ocellar triangle base 1.2–1.3 times its sides. POL 2.3–3.2 times Od, 0.6 times OOL. Eye glabrous, in lateral view oblique, its maximum diameter 1.2 times minimum diameter. Malar space 0.6–0.7 times maximum diameter of eye, 1.3–1.5 times basal width of mandible. Face convex, its width 1.15–1.20 times maximum diameter of eye, 1.3–1.4 times height of face and clypeus combined. Clypeal suture complete, distinct laterally and fine dorsally. Ventral margin of clypeus with distinct flange. Hypoclypeal depression medium-sized and rounded, its width 0.5 times shortest distance from edge to eye, 0.35–0.40 times width of face. Occipital carina dorsally complete and not broken toward ocellar triangle, not reaching below hypostomal carina and obliterated short distance before mandible base. Hypostomal flange very narrow.</p>
      <p>ANTENNA. Antenna slender, almost filiform, 23–30-segmented, 0.8–0.9 times as long as body. Scape 1.6–1.8 times longer than maximum width. First flagellar segment 5.5–6.0 times longer than apical width, 1.1–1.2 times longer than second segment. Penultimate segment 2.7–3.0 times longer than width, 0.45–0.50 times as long as first segment, 0.8 times as long as apical segment; latter acuminate apically and without spine.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed, its maximum length 2.1–2.3 times its maximum height. Pronotal carina rather distinct, its anterior branch situated in anterior 0.40–0.45, its fine posterior branch laterally not connected with anterior branch, dorsomedially almost fused with posterior margin of pronotum on short distance. Pronotal lateral depression indistinct and not delineated by carinae. Mesoscutum (lateral view) not high, obliquely and curvedly elevated above pronotum, its median lobe (dorsal view) distinctly convex anteriorly and without anterolateral corners, with distinct crenulate longitudinal median furrow in posterior 0.3; mesoscutum in dorsal view 1.20–1.25 times as long as wide. Notauli present only in anterior third (very rarely keeping fine carinae till median furrow) narrow, shallow, crenulate, completely fused posteriorly. Prescutellar depression shallow, rather short medially but widened towards sides, with distinct median carina, finely rugulose-carinate, 0.25 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum slightly convex, with distinct lateral carinae, 1.1–1.2 times as long as maximum anterior width. Subalar depression rather narrow, very shallow, reticulate-rugose. Precoxal sulcus almost indistinct to very shallow and short. Postpectal carina absent. Metanotum with low, wide and distally rounded medio-dorsal tubercle (lateral view). Metapleural flange (lobe) very narrow, short, subpointed, sometimes almost indistinct. Propodeum flat, without lateral tubercles.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 14.
<tp:taxon-name>
Parana arabica
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head and mesoscutum, dorsal view. 
C
. Head, front view. 
D
. Head, lateral view. 
E
. Basal segments of antenna. 
F
. Apical segments of antenna. 
G
. Mesosoma, dorsal view. 
H
. Mesosoma, lateral view. 
I
. Hind leg. 
J
. Propodeum and petiole of metasoma, dorsal view.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 15.
<tp:taxon-name>
Parana arabica
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Fore wings. 
B
. Hind wing. 
C
. Metasoma, dorsal view. 
D
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing 4.8–5.4 times longer than wide. Pterostigma narrow in basal half and widened in apical half, 4.2–4.8 times longer than its maximum width. Radial vein (r) arising behind middle of pterostigma, from basal 0.6. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened, metacarpus (1-R1) 1.3–1.4 times longer than pterostigma. Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 2.3–3.3 times longer than first abscissa (r) and forming with it obtuse angle, 0.50–0.65 times as long as the weakly curved third abscissa (SR1), 1.0–1.3 times as long as weakly curved or straight first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell weakly narrowed distally, its length 3.1–3.6 times maximum width, 1.0–1.1 times length of brachial (subdiscal) cell. Second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M) short, 0.8–1.5 times as long as recurrent vein (m-cu). Nervulus (cu-a) strongly antefurcal, distance between basal vein and nervulus 1.8–2.5 times nervulus length. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) submedially strongly sinuate and deep curved to longitudinal anal vein (1-1A). Narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell closed apically before recurrent vein. Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial. Hind wing 5.5–6.0 times longer than its maximum width. First costal abscissa (C+SC+R) 0.7–1.0 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.45– 0.50 times as long as second abscissa (1M). Recurrent vein (m-cu) very short, unsclerotised and not pigmented, distinctly antefurcal, strongly oblique towards base of wing.</p>
      <p>LEGS. Fore tibia anterior margin with short, rather thick, sparse spines arranged in single line. Segments of middle tarsus considerably longer than their width. Hind coxa short, shortly oval to subround, without basoventral corner and tubercle, 1.3 times longer than maximum width. Hind femur narrow, elongateoval, 3.8–4.5 times longer than wide. Hind tibia with several slender spines on outer distal margin. Hind tarsus 1.1 times longer than hind tibia. Hind basitarsus 0.55–0.60 times as long as remaining segments combined. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.6 times as long as basitarsus, 1.5–1.7 times longer than narrow fifth segment (without pretarsus). Tarsal segments slender. Claws short, thick basally, with short and weakly curved distal part.</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Petiole in lateral view, ventrally almost straight, dorsally very weakly arched in anterior half and almost straight in posterior half, highest in anterior fourth; in dorsal view, petiole rather slender, subparallel-sided or very weakly and evenly widening towards apex, without spiracular tubercles and dorsope. Length of petiole 2.8–3.4 times its posterior width, 1.5–1.6 times length of propodeum;posterior width 1.9–2.2 times minimum anterior width. Second to sixth tergites with laterotergites separated; second and third separated laterotergites not fused. Second suture very shallow, narrow, evenly curved. Median length of second tergite 1.3–1.4 times its anterior width, 1.6–1.7 times length of third tergite. Median length of second and third tergites combined 2.1–2.4 times its anterior width, 0.8–0.9 times their maximum width. Ovipositor straight. Ovipositor sheath 1.5–2.2 times longer than petiole, 0.4–0.7 times as long as metasoma, 0.8–1.25 times as long as mesosoma, 0.4–0.7 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Head entirely densely small reticulate-granulate. Mesosoma almost entirely densely reticulate-granulate, propodeum without areas, with long, distinct, complete longitudinal lateral carinae weakly convergent backwards. Hind coxa entirely coriaceous; hind femur dorsally and laterally coriaceous, smooth ventrally. Petiole granulate-reticulate, second and third tergites entirely densely small reticulate-areolate. Fourth to sixth tergites entirely of almost entirely densely and finely coriaceous. Vertex mainly glabrous, with short white setae laterally. Mesoscutum mainly glabrous, with very short and sparse white setae arranged along notauli and laterally. Setae of hind tibia semi-erect, short and rather sparse, their length on dorsal surface 0.3–0.4 times maximum width of tibia.</p>
      <p>
COLOUR. Body mainly reddish brown to dark reddish brown, rarely mainly pale reddish brown or reddish brown, with pale spots; head always in lower half or entirely paler, mainly yellowish brown; mesosoma almost darker to black below. Palpi brown to dark brown, but sometimes paler basally.Antenna yellow to brownish yellow in basal two–third, 5–12 
th
apical segments dark brown to black. Legs mainly brownish yellow or light reddish brown to dark reddish brown or almost black; hind tibia sometimes reddish brown, always pale (yellow or pale reddish brown) basally on short distance; all tarsi mainly yellow with faint infuscation, apical segments entirely and often anterior half of hind basitarsus dark to dark brown. Ovipositor sheath brownish yellow or pale reddish brown in anterior 0.25–0.50, brown to black in posterior half. Fore wing strongly darkened, with contrasting small hyaline spots and stripes (
Fig. 15A
). Pterostigma dark brown in apical 0.5, whitish yellow or white in basal half.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
The 
UAE
, 
Yemen
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
