<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Dendrosotinus (Gildoria) subelongatus Belokobylskij 2021, sp. nov.</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5559896</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/87A8D93DF6CCFBC7E37C08B148152D17</uri>
         <article-title>Review of the braconid parasitoid subfamily Doryctinae (Hymenoptera, Braconidae) from the United Arab Emirates and Yemen</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.765.1479</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Dendrosotinus
(
Gildoria
) 
subelongatus

Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
09D12F3B-FE94-4ABC-9854-B26E98F9109E
</p>
      <p>
Figs 5–6
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Comparative diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
This new species is very similar to 
D
. 
<tp:taxon-name>
(
G
.) 
elongatus
van Achterberg, 2003
</tp:taxon-name>
(
van Achterberg 2003
) known only from the 
Canary Islands
, but differs from it by the ovipositor sheath short, distinctly shorter than fore wing (longer than fore wing in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
elongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), vertex rather evenly and finely curvedly transversely striate-reticulate (coarsely reticulate with undulate striation in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
elongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), second radial abscissa (3- SR) of fore wing short, 0.7 times as long as third abscissa (SR1) (long, almost equal in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
elongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), hind tarsus long, 0.9 times as long as hind tibia (short, 0.7 times as long as hind tibia in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
elongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), propodeum with delineated areola (without areola in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
elongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
), and body mainly brownish yellow to yellow partly (mainly reddish brown to partly dark reddish brown in 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
elongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Name derived from a combination of ‘ 
sub
’ (Latin for ‘under’) and ‘ 
<tp:taxon-name>
elongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
’ (Latin for ‘elongate’) for its similarity to 
<tp:taxon-name>
D
. 
elongatus
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
• 
♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Fujairah
(1314), light tr., 

13–19.iv.2005

, 
25°08′ N
, 
56°21′ E
. 
A.v. Harten
, RMNH’05”; 
RMNH
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratype
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES
• 
1 ♀
; “ 
United Arab Emirates
, 
Fujairah
(1587), hand coll., 

2–13.v.2005

, 
25°08′ N
, 
56°21′ E
. 
A.v. Harten
, RMNH’05”; 
RMNH

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 2.0– 
2.5 mm
; fore wing length 
1.6–1.9 mm
.
</p>
      <p>HEAD. Head width (dorsal view) 1.4–1.6 times its median length, 1.2 times width of mesoscutum. Head behind eyes (dorsal view) weakly convex in anterior half, weakly roundly narrowed in posterior half. Transverse diameter of eye (dorsal view) 1.2–1.4 times longer than temple. Ocelli small, arranged in triangle with base 1.2–1.3 times as wide as its sides. POL 4.0–4.5 times Od, 0.9–1.0 times OOL. Eye glabrous, its maximum diameter 1.10–1.15 times minimum diameter. Malar space 0.55–0.60 times maximum diameter of eye, 0.8–0.9 times basal width of mandible. Face convex, its width 1.2 times maximum diameter of eye, 1.4–1.5 times height of face and clypeus combined. Clypeal suture almost complete, distinct laterally and fine dorsally. Hypoclypeal depression medium-sized and rounded, its width 0.7 times shortest distance from edge to eye, 0.35–0.40 times width of face. Occipital carina dorsally complete and not broken toward ocellar triangle, not reaching below hypostomal carina and obliterated at rather long distance before mandible base. Hypostomal flange very narrow.</p>
      <p>ANTENNA. Antenna rather slender, almost filiform, 18-segmented, 0.8 times as long as body. Scape 1.4– 1.5 times longer than maximum width. First flagellar segment 5.0–6.0 times longer than apical width, about as long as second segment. Penultimate segment 2.5 times longer than width. 0.6 times as long as first segment, about as long as apical segment; latter acuminate apically.</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Mesosoma not depressed, its maximum length 1.9–2.1 times its maximum height. Pronotal carina fine, situated submedially. Mesoscutum (lateral view) not highly, but distinctly curvedly elevated above pronotum, its median lobe (dorsal view) protruding forwards, distinctly convex anteriorly and without anterolateral corners, with almost complete, rather deep posteriorly and very shallow anteriorly median longitudinal furrow; mesoscutum in dorsal view 1.1 times longer than wide. Notauli complete, entirely deep, crenulate-rugulose. Prescutellar depression deep, longer laterally than medially, evenly curved, with 5–7 curved carinae, finely rugulose between carinae, 0.3–0.5 times as long as scutellum. Scutellum distinctly convex, with distinct lateral carinae, 1.0– 1.1 times longer than maximum anterior width. Subalar depression rather wide, shallow, rugulose with curved striation. Precoxal sulcus distinct, shallow anteriorly and rather deep posteriorly, rather wide, densely reticulate, running along anterior 0.5–0.6 of lower part of mesopleuron. Metanotum with low, wide and rounded distally medio-dorsal tubercle (lateral view). Metapleural flange (lobe) wide, short and subrounded distally. Propodeum weakly convex, without distinct lateral tubercles.</p>
      <p>WINGS. Fore wing 3.6–3.8 times longer than wide. Pterostigma rather narrow, 5.2–6.5 times longer than its maximum width. Radial vein (r) arising behind middle of pterostigma, from its basal 0.55–0.60. Radial (marginal) cell not shortened, metacarpus (1-R1) 1.0–1.1 times longer than pterostigma. Second radial abscissa (3-SR) 2.4–2.5 times longer than first abscissa (r) and forming with it weakly obtuse angle, 0.65–0.70 times as long as the weakly or very weakly curved third abscissa (SR1), 1.3 times longer than straight first radiomedial vein (2-SR). Second radiomedial (submarginal) cell not narrowed distally, its length 3.1–3.3 times maximum width, 1.5–2.0 times length of narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell. Second abscissa of medial vein (2-SR+M) rather long, 0.4–0.6 times as long as recurrent vein (m-cu). Third abscissa of medial vein (2-M) very weakly sinuate. Nervulus (cu-a) short, distinct, strongly postfurcal, distance between basal vein (1-M) and nervulus (cu-a) 1.3–1.5 times nervulus (cu-a) length. Mediocubital vein (M+CU1) rather evenly and more or less distinctly curved to longitudinal anal vein (1-1A). Narrow brachial (subdiscal) cell closed apically distinctly before recurrent vein (m-cu), apically reclivous and curved. Parallel vein (CU1a) interstitial. Hind wing 4.6 times longer than its maximum width. First costal abscissa (C+SC+R) 0.9 times as long as second abscissa (1-SC+R). First abscissa of mediocubital vein (M+CU) 0.5 times as long as second and third abscissae (1-M) combined. Recurrent vein (m-cu) short, unsclerotised and not pigmented, distinctly antefurcal, strongly oblique and curved towards base of wing.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 5.
<tp:taxon-name>
Dendrosotinus
(
Gildoria
) 
subelongatus
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Habitus, lateral view. 
B
. Head and basal segments of antenna, front view. 
C
. Head and mesoscutum, dorsal view. 
D
. Head and basal segments of antenna, lateral view. 
E
. Head and mesosoma, lateral view. 
F
. Mesosoma and first metasomal tergite, lateral view. 
G
. Hind leg.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Hind coxa without basoventral tubercle, but with weak convex basoventral corner, 1.7 times longer than maximum width. Hind femur elongate-oval, 3.0–3.1 times longer than wide. Hind tibia without spines on outer distal margin. Hind tarsus 0.9–1.0 times as long as hind tibia. Hind basitarsus thickened, 0.6 times as long as remaining segments combined. Second segment of hind tarsus 0.55–0.60 times as long as basitarsus, 1.3–1.4 times longer than narrow fifth segment (without pretarsus).</p>
      <p>METASOMA. Metasoma 1.1 times longer than mesosoma and head combined. First segment with weakly elongated acrosternite, its length 0.3 times tergite length. First tergite rather long and not strongly wide, with spiracular protuberances in anterior third, distinctly and almost linearly widened from base to apex. Length of first tergite 1.3–1.4 times its maximum posterior width; posterior width 2.0–2.2 times its minimum anterior width. Second suture fine to very fine laterally, absent medially, with weakly sublateral bands. Second tergite with very shallow, subparallel, sublateral and almost straight narrow depression in anterior half. Median length of second and third tergite combined 1.5–1.6 times anterior width of second tergite, almost equal to their maximum width. Ovipositor sheath 0.9–1.0 times as long as metasoma, 1.3–1.4 times as long as mesosoma, 0.70–0.75 times as long as fore wing.</p>
      <p>SCULPTURE AND PUBESCENCE. Vertex entirely and densely reticulate-areolate, usually arranged in curved transverse striation, often with very dense and numerous additional coriaceous; frons densely transversely undulately striate with dense rugosity-reticulation between striae; temple oblique striaterugulose in upper two-third, almost smooth in lower third; face densely transversely striate, almost smooth between striae. Mesoscutum entirely densely rugulose-reticulate arranged in transverse semicurved striae, partly with fine granulation, rugulose in narrow medio-posteriar area; scutellum entirely densely and finely rugulose-reticulate. Mesopleuron mainly densely reticulate-coriaceous. Propodeum with basolateral areas distinctly delineated by carinae, areas entirely rather finely and densely reticulatecoriaceous, median longitudinal carina distinct in anterior half; areola rather large, sparsely rugosestriate and delineated by irregular carinae. Hind coxa mainly rugulose- or rugulose-striate; hind femur distinctly coriaceous almost entirely, rugose-striate in dorsal half. First metasomal tergite entirely densely longitudinally striate with dense reticulation between striae, without distinct dorsal carinae. Second tergite entirely and third in anterior third densely and rather finely, weakly curvedly striate with dense fine reticulation, laterally striation fine or absent; third tergite smooth on remaining part. Following tergites entirely smooth. Vertex mainly with sparse short semi-erect pale setae. Mesoscutum entirely with short, dense semi-erect yellow setae. Setae of hind tibia semi-erect, short and rather dense, their length on dorsal surface 0.3–0.4 times maximum width of tibia.</p>
      <p>COLOUR. Body mainly brownish yellow to yellow partly, faintly infuscate dorsally. Palpi pale yellow. Antenna mainly pale brown, five basal segments yellow. Legs mainly almost entirely yellow, whitish yellow basally. Ovipositor sheath almost yellow in anterior half, brown in posterior half. Fore wing faintly maculate, with rather distinct infuscate transverse stripes along basal view and below middle of pterostigma. Pterostigma dark brown in apical two-third, whitish yellow or white in basal third.</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Dendrosotinus
(
Gildoria
) 
subelongatus
Belokobylskij
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, holotype, ♀ (RMNH). 
A
. Wings. 
B
. Propodeum and metasoma, dorsal view. 
C
. Metasoma, lateral view.
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Yemen
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
