<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
Genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tirana
Esquete
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
8DA0AF85-5BE1-43B5-8510-56C14B79333E
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tirana vallis
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Neuter
</p>
      <p>Body elongate (8.9 times as long as broad). Pereonites subrectangular or subsquare, pereonites 1–3 slightly wider anteriorly, pereonite 6 slightly wider posteriorly. Pleonites without hyposphaenia. Antenna article 2 with dorsodistal spine, article 4 elongate (&gt; 10 times as long as broad). Mandible molar with spiniform prolongations. Maxilliped endites with slender gustatory cusps. Cheliped carpus slender (1.8 times as long as wide). Chela slender (1.8 times as long as broad). Pereopods 4–6 carpus with one spine more than 0.5 times as long as propodus; propodus with ramified subdistal spines. Pleopods well developed, birramous, with long plumose setae. Uropods rami slender (&gt; 5.0 times as long as broad), endopod article 1 about as long as article 2.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
Following the steps of 

Błażewicz 
et al.
(2019)

for the species of the genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paranarthrurella
</tp:taxon-name>
, we name the new genus after a folk dance from 
Portugal
named ‘tirana’, object of great traditional and cultural value. Gender: feminine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The new genus presents a combination of the characters that define the other two species of the family, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paranarthrurella
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Armatognathia
: It
</tp:taxon-name>
shares with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paranarthrurella
</tp:taxon-name>
an elongate body, maxilliped endites with slender gustatory cusps, and an uropod endopod article 1 about as long as article 2, and with 
<tp:taxon-name>
Armatognathia
</tp:taxon-name>
it shares the presence of a distal spine in antenna article 2, presence of welldeveloped pleopods, and a molar with spiniform processes. Furthermore, females of (the new genus) have well-developed pleopods, which are present in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Armatognathia
</tp:taxon-name>
and absent in most species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paranarthrurella
</tp:taxon-name>
. Despite being described as “absent” in the diagnosis of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Paranarthrurella
</tp:taxon-name>
provided by 

Błażewicz 
et al.
(2019)

, illustrations of neuter specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rocknroll
Błażewicz &amp; Jóźwiak, 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. corroboree
Błażewicz &amp; Jóźwiak, 2019
</tp:taxon-name>
show what seem to be rudimentary pleopods. However, those are significantly different from the ones of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Tirana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Tirana
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
also presents unique characters within the family: the antenna article 4 is more elongate (10 times as long as broad) than in the other species of the family (4–5 times as long as broad); the cheliped is more slender (1.8 times as long as broad) than in the other species (&lt;1.6); the pereopods 4–6 carpus spines reach at least half of the length of the propodus; the propodus of pereopods 4–6 have ramified subdistal spines; finally, the uropod rami are more slender than in the other species of the family (&gt; 5.0 times as long as broad, while in the other species is &lt;4.0).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
