<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Sibogasyrinx archibenthalis</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5536349</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/E43BBB1DFFE4FFEB26137A4A75F1F7FF</uri>
         <article-title>Rare, deep-water and similar: revision of Sibogasyrinx (Conoidea:
            Cochlespiridae)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.773.1509</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Sibogasyrinx archibenthalis ( Powell, 1969 ) </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Fig. 3R–T </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Leucosyrinx ( Sibogasyrinx ) archibenthalis Powell, 1969: 344
         </tp:taxon-name> , pl. 264 figs 6–7. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> Holotype PHILIPPINES • Mindanao I., Iligan Bay , Tabu Point ;
            08°16′45″ N , 124°02′49″ E ; depth 924 m ; R/V Albatross , stn 5513; USNM 238773 .
         </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> MEASUREMENTS ( holotype ). SL 41.8 mm . </p>
      <p>SHELL. Fusiform, narrow, with high, very narrow, flat-sided spire and relatively short,
         almost straight, un-notched siphonal canal. Protoconch small, globose, of 1.5 smooth
         whorls. Teleoconch of 12 whorls. Spire whorl profile quite straight and descending steeply
         to a narrowly rounded, flange-like, peripheral carina, abutting lower suture. Last whorl
         distinctly angled by peripheral carina, and base rapidly contracting toward moderately long
         anterior canal. Axial sculpture of rounded peripheral nodules, about 13 per whorl, but
         these become obsolete on last two whorls; subsutural nodules or folds lacking. Spiral
         sculpture of dense well defined and regular spiral cords, 11–12 on subsutural ramp. Anal
         sinus moderately deep, subsutural, broadly arcuate, confluent with large forward extension
         of outer lip. Colour opaque white, covered by a thin pale buff periostracum.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> The species is known only from the holotype . In shell shape it is most similar to
            <tp:taxon-name> S. pyramidalis </tp:taxon-name> . The differences are most obvious when
         comparing specimens of the same size (e.g., Fig.3 D–F and 3R ); the last whorl is lower and
         the canal is proportionally much shorter in <tp:taxon-name> S. archibenthalis
         </tp:taxon-name> , while the spiral cords on the subsutural ramp are more pronounced and
         are of the same strength as on the remaining part of the last whorl. The last whorl is more
         angular in <tp:taxon-name> S. archibenthalis </tp:taxon-name> and the shell has a higher
         number of teleoconch whorls; in the holotype of <tp:taxon-name> S. archibenthalis
         </tp:taxon-name> the number of teleoconch whorls is 12 (SL 43 mm ), compared with 9.5 (SL
         46.8 mm ) in samples of <tp:taxon-name> S. cf. pyramidalis </tp:taxon-name> 1 from the
         Philippines of similar shell size. Therefore, at present we consider <tp:taxon-name> S.
            archibenthalis </tp:taxon-name> to be a valid species. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
