<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma
Machado
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
5BDEDDA5-91E4-4D7C-A632-C305D02748FD
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="type_taxon">
      <p>
Type
species

</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Stephanopis pentacantha
Mello-Leitão, 1929
</tp:taxon-name>
. Designated here.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
The species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
resemble some of those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epicadus
</tp:taxon-name>
[e.g., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epicadus caudatus
(
Mello-Leitão, 1929
)
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epicadus tuberculatus
(Petrunkevitch, 1910)
</tp:taxon-name>
] by their cryptic bark-dwelling habitus with predominant brown or reddish-brown body coloration, and those of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epicadinus
</tp:taxon-name>
, especially by their small size (varying from approximately three millimeters of the total body length for males and nine to females) and spiny habitus (body covered by many setae and rugose teguments, and opisthosoma bearing stout conical projections) (
Fig. 2A–D
). However, they can be easily recognized and distinguished from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epicadus
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epicadinus
</tp:taxon-name>
and other genera of 
<tp:taxon-name>Stephanopinae</tp:taxon-name>
by the presence of a pair of ventral macrosetae on their anterior patellae (I and II) (
Fig. 1D
), sensorial pits (three to five trichobothria surrounded by a small group of duster-shaped setae) on dorsal tibial depressions preceded by a strong plumose macroseta (
Fig. 1C
), and a pair of circular taints on the posterior slope of the prosoma (
Figs 3A
, 
4A
, 
7A
). Differently from 
<tp:taxon-name>
Epicadinus
</tp:taxon-name>
, the species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
have five opisthosomal projections instead of three, and short leaf-shaped setae covering their entire body instead of long needle-shaped ones (
Fig. 1A–B
). Females present a flat epigynal plate, short copulatory ducts and a single pair of oval spermathecae (
Fig. 10C–F
); the male palp bears a pear-shaped tegulum with a short and fixed embolus, and a single tipped, stout and conical RTA (
Fig. 11C–F
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>
The name of the genus is a combination of the Greek words ‘ 
kryptos
’ (κρυπτός) and ‘ 
chroma
’ (χρῶμα), which respectively mean ‘hidden’ and ‘color’. The name is a reference to the general color pattern of these spiders, which is associated to their cryptic behavior. Gender feminine.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
PROSOMA. Granular surfaced due to the presence of spherical setae sockets (
Fig. 1A–B
); slightly longer than wide, pear-shaped and usually covered with organic particles.ALE almost two times as large as AME, prosoma coloration shows a gradient of brown and dark-yellow shades (predominantly reddish brown in 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma hilaris
Machado &amp; Teixeira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
), lighter on the posterior slope, where there is a pair of rounded spots close to the anterior border of the opisthosoma (
Figs 3A
, 
4A
, 
7A
); in some cases the individual has a yellow longitudinal line between the MS and PME (
Figs 3A
, 
5A
, 
7A
, 
9A
). Anterior eye row strongly recurved, AME close to each other, and posterior eye row procurved (
Fig. 11A–B
). Clypeus with a central pair of serrated macrosetae (
Fig. 1A
). Sternum scutiform, slightly longer than wide in females and as long as wide in males, with brush-shaped setae. Carapace with a conical medianposterior projection pointing backwards (except for 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. hilaris
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. parahybana
</tp:taxon-name>
(Mello- Leitão, 1929) gen. et comb. nov., which have just an obtuse and slight elevation on the top of the thoracic area); opisthosoma short with five stout projections (two lateral pairs and one single and larger terminal projection), anal region and spinneret ring area projected backwards. Mouthparts: chelicerae with five equal-sized teeth; three on the promarginal row and two on the retromarginal. Labium truncated, slightly wider than long. Endites truncated, longer than wide, with scarce promarginal scopula.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 1.
Scanning electron microscopy of a male of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma pentacantha
(
Mello-Leitão, 1929
)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
(MCTP 7362). 
A
. Prosoma, frontal view. 
B
. Detail of a leaf-shaped setae and its spherical socket. 
C
. Sensorial pit preceeded by a plumose macrosetae on tibia I. 
D
. Pair of ventral macrosetae on patella I. 
E
. Metatarsal macrosetae. 
F
. Tarsal claw and detail of setae tuft.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Anterior femora enlarged and bearing many conical setiferous tubercles, legs I and II stouter and longer than legs III and IV, femora I and II with dorsal and dorsolateral stout macrosetae in conical sockets. Tibia I and II with five pairs of ventral macrosetae, metatarsi I and II with three ventral and one dorso-distal pair (
Fig. 1E
). Tarsal claws curved, pectinated, unequal in number of teeth (mesial claw with numerous thin teeth and ectal having three stout ones); subungueal tufts scarce, with brush-shaped setae (
Fig. 3B
).
</p>
      <p>
OPISTHOSOMA. Five short conical projections (two dorsolateral consecutive pairs, and a single caudal one), straight or slightly concave anterior border and rough surfaced, covered by leaf-shaped setae (
Fig. 1B
). Anal region and spinneret ring projected backwards, elongated.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 2. A–D
. Color variations of live specimens of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma
Machado
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
Photo credits: Thiago Carvalho.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Palpus with cymbium and tegulum pear-shaped, without apophyses; RTA single tipped, stout and presenting grooves at the apex (
Figs 8D
, 11D, 13D). The internal morphology of female genitalia is very conservative, presenting a single pair of reniform spermathecae without any accessory glands or coiled ducts (
Figs 3D
, 
4D
, 
7D
, 
10D
, 12D, 16D); in ventral view the copulatory openings are excavated in relation to the rest of the surface of the genital area, separated by a septum and located close to the edges of the posterior margin of the epigynal plate (
Figs 10C
, 12C, 16C).
</p>
      <p>
Composition
</p>
      <p>
Nine species distributed within the Neotropical Region: 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma gigas
Machado &amp; Viecelli
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma hilaris
Machado &amp; Teixeira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma macrostyla
</tp:taxon-name>
(Mello- Leitão, 1929) gen. et comb. nov., 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma parahybana
(
Mello-Leitão, 1929
)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma pentacantha
(
Mello-Leitão, 1929
)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma quadrata
Machado &amp; Viecelli
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma quinquetuberculata
(
Taczanowski, 1872
)
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et comb. nov.
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma renipalpis
(
Mello-Leitão, 1929
)
</tp:taxon-name>
comb. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma septata
Machado &amp; Teixeira
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. et sp. nov.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Brazil
(Amazonas, 
Bahia
, 
Espírito Santo
, 
Minas Gerais
, 
Pará
, 
Paraíba
, 
Paraná
, 
Pernambuco
, 
Roraima
, 
Rio de Janeiro
, 
Rio Grande do Sul
, 
Santa Catarina
, and 
São Paulo
) and 
French Guiana
(Cayenne, Maripasoula, Saint-Élie and Saül) (
Figs 9
, 18).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Variations
</p>
      <p>
Each one of the color variations documented here (from greyish-green to dark-yellow or predominantly reddish-brown), as well as the stained (e.g., opisthosoma of 
<tp:taxon-name>
K. septata
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
– 
Fig. 16A
) and striped patterns (e.g., prosoma of the specimen in the 
Fig. 2A
) were observed in all species. Therefore, since all species of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Kryptochroma
</tp:taxon-name>
gen. nov.
can present any combination of tegument hue, is it virtually impossible to identify them solely based on their color.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
