<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Stegopoma giganteum Ramil &amp; Vervoort 1992</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5088924</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/EB6F5251FFB9FF97ED25FB6D37B2FB56</uri>
         <article-title>Hydroids (Cnidaria, Hydrozoa) from the Vema and Valdivia seamounts (SE Atlantic)</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.758.1425</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Stegopoma giganteum
Ramil &amp; Vervoort, 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Fig. 3D–E
; 
Table 3
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Stegopoma giganteum
Ramil &amp; Vervoort, 1992: 36–38
</tp:taxon-name>

, fig. 5e–f.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation>
SOUTH ATLANTIC OCEAN
• 
5 colonies
, up to 
15 mm
high (1 growing on 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zygophylax
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
, 1 on bivalve shell, 1 on ghost fishing net with a gonotheca); 
Valdivia Seamount
, stn BT12; 24°49′01″–24°47′38″ S, 6°24′40″–6°25′26″ E; 887– 

886 m
depth

; 

7 Feb. 2015

; SEAFO-2015 leg.; 
SEAFO-2015-40222
, 
SEAFO-2015-40612
, 
SEAFO-2015-40811
, 
SEAFO-2015-40827
, 
SEAFO-2015-40852
, LZM-UV slide R. 587
</tp:material-citation>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Colony composed of a thin and ramified stolon, growing attached on the hydrocaulus and branches of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Zygophylax
sp.
</tp:taxon-name>
, from which arise pedicellate hydrothecae and gonothecae. Hydrothecae placed at the end of long, slender, smooth-walled and unbranched pedicels with some transversal scars due to regeneration after damage. Hydrothecae large, tubular, with smooth walls, almost bilaterally symmetrical, and slightly widening distally (
Fig. 3D
). Aperture closed by a triangular operculum adopting the shape of a gabled roof, formed by two opposite, semicircular sections on the distal part of the hydrothecal wall; opercular apparatus provided with longitudinal strips running downwards from top to basis. Hydranths are damaged or absent, and their description is not possible, but we can confirm that they are attached to the inner side of the hydrothecal base by means of a hyaline membranous ring, identical to the description given by 
Ramil &amp; Vervoort (1992)
; this membranous ring indicates the boundary between the pedicel and the hydrotheca.
</p>
      <p>
Table 3.
Measurements of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Stegopoma giganteum
Ramil &amp; Vervoort, 1992
</tp:taxon-name>
, in µm.
</p>
      <p>
SEAFO-2015
Stn BT12
Hydrotheca, length ‘diaphragm-rim’
2000–3300
max. diameter
412–550
Pedicel, length
5000–10 000
diameter
110–130
Gonotheca, length
3100
max. diameter
725
</p>
      <p>
The gonotheca shows similar morphology to that described for the hydrotheca, including the closing apparatus, but it is supported by a shorter pedicel (
Fig. 3E
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
This is the first record of 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. giganteum
</tp:taxon-name>
after its original description. The large size of the hydrothecae (
2–3 mm
long), with long and narrow pedicels, are distinctive features of this species. In addition, the opercular apparatus, the presence of a hyaline membranous ring at the attachment site of the hydranth to the hydrothecal base, and the gonothecal shape fit well with the original description of this species. Consequently, despite the wide geographical distance between the 
type
locality and the present record, we include this material in 
<tp:taxon-name>
S. giganteum
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
This species is only known from off Cape 
São Vicente
(
Portugal
; 
type
locality) where it was collected at a depth of 
1523 m
(
Ramil &amp; Vervoort 1992
). This is the first record for the South Atlantic.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
