<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Elliptera zipanguensis subsp. zipanguensis Alexander 1924</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4557220</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri">http://treatment.plazi.org/id/D22AD5CEE063DED98F61175FCD4E0C91</uri>
         <article-title>Review of East Palaearctic Elliptera (Diptera, Limoniidae) immatures with description of a new species</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi"/>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Elliptera zipanguensis zipanguensis
Alexander, 1924
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 13–15
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
Adult
(
Fig. 13
) Vein 
Rs
long and straight, and very close to vein 
R
, 

R 
2

indistinct, discal cell open by the atrophy of the outer deflection of 

M 
3

, 
m-cu
at branching point of 
M
. Halter brownish. Frontal coxae brown frontally, whitish yellow posteriorly, middle and posterior coxae whitish yellow. Trochanters whitish yellow. Femora light brown with yellowish base. Tibiae and tarsi brown. Abdominal tergites dark brown, sternites yellowish brown, pregenital segments blackish. Male genitalia dark brown. Ninth tergite with distinct lateral lobes on posterior margin. Outer gonostylus strongly sclerotized, inner gonostylus fleshy and setose. Cercus of ovipositor short with distinctly raised and hardened apical part.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Larva
Body up to 
9.2 mm
long. Head capsule heavily sclerotized. Hypostoma with eleven teeth. Abdominal segments II–VII with dorsal and ventral creeping welts. Spiracular disc surrounded by four lobes with lateral lobes sclerotized only along margins.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
SOUTH KOREA
• 
1 larva
(in ethanol); 
Ganngwon-do
, 
Samcheck-ri
, 
Gagok-myeon
, 
Deokpungni Yongsogol
; 

8 Jun. 2011

; 
H. Soh
leg.; GenBank: 
MT233406
; 
NIBR
IN 0000499882

• 

1 larva
(in ethanol); same collection data as for preceding; GenBank: 
MT233407
; 
NIBR
IN 0000499924

• 

1 larva
(in ethanol); 
Gyeongsangbuk-do
, 
Uiseong-gun
, 
Anpyeong-myeon
, 
Bakgok-ri
; 

7 Apr. 2012

; 
J.O. Suk
leg.; GenBank: 
MT233408
; 
NIBR
IN 0000564371

• 

1 larva
(in ethanol); 
Gangwon-do
, 
Pyeongchang-gun
, 
Daegwallyeong-myeon
; 

1 Jul. 2011

; 
M.J. Baek
leg.; GenBank: 
MT233410
; 
NIBR
IN 0000564293

• 

19 larvae
(in ethanol); 
Gyeongsangnam-do
, 
Hadong-gun
, 
Hwagae-myeon
, 
Beomwang-ri
; 
35°16.59′ N
, 
127°37.08′ E
; 

364 m
a.s.l.

; 

24 May 2015

; 
V. Podeniene
leg.; GenBank: 
MT233409
; 
NIBR

• 

3 larvae
(in ethanol); same collection data as for preceding; 

8 May 2013

; 
V. Podeniene
leg.; 
NIBR

• 

1 ♂
(in ethanol); 
Gangwon-do
, 
Chuncheon-si
, 
Dongsan-myeon
, 
Kangwon National University Experimental Forest
; 
37°46.75′ N
, 
127°48.95′ E
; 

225 m
a.s.l.

; 

9 Oct. 2018

(1); 
S. Podenas
leg.; 
S. Podenas
det.; GenBank: 
MT233414
; 
NIBR

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 13.
Male of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elliptera zipanguensis zipanguensis
Alexander, 1924
</tp:taxon-name>
(NIBR).
</p>
   <p>
Fig. 14.
Larva of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elliptera zipanguensis zipanguensis
Alexander, 1924
</tp:taxon-name>
(NIBR). 
A–C
. General view. 
A
. Lateral aspect. 
B
. Dorsal aspect. 
C
. Ventral aspect. 
D
. Labrum, clypeus and antennae. 
E
. Right mandible, dorsal view. 
F
. Hypopharynx and prementum. 
G
. Hypostoma. 
H
. Spiracular field. 
I
. Spiracular field.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Larva
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Length 
6.1–9.2 mm
, width 
1.5–1.6 mm
. In general similar to that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. mongolica
Podeniene, Podenas &amp; Gelhaus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
E
. 
jacoti
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Cylindrical, dark brown, hairs on dorsal and ventral sides darker than on lateral side. Abdominal segments II–VII divided into anterior and posterior parts, anterior part with dorsal and ventral creeping welts (
Fig. 14
A–C). Creeping welts with dark brown spines, arranged into transverse rows. All thoracic and first abdominal segments shorter than wider. Abdominal segments II–VIII approximately as long as wide.
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Length 
0.90–0.94 mm
, width 
0.80–0.85 mm
. In general similar to that of 
<tp:taxon-name>
E. mongolica
Podeniene, Podenas &amp; Gelhaus
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
E
. 
jacoti
</tp:taxon-name>
. Differences were noticed in arrangement of sensory structures on labrum and frons, shape of mandible, number of teeth on hypostoma and prementum. Labrum on each side bears two medium-length setae and three sensory pegs in the middle of anterior part (
Fig. 14D
). One long and three medium-length setae and sensory pit located on each side along the anterior margin of the frons (
Fig. 14D
). Mandible conus-shaped, with two large apical teeth, first apical tooth blunt, second acute (
Fig. 14E
). First ventral tooth is similar to first apical, second ventral slightly shorter than first ventral, basal tooth smallest triangular. Dorsal tooth well developed with acute apex. Prementum has four large teeth anteriorly in the middle and numerous small acute teeth on both sides (
Fig. 14F
). Hypostoma with 11 teeth, the middle tooth most prominent (
Fig. 14G
).
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 15.
Habitat of larvae of 
<tp:taxon-name>
Elliptera zipanguensis zipanguensis
Alexander, 1924
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
ANAL DIVISION. Spiracular field surrounded by four lobes, ventral lobes considerably longer than lateral lobes (
Fig. 14
H–I). Each lateral lobe as long as wide and posterior margin with U-shaped dark sclerite. Four medium-long setae located along the outer margin of lobe. Ventral lobe twice as long as width at the base and bears a dark U-shaped sclerite, the posterior branches fused medially into a connected line (
Fig. 14H
). A long seta located apically, three medium-length setae along outer margin of lobe. Two pairs of sensory pits located on dorsal margin of spiracular field. Spiracular field fringed with long firm setae, longest along the apical margins of lobes. Spiracles large, oblong, placed obliquely and inclined dorsally (
Fig. 14
H–I). Anal field with two pairs of conical, white, fleshy anal papillae (
Fig. 14C
).
</p>
      <p>
Habitat
</p>
      <p>
Larvae develop on vertical cliff surfaces kept wet by a film of water supporting algal growth (
fauna hygropetrica
) (
Fig. 15
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Recorded from the Far East of 
Russia
, North and South Koreas and 
Japan
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
