<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus championi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
DADDC62C-E4BF-479F-89B8-9E057724D7CC
</p>
      <p>
Figs 3
, 
7C
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus championi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is within 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. testudo
</tp:taxon-name>
group and can be distinguished by several genital characters: (1) apex of median lobe oval in ventral view; (2) concave structure between parameres an elongated narrow and deeply V-shaped with pointed end; (3) dorsal side of parameres narrowed gradually towards apical end, small bump near the apex in lateral view; (4) apical emargination of parameres V-shaped in ventral view.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <p>
Fig. 3.
<tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus championi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (NHMUK011225382). 
A
. Dorsal habitus. 
B
. Genitalia, dorsal. 
C
. Genitalia, lateral. 
D
. Genitalia, ventral.
</p>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is named after Harry George Champion, who collected this species.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
INDIA
• 
♂
; “ 
Haldwani
, Dist., 
Kumaon
, 
India
: H.G.C. // 
H.G. Champion
B.M. 1953-156 // 
NHMUK011225382
”; 
BMNH
.

</p>
      <p>
Paratypes
INDIA
• 
18 specs
; same collection data as for holotype‚ with additional label: “ 
NHMUK011225383
”, “ 
NHMUK011225384
”, “ 
NHMUK011225385
”, “ 
NHMUK011225386
”, “ 
NHMUK011225388
”, “ 
NHMUK011225436
”, “ 
NHMUK011225441
”, “ 
NHMUK011225442
”, “ 
NHMUK011225443
”, “ 
NHMUK011225444
”, “ 
NHMUK011225492
”, “ 
NHMUK011225494
”, “ 
NHMUK011225495
”, “ 
NHMUK011225496
”, “ 
NHMUK011225497
”, “ 
NHMUK011225498
”, “ 
NHMUK011225499
”, “ 
NHMUK011225500
; 
BMNH

• 

6 specs
; “ 
Haldwani
, Dist., 
Kumaon
, 
India
: H.G.C. 
H.G. Champion
B.M. 1953-156” // [with additional label] “ 
NHMUK011225387
”, “ 
NHMUK011225437
”, “ 
NHMUK011225438
”, “ 
NHMUK011225439
”, “ 
NHMUK011225440
”, “ 
NHMUK011225493
”; 
BMNH

• 

2 specs
; “ 
Haldwani
, Dist., 
Kumaon
, 
India
: H.G.C. // 
G.C. Champion B.M.
1926-146. // E. M. M. 1925. Det. G.C.C. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Cacc. ripicola
Ch
</tp:taxon-name>
” // [with additional label] “ 
NHMUK011225548
”, “ 
NHMUK011225549
”; 
BMNH
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Elongate, oval, dorsum convex, EL: 
3.33 mm
, EW: 
2.47 mm
, PL: 
0.93 mm
, PW: 
2.06 mm
. Colour: dorsal side brown; venter brown, tibia reddish brown, tarsal claws light brown. Dorsal surface densely covered with long setae with patches of white setae forming a wavy pattern, ventral surface with relatively long setae.
</p>
      <p>
DORSUM. Head: partially retracted into pronotum; overall surface smooth, densely punctured across surface. Antennae: 11 segmented, filiform, fully pubescent, antennomeres long and slender, 1 
st
AS
widest, 2 
nd
AS
narrow and long, 3 
rd
AS
smallest, 4 
th
–11 
th
AS
long, thin and obtusely angled on one side. Pronotum: transverse, widest at posterior end, narrowest at anterior end, narrower than elytra; anterior margin convex, posterior margin trisinuate, lateral margin convex; surface covered with dense punctation, surface between punctures smooth and shiny. Scutellum: subtriangular, large, lateral sides nearly straight. Elytra: longer than wide; anterior margin slightly convex, sinuate; anterior lateral angle nearly right angled, pointed; lateral margins strongly bordered; surface with mixtures of small fine and medium sized punctuations; elytral striae more clearly visible towards lateral end; surface between punctures smooth and shiny.
</p>
      <p>
VENTER. Prosternum: concave on anterior margin, outer lateral margin concave; prosternal process as long as wide, lateral margin sinuated, posterior margin rounded. Mesoventrite: wider than long, narrowed towards posterior; anterior end concave where prosternal process fits, discrimen visible; laterally subparallel and gently curved, posteriorly flat, anteriorly trisinuate. Metaventrite: long and wide, flat on the middle; discrimen thin visible across each end. Abdomen: five clearly visible ventrites. Intercoxal process with pointed apex. Posterior margin of 1 
st
and 2 
nd
ventrites convex, 3 
rd
–4 
th
ventrites slightly concave around the middle, 5 
th
ventrite semioval. Surface covered with long, light yellow, recumbent setae.
</p>
      <p>LEGS. Tibia: protibia with outer and inner lateral ends curved. Meso- and metatibia with outer lateral margin almost straight, inner lateral margin straight. Tarsi: simple, segments increase in length towards</p>
      <p>
the apex, 5 
th
tarsal segment as long as 1 
st
–4 
th
tarsal segment combined. Tarsal claws: long, narrow, symmetrical.
</p>
      <p>GENITALIA. Aedeagus: elongate, strongly sclerotised. Base: asymmetrical, widest around basal 0.2 from both lateral and ventral view. Median lobe: approximately ¼ length of genitalia; longer than parameres; gently curved on dorsal side, slightly bisinuate on ventral side, widest at middle, narrowing towards the apex, apex with round point in lateral view; apex pointed, split into two on anterior half and edge blunt, lower half of lateral end gently concave in dorsal view; apical end oval in ventral view. Parameres: wider than median lobe in ventral view; apical emargination V-shaped, concave structure between parameres elongated narrow and deeply V-shaped with pointed end; narrowed gradually towards apical end, small bump near the apex in lateral view; gently curved on ventral side in lateral view; apex narrow oval and not overlap with median lobe, majority of parameres do not overlap median lobe with one space visible in lateral view.</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>
No morphological difference from male except for the 5 
th
longer abdominal ventrite. Ovipositor long, gonocoxites strongly tapering to a point.
</p>
      <p>
Morphological variation
</p>
      <p>
EL: 2.74‒ 
2.35 mm
, EW: 1.04‒ 
0.87 mm
, PL: 2.16‒ 
1.97 mm
, PW: 3.33‒ 
3.01 mm
.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus championi
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
