<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus abboti
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>

urn:lsid:zoobank.org:act: 
42E7B7FB-5372-4F1E-9610-14F21C60406F
</p>
      <p>
Figs 6
, 
7F
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p>
Diagnosis
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus abboti
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is within 
<tp:taxon-name>
C. compactus
</tp:taxon-name>
group and can be distinguished by several genital characters: (1) apex of median lobe asymmetrical in ventral view; (2) concave structure between parameres deeply U-shaped with rounded end; (3) parameres deeply curved on dorsal side and gently curved on ventral side in lateral view; (4) apical emargination inward slanted and V-shaped.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>This species is named after Nick Abbot, who is a radio presenter.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
INDIA
• 

♂

; “ 
AT LIGHT
// 
Haldwani
Divn. 
Kumaon
, U.P. // 4016 // 4016 // 
<tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus testudo
, Ch.
</tp:taxon-name>
// 
<tp:taxon-name>Caccothryptus testudo Champ.</tp:taxon-name>
// 
H.G. Champion
B.M. 1953-156 // 
NHMUK011225275
”; 
BMNH
.

</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Elongate, oval, dorsum convex, EL: 
3.21 mm
, EW: 
2.62 mm
, PL: 
1.01 mm
, PW: 
2.05 mm
. Colour: dorsal side brown; venter brown, tibia reddish brown, tarsal claws light brown. Dorsal surface densely covered with long setae with patches of white setae forming a wavy pattern, ventral surface with relatively long setae.
</p>
      <p>
DORSUM. Head: partially retracted into pronotum; overall surface smooth, densely punctured across surface. Antennae: 11 segmented, filiform, fully pubescent, antennomeres long and slender, 1 
st
AS
widest, 2 
nd
AS
narrow and long, 3 
rd
AS
smallest, 4 
th
–11 
th
AS
long, thin and obtusely angled on one side. Pronotum: transverse, widest at posterior end, narrowest at anterior end, narrower than elytra; anterior margin convex, posterior margin trisinuate, lateral margin convex; surface covered with dense punctation, surface between punctures smooth and shiny. Scutellum: subtriangular, large, lateral sides nearly straight. Elytra: longer than wide; anterior margin slightly convex, sinuate; anterior lateral angle acute, pointed; lateral margins strongly bordered; surface with mixtures of small fine and medium sized punctuations; elytral striae not clearly visible throughout; surface between punctures smooth and shiny.
</p>
      <p>
VENTER. Prosternum: concave on anterior margin, outer lateral margin concave; prosternal process as long as wide, lateral margin sinuated, posterior margin rounded. Mesoventrite: wider than long, narrowed towards posterior; anterior end concave where prosternal process fits, discrimen visible; laterally subparallel and gently curved, posteriorly flat, anteriorly trisinuate. Metaventrite: long and wide, flat on the middle; discrimen thin visible across each end. Abdomen: five clearly visible ventrites. Intercoxal process with pointed apex. Posterior margin of 1 
st
and 2 
nd
ventrites convex, 3 
rd
–4 
th
ventrites slightly concave around the middle, 5 
th
ventrite semioval. Surface covered with long, light yellow, recumbent setae.
</p>
      <p>
LEGS. Tibia: protibia with outer and inner lateral ends curved. Meso- and metatibia with outer lateral margin almost straight, inner lateral margin straight. Tarsi: simple, segments increase in length towards the apex, 5 
th
tarsal segment as long as 1 
st
–4 
th
tarsal segment combined. Tarsal claws: long, narrow, symmetrical.
</p>
      <p>
GENITALIA. Aedeagus: elongate, strongly sclerotised. Base: asymmetrical, widest around basal 
0.2 in
ventral view, widest at middle in lateral view. Median lobe: approximately 
2
/ 
5
the length of genitalia; longer than parameres; curved on both dorsal and ventral side, consistent width, narrows near the apex, apex with rounded in lateral view; apex pointed, split into two on anterior ¼ and edge blunt, lower half of lateral end gently convex in dorsal view; apical end asymmetrical in ventral view. Parameres: wider than median lobe in ventral view; apical emargination inward slanted and V-shaped, concave structure between parameres deep U-shaped with rounded end; narrowed towards apical end, apical end oval in lateral view; deeply curved on dorsal side in lateral view; gently curved on ventral side in lateral view; apex narrow oval and overlaps with median lobe, majority of parameres overlaps with median lobe with no visible spacing in lateral view.
</p>
      <p>
Fig. 6.
<tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus abboti
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
, ♂, holotype (NHMUK011225275). 
A
. Dorsal habitus. 
B
. Genitalia, dorsal. 
C
. Genitalia, lateral. 
D
. Genitalia, ventral.
</p>
      <p>
Female
</p>
      <p>Unknown.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Caccothryptus abboti
</tp:taxon-name>
sp. nov.
is known only from the 
type
locality.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
