<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Andrena
(
Lepidandrena
) 
baetica
Wood, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 66–69
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
</p>
      <p>
PORTUGAL
• 
1 ♂
; 
Algarve
, 
Tareja
; [
37.173° N
, 
7.879° W
]; 

13 Apr. 1991

; 
J. v. Corstanje
leg.; 
NMNL
(illustrated 
Figs 66–69
)

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
Male
</p>
      <p>
MEASUREMENTS. Body length 
9 mm
(
Fig. 66
).
</p>
      <p>
HEAD. Black, 1.1 times as wide as long (
Fig. 67
). Clypeus black, slightly domed and slightly flattened centrally, densely punctured laterally with punctures separated by 0.5 puncture diameters, becoming sparser centrally, separated by 1 puncture diameter, narrow central impunctate line present. Gena, clypeus, and inter-antennal area with white hairs, vertex with a mixture of white, brown, and black hairs, and frons and inner margin with black hairs, all hairs variable in length, longest exceeding length of scape. Antennae uniformly dark, A3 slightly shorter than A4+5.
</p>
      <p>MESOSOMA. Scutum shagreened, very weakly shining, densely punctured, punctures separated by 0.5–1 puncture diameter, slightly sparser centrally. Scutellum comparatively less shagreened, weakly shining, very densely punctured, punctures separated by &lt;0.5 puncture diameters. Episternum and propodeum reticulate, dull. Propodeal triangle large, clearly marked with raised carina, internal surface with weak longitudinal rugae. All parts of mesosoma with long white hairs which exceed length of scape. Legs dark, apical tarsal segments lightened orange, including hind basitarsi. Wings hyaline, venation orange, nervulus interstitial.</p>
      <p>
Figs 66–69.
<tp:taxon-name>
Andrena baetica
Wood, 2020
</tp:taxon-name>
(NMNL). 
66
. Male profile. 
67
. Male face. 
68
. Male terga. 
69
. Male genitalia. Not to scale.
</p>
      <p>
METASOMA. Terga dark, apical margins lightened dark red, very densely and uniformly punctate, punctures separated by 0.5 puncture diameters, underlying surface weakly shagreened, shining (
Fig. 68
). T1–4 with loose apical hair bands, those on T1–3 interrupted, on T4 complete. S8 short, projecting area as wide as long, apical margin notched. Genitalia long, gonocoxa inflated, therefore forming a channel along their internal margins, apical teeth broadly rounded (
Fig. 69
). Penis valve triangular, narrowing apically to a rounded point. Gonostyli narrow and elongate, dorsal face flattened and bearing sparse, short hairs.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>
Andrena baetica
</tp:taxon-name>
is morphologically close to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. mocsaryi
Schmiedeknecht, 1883
</tp:taxon-name>
, but differs in the shorter, squamous hairs on the scutum (

Wood 
et al
. 2020

). The discovery of this male material further confirms the proximity of 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. baetica
</tp:taxon-name>
to 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. mocsaryi
</tp:taxon-name>
through genital structure (
Fig. 69
, see illustrations in 
Schmid-Egger &amp; Scheuchl 1997
), but also confirms its specific status as it possesses an entirely black clypeus, whereas 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. mocsaryi
</tp:taxon-name>
has a yellow clypeus, and the apex of S8 is truncate to slightly emarginate, whereas in 
<tp:taxon-name>
A. mocsaryi
</tp:taxon-name>
it is slightly pointed (
Schmid-Egger &amp; Scheuchl 1997
).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="distribution">
      <p>
Distribution
</p>
      <p>
Southern Spain (Cadiz, Los Alcornocales; Cazorla, Sierra Pozo) and southern 
Portugal
(Alentejo; Algarve) (

Wood 
et al
. 2020

).
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
