<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name>
Pseudoceros rawlinsonae
var. 
galaxy
</tp:taxon-name>
var. nov.
</tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Figs 1C
, 
3
E–I
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="etymology">
      <p>
Etymology
</p>
      <p>The name ‘galaxy’ comes from the pattern of the small white spots on the dorsal surface, which resemble a star galaxy.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p>
Material examined
(2 specs)
</p>
      <p>
Holotype
CAPE VERDE
• S„o 
Vicente Island
, 
Baía das Gatas
; 
16°54′09.33″ N
, 
24°54′25.25″ W
(
Fig. 1C V
2
); 

5 May 2017

; 
Leopoldo Moro
leg.; 
MNCN 4.01/2729 to 2798
(70 slides). One sagittally sectioned specimen stained with AZAN.

</p>
      <p>
Additional material
</p>
      <p>
CAPE VERDE
• 
1 spec.
; same collection data as for holotype; 
RCCN

.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p>
Description
</p>
      <p>
BODY. Shape oval. Length 
2.3 cm
. Smooth dorsal surface. Background color dark to velvety brown with white dots and spots that draw a longitudinal line along the body axis. One thin bright yellow external line and another internal and black line surround the entire body margin. The yellow one is interrupted at the pseudotentacles level (
Fig. 3
E–F). Marginal body edges lined with transversal whitish elongated drops (
Fig. 3F
). Ventral coloration dark grey to black. Ventral sucker in the middle of the body (
Fig. 3G
). Pseudotentacles constitute two simple folds that present each of them a small cluster of tentacular eyes in their margin. Round cluster of cerebral eyes present and surrounded by a spot of white pigment. Pharynx ruffled, butterfly-shaped and located at the anterior third of the body. Oral pore, female and male gonopore close to each other and located at the anterior end (
Fig. 3G
). Male and female genital pores located after the pharynx in the anterior half of the body (
Fig. 3
H–I).
</p>
      <p>
MALE REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM. Male genital pore between the posterior lobes of the ruffled pharynx. Male copulatory organ dorso-ventrally orientated consists in a prostatic vesicle and a very muscular seminal vesicle, as well as a penis papilla armed with a stylet (
Fig. 3
H–I). 
Vasa deferentia
open separately into the seminal vesicle. Seminal vesicle rounded, frontally oriented and lined with a thick muscular wall. Prostatic vesicle rounded, muscular and smaller than the seminal vesicle. Sperm duct muscular and long, extends frontally to join the prostatic duct inside the proximal end of the conical stylet. The short ejaculatory duct appears surrounded by the stylet cone and the penis sheath. The male atrium is wide and tetra-folding (fork-like) as characteristic of the genus (
Fig. 3I
).
</p>
      <p>FEMALE REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM. With a short muscular vagina, backwards oriented and surrounded by cement glands.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p>
Remarks
</p>
      <p>
The genus 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudoceros
</tp:taxon-name>
comprises approximately 89 species with similar copulatory organs, but bright and unique coloration patterns. However, within these patterns some taxa share evident similarities. 
<tp:taxon-name>
Pseudoceros rawlinsonae
var. 
galaxy
</tp:taxon-name>
shares with 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. bicolor
Verril, 1902
</tp:taxon-name>
, 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. mororum
</tp:taxon-name>
and 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rawlinsonae
Bolaños, Quiroga &amp; Litvaitis, 2007
</tp:taxon-name>
the brown background and one whitish, broad marginal band, but in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. bicolor
</tp:taxon-name>
the marginal band is wide with inner waves (

Litvaitis 
et al
. 2010

: fig. 4a–i); 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rawlinsonae
</tp:taxon-name>
shows, in addition to the wide band, a thin orange line (

Litvaitis 
et al.
2010

: fig. 4j–p); in 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. mororum
</tp:taxon-name>
the whitish band is interrupted and drop-shaped and additionally, two orange marginal stripes border the entire body (

Cuadrado 
et al
. 2017

: fig. 6a–b); finally, the 
Cape
Verdean species shows, together with the drop-shaped white band, two black and orange thin lines (
Fig. 3
E–F).
</p>
      <p>
Although the four previously mentioned species can be clearly differentiated due to their coloration, this is not the case in the molecular analysis (Fig. 8). In both the Bayesian and Maximum Likelihood analyses, individuals from 
Cape Verde
appear closely related to 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rawlinsonae
</tp:taxon-name>
, so much so that the separation of both populations (the Cape Verdean population and the Caribbean population) is only possible at the level of variety, not of species. Therefore, we determined the individuals from 
Cape Verde
as a 
<tp:taxon-name>variety within</tp:taxon-name>
the species 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rawlinsonae
</tp:taxon-name>
.
</p>
      <p>
Nonetheless, we want to emphasize that the decision to maintain this population (organisms) as a ‘variety’ of the species 
<tp:taxon-name>
P. rawlinsonae
</tp:taxon-name>
is the sole and exclusive responsibility of the authors. We are aware that ‘variety’ is not a taxonomic category (according to ICZN) and that therefore it will remain a non-existent species until molecular analyses allow us to consider it as such.
</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
