<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tp:taxon-treatment xmlns:tp="http://www.plazi.org/taxpub">
   <tp:treatment-meta>
      <mixed-citation>
         <named-content content-type="treatment-title">Plesiastropecten hallovensis Peyer
            1944</named-content>
         <uri content-type="zenodo-doi">http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5036854</uri>
         <uri content-type="treatment-bank-uri"
            >http://treatment.plazi.org/id/F160A367716BFFACFDD0724BFB7727D1</uri>
         <article-title>The fossil record of the family Benthopectinidae (Echinodermata,
            Asteroidea), a reappraisal</article-title>
         <uri content-type="publication-doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.5852/ejt.2021.755.1405</uri>
      </mixed-citation>
   </tp:treatment-meta>
   <tp:nomenclature>
      <tp:taxon-name> Plesiastropecten hallovensis Peyer, 1944 </tp:taxon-name>
   </tp:nomenclature>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Fig. 14 </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="reference_group">
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name> Plesiastropecten hallovensis Peyer, 1944: 320 </tp:taxon-name> , pls 7–8. </p>
      <p>
         <tp:taxon-name>Plesiastropecten hallovensis</tp:taxon-name> – Blake 1984: 633 , fig. 1a–h.
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="diagnosis">
      <p> Diagnosis </p>
      <p>As for genus.</p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="materials_examined">
      <p> Material examined </p>
      <p>
         <tp:material-citation> The holotype ( MZA L13a ) is a complete asteroid in a claystone
            matrix, comprising part and counterpart, from the Lower Jurassic (Hettangian, liasicus
            ammonite Zone) of Hallau, Canton Schaffhausen, Switzerland ( Peyer1944 ). It is
            contained in the collections of the Museum zu Aller Heiligen, Schaffhausen, and has
            suffered from considerable over-preparation. Additional material includes a suite of
            specimens from the same locality and horizon, most notably, specimen MZA L 13b/32a-e,
            which is a partially dissociated individual of which one arm is well preserved ( Blake
            1984 : fig. 1a–g). This specimen is coated with a glue-like substance which obscures
            much detail and requires specialist preparation. The present description is based on
            these two individuals. </tp:material-citation>
      </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="description">
      <p> Description </p>
      <p> The overall form is well shown by the type specimen ( Fig. 14A ); the arms are moderately
         long and tapering, the interbrachial angles acute (R:r = approximately 6:1). The arms bear
         an even fringe of closely spaced marginal spines. The marginals are numerous, narrow and
         short with a three-tiered structure, resembling tiny ‘cottage loaves’ of bread ( Fig. 14F
         ). They are clearly visible in MZA L 13b/32a-e, and are robustly paxilliform, bearing a
         single large spine pit centrally. The abactinal ossicles are conspicuous and relatively
         large, convex to flat and carry four to six, lobe-like lateral projections. Each abactinal
         has a single, large and centrally placed crater-like spine pit ( Fig. 14B, D ). The
         ossicles imbricate, and the lobes are notched on their inside (actinal) surfaces for
         contact with adjacent ossicles. These ossicles are more or less radially symmetrical in the
         disc, but elongated in the arm, where the abactinal ossicles are arranged in three rows
         comprising radials and two adradials ( Fig. 14B ). In the distal arm, the large radial and
         adradials are separated from adjacent ossicles of the same row by smaller inset ossicles.
         The adambulacrals were prepared in a small part of specimen MZA L 13b/32b. They are very
         broad and short (3:1), and carry 5–6 large, horseshoe-shaped spine bases arranged in a
         single transverse row ( Fig. 14E ). The adambulacrals of opposing rows are slightly angled
         (150°) in a proximal direction. The ambulacrals are only seen in abactinal view, and the
         ambh forms a conspicuous, elongated triangular proximal wing which overlaps the more
         proximal adjacent ambulacral ( Fig. 14D ). The ambb is oval and symmetrical. The marginal
         spines are conspicuous, forming an even comb-like fringe to the starfish. Each marginal
         plate carries a single tapering spine with a unique construction. The cross section is a
         shallow U-shape, and the abactinal surface bears a groove. The rounded actinal surface is
         made up of 4–6, length-parallel coalescing rods of trabecular stereom. The lateral margins
         of the spines carry outwardly directed short barbs, probably lost on the holotype through
         over-preparation. The base of the spine is swollen and rounded, and a simple socket on the
         base articulates with a boss on the marginal. The abactinal spines are shorter, and round
         in cross section; these are also composed of elongated trabeculae. The 5–6 adambulacral
         spines articulate with horseshoe-shaped bases, and are long and gently curved. </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
   <tp:treatment-sec sec-type="discussion">
      <p> Remarks </p>
      <p> The robust paxilliform construction of the marginals is not found in any benthopectinid
         asteroid, but is characteristic of modern solasterids and the Jurassic genus
            <tp:taxon-name> Plumaster </tp:taxon-name> , and each marginal carries only a single
         spine. We cannot agree with Blake (1984) that these resemble marginals of benthopectinids,
         other than in that they carry large spines. The large, oval or rounded, imbricating
         abactinal ossicles which are alternately large and spine-bearing and small and spineless in
         the arm are quite different from the parapaxillae of benthopectinids. The construction of
         the marginal and abactinal spines, with elongated trabeculae running along the length of
         the spines and a semicircular, concavo-convex cross section bearing two rows of lateral
         thorns, are dissimilar to benthopectinid spines, which are conical, cylindrical and carry
         numerous, irregular, distally directed thorns. The concavo-convex construction is otherwise
         seen only in the multi-armed Early Jurassic <tp:taxon-name> Plumaster ophiuroides (Wright,
            1863) </tp:taxon-name> . The transversely broad, short adambulacrals, carrying 5–6 large
         curved adambulacral spines, are quite unlike adambulacrals of benthopectinids which are
         narrow and rather elongated, but are similar to those of <tp:taxon-name> Plumaster
         </tp:taxon-name> ( Gale 2011b : figs 13–14). The elongated, imbricating proximal flanges of
         the ambulacral heads are not found in any benthopectinid, where the ambulacral heads are
         short, upright and do not imbricate, as in all paxillosidans ( Gale 2011a ), but are
         similar to those of <tp:taxon-name> Plumaster </tp:taxon-name> ( Gale 2011b : fig. 14b–c).
         Other than a superficial similarity in shape and the presence of elongated marginal and
         abactinal spines (also found in other asteroids), <tp:taxon-name> Plesiastropecten
            hallovensis </tp:taxon-name> does not show any of the characteristics of the
            <tp:taxon-name>Benthopectinidae</tp:taxon-name> , but bears a close similarity to the
         Pliensbachian–Aalenian multiarmed genus <tp:taxon-name> Plumaster </tp:taxon-name> , with
         which it shares broad, short adambulacrals with 5–6 large transversely arranged, hyaline
         spines and the flanged, imbricating abactinal ossicles ( Gale 2011b ). </p>
   </tp:treatment-sec>
</tp:taxon-treatment>
